Part Ⅲ

1. The first chapter recounts how Justice brought the Queen of Heaven to live in the City of Ladies

Lady Justice came to me in all her glory and said, 'In my opinion, Christine, you have indeed done your very best to bring your task to fruition. With my sisters' help, you've made a fine job of building the City of Ladies. It's now time for me to add the finishing touches, as I promised you I would. I shall bring you a most noble queen, she who is blessed amongst all women, to dwell here with her fine company. She will govern and rule over the city and will fill it with the great host of ladies who belong to her court and household. I can see that the palaces and splendid mansions have now been decorated and made ready and that the streets are all covered with flowers to celebrate the arrival of both the queen and her retinue of most worthy and excellent ladies.

'So let all princesses, ladies and women of every rank come forth to receive, with honour and reverence, she who is not only their queen, but also reigns with supreme authority over all earthly powers, second only to her one begotten son whom she conceived of the Holy Spirit, and who is the son of God the Father. It's truly fitting that a gathering of the whole of womankind should beg this revered, noble and magnificent princess to deign to join their number and to live amongst them in their city here below. Nor will she despise them for their lowliness in comparison with her own greatness. There is no doubt that she, in her humility, which surpasses that of all other women, coupled with her goodness, which is greater than that even of the angels, will not refuse to live in the City of Ladies. She will reside in the highest palace of all, one that my sister Rectitude has already prepared for her, and which is entirely made up of glory and praise.

'Let every woman now come forward and say, with me, "We greet you, O Queen of Heaven, with an Ave Maria, the same greeting that the Angel of the Annunciation made to you and which gives you more pleasure than any other form of address. The whole of woman-kind now implores you to agree to live in their midst. Extend your grace and pity to them by acting as their protectress, shield and defender against all attacks from their enemies and the world at large. Let them drink deep from the fountain of virtues which flows from you and may they quench their thirst so fully that they learn to abhor all forms of vice and sin. Please come to us, O Celestial Queen, Temple of God, Cell and Cloister of the Holy Spirit, Dwelling-place of the Trinity, Joy of the Angels, Light and Guide of those who stray, and Hope of all True Believers. O my lady, who could dare even to think, let alone utter, the idea that women are vile, seeing how exalted you are! Even if the rest of womankind were evil, the light of your goodness shines out so brightly that it puts all wickedness into the shade. Since God decided to take a member of the female sex as His bride and to choose you, most excellent lady, because of your great worth, all men should not only desist from attacking women but should hold them in the highest esteem."'

The Virgin replied, 'Justice, my son's dearly beloved, I will gladly come to live amongst these women, who are my sisters and friends, and I will take my place at their side. This is because Reason, Rectitude, you Justice and even Nature, have all persuaded me to do so. Women serve, honour and praise me without end, thus I am now and ever shall be the head of the female sex. God Himself always wished this to be so and it was predestined and ordained by the Holy Trinity.'

Flanked by all the other women who fell to their knees and bowed their heads, Justice replied, 'My lady, may you be praised and honoured for all eternity. Save us, Our Lady, and intercede on our behalf with your son who refuses you nothing.'

[...]

3. About Saint Catherine

'The ladies whom we shall invite to from the company of the blessed Queen of Heaven, who is Empress and Princess of the City of Ladies, are blessed virgins and holy women. We shall thus prove that God loves the female sex by showing that He endowed women, just as He did men, with the strength and fortitude needed to suffer terrible martyrdoms in defence of His holy faith, despite the fact that these women were only tender, young creatures. The whole of womankind can benefit from hearing about the lives of ladies such as these, whose heads are crowned with glory, for the lessons which they impart are more edifying than any others. It is for this reason that they will be the most revered inhabitants of the city.

'The most eminent of these exemplary women is Saint Catherine, who was the daughter of King Costus of Alexandria. Though this worthy maiden was only eighteen years old when she inherited her father's lands, she conducted both her private life and her public affairs with great discernment. She was a Christian and had refused to marry, preferring to devote herself entirely to God. One day, the Emperor Maxentius came to Alexandria in order to perform an important sacrifice as part of a great ceremony in honour of the pagan gods. Catherine, who was at home in her palace, could hear the bellowing of the animals which were being prepared for the ritual slaughter as well as the loud clamour of music. She sent word to find out what was going on and was told that the emperor had already arrived at the temple to make the sacrifice. No sooner had she heard this than she went up to the emperor and began to speak to him most eloquently about the error of his ways. Being well versed in both theology and the sciences, Catherine used philosophical arguments to prove that there was only one God, the Creator of all things, and that He alone should be worshipped. When the Emperor Maxentius heard this beautiful and noble maiden speak with such extraordinary authority, he didn't know what to say but could only gaze deeply at her in amazement. He sent for the wisest men that could be found in the whole of the land of Egypt, a country which was famous for the brilliance of its philosophers, fifty of whom were eventually brought to his court. However, once they realized why they had been summoned, they were extremely unhappy, saying that it was foolish of the emperor to have gone to all the trouble of bringing them from so far away simply to argue against a girl.

'To keep my tale brief, when the day of the debate arrived, the blessed Catherine blinded them with so many arguments that they were all convinced by what she said and were unable to answer her questions. The emperor was very angered by this and made all sorts of threats to them, but to no avail. By the grace of God, every one of them was won over by the virgin's holy words and became converted to Christianity. In his rage, the emperor sentenced all the philosophers to be burnt to death. The saintly virgin comforted them during their martyrdom, assuring them that they would be received into everlasting glory and praying to God to keep them strong in their faith. It was thus thanks to her that they took their place among the ranks of the blessed martyrs. God revealed His miraculous workings through them, for the fire destroyed neither their bodies nor their clothes: even after they had perished in the flames, not a single hair on their heads had been singed and their faces looked as though they were still alive. The tyrant Maxentius, who was inflamed with desire for the beautiful, holy Catherine, began to pay court to her in an attempt to persuade her to do his bidding. However, when he saw that he was getting nowhere with her, his pleas turned to threats and then to torture. He inflicted a cruel beating on her before throwing her into prison, with the express order that she was to be placed in solitary confinement for twelve days, at the end of which time he hoped to have starved her into submission. Yet the angels of the Lord went to her and gave her succour. When the twelve days were up, she was brought before the emperor once more. Seeing that she was even healthier and lovelier than ever, he was convinced that someone must have been visiting her in secret. He therefore ordered all the prison guards to be tortured. However, Catherine took pity on them and swore to Maxentius that the only comfort she had received came from God Himself. At a loss as to how to inflict an even crueller torture on her than before, the emperor took his prefect's advice and had wheels made which were fitted with razorblades. These wheels ground against each other in such a way that anything caught between them was tom to shreds. The emperor had Catherine stripped and forced her to lie between the wheels, yet she never once left off worshipping God with her hands clasped in prayer. The angels came down and smashed up the wheels, killing all the torturers standing nearby in the process.

'When the emperor's wife learnt about all the miracles that God was performing on Catherine's behalf, she converted to Christianity and criticized her husband for his conduct. She went to visit the holy virgin in her cell and begged her to pray to God for her sake. Because of this, the emperor had his wife tortured and her breasts cut off, whereupon the virgin said to her, "Most noble queen, don't be afraid of these tortures, for today you shall be received into neverending joy." The tyrant ordered his wife to be beheaded, at which sight huge numbers of his subjects converted. He asked Catherine to become his wife but when he realized that she was turning a deaf ear to all his pleas, he finally condemned her to be decapitated as well. In her prayers, she invoked the grace of God for all those who would remember her martyrdom and who would call out to her for help in their time of suffering. A voice came down from heaven saying that her prayer had been granted. As her martyrdom came to an end, milk, rather than blood, poured forth from her body. The angels took her saintly corpse and carried it to be buried on Mount Sinai, which was twenty days' journey away from Alexandria. God performed many miracles at her tomb, which lack of space prevents me from recounting: suffice to say that, from this tomb, flowed an oil which cured many illnesses. The Lord then punished the Emperor Maxentius in the most horrible ways.'

[...]

17. About Saint Afra, a repentant prostitute who turned to God

'Afra was a prostitute who converted to Christianity. She was brought before the judge, who said to her, "As if it weren't enough for you to sin with your body, you go and commit an error of faith by worshipping a foreign god! Sacrifice to our gods and they will pardon you." Afra replied, "I will sacrifice to my Lord, Jesus Christ, who came down to earth for the sake of sinners. It says in his Gospel that a female sinner washed his feet with her tears and was forgiven. He didn't despise either prostitutes or sinful publicans, but rather allowed them to sit and eat with him." The judge retorted, "If you don't agree to make a sacrifice, you'll never see any of your clients again, nor will you receive any more presents from them." She answered, "I will never again accept a tainted gift. As for those that I did wrongfully receive, I've asked poor people to take them away and to pray for my soul." The judge sentenced Afra to be burnt to death for having refused to worship the gods. As she was being put into the fire, she glorified God, saying, "O Lord Almighty, Jesus Christ, you who call all sinners to repent, please accept my martyrdom in this hour of my passion and deliver me from the everlasting fire by means of this earthly fire that has been prepared for my mortal body." As the flames leapt up around her, she cried out, "Lord Jesus Christ, please receive me, a poor sinful woman martyred in your holy name, you who made a single sacrifice of yourself for the whole world. You were a righteous man nailed to a cross for the sake of all those who were immoral, a good man who died for the wicked, a blessed man for the damned, a gentle man for the cruel, an innocent and pure man for the corrupt. To you I offer the sacrifice of my body, you who live and reign with the Father and the Holy Ghost for ever and ever." Thus the blessed Afra ended her days, on whose behalf Our Lord later performed many miracles.'

18. Justice talks about several noble ladies who served the Apostles and other saints and gave them shelter

'My dear friend Christine, what more can I tell you on this subject? I could go on recounting an infinite number of such stories to you. Because you said before that you were so astonished at the amount of criticism that writers have heaped on women, I can assure you that no matter what you've read in the works of pagan authors, I think you'll find few negative comments on women in holy legends, in stories of Jesus Christ and his apostles, and even in lives of the saints. If you look at such texts, what you will find instead are countless instances of women who were endowed by God with extraordinary constancy and virtue. What great acts of kindness women have unstintingly and diligently performed for the servants of God! What exemplary charity and devotion they have shown them! So much hospitality and so many other kindnesses are surely not things to be taken lightly. Even if certain foolish men want to dismiss them as insignificant, it is undeniable that, according to our faith, such acts are the rungs on the ladders that lead to heaven.

'We can cite the example of Drusiana, a noble widow, who took Saint John the Evangelist into her home, where she served him and prepared his meals. Saint John returned from exile, much to the delight of the people of the city who came out to greet him, just as Drusiana's dead body was being lowered into the ground. She had died from grief at his lengthy absence. The neighbours said to him, "John, here lies Drusiana, the lady who was such a kind hostess to you and who died because you stayed away so long. She'll never serve you again." At this, Saint John exclaimed, "Rise up, Drusiana! Go home and get my food ready for me!", whereupon she was brought back from the dead.

'Likewise, we could mention the worthy Susanna, a noblewoman from the city of Limoges. She was the first person to give shelter to Saint Martial, who had been sent by Saint Peter to convert the French. This lady showed him every kindness.

'Likewise, the same can be said of Maximilla, that excellent lady who cut Saint Andrew down from the cross and buried him, thus putting her own life in danger.

'Likewise, the holy virgin Ephigenia was a devoted follower of Saint Matthew the Evangelist, whom she served. After his death, she built a church dedicated to him.

'Likewise, there was another fine lady whose pure love for Saint Paul the Apostle was so great that she went everywhere with him and served him most diligently.

'Likewise, at the time of the apostles, lived a noble queen by the name of Helen - not the mother of Constantine, but the queen of Adiabene - who went to Jerusalem. The city was desperately short of food because of a famine that was raging all around. When Helen learnt that Our Lord's saints, who had come to Jerusalem to preach to and convert the people, were dying of hunger, she bought enough food to keep them well supplied until the famine was over.

'Likewise, when they were taking out Saint Paul to be beheaded on Nero's orders, an honourable lady by the name of Plautilla, who used to look after the saint, came up to him shedding bitter tears. Saint Paul asked her for the veil that she was wearing on her head. As she handed it to him, some wicked people who were standing nearby mocked her, saying more fool her for giving up such a pretty object. Saint Paul used the veil to blindfold himself. Later, after his death, the angels gave the blood-stained veil back to her, which she then kept as a precious relic. Saint Paul appeared to her and said that, for having done him this service on earth, he would do her a service in heaven by praying for her soul. I could tell you about many other cases like this.

'Basilissa was a noble lady full of the virtue of charity. She was married to Saint Julian. On their wedding night, they made a pact that they would both preserve their virginity. It's impossible to measure the full extent of this virgin's saintliness or the vast numbers of women and maidens who were saved by her holy teachings and encouraged to lead a devout existence. In short, her exemplary charity won her such divine favour that Our Lord spoke to her in person when she was on her deathbed.

'My dear Christine, I'm not sure what more to say to you. I could tell you endless stories about women of all different social ranks, whether virgins, wives or widows, whose wonderful strength and constancy revealed how God was working through them. Let what I have said be enough. It seems to me that I have well and truly acquitted myself of my task, which was to complete the high turrets of your city and to fill it up with illustrious ladies, just as I promised. These final examples will act as the gates and portcullises of our city. Although I haven't cited the names of every single holy lady who has ever lived, or is still living, or is indeed yet to come, for it would be impossible for me to do so, they can all none the less take their place in this City of Ladies, about which we can say: "Gloriosa dicta sunt de te, civitas Dei."[＊] I'm therefore handing it over to you now that it is finished and the gates are closed and locked, just as I said I would. Adieu, and may the peace of God remain with you always!'

19. The end of the book: Christine addresses all women

'Most honourable ladies, praise be to God: the construction of our city is finally at an end. All of you who love virtue, glory and a fine reputation can now be lodged in great splendour inside its walls, not just women of the past but also those of the present and the future, for this city has been founded and built to accommodate all deserving women. My dearest ladies, the human heart is naturally filled with joy when it sees that it has triumphed in a particular endeavour and has defeated its enemies. From this moment on, my ladies, you have every reason to rejoice - in a suitably devout and respectable manner - at seeing the completion of this new city. It will not only shelter you all, or rather those of you who have proved yourselves to be worthy, but will also defend and protect you against your attackers and assailants, provided you look after it well. For you can see that it is made of virtuous material which shines so brightly that you can gaze at your reflections in it, especially the lofty turrets that were built in this final part of the book, as well as the passages which are relevant to you in the other two parts. My beloved ladies, I beg you not to abuse this new legacy like those arrogant fools who swell up with pride when they see themselves prosper and their wealth increase. Rather, you should follow the example of your queen, the noble Virgin. On hearing that she was to receive the supreme honour of becoming the mother of the Son of God, her humility grew all the greater as she offered herself up to the Lord as His handmaiden. Thus, my ladies, since it is true that the more virtuous someone is, the more this makes them meek and mild, this city should make you conduct yourselves in a moral fashion and encourage you to be meritorious and forbearing.

'As for you ladies who are married, don't despair at being so downtrodden by your husbands, for it's not necessarily the best thing in the world to be free. This is proven by what the angel of the Lord said to Esdras: "Those who used their free will fell into sin, turned their backs on God and corrupted the righteous; for this reason they were destroyed." Those wives whose husbands are loving and kind, good-natured and wise, should praise the Lord. This is no small boon but one of the greatest blessings in the world that any woman can receive. Such wives should serve their husbands with devotion, and should love and cherish them with a faithful heart, as is their duty, living in peace with them and praying to God to keep them safe and sound. Those wives whose husbands are neither good nor bad should none the less thank the Lord that they're not any worse. They should make every effort to moderate their husbands' unruly behaviour and to strive for a peaceable existence with them according to their social condition. Those wives with husbands who are wayward, sinful and cruel should do their best to tolerate them. They should try to overcome their husbands' wickedness and lead them back to a more reasonable and respectable path, if they possibly can. Even if their husbands are so steeped in sin that all their efforts come to nothing, these women's souls will at least have benefited greatly from having shown such patience. Moreover, everyone will praise them for it and will be on their side.

'So, my ladies, be humble and long-suffering and the grace of God will be magnified in you. You will be covered in glory and be granted the kingdom of heaven. It was Saint Gregory who said that patience is the key to paradise and the way of Jesus Christ. You should all resolve to rid yourselves henceforth of silly and irrational ideas, petty jealousies, stubbornness, contemptuous talk or scandalous behaviour, all of which are things that twist the mind and make a person unstable. Besides, such ways are extremely unhealthy and unseemly in a woman.

'As for you girls who are young virginal maidens, be pure and modest, timid and steadfast, for the wicked have set their snares to catch you. Keep your gaze directed downwards, say few words, and be cautious in everything you do. Arm yourselves with strength and virtue against the deceitful ways of seducers and avoid their company.

'As for you widowed ladies, be respectable in the way you dress, speak and hold yourselves. Be devout in your words and deeds, prudent in the way you run your affairs, and patient, strong and resilient in the face of suffering and aggravation, for you will have sore need of such qualities. Be unassuming in your temperament, speech and bearing, and be charitable in your actions.

'In short, all you women, whether of high, middle or low social rank, should be especially alert and on your guard against those who seek to attack your honour and your virtue. My ladies, see how these men assail you on all sides and accuse you of every vice imaginable. Prove them all wrong by showing how principled you are and refute the criticisms they make of you by behaving morally. Act in such a way that you can say, like the Psalmist, "The evil done by the wicked will fall on their own heads." Drive back these treacherous liars who use nothing but tricks and honeyed words to steal from you that which you should keep safe above all else: your chastity and your glorious good name. O my ladies, fly, fly from the passionate love with which they try to tempt you! For God's sake, fly from it! No good can come to you of it. Rather, you can be sure that though it may seem to be superficially attractive, it can only be to your harm in the end. This is always the case, so don't think otherwise. My dear ladies, remember how these men accuse you of being weak, flighty and easily led, and yet still use the most convoluted, outlandish and bizarre methods they can think of to trap you, just as one would a wild animal. Fly, fly from them, my ladies! Have nothing to do with such men beneath whose smiling looks a lethal venom is concealed, one which will poison you to death. Instead, my most honoured ladies, may it please you to pursue virtue and shun vice, thus increasing in number the inhabitants of our city. Let your hearts rejoice in doing good. I, your servant, commend myself to you. I beg the Lord to shine His grace upon me and to allow me to carry on devoting my life to His holy service here on earth. May He pardon my great faults and grant me everlasting joy when I die, and may He do likewise unto you. Amen'

End of the Third and Final Part of the Book of the City of Ladies.

注释

＊　Glorious things are spoken of thee, O city of God.

“伟大的思想”中文版序

企鹅“伟大的思想”系列丛书自2004年开始陆续面世，在英国、美国和德国均有出版。在英国出版品种最多，已付梓八十种，尚有二十种计划出版。该丛书在全球众多读者间，尤其是学生当中，普及了哲学和政治学，销量已远超二百万册。中文版“伟大的思想”的推出，是该系列的又一延续和发展，令人欢欣鼓舞。

推出这套丛书旨在让读者再次与一些伟大的非小说类经典著作面对面地交流。长久以来，此类书籍的出版都建立在这样一个假设之上——此类著作供学生课堂学习之用，因此需辅以导读、详尽的注释及参考书目等。此类版本无疑十分有用，但我想，如果某一版本能够重建托马斯·潘恩的《常识》或约翰·罗斯金的《艺术与人生》初版时的环境，为读者与作者营造更为亲密无间的氛围，使读者除了原作者及其自身的思考外没有其他参照，也许会更有吸引力。

但是，这一做法亦存在严重缺陷：每位作者的表述难免有难解或不可解之处，一些重要的背景知识或许也有所缺失。例如，读者对亨利·梭罗创作时的情形毫无头绪，也不了解该书的反响及影响。不过，这样做的优点也显而易见，最为显著的便是作者的初衷又一次受到重视——托马斯·潘恩的愤怒、查尔斯·达尔文的灵光、塞内加的隐逸。他们给许多国家的众多读者带来的生活影响难以估量，有的影响甚至长达几个世纪，几乎没有什么比阅读这些作家更令人拍案叫绝的了。倘若没有亚当·斯密或阿图尔·叔本华，将无法想象我们今天的世界。这些小书创作年代久远，但其中的话语彻底改变了我们的政治学、经济学、精神世界、社会规划和宗教信仰。

“伟大的思想”系列一直求新求变，地域不同，收录的作家亦不同。一些作家在中国或美国更受欢迎，而英国版“伟大的思想”收录的一些作家在其他国家和地区则鲜有人知。称其为“伟大的思想”，我们亦是慎之又慎。这些思想之所以伟大，在于其影响深远，但这并不意味着这些思想都是“好”思想，实际上一些书或可列入“坏”思想之列。丛书中收录的很多作家受到同样收录于该丛书的其他作家的巨大影响，例如，马塞尔·普鲁斯特承认受约翰·罗斯金影响很大，米歇尔·德·蒙田也承认深受塞内加影响。但也有些作家彼此憎恶，若发现彼此都被收录于同一丛书，一定会深感苦恼。至于他们思想的或“好”或“坏”，读者可自行判明。我们衷心希望，您可以享受阅读这些著作的乐趣。

“伟大的思想”出版者

西蒙·温德尔

导读

塞内加（Lucius Annaeus Seneca，约公元前4—公元65），古罗马帝国著名的斯多葛学派哲学家、政治家、雄辩家、悲剧作家。

塞内加是罗马文学史上的一位巨人，他的著作覆盖了自然科学、哲学、文学等多个领域，有《疯狂的赫拉克勒斯》《特洛伊妇女》《菲德拉》《美狄亚》《腓尼基少女》《俄狄浦斯》《阿伽门农》《提埃斯忒斯》等至少八部得到确认的悲剧流传于世。他在散文与韵文创作领域的非凡成就对后世欧洲的散文与韵文写作产生了深刻的影响。

塞内加生于西班牙南部城市科尔多瓦，幼年到罗马接受早期教育。他的父亲是当时非常著名的修辞学家，一生潜心教学及写作，使得塞内加从小就开始接触和学习修辞学，这对他后来的演说口才及写作能力有极大的助益。他的母亲赫尔维亚是一位贵妇人，敏于政治。父亲在学术上的造诣及母亲的政治意识，与塞内加的人格发展和他接受的人材培养计划有必然的联系，他从小就接受过多方面的教育，以便能进入为国家服务的职业领域，既受过演说训练，又潜心学习过法律并成为了一名律师；稍长便开始学习哲学。

当斯多葛学说进入塞内加的视线后，他为这一学派的教义深深痴迷，并成为该学说的狂热支持者。他将斯多葛派的顺乎天命、安于现状、接受自己在社会中所处的地位、恬淡寡欲等主张内化为自己日常生活，甘之如饴地过着苦行僧式的极简生活。他投入之深，以至严重影响到身体健康，并曾一度恶化到危及生命，不得不接受治疗。

身体略有复元的塞内加，虽然仍然秉信斯多葛学派提倡的清心寡欲生活，崇尚与物质财富无关的内心幸福，但他重新审视了斯多葛派的某些教义，并将眼光投向更广阔的哲学领域。他也曾先后拜昆体良学派的两位学者为师，受该学派的启发，他创立了带有鲜明个人风格且兼收并蓄博采众长的塞内加派斯多葛学说。

哲学严密的思维方式助推了塞内加的演说才华和雄辩术。有一件事能说明塞内加的雄辩口才有多么令人羡慕嫉妒恨：他曾因无敌的辩才先后惹起两任皇帝的嫉妒，其中一位，即罗马帝国的第三任皇帝——丧心病狂的暴君卡里古里，甚至安排人要去暗杀塞内加。能幸免于难是因为塞内加糟糕的身体状况让人觉得他已病入膏肓时日不多，没有暗杀的必要了。

罗马帝国第四任皇帝克劳狄乌斯上任的第一年，塞内加就被指控与前任皇帝卡里古里的妹妹茱莉亚·里维拉有染而被流放到法国东南部的科西嘉岛。在长达八年的流放生活中，他致力于自然科学研究和诗歌写作。直到公元49年才被召回罗马。

塞内加生活在一个动荡多变的时代，先后经历过五位皇帝的执政。虽然年轻的塞内加淡泊名利，志趣高洁，始终提倡简朴的生活和内心的宁静，但并不排斥为国家服务，正如斯多葛派主张的：在公共生活中，人们应该勇于为国家献身；在个人生活领域，人们应该竭尽可能地掌握智慧。塞内加在三十多岁时以财务官的身份首次开始了他的职业生涯，这正是一份既需要有为国服务的情怀，又需要有足够智慧的工作。从此他的生命轨迹转向政坛。后成为元老院元老，担任过司法事务执政官，并凭借渊博的知识当上了年仅十二岁的尼禄（Nero）的家庭教师。尼禄即皇位后，塞内加顺理成章地成为其政府顾问和演讲撰稿人，辅佐皇帝制定决策，权倾一时。随着尼禄年龄渐长，塞内加的权力逐年削减。公元65年，以皮索为首的贵族共和派反对尼禄，谋刺皇帝计划败露，多疑的尼禄怀疑塞内加参与了此次谋杀。君要臣死，臣不得不死，一代大儒被迫自尽。

自古以来，塞内加都不缺追随者和仰慕者，后世的文学家、哲学家，如休谟、狄德罗、罗素等，无数大师心悦诚服地为之折腰，心甘情愿地以这位智者为人生的指路明灯。

本书所选取的三篇文章是塞内加的思想成熟期至晚年的作品，比较全面地表现出了塞内加的内心世界及其主要思想观点。

“论生命之短暂”是塞内加写给朋友保利努斯（Paulinus）的书信，阐述了作者秉持的时间观念，对如何珍惜时间和合理利用时间、如何把时间花在有意义的事上进行了充分论证，批驳了人们抱怨生命过于短暂的错误认识，指出与其无意义地抱怨自然母亲之吝啬，不如马上停止愚蠢地挥霍时间，去做时间的主人，而不是做一个“杂务缠身者”。全文妙语连珠，句句精炼，闪烁着深邃的人生智慧，展示了一代雄辩大师极强的语言说服力。

“致赫尔维亚的告慰书”创作于塞内加因通奸指控而被流放于科西嘉岛的第二或第三年，是给他挚爱的母亲赫尔维亚（Helvia）的信。他在信中首先回顾了命运给母亲带来的种种痛苦，鼓励母亲学会承受不幸，战胜困难。然后以宽阔的胸襟表明自己并未感到愧疚或消沉，安慰母亲不要悲伤。这封家书，表现了作者在逆境中依然保持人格高洁、不屈服于命运捉弄的坚强个性。

“论心灵之安宁”是塞内加晚年的作品。好友塞雷努斯（Serenus）向其倾诉自己生活中的种种焦虑、担忧、厌倦情绪，以及对自己的道德要求很高但意志力薄弱、思想游移等问题，来信的末尾向这位智者求安心之法。塞内加在回信中充满哲理地剖析了产生这些问题的思想原因，并分享了一套对治的方法。例如，他认为对治厌倦情绪最好的方法是“使自己忙于摄职从政的实际活动”；对于私有财产的忠告是财产“既不低于贫困线也不要超出太多”；要让心灵回归自我，就要懂得适时独处，等等。同时也指出，这些恢复和保持心灵宁静的方法都只是一种手段，“除非那摇摆不定的心灵能时时刻刻得到精心呵护，否则这些方法仍不足以维护一个如此脆弱的东西”。正所谓——时时勤拂拭，勿使惹尘埃。该文看似私人交流，但讨论的问题是任何时代、任何人群、任何年龄都普遍存在的心灵问题，塞内加的回信无疑对历代读者都有穿越时空的指导意义。

杨光美

论生命之短暂

保利努斯[1]啊，大多数人都抱怨自然之吝啬，因为人生短暂，而这被赋予的短暂人生竟又是如此瞬间即逝，以致除极少数人之外，其余的人都还没来得及开始生活便寿数已尽。并非只有平庸之辈和疏于思考的大众苍生才对人们所说的这种世间通病发出哀叹，那些声名显赫的人也会因同样的感觉而抱怨，因此才有了最伟大的医学之父的至理名言：“人生苦短，艺术恒久。”[2]连亚里士多德也会因此而大发牢骚，那是与其智者身份极不相宜的。他指责自然如此偏宠动物，竟让它们活出相当于人的五个，乃至十个生命周期，却把人的生命限制在极其短暂的时间里，尽管他为众多伟大的成就而生。生命并非短促，而是我们荒废太多。一生足够漫长，如能悉心投入，足以创造丰功伟绩。然而，在漫不经心、挥霍无度、汲汲于无聊琐事、最终到达万劫不复的终极之时，我们才会幡然醒悟。浑然不觉中，时光荏苒，生命已经逝去。因而，实际赋予我们的生命原非短暂，是我们自己使然；上天所赐不薄，是我们将其荒废虚掷。这正如败家之子将到手的万贯家财一掷千金，顷刻散尽。若托付给经营有方者管理，即便这财富不多，也可提升使用价值。所以，倘能妥善安排，我们的生命便可延长。

我们为何要埋怨自然母亲？她已经仁至义尽：生命，如能善用，便足够长久。然而，有人贪得无厌，欲壑难填；有人碌碌无为，不务正业；有人醉生梦死；有人慵懒怠惰；有人因政治野心而总是仰人鼻息，结果心力交瘁；有人经商发财，唯利是图，得陇望蜀；有人热衷穷兵黩武，总是损害他人，或总是惴惴不安，唯恐大祸临头，因而备受煎熬；有些人殚精竭虑，心甘情愿鞍前马后侍奉大人物而费力不讨好；很多人或觊觎他人的财富，或抱怨自己的贫穷，无暇他顾；不少人没有追求，随波逐流，反复无常，永不满足。有些人一生了无目标，而就在他们无精打采哈欠连天之时，死神已不知不觉地降临——至此，我毫不怀疑那位最伟大诗人的经典名句：“我们真正活过的那段生命仅仅是一小部分。”[3]的确如此，其余的部分不能算是生命，仅仅是时间而已。恶习裹挟着人们，从四面八方发起进攻，使人们不得再起身睁眼去识辨真相，只能俯首就擒，任欲火中烧而不能自拔，永远失去自我。即使侥幸得到一丝安宁，依然辗转反侧，终难摆脱邪念的缠磨回归平静，就像深海的水即使在风暴肆虐过后仍然翻腾不息。你觉得我说的都是公认的邪恶之徒？看看那些被众人追捧的幸运儿吧，祝福的甜言蜜语令其窒息。多少人为财富所累！多少人高谈阔论，终日为展示自己的天赋才华而呕心沥血！多少人沉溺于无度的享乐而憔悴枯槁！又有多少人囿于门客的包围之中而身不由己！总而言之，纵观这些人，从平民百姓到达官显贵——这位请求法律援助，那位提供帮助；这位接受审判，那位为其辩护，而另一位作出判决；无人为自己提出要求，每个人都在为他人耗散精力。问到那些知名人士，你就会发现他们都有这样的显著特征：甲想讨好乙，乙想讨好丙，没有人为自己操心。于是又有某些人无名火起——他们抱怨上司目中无人，因为当他们希望有人倾听时，上司却忙得无暇旁顾。不过如果一个人自己总是自顾不暇，又怎敢抱怨他人傲气十足呢？然而，无论你是何许人，大人物有时还会将目光投向你，即便看起来盛气凌人，他仍会洗耳恭听你的见解，准许你与他比肩而行。可是你却对自己从来都不屑一顾，不屑聆听自己的心声。由于你已经表明并非因为你指望别人的陪伴，而是不能容忍自己给自己作伴，所以，你没有理由认为别人就该关注你。

即便是先哲也会对此话题予以考量，对于人类头脑的浑浑噩噩他们也会惊奇不已。人们不会让别人获取自己的地产，一点儿小小的地界纠纷，都会使他们即刻抄起石头拿起武器大动干戈；然而他们却能任由别人侵占他们的生命——咳，他们甚至自己请人来掌控他们的生命。你会发现没人会愿意跟别人分享自己的钱财，但是我们每个人瓜分了自己的生命！人们在捍卫个人财产时锱铢必较，而一旦挥霍起本该吝惜的时间，却又出手大方。所以我要拉住一位先辈对他说：“我看您已来到了生命的最后一个阶段，已近期颐之年，或已过期颐，来，给我们盘点一下您这一辈子吧。”算算你用了多少时间与债主周旋，多少时间与情妇厮混，多少时间与贵族结交，多少时间与门客敷衍，多少时间和老婆吵架，多少时间惩治奴仆，多少时间为了履行社会义务而在城里奔忙，还得算上自己生病的时间，再加上无所事事流逝的时间，你会发现，属于你的时间比你原来估算的要少多了。回想一下什么时候有过固定的目标，按自己计划过的日子才几天；什么时候随心所欲地干事，什么时候表情自然，什么时候心无旁骛，如此漫长的一生取得了哪些成就；不知不觉中多少人侵扰过你的生活；无缘由的悲痛、愚蠢的嬉笑、贪得无厌、外界的诱惑使你失去了多少人生的大好时光，自己却所剩无几，你会感到自己死得太早了。

为什么会这样呢？你活着就好像命中注定会长生不老，你从未感到自身的脆弱，你对时光流逝浑然不觉，因而挥霍虚度，好像时光会满载而至，源源而来——而其实，你为别人或别的事情付出的那一天很可能就是你的末日。恐惧时，你知道终会一死；贪求时，你似乎长生不老。你会听到很多人这样说：“等我五十岁时就退休赋闲；等我六十岁时就推掉所有公干。”但，谁能保证你那么长寿呢？谁能确保你能按照自己设定的路线活下去呢？当你的生命只剩下残羹冷炙，当你的时间已无法用在其他事情上时才开始思考，你不觉得惭愧吗？当生命即将结束时才准备开始真正的生活，就已经为时太晚了！忘了人终有一死，而把那些明智的计划拖延到五六十岁时才开始实施，想在很少有人能活到的那个岁数才开始生活，这是多么愚蠢！

你会发现很多达官显贵都曾声称他们渴望闲暇、赞赏闲暇，觉得悠闲的生活比自己的尊荣更可贵。有时他们渴望能从高位平安卸任，因为即便没有外界袭击和骚乱，好运自己也会顷刻间灰飞烟灭。

被奉若神明的奥古斯都大帝[4]得到诸神的恩泽比谁都多，而他却不断地祈求歇息，希望能暂停公务，休息片刻。他句句不离的话题是对赋闲的企盼。他曾用慰藉的话宽解自己的辛劳，虽然虚假却很中听。他说，有那么一天，他会为愉悦自己而生活。他在致元老院的一封信中承诺他的隐退将不会缺少尊严，也不会与先前的荣耀相矛盾，在这之后，我在信里看到：“但更要谨记的是，不能光承诺，而要付诸实践。但那令人欣喜的现实依旧遥遥无期，所以我把对美好时光的向往讲出来高兴高兴，提前享受那种愉悦。”休闲对于他如此珍贵，在还不能真正享用时，竟然先搞起精神会餐。像他这种自视一人即可主宰万物，决定百姓、社稷福祉的人物，一旦想到有朝一日能将尊贵置于一旁都会欣喜万分。然而，从亲身经历中他知道，四方仰慕的尊荣令他付出了多少汗水，又隐藏着多少不为人知的焦虑。他不得不先向自己的同胞开战，再和同僚打仗，最后向亲人宣战，造成尸山血海。他征战于马其顿、西西里、埃及、叙利亚、亚洲——几乎所有的国家——当他的军队厌倦了血洗罗马，他又向国外敌军开火。当他平定阿尔卑斯地区，制服那些在他和平帝国中部崛起的敌人时，当他把疆土扩展到莱茵河、幼发拉底河和多瑙河一带时，在罗马本土，穆列纳、凯皮奥、雷必达、埃格纳提乌斯等却在秣马厉兵与之抗衡。当他还未逃脱这些人的阴谋时，他的女儿[5]及其周围所有因与之通奸而像发过誓一样效忠于她的贵族青年，还有埃乌勒斯以及那个与安东尼联手的第二个可怕的女人，使他在风烛残年仍惊恐不安。他将这些“痈疽”和那些左膀右臂统统除掉，但马上又有新的取而代之，就像身体的血量过多总要从某个地方破口而出。所以他渴望闲暇，期盼并想象可以从烦劳中换得解脱。万民向他祈求，而他祈求的无非如此。

当马尔库斯西塞罗[6]受到喀提林[7]、克劳狄乌斯[8]、庞培、克劳苏等人[9]的排斥时——他们有的是公开的敌人，有的是可疑的朋友——当国家形势动荡、风雨飘摇时，他备受煎熬，试图力挽狂澜，救国家于穷途末路之时，但最终却被风暴席卷而去。在太平盛世时他不得安宁，在灾祸临头时他无法忍受，他多少次诅咒那执政官的职位，而此前他曾不停地称颂它，当然，那也是不无道理的。当老庞培被征服，儿子仍在西班牙力图收拾他的残部时，西塞罗给阿提库斯写了一封信，信中他用了多么凄婉的字句！“你想知道我在这里干什么吗？”他写道，“我像半个囚徒似的待在自己图斯库兰的别墅里。”接着他哀叹过去，抱怨现在，绝望地叹息未来。西塞罗称自己为半个囚徒，但是智者绝不致使用如此悲怆的字眼。他永远不会成为“半个囚徒”，而是享受稳定、彻底的自由，随心所欲地做自己的主宰，至高无上地生活。因为还有什么东西能凌驾于一位超越命运之神的人之上呢？

李维乌斯杜路苏斯[10]孔武有力，曾提出改革格拉古兄弟灾难性政策的法案，因而得到全意大利人的支持。但他的措施不会有成果，因为从一开始就无法贯彻，一旦实施又无法放弃。据说他曾诅咒自己一直以来的动荡生活，还说他是唯一一个从未享受过假期的人，从小就没有。因为，在他尚未成年的时候，身着青年装的他就斗胆在陪审团面前为一些被告说话，并且居然在法庭上产生了影响，结果正如大家所知，他迫使法庭作出了有利于他当事人的判决。小小年纪却有如此野心的人什么事干不出来呢？你就该知道，如此年轻就这么胆大妄为会给公众和个人带来多大的麻烦。所以当他抱怨自己从未享受过假期时已为时太晚，因为他从小就在会议广场制造大麻烦。现在还不能确定他的死是不是自己一手造成的，他是因为腹股沟突然受伤后就倒下了。有些人怀疑他是自戕，但是没有人怀疑他死得适逢其时。

再提这种人就有点儿多余了，他们在别人眼里是最幸福的，但他们自己对此有着清醒的认识，他们表达了对自己一生中每个行动的憎恶。然而，抱怨归抱怨，他们既改变不了自己也改变不了别人，说完激情之辞，心情又恢复原样。

可以肯定地说，你的生命即便能延续千年，也还会缩成最短的期限：那些恶习将吞噬所有时间。你真正拥有的时间——以为可以延伸，但其实稍纵即逝——也必将很快从你身边溜走：因为你没有抓住它，或将它拉回来，或试图拖延它——这个速度最快的东西，而是让它溜掉了，似乎它是某种多余的或可以替代的东西。

不过，在所有最可恶的坏人中，最令人不齿的就是那些沉溺于酒色的家伙，因为这是最不可救药的沉沦。其他人即便执着于一种虚幻的荣耀，也算得上是值得称道的虚妄。你可以列出那些沉醉于不当的仇恨和战争的或贪婪或暴躁的家伙，但他们即便有罪也不失男人气概，而那些耽于声色犬马之徒却是劣迹斑斑的无耻人渣。看看这些人是如何花费时间的——他们算账花了多少时间，算计别人或担心被别人算计用了多少时间，奉承谄媚别人，别人奉承自己，支付或收取保释金，赴宴（这在现在被算作公事了）各用去多少时间，你会看到，这些活动，无论好坏，都让他们忙得喘不过气。

最后一点，人们普遍认为，一个人如果沉迷于某种事务，就会一事无成——修辞教育或通识教育都学不好——因为精力分散了，大脑对任何东西都不能深入吸收，而是会排斥一切所谓硬塞进来的东西。对于那些沉迷于某一活动的人来说，生活是最不重要的事，而没有比生活这门课程更难学的了。其他技艺的老师到处都能找到，实际上有些技艺连小孩子都非常精通，可以胜任教师一职。但是，学会如何生活却要耗费一生的时间，而让你更惊诧的是，学会如何死去也要花费一生的时间。那么多精英人物都放下负担，放弃财产、放弃生意、放弃享乐，把学习如何生活作为自己余生的目标。但这些逝者生前大多坦言他们还是没有弄明白这个问题——其他人就更不明白了。相信我，伟人、圣人的标志就是从不浪费自己的时间，他的寿命之所以长久是因为他将自己所有的时间全部为己所用，没有闲置，没有荒废，没有置于别人的掌控之下。作为自己时间的监护人，他精打细算，从未发现有什么东西值得拿自己的时间交换。所以他有足够的时间，而那些长时间被公事所扰的人必定所剩无几了。

你也不会想到，这些人有时也没能意识到自己丢失了什么。确实，你会听到有些为巨大财富所累的人有时会在一群门客当中，在法院辩护时，或在做着其他体面而又痛苦的事时大喊“不能活了”。当然不能了，所有找你办事的人都让你远离了自我。被告人窃走了你多少天？那个候选人呢？那个为自己的继承人送了葬之后疲惫不堪的老妪呢？还有那个装病来挑起遗产继承人贪欲的人呢？还有那个把你这样的人当朋友不是为了友谊，而是为了炫耀的颇有势力的朋友呢？我跟你说呀，把这一辈子的日子标示出来盘点一下，你会发现自己所剩极少——而且都是边角废料。某人得到了垂涎已久的职权却又想弃之不顾，反复说着：“这一年怎么还不到头呀？”另一位觉得能有机会来举办竞赛是了不起的成功[11]，但是一旦举办，他又说：“什么时候我才能脱身呀？”这位演讲者受到广场四面八方听众的捧场，台下挤满了听众，远处的根本听不到他的讲演，而他却说：“什么时候才能休假呢？”每个人都在为生计奔忙，因渴望未来、厌倦现在而烦恼。但是将自己的时间为己所用的人，总是把每一天安排得像是最后一天的人，他们既不渴望又不惧怕明天的到来。现在每个时辰还会给他带来什么新的乐事呢？他一切都尝试过了，充分享受过了，再有其他的，命运尽可自行安排了。他现在无忧无虑，这样的一生什么都不会被拿走，而只能为其添加内容，就像一个吃饱了的人已不再需要任何食物，但是再加点儿也还能吃下去。所以不要以为头发花白、满脸皱纹的人就是活得长，他不是活得长，只是在世上待得时间长。如果一个人出海遇到狂风暴雨，被变幻肆虐的风吹得团团转，你可能会觉得他航行了很远，其实航行得并不远，只是浮沉动荡的时间长而已。

看到有的人想要占用别人的时间，而对方又欣然应允，我总是感到惊讶。双方都只是想到了占用时间的事由，却都没有考虑到时间本身——似乎什么都没索取，什么都没付出。因为时间是无形的，无法明摆着被查看，因而被认为是很廉价的——几乎没有任何价值。这一点蒙蔽了人们，使他们忽视了这人生中最宝贵的商品。人们接到养老金、抚恤金时会很高兴，为这些钱他们曾付出劳动、提供援助或者服务。但是没有人计算时间的价值——人们大肆挥霍，好像它毫无价值。但就是这些人，如果受到死亡的威胁，你就会看到他们向大夫乞求；如果他们惧怕死刑，为了保命他们会倾其所有。情绪完全不一样了呀。如果我们每个人能像计算过去岁月那样将未来的岁月当面推算出来，那些看到自己来日不多的人会是怎样震惊呀，他们将会怎样小心翼翼地利用这些时间呀！而且如果数目确定下来，无论多小的数目，也都容易安排了。对于那不知会在什么时候戛然而止的生命，我们要更慎重地存留。

但是，你不要认为这些人不知道时间有多么宝贵。他们一般会对特别喜欢的人说，他们会将一些岁月献出，而且他们确实在无意识中献出了。不过，这份礼物使他们自己有所失却并未使别人有所得。但他们其实并不知道自己是否有所失，这样他们就能承受在自己毫无察觉的情况下造成的损失了。岁月不能倒流，人生无法复原，生命沿着它初始的路线前行，既不会倒退也不作更改。它不会发出响动提醒你它的迅驰，而是无声无息地向前溜走。它不会因帝王的指令或平民的喜好而延长。它从第一天起步，一路前行，没有停顿，没有转向。那么结果呢？当生命匆匆前行的时候，你曾沉迷不悟，这期间死亡降临，而你对此别无选择，只能接受。

还有比自吹有远见卓识的人更白痴的吗？为了改善生活，他们煞费苦心，用生命安排生命。他们把目标设定于遥远的未来。但是拖延就是对生命最大的浪费：它夺走了到来的每一天，冀望未来，而放弃现在。生活的最大障碍就是期待，期待使人心系明天而失去今日。你筹划的是命运掌控的东西，却放弃了自己手中的东西。你在看什么？在为什么目标而操劳？所有的未来都是不确定的：马上开始生活。倾听我们伟大诗人的呼唤吧，他仿佛受到神谕的启示，吟唱出极富教益的诗句：

对于这里不幸的人来说，

生命中最美好的一天总是最先消失的一天。[12]

他的意思是说，“你为什么闲逛？”“你为什么无所事事？你不先抓住它，它就会溜走”。而即使你抓住它，它仍会跑掉。所以你在利用时间时必须使自己适应时间那瞬间即逝的速度，你必须像从一条随时可能枯竭的激流中喝水一样快速敏捷。为谴责那种无休止的拖延，诗人很委婉地用了“最美好的一天”而不是“最美好的岁月”。你贪婪也罢，但为什么要如此漠然如此怠惰拖拉（而时间正在飞逝），把今后几个月几个年头的时间都一溜儿排开摆在眼前？诗人讲的是当下这一天——而且是正在溜走的这一天。所以对于不幸的人——就是那些沉迷于杂务中的人——来说，最美好的一天总是最先溜掉的一天，这难道还有疑问吗？当他们心理还很幼稚时，人却已变老，对此他们毫无准备、毫无设防，因为他们没有准备，突然间不期而遇，根本没意识到它早已一天天逼近。就像旅行者以聊天、阅读或沉思冥想打发时间，不知不觉中发现已经到达目的地。所以在人生这一疾驰不停的旅途中，无论是醒着还是睡着，都是同速前行，那些沉迷于杂务的人只有到旅行结束时才会有所知觉。

如果我要把这个论题分为几个小标题并提供证据，我会找出很多论据来证明：凡是沉迷于杂务的人，都会觉得生命很短促。但是，法比亚诺斯[13]——他绝非现在的学院派哲学家，而是真正老派的哲学家——经常说，我们必须对激情施以暴力攻击，而不能采取逻辑推理，必须对敌人的战线加以猛烈进攻，而不只是用针刺。恶习必须被击溃，不能只是戳戳而已。尽管如此，为了让这些人因自己的过失而反省自责，必须对他们进行教育，而不能放任不管。

生命分为三个阶段：过去、现在和将来。其中，现在是短暂的，将来是不确定的，过去是定型的。对于过去，命运已无力掌控，任何人也无法重新掌控。而这也正是那些沉迷于杂务的人失去的东西，因为他们没有时间回首往事，即便有，回忆那些抱憾终生的事也是不愉快的，所以他们不愿意再次回想那些荒废的时光，如果那些恶习还清晰可现，他们也没有胆量再去回想——即使那些阴险的恶行被一时欢乐的魔力掩饰也是如此。没人愿意回到过去，除非他的所有行为都通过了良心的自我审查，这是无法自欺欺人的。那些不敢回首往事的人都是贪得无厌、妄自尊大、急功近利、见利忘义、巧取豪夺、穷奢极欲之徒。然而过去是我们时间的一部分，是神圣的、独立的，它超越人类面临的一切不幸，超出命运的掌控，不为欲望、恐惧、疾病所困扰，无人能妨碍它，褫夺它，那是一种无法干预的、持久的拥有。我们是一天一天、一分钟一分钟地度过眼前的日子。但是，过去的日子却可以全部出现在你的脑海里。你可以任意扣留它们，审视它们——而那些沉迷于杂务的人是无暇这样做的。这是一种平静的、没有任何烦扰的心境，它可以徜徉于生命的每个阶段，而那些杂务缠身者的心呢，就像套上了马轭不能回头看。所以，他们的生命消失于无底深渊，如同液体倒进无底的容器，徒劳无益。所以，无论给我们多少时间，如果无处安放，它还是会从心里的缝隙或漏洞中溜走。眼前的时间极其短暂，因此很多人都没有意识到它的存在。因为它永远向前，步履匆匆，稍纵即逝；它曾在到来前停息，从此再无耽搁，如同天空抑或星辰，斗转星移，从未原地止步。所以杂务缠身者只关注现在，而现在的时光是如此短暂，根本无法抓住，甚至在他们沉溺于各种娱乐活动时就被窃取了。

总之，你想知道他们为什么不能长寿吗？看看他们是如何渴望长生不老吧。羸弱的老翁乞求再多活几年；他们假装更年轻，并以此自慰，极力欺骗自己的同时也欺骗命运。但是疾病会提醒他们寿数已尽，面对死亡，他们是如此恐惧，似乎不是度过生命，而是被拖拽而去。他们大喊大叫说自己是傻瓜，因为他们还没有真正活过呢，倘若病痛痊愈，他们会悠闲安度余生。接着他们回想起自己巧取豪夺却无缘享受是多么的徒劳，自己的辛苦是多么的徒劳。不过，对于那些远离一切杂务的人来说，生命一定是足够长了，没有挥霍，没有虚度，没有任命运摆布，没有漫不经心的丢失，没有无度施舍而浪费，没有多余的部分，可以说，全部生命都用在了有效的投资上。所以无论生命如何短暂，都是充实的。因此，无论末日何时到来，理智的人都会以坚实的步伐义无反顾地迎接死神的降临。

也许你想知道我把什么人叫作“杂务缠身者”吧。你不会认为我指的是那些得靠看门犬[14]才能逐出法院的人吧，或是那些你常见的要么被自己的支持者体面地、要么被别人的支持者轻蔑地击垮的人，或是那些为履行社会职责从自家蹿出去敲别人家大门的人，或是那些在执政官拍卖矛[15]下忙于钻营而终有一天使自己臭名昭著的人？有人即使赋闲也会让自己杂务缠身：在自家的乡村房舍中，在长椅上，在独处时，甚至在一个人的时候，他们都不能好好陪陪自己。你不能说那些人的生活是悠闲的，那不过是无所事事的心不在焉。你能说那个神情焦虑却一丝不苟地摆弄科林斯铜器的人悠闲吗？几个收藏家的狂热使这些青铜价格虚涨，他们每天大部分时间都花在这些金属的斑斑锈迹上。那个坐在格斗场（我们的耻辱呀！我们还要忍受着那些不是来自罗马的恶行）急切地看着斗士们角逐的人悠闲？那个为自己成群的驮畜按年龄和颜色配对的人悠闲？为竞技新秀提供生活费的人悠闲？还有，有些人在理发店花好几个小时就是为了剪掉一夜之间长出的那点儿头发，跟那几根分散的较真儿，把乱了的理顺，将日渐稀疏的头发从两鬓梳过来盖在前额，理发员稍有不慎他们就会大为光火——就好像他们剪掉的是个真人！如果剪错了，或梳得不对，或没有全部束入发圏，他们就会勃然大怒，你能说他们悠闲？这些人有几个不是任由国家骚乱却不想让自己的头发凌乱，有几个不是对脑袋的潇洒比对它的安全更操心，有几个不是重整洁而轻荣誉？那些把时间都花在梳子和镜子之间的人，你能说他们悠闲？还有一些人，整天忙于作曲、听音乐、学唱歌，他们变着声发出极不自然的音调，而自然设计的最优美最淳朴的音调应该是直接发出来的；有的人总是打着响指，就好像为心里想着的曲调打着节拍，甚至在一些严肃的，甚至是悲痛的场合下你都能听见他们哼着小调。这些人的生活不是悠闲，只能说是闲散地干着事。还有，老天呀，那些宴会，我可不认为那是悠闲的时光。看他们如何紧张地摆放银器，如何认真地让侍者穿上制服，如何焦虑不安地看着厨师处理猪肉，一脸恭敬的奴仆们如何快步流星地忙来忙去，如何熟练地把家禽切成合适的块儿，那些卑微的小奴仆如何小心翼翼地为酒鬼们擦去口水。这一套玩意儿使他们慢慢获得高雅、有品位的名声，这些做法甚至延伸到私生活的所有方面，以致现在若是没有这些铺张虚华，他们便不能吃喝了。

还有些人我也不认为他们是悠闲的。这些人坐在轿子上被抬来抬去，总是那么准时，好像不坐就会有人不答应；另有些人，总得有人告诉他们什么时候沐浴，什么时候游泳，什么时候进餐——过度放纵麻木的头脑使他们萎靡不振，以致自己都不能确定饥饱。我听说有这么一个放纵的人——如果“放纵”可以用来形容那些摒弃了人类生活中一般习惯的人——当被人从浴室抬到轿子上时，他问：“我现在正坐着吗？”你觉得，这个连自己是不是坐着都不知道的人是否知道自己还活着，还能看清现实，还很悠闲呢？我是该在他真不知情的情况下可怜他，还是在他假装不知情的情况下可怜他呢，这很难说。他们确实遗忘了很多东西，但也佯装遗忘了很多东西。他们以某些恶行为乐，以此证明自己的好运：似乎他们是卑微低贱的人，他们知道自己在做什么。这之后看看你是否还会指责那些哑剧演员，他们创作了很多情节抨击骄奢淫逸的作风，其实他们忽略的远比创作的多。这么多难以置信的恶行出现在这一代，表明这个方面真是人才辈出，所以我们现在真的要责备那些忽略了它们的哑剧演员了。想一想，有人如此沉溺于奢华的生活以致得让别人来告诉他是否在坐着！所以这个人不是悠闲自在，得用另外的词语来描述他——有病，或者干脆说他是死人。真正优哉游哉的人会知道自己是不是悠闲的，而这个人半死不活，需要别人告诉他自己身体的姿势——这样的人怎么能控制自己的时间呢？

一一谈论那些把所有时间用在下棋或打球，或精心进行阳光浴的人是很无聊的。那些要郑重其事地从事某种活动来获得乐趣的人不是悠闲之人。譬如，毋庸置疑，那些把时间用在没有价值的文学研究上的人是徒劳无益的——甚至在罗马人中也有很多人在从事这项工作。要搞清尤利西斯有多少桨手，是先有《伊里亚特》还是先有《奥德赛》，以及它们是否是同一个作者，还有诸如此类的其他问题——原本只是希腊人干的傻事。这些内容自己留用，不能增加个人的知识；用于发表，只能令人生厌而无人把你当成学者。而罗马人现在也对这些无用的知识充满了无端的热忱。最近我听到有人报道，诸如哪个罗马将军率先作的这个或者那个传闻：杜伊流斯是赢得海战的第一人，库里乌斯·丹塔图斯率先让大象引领了凯旋队列。至于这些事，即便他们还算不上建立功勋，但至少与对国家作出卓越贡献相关：这些知识毫无用处，之所以让人们感兴趣就是因为这些毫无意义的事实的吸引力。我们还可以原谅那些调查谁是第一个说服罗马人登船的人。是克劳狄乌斯，他因此又被称为科德克斯（Caudex），因为几块木板连在一起的东西在古代被称为Caudex。又因此，法典叫科德克斯（Codices）[16]，而至今，那些在台伯河上运送给养的船仍沿袭过去的名字——科德克利阿（Codicariae）。无疑，了解瓦勒里乌斯·科尔维鲁斯是第一位征服了麦萨拿的人也是颇为重要的，而且他是瓦勒里家族第一个用所征服的城市麦萨拿（Messana）的名字作姓氏的人——这个姓在口口相传中被错拼成麦萨拉（Messalla）。或许你也会容许有些人把卢西乌斯·苏拉第一个放狮子出现在竞技场的事当真吧，虽然通常这些狮子是带着链条展示的，后来国王博库斯派标枪手杀死了它们。了解庞培干的那件事可能也是可以谅解的——但是有意义吗？——他是让十八头大象在竞技场上与无辜之人搏斗的第一人。一个国家的首领，一个据称在老一辈的领导人中尤其慈善的人，竟认为这是令人难忘的以新颖方式屠戮人类的奇观。“让他们战死？不够刺激。把他们撕成碎片？不够刺激。得让硕大无比的动物把他们踩碎”。这类事最好还是永远忘掉，免得将来被某些大权在握的人知道了，这些人可不想有人在干这种惨无人道的事情上超越他们。啊，那繁华盛世给我们心里投下了怎样的阴霾啊。当他让这些不幸的人与野生动物搏斗的时候，当他在罗马人面前制造血流成河的场面，而这些罗马人随即又将被迫流血的时候，他认为自己是超越自然法则的，他可以将那么多可怜的人投向外来的野兽。可后来他自己呢，亚历山大人背叛了他，他最终被最卑微的奴隶刺死，直到那时他才明白，自己的姓氏（Great）不过是虚妄的自吹。

不过，还是言归正传吧，接着谈一些人如何徒劳无益地研究同一些话题。我所提到的那个人汇报说，梅特卢斯在西西里征服了迦太基人以后，用120头大象在他的二轮战车前开道，这在所有的罗马人中独一无二，而苏拉则是最后一个延长城界的罗马人。一旦占领意大利（从来都不是行省）的领土，就延长城界，这是一种古老的做法。了解这些比知道另一件事更好吗？他曾断言，阿芬丁山之所以在城界之外，或是因为平民都撤到那儿，或是因为瑞摩斯神曾在那里占卜说飞禽是不吉利的——后来还有无数理论都是错误的或者几乎无异于谎言。即便你承认他们这样说是出于虔诚，即便他们保证所说的是真实的，但谁的错少一些呢？谁的热情会受到限制呢，会让谁更自由，更公正，更宽宏大量呢？法比亚诺斯曾说，有时他很想知道，干脆什么研究都不搞是不是比总纠缠这些问题好。

在所有人中，只有那些把时间用于研究哲学的人是真正悠游自在的，只有他们算是活着的。因为他们不仅仔细关注自己的人生，而且将所有年代收为己有，把过去所有的岁月都加到自己的岁月里。除非我们不领情，否则应该承认，所有那些书写了神圣教义的伟大先哲都为我们而生，为我们指明人生之路。他人的艰辛工作引导我们，使我们面对的事物从暗昧走向显明。没有任何年代将我们拒之门外，我们可以接近所有时代。如果我们具备了崇高思想，能够跨越人类弱点的狭窄界限，就可以在久远的时间大道上徜徉。我们可以与苏格拉底辩论，向卡尼阿德斯质疑，与伊壁鸠鲁共度退隐的生活，和斯多葛学派的哲学家一起克服人性弱点，与犬儒派学者共同超越人性的局限。既然自然允许我们与每个时代结交，我们为什么不舍弃这短暂的现实，全身心地研究过去呢？那是无尽的、永恒的、可与睿智的先哲共享的时光。

那些为社会职责到处奔波的人不仅扰乱自己，而且侵扰他人的生活。他们要按时完成狂热的巡回，每日穿行于各家各户，不漏掉一家开启的大门，带着自私的问候走遍相隔甚远的家家户户。在如此大的城市，面对各种欲求，他们能拜见到的究竟能有几个人？有多少人因为昏昏欲睡，或正忙于自己的事，或冷漠无理而将他们拒之门外？有多少人让他们煎熬等待多时后，佯装急事在身，从他们身边匆匆而过？有多少人不走挤满门客的大厅而从隐秘的旁门逃走——好像欺骗并不比拒绝更失礼似的？有多少人头天酗了酒此时半睡半醒，慵懒迷糊，不雅地打着哈欠，还要别人低声地、上千遍的提醒，才能连嘴唇几乎都不动地与那个为了等别人睡醒而不得不中断自己睡眠的可怜虫打招呼，叫出他的名字？

你应该这样认为：那些每天希望成为芝诺、毕达哥拉斯、德谟克利特及其他人文学科的宗师，还有亚里士多德和色奥弗拉斯多的密友的人，才是在履行真正有价值的职责。这些人不会因为太忙而不接见你，他们会让到访者高兴地离去，并且更加专注于自身，而绝不会空手而归。他们日夜在家恭候所有人的到访。

他们没有人会强迫你去死，而是教你如何去死。这些人不会耗费你的时间，他们每个人都会将自己的岁月奉献与你。与这些人的谈话不会有任何危险，与他的友谊不会危及你的生命，拜访他无须你付出高昂代价。从他们那里你想拿什么就拿什么，如果没有拿够，那不是他们的错。成为这些人的门客，是多么幸福，老年生活将会多么惬意！你将会有很多朋友，事无巨细都可以向他们讨教，你可以每天就自己的事向他们咨询，这些朋友会告诉你真话但不会刺伤你，表扬你但不会奉承你，他们会为你提供一种仿效模式。

我们总习惯说自己无力选择父母，他们是命运偶然间配送给我们的。但是，我们可以做我们愿意做的任何人的孩子。有很多高尚的才智超群的家庭，选择你希望被收养的那一家，你将不仅继承其姓氏，还能继承其财产。这些财产不需要吝啬小气的看管，分享的人越多，它就越巨大。这些将为你提供一条永生之路，将你带到一个任何人都不会沮丧的地方。这是延续生命——甚至永生不朽的唯一方法。荣誉、纪念碑，无论雄心勃勃的家伙们通过法令颁布什么，或在公共建筑物上竖起什么，它们顷刻之间都会被损毁。没有任何东西是时间的流逝不能将其损毁和移除的，但是它无法损毁那些被哲学界视为神圣的作品，岁月无法消灭、减损它们。下一个、每一个随后的年代，只能使它们备受敬重，因为人们只嫉妒眼前的事物，而对遥不可及的东西却毫不掩饰赞赏之情。所以哲学家的生命可以绵延广阔，不受他人所受的限制。只有他不受人类法则的限制，在所有的年代被视为神明。一些过去的时光，他抓住，藏入记忆；眼下的时光，他利用；未来的时光，他预见：所有这些组合成他绵长的人生。

但是对于忘记过去、忽略现在、恐惧未来的人来说，生命是短暂的、焦灼不安的。在末日到来时，这些可怜的家伙才意识到他们一生无所事事，但为时已晚。有时他们乞求死神的到来，但是这并不能证明他们长寿。愚昧无知使他们焦躁不安而备受折磨，害怕的事情偏偏发生：他们之所以渴望死，是因为他们害怕死。他们感到度日如年，或者在预定吃饭的钟点到来前抱怨每个小时都过得那么缓慢，这些也都不能证明他们活得长久。因为一旦他们没有杂务缠身，他们就会因无事可做、不知如何利用空闲或打发光阴而坐立不安，他们会急于找点儿其他的事情来做，而在这期间他们会厌倦烦躁。确实如此，正如宣布一场角斗开始时，或人们期待某个展览或娱乐活动时的心情一样——他们急于想跳过这中间的一段时间。任何期盼已久的事情的拖延对他们来说都是漫长而乏味的，真正享受的时间是短暂而快速的，而且会由于他们的过失而使这一享受更加短暂，因为他们急匆匆地追求一种又一种的享受，不能固守一种欲望。他们过的每一天不是长久的而是令人懊恼的；另外，在他们酗酒嫖娼的过程中，夜晚似乎也变得短暂了，因而就有癫狂的诗人编撰故事描绘朱庇特沉溺于做爱的欢愉，把夜晚也加长了一倍，以此来助长人性的弱点。他们援引神来支持这些人，让神也变得荒淫无度，还为他们开脱，当成我们过错的先例，这除了加剧恶行还能有什么意义？他们付出高昂代价得到的夜晚对这些人来说难道不是太短暂了吗？他们等待夜幕而失去白昼，惧怕天明而丧失夜晚。

即便在极尽淫乐之时，他们也会因种种恐惧而不安、焦虑。就在纵情享乐达到高潮时，烦躁忧虑的情绪悄然而至。“还能持续多长时间？”这种情绪曾使国王们对手中的权力发出哀叹，想到末日无可避免终究会来，他们惶惶不可终日，这远远胜过好运带给他们的快乐。当波斯国最不可一世的国王[17]派遣军队跨过广袤的平原时，这数不胜数的军队，只能通过估量知晓其规模。想到百年之后这庞大的队伍将无一幸免，他不禁潸然泪下。而正是他这个泪流满面的人给他们带来了厄运，使他们丧生于海洋、陆地、战场及溃逃路上，用不了多久就会全军覆没，而他还在担心他们的百年大限。

是什么使他们即使在高兴时也会忐忑不安？是他们的快乐理由不够充足。快乐是被煽动起来的，没有根基。身居高位的快乐并不牢靠，那些快乐，他们自己都承认是可悲的，又何足挂齿呢？所有的好运都会产生忧患，受到命运垂青时，总是我们最不信命的时候。为了保住已有的成就，我们需要其他的成就；为了证明已经实现的祈祷，我们需要再次祈祷。任何意外所获都是不稳定的，地位越高越容易跌倒。注定要倒台的东西，不能为任何人带来快乐。所以对于那些经过千辛万苦获得的成就要用更大的辛苦保住的人来说，生活必定不但短暂而且痛苦。他们辛辛苦苦获得想要的一切，又要忧心忡忡保有所得的一切，而这当中他们从没有考虑过时间成本，而时光流逝，韶华无返。新的嗜好代替了旧的嗜好，希望激起更多的希望，野心衍生更大的野心。他们没有设法结束苦难，只是不断为它变换理由。我们发现自己在公众中享有的荣耀是一种痛苦，但是却为他人的荣耀花费更多的时间。我们不再费力争当候选人，却又开始为其他人拉票。我们已经摆脱了当起诉人的烦恼，却又处理起当法官的麻烦。有人不再当法官却当起法院院长，在挣钱管理别人财产的工作中年事日高，于是又将所有时间用于照看自己的财产。马略结束戎马生涯却又开始忙于执政官的工作；昆提乌斯很快完成独裁者之职，但又在犁地时被召回；西庇奥在没有足够的指挥经验时就去与迦太基人打仗，打败了汉尼拔，战胜了安提奥库斯，成了杰出的执政官，确保了他弟弟的职位。如果不是他自己禁止，他的塑像就会被立在朱庇特的旁边了。但是国家的动荡困扰着拯救国家的人，他年轻时就蔑视那些只应赋予神的荣耀，最终老了，他执意过着流放的生活，并乐在其中。总有焦虑的原因，或因为富足，或因为窘迫。生活滚滚向前，一个牵绊接着一个牵绊。我们总是渴望悠闲自得的生活，但却从未享受过。

所以，亲爱的保利努斯，从人群中脱身吧。你已经经历了超出自己年龄的太多的狂风暴雨，现在至少应该退隐到一个平静的港湾，想一想经历了多少风浪，多少暴雨——有些是在私人生活中经受的，有些则是在公共活动中。你是积极、勤勉的典范，你的美德长期以来有目共睹，尝试一下，在休闲的生活中如何继续保持。你生命的大部分，当然也是最美的一部分，已经献给了国家，现在也给自己一些时间吧。我不是让你无所事事慵懒怠惰，也不是让你在蒙头大睡和那些大众喜好的娱乐中消磨自身的能量。这不是休息。当你退隐并享受平和的心境，你会发现，有很多比你迄今为止一直积极从事的要重要得多的活动值得你为之忙碌。没错，你是在管理世界的账目，像管理他人的一样严谨，像管理自己的一样仔细，像管理国家的一样认真。在这种难免遭人怨恨的工作中你却赢得了人们的爱戴，但是相信我，读懂自己人生的资产负债表要比看懂玉米生意的负债表更有意义。你要从这光荣、但与幸福生活难以相融的工作中摆脱出来，恢复你旺盛的精力和承担伟大责任的卓越才能。你要想想，年轻时人文学术方面的训练，其目的并非是将成千上万次玉米称重的工作放心地托付于你。你曾向自己承诺要做更有价值、更伟大的事情。他们不缺少称职的、努力工作的人。呆头呆脑的驮畜比纯种马更适合驮重，谁会让马负重而减缓其疾驰的速度呢？再想想，当你勉为其难承担如此繁重的责任时，心情是多么焦虑。你解决的是人们吃饱肚子的问题，饥饿的人们不会听你讲理，不会因受到公平待遇而心平气和，也不会因恳求而让步。最近，就是盖乌斯·恺撒死后的几天里——他死时还心烦意乱呢（如果逝者也有感情就好了），因为他看到罗马人民只有够七天或最多八天的食物维持生计，而他还在建桥造船，滥用国家的资源——我们面临着粮食匮乏最艰难的时刻，这比受围困的人的境况更糟。他仿效别国那个威风扫地的疯子国王，几乎毁掉这个城市，造成饥荒，以及饥荒之后全面的崩溃。那么那些负责谷物供应的人面对石头、武器、火——还有盖乌斯的威胁时怎么想呢？他们以弥天大谎极力掩饰潜藏于国家要害部门的滔天大罪——他们这样做肯定也是情有可原的。某些疾病的治疗是不能让病人了解病情的，要是知道了，会使很多人不治而死。

你应该退休从事这些更安静、更安全、更重要的工作。你认为监督那些狡猾且不负责任的货主将谷物毫发未损地运进谷仓、照看它们不要在热天受潮霉烂并确保其重量与数量相吻合的工作与从事神圣高尚的研究是同样的工作吗？通过这些研究你可以了解神的实质，神的意志，神的生活方式，神的形态，知道什么样的命运在等待你的灵魂，当我们从身体解脱出来时自然会将我们安放何处，是什么力量在中心支撑着世界上所有最重的元素，什么力量使最轻的元素悬浮于上，什么将火送往最高的地方，又是什么使星宿运行变幻有致——你可以不断学到很多无比神奇的其他知识，你真的应该离开那里，全身心投入到研究领域之中。趁现在血还是热的，就应该将精力投入到更有价值的事情上。这样的生活会使你发现很多值得研究的东西：对美德的热爱与实践、对激情的忘却、生与死的知识，以及心平气和的生活。

是的，那些杂务缠身者的状况确实可怜，但最不幸的是那些人，他们甚至不是为自己的杂务缠身而辛苦，而是根据别人的睡觉时间来调整自己的睡眠，根据别人的步法来行走，在爱与恨这些最自主的事情上也要唯他人之命是从。如果这种人想知道他们的生命有多短暂，先让他们想想生命中属于自己的那部分有多稀少吧。

所以，当你见到有人屡次官袍加身，或在广场上名声大振，不要羡慕他们：这些都是以生命为代价获取的。为了某一年代能以他们的名字命名，他们耗尽自己所有的年代。有些人从事业开始就奋斗，一路拼搏，还没有到达自己雄心壮志的巅峰就结束了生命。有些人忍辱负重爬到至尊无上的地位，却又不禁黯然神伤，因为他们所有的艰辛都不过是为了一块墓志铭。有人年事已高便试图作些调整，产生新的希望，以期显得年轻，却发现羸弱的身体已不堪折腾。一位老者上气不接下气地在法庭上为完全陌生的当事人辩护，企图赢得那些根本不知情的旁观者的掌声，这是很丢人的场面。看到一个人在履行职责时累垮也是很不体面的，他并非因劳累过度而精疲力竭，而是因为自己的生活方式。同样丢人的是一个人在查看账目时咽了气，而那个等待已久的继承人笑着舒了一口气。有件事想起来了，不得不说说。塞克斯图斯·图拉纽斯是公认的办事审慎认真的老者。当他九十高龄时，他的退休请求得到了盖乌斯·恺撒的恩准，于是他让人将他放在床上，全家人聚齐哀悼他，好像他已经归天。整座房子都为老主人的歇息而悲哀，直到他又起来恢复工作。以身殉职真的就那么令人愉快吗？很多人都是这样，自己无力工作时仍想工作。他们挑战身体的虚弱，视暮年为痛苦，无端地认为人一老了就被弃置不用了。法律规定五十岁以后不能当兵，六十岁以后不能进元老院，法律赋予人们赋闲的权利，而人们自己却难以接受。掠夺别人又被人掠夺，互相干扰，彼此不得安宁，你使我痛苦，我使你痛苦。在这过程中，生命流逝，生活过得差强人意，缺少欢乐，精神状态也未得到改善。没人把死亡放在心上，没人对好高骛远的理想加以限制。确实，还有些人把身后的事都安顿停当了——规模宏大的墓穴，公共殿堂里的供奉，葬礼时的炫耀，下葬时的铺张。其实，这些人的葬礼只需举着火把和小蜡烛，他们的生命似乎才是最为短暂的[18]。

致赫尔维亚的告慰书[19]

最亲爱的母亲，我常常有一种冲动，想要安慰您，但又总是克制住了。促使我斗胆这样做的原因有很多。首先，当我想到即使不能阻止您流泪，至少可以为您抹去泪水时，我会把我自己所有的烦恼放置一边。其次，如果我能先让自己振作起来，肯定也会更有力量让您振作起来。另外，我担心虽然命运已被我征服，但她却可能征服我身边的亲人。所以，在止住自己的伤口流血之后，我倾尽所能，挣扎向前为您包扎伤口。但另一方面，一些其他的考虑又使我踟蹰不前。我意识到您初创的伤口正疼痛难忍，不该马上触动，以防慰藉本身会刺激它、让它发炎：病痛也一样，没有什么比过早的治疗对它更有害的了。所以我在等待，直到您的悲痛慢慢减轻，让时间来软化它，使它可以经受治疗，可以被触动、解决。此外，虽然我查阅了所有最著名的作者关于如何控制和缓解悲痛的著述，但还是找不到任何关于安慰自己的至亲，而自己本身又是他们所哀痛对象的实例，所以在这种尚无前例的情况下，我犹豫了，担心自己非但不能给您安慰，反而会刺激您的悲伤。而且，一个人从自己的棺椁中抬起头来安慰他的至爱亲人，需要的是那些有别于普通平常词汇的新奇话语。但巨大强烈的悲痛会剥夺人们遣词造句的能力，因为悲痛本身往往会抑制声音的发出。无论如何，我会尽最大力量，不靠小聪明，因为我本人就是慰问者，所以自己也能成为最有效的慰藉。因为您从未拒绝我任何事，所以至少这一次也别拒绝我来终结您的忧伤（尽管悲痛总是很顽固）。

想想由于您的纵容，我对自己作出了怎样的承诺。我毫不怀疑自己对您远比悲伤对您的影响更大，虽然没有什么比悲伤更能影响不幸的人。所以，为了不和它立即发生冲突，我会首先支持它，给它很多鼓励：我会重新揭开、暴露那些已经愈合的伤口。有些人会反对：“这算什么安慰，把已忘却的疾病又找回来，在心灵几乎无法忍受伤痛的情况下，让它又看到所有的悲痛？”但是想一想，那些危及生命的病尽管经过治疗，还是难以除根，这类病一般来说是要采取逆向疗法的。所以我要让心灵先感受痛苦，给它穿上丧服，这不是温和的处方，而是烧灼与刀割。我想达到什么目的？我要获得一颗战胜了很多苦难的心灵，这样的心灵羞于为伤痕累累的身体上又出现一个伤口而焦虑。所以让那些人继续哭泣、哀叹吧，长久的安乐生活已经将他们自我放纵的心灵变得很脆弱，让他们受到微小伤痛的威胁就崩溃吧，而让那些长期经受苦难的人们以勇敢坚强来忍受最大的伤痛。长久的不幸确有好的一面，它使饱受折磨的人最终变得坚忍不拔。

命运从未停止给您带来痛苦，甚至连您出生的那一天都未能幸免。您一出生，不，甚至您正在出生时就失去了母亲，在生命的初始就有了被遗弃的感觉。您在继母的照顾下长大，是您用亲生女儿般的敬重与孝顺使她成为一位名副其实的母亲。然而，即便有一个好继母也会让孩子付出很大代价。正当您期盼舅舅的到来时，您却失去了他——一个最善良、最优秀、最勇敢的人。祸不单行，命运似乎唯恐还不够残酷，不到一个月的时间您又掩埋了给了您三个孩子的最亲爱的丈夫。噩耗传来，您还沉浸在悲痛之中，而三个孩子又都不在身边。厄运似乎有意集中到这个时候，使您的悲哀无处宣泄。危难与恐惧不断向您袭来，我不再一一赘述。但最近同样的厄运再次袭来，您放三个孙子出门，取回来的却是他们的三具尸骨。我的儿子在您的怀抱中，在您的亲吻中死去。掩埋他不到二十天，您就听到我被带走的消息。您还不曾为生者悲伤。

在所有刺痛您的伤害中，我承认，最后一个是最令您伤心的，岂止是切肤之痛，简直是撕心裂肺、五内倶焚。但是正如新兵，即使表皮受点伤也会尖叫，害怕医生给他处理伤口，好像那比刀刺都可怕；而老兵呢，即使伤势很重，也会忍着一声不吭地让医生清理伤口，似乎身体不是自己的，所以您现在必须勇敢地等待疗伤。好啦，把那些哭泣、悲伤，以及女人们通常悲哀的聒噪表示都收起来吧。如果您还没有学会如何承受不幸，那些痛苦您就白受了。我看起来对您这样够胆大了吧？我没有隐藏您所遭受的任何苦难，而是把它们全堆到您面前。

我已经在勇敢对您进行治疗了，因为我决定要战胜您的苦痛，而不是自欺欺人。而且，如果我首先就能表明，在我这样的情况下，我所有的一切都不足以称为不幸（更不用说会让那些亲属感到不幸了），然后，我能够向您表明您的命运同样不是痛苦的，因为您的命运完全取决于我的命运，我想我就能征服您的痛苦了。

首先，我要陈述一个事实，这是您出于爱而希望听到的：我并没有受苦。我说得清楚些，如果能的话，那种处境，就是您以为会令我崩溃的处境，是可以忍受的；但是如果您不相信，至少我对自己能够在别人感到很不幸的处境中活得很愉快这点是很满意的。没有必要相信别人对我的传言，我肯定地告诉您我并没有什么不幸的，这样您就不要半信半疑地焦虑苦恼了。为让你放心，我还要告诉您，根本没有什么能让我不幸。

我们生在原本优越的环境中，是我们放弃了这种环境。幸福的生活不需要什么优良的装备，这是自然的本意，每一个人都能使自己幸福，外部的东西并不重要，顺境与逆境都没有多大的影响。顺境不能抬高圣贤，逆境也无法使他压抑，因为他总是尽最大可能地依靠自己，从自身获取全部的乐趣。那又如何？我把自己称为先哲了？当然没有。如果我能，我不仅会否认自己是不幸的，我还要声称自己是最幸运的，已经离神很近了。正如现在这样，为了尽最大努力来减少不幸，我现在已经拜倒在智者的脚下，由于自己还未坚强到可以自助，我就投身于另一阵营——我是指那些能够很轻松地保护自己及其追随者的人们。他们命令我像站岗的卫兵一样站稳，还要能够尽早地预见命运的进攻与突袭。命运总是猛烈袭击那些毫无预警的人，而那些对其早有预警的人就会轻而易举地抵挡她的进攻。敌人的到来只会使那些疏于警戒的人溃不成军，而对于那些在战争来临之前早就列队整装、从容应对的人来说，他们可以轻松地抵御敌人的首次进攻，而首次冲击往往是最猛烈的。我从来未敢相信命运，即便有时她看似平和。所有她好心施惠于我的东西——金钱、官职、权势——我都束之高阁，以便将来她索要之时可以直接从那里拿走而不必烦扰我。我一直与这些东西保持很大的距离，所以她只是将它们取走了，而不是夺走。如果不是最初被命运的恩惠所骗，人们是不会在受到她的攻击时溃散的。那些喜欢她的礼物，把它们当成自己永远所有，并想因之受到别人羡慕的人，在那虚假短暂的快乐背弃了他们虚伪、幼稚、无视长久快乐的心智时，就会变得低三下四、伤心欲绝。但是，在顺境中不飘飘然的人在形势发生变化时就不会崩溃。他已经经过考验变得坚忍不拔，保持面对任何境遇都不可战胜的心态：因为幸运时他已练就自己应对逆境的力量。所以，我从来不相信在人们祈望得到的东西中有什么是真正的好处，而且我发现它们都是空虚的，外表涂有耀眼诱人的色彩，而内部全然无法与之相匹配。而现在，在这些所谓的罪恶中，我并没发现什么可怕或险恶的东西，一般的看法都是危言耸听。当然，受到某种成见和流行的观念的影响，“流放”这个词听起来更加刺耳，让听者感到郁闷、厌恶。因为这是大众的看法，而智者总的说来并不接受大众的看法。

所以，把这多数人的判断放到一边，因为这些人被事情的表面所蒙蔽，不管他们相信表象的原因是什么，还是让我们好好看看流放的实质吧：很清楚，就是换个地方。我不应该缩小它的力量，抹掉它最坏的特点，所以我同意，换个地方会带来诸如贫穷、耻辱、遭受蔑视这些弊端。这些我会在后面谈到，同时还要谈谈更换处所所带来的苦恼。

“被驱逐出自己的国家，这简直难以忍受。”好吧，看看这群人，偌大的罗马几乎容纳不下他们，而这些人大部分都背井离乡。他们从自己的城市或属地，应该说从世界各地，聚集到一起，有的心怀抱负，有的履行公务，有的肩负使命，有的就是想找一个乌七八糟的地方以方便自己沉溺于某种恶习，有的怀着对人文研究的热爱，有的参观公演，有的为了友谊，有的精力旺盛来寻得一方广阔天地以展示自己的才能，有的出卖色相，有的推销辩才。各色人等都迫不及待地涌入这个既看重美德也放纵恶行的城市。挨个问问他们来自何方，你会发现大多数人是背井离乡来到一个伟大、漂亮，但不属于自己的城市。且不说罗马这个堪称属于所有人的城市，看看其他地方，每个城市里大部分人口都是移民。且不说那些位置优越方便而吸引很多人的城市，单是那些人烟稀少满是石头的岛屿，西阿苏斯和赛里婆斯，吉阿鲁斯和柯苏拉，你会发现所有这些流放地都有人愿意逗留。在这到处都是陡峭岩石的不毛之地上能找到什么？还有比这里的资源更匮乏的吗？还有比这里的人更野蛮的吗？还有比这里的地形更崎岖不平的吗？还有比这里的气候更反复无常的吗？然而，在这里居住的外来人比本地人还多。所以更换处所并不就是苦差事，连这样的地方都能吸引人们离开自己的家乡。我曾无意中听人说过，在人的精神中有一种天生的不安分和渴望易地而居的冲动，人有一种求变、不安分的禀赋，它使人在任何地方都不能安于静止不动，而是到处奔走，向往那些已知的未知的地方，如同一个流浪者无法忍受止步不前，而主要以猎奇为乐。想想它的起源其实并不奇怪。它不是起源于质重、尘世的物质，而是来自天国的精神，而天国的本质就是永动，以极快的速度流动驱走。看看那些点亮世界的星宿，没有一个是静止的。太阳永不停止地运行，从一个地方到另一个地方，虽然它同宇宙一起旋转，但其实是与天宇背道而驰。它经过黄道十二宫，不停运行，从一点到另一点，它的运动是永恒的。所有的行星都旋转而过，按不可抗拒的自然规律，从一开始就从一点到另一点地运行。经过固定的年限，完成巡行的路程之后，它们会重新开始，按先前的路线运行。人的思想成分和神造之物一样，所以当神造的自然在不停的极速运动中找到乐趣，甚至得以自我存续时，想到人们会反对迁移，反对易地而居该是多么愚蠢啊。

好了，现在把您的注意力从天上转到人间吧，您会看到，所有的国家和民族都改变了居所。希腊的城市为什么建立在荒蛮的土地上？为什么我们在印度人和波斯人中听到马其顿语？塞西亚和所有凶悍野蛮部落占据的广阔地区上却出现了蓬托斯沿岸的希腊城市，那里漫长的严冬和与天气相匹配的土著人的野蛮性格都无法阻止人们迁徙的活动。在亚洲有一群雅典人，米利都派出足够的人员对七十五个城市进行殖民，被下游海水冲刷的整个意大利海岸曾经是大希腊。亚洲声称伊特鲁里亚人归她所有；提尔人住在非洲，腓尼基人住在西班牙；希腊人迁入高卢，而高卢人移到希腊；比利牛斯山没有挡住日耳曼人迁徙的通道——走过没人踩过的道路，穿过无人知晓的土地，他们挑战人类不安分的特性，随后又接来妻子、孩子和年迈的父母。有些人长期流浪并未刻意选择落脚地，但是旅途的疲劳使他们随即定居在一个最近的地方；有些人通过武力在别国立住了脚；有些部落在寻找未知地时全部被大海淹没了；有些又因为给养殆尽而陷入进退两难的境地，于是便定居下来。人们背井离乡迁往别处的原因不尽相同，有的因为敌军进攻城市沦陷而逃离，失去自己的家园而被迫远走他乡；有些因民事纠纷而被驱除；有些是因为人口太多而被迫移民；有些是因为疫病，或地震，或土地贫瘠物资匮乏而无法生存；还有那些关于沿海地区非常富足的夸大其词的报道，使有些人抵挡不住诱惑。不同的原因使不同的人离家出走，但至少这一点是清楚的——任何东西都没有停留在它的起点。人类总是在迁徙，大千世界每天都有变化——新的城市建立起来，新的国名出现，旧的消失，或者被更为强大的国家吞并。但是这些国家的迁徙除了使一个民族离境出走还有别的意义吗？我为什么要和您兜这么大圏子？为什么不厌其烦提到安特诺建立帕塔维乌姆，伊万德将阿卡迪亚王国建立在台伯河畔？狄俄墨得斯和其他人怎样？他们既是征服者，又是被征服者，特洛伊战争把他们撒落在他乡的土地上。唉，罗马帝国本身就曾把流放者当成它的缔造者，就是那个人，当他的故国沦陷后怀着对得胜者的恐惧，被迫带着几个幸存者，背井离乡，长途跋涉，来到意大利。接着，这个民族又在每个行省建了多少殖民地！罗马人每攻克一地，便在那里定居下来。老百姓自愿加入这样的移民行列，甚至连老人也会离开自己家的祭坛，移居海外。这一点无须进一步阐明，但我还要加上一个您眼前的例子：就是这个岛屿，它的居民就在经常更换。更不用说那些年长日久的已经说不清了的事了，现在住在马赛的希腊人，他们离开福西斯后首先就定居在这个岛上，后来不知什么原因他们迁走了，是因为气候恶劣，还是因为看到意大利人权倾天下，抑或是因为缺少海港。但显然不是由于当地人的野蛮，因为他们在高卢时就居住在当时最凶蛮未开化的人中间。随后，利古里亚人来到这个岛，西班牙人也来了，证据便是他们有着相似的风俗习惯：科西嘉人戴的头巾、穿的鞋都和坎塔布里亚人相同，使用的一些词汇也相同——只有一部分，因为他们的语言在与希腊语和意大利土语融合过程中，总体上已经失去了本地的特征。接下来，罗马公民的两个属地的居民又被带到这里定居，一个是马略遣送来的；另一个是苏拉遣送来的。这块贫瘠的不毛之地人口变更得却如此频繁！总之，您很难找到一个国家仍然只住着本土的原住民。各地都是五方杂处，四海融融，一拨儿接着一拨儿：这伙人向往的是那伙人看不上的；一个人赶走了别人，另一个人又把他赶出去。所以命运注定任何东西都不会永远保持一成不变。

为了给真正的迁徙以补偿，并忘掉由于流放所引发的其他不便，罗马最博学的人法罗认为，我们无论走到哪里，所面对的自然秩序都是相同的，这一点足够补偿了。马库斯·布鲁特斯认为流放者自己的美德是随身携带的，这一点就足够了。即便有人认为这两点分开来看都不足以慰藉流放者，他也得承认两者结合在一起具有无上的力量。因为无论走到哪儿，只要有宇宙的本性和个人的德行这两种最宝贵的东西陪伴，我们失去的就微不足道了。相信我，这是造物主的意旨，无论是全能的神，还是创造巨著的无形力量，还是以均等压力渗透于所有从最大到最小物质的神圣精神，还是命运之神及不可改变的因果顺序——我认为，这就是他的意旨，即我们财产中最没有价值的东西才会被置于别人的掌控之下。人类最好的东西是不受人类控制的：它既不能被赠予更不能被取走。自然所创造的伟大、辉煌的世界，以及注视它、惊叹它，并成为其中最耀眼部分的人的思想，是我们永恒的财产，将与我们同在。所以，满怀热切的希望，挺直胸膛，让我们以勇敢的步伐快速按境遇所指示的方向行进，让我们行走于任何国度：这个世界上没有流放地，因为对于人类来说没有什么地方是异国他乡，从地球表面的任何一点遥望苍穹，神的领地与人之间的距离都是相等的。因此，只要我的眼睛不离开那些永远看不够的景象；只要我能仰望太阳、月亮，凝视其他的行星；只要我能追踪它们的盈昃升落，发现它们运行快慢的周期和原因；只要我能看到所有夜空中闪烁的星宿——有些原地不动，有些并未远行而是绕地环行，有些倏忽弹出，有些火花四射令人炫目缭乱，像是要坠落人间，抑或又拖着闪亮长尾一扫而过；只要我能够与它们交流，像人类至今可以做到的那样，与神结盟；只要我的心可以永远向上，努力追寻这类的光景——那么我立于何方又有什么关系呢？

“但是这个国家并不富足，没有苍翠繁茂、果实累累的树木；没有可供航行并以其河道之水灌溉国土的大河；它物产匮乏，连自己的居民都难以为继，更无他国所稀缺的东西，没有贵重的大理石可以开采，没有金银矿脉可以挖掘。”但是只对世俗的东西感兴趣是狭隘的心理，应该将其引向万方倶在、万方倶亮的东西。还须想到的是，由于人们对虚假物品的随意相信，世俗的东西会妨碍人们对真实物品的认识。柱廊越长，大厦建得越高，步道越宽，避暑洞穴挖得越深，餐厅的穹顶盖得越大，天国的景象也就越多地被遮蔽。命运将你抛向一个地方，在那里，最豪华的住处不过是一间棚屋。如果你知道关于罗慕路斯[20]小屋的故事而能勇敢地忍受这一点，那么你真的就会有一种无所谓的态度，而这也是少许的慰藉。你应这样说：“我想，这个简陋的小屋是庇护美德的，当人们看到那里有正义、节制、智慧、虔诚、能正确分配责任的制度、人与神的知识，它随之就会变得比任何庙堂都壮丽了。能够聚集如此多的高尚品德的地方不能算是狭小的，能与此相伴的流放不能说是痛苦的。”

布鲁图斯[21]在他的《论品德》一文中说，他看到马塞卢斯[22]在米提勒涅流放时过着人性所能享有的快乐生活，而且对人文学科产生了从未有过的兴趣。而且，他加了一句说，当他打算离开马塞卢斯返回罗马时，他觉得自己要被流放，而不是把别人留在流放地。马塞卢斯感到这时能因流放而赢得布鲁图斯的好感比因执政官之职赢得全国的好感要幸运得多！因为自己留在了流放地而让别人感到他自己才是个流放者，这是怎样的一个人啊？赢得别人，一个甚至连他的亲戚加图都尊崇的人的赞赏该是怎样的一个人啊[23]？布鲁图斯还说盖乌斯·恺撒不肯在米提勒涅停船，因为让一个伟大的人饱受屈辱他实在看不过去。确实，元老院接受了公众将他召回的请求，他们那么急切，那么忧伤，那天他们好像都与布鲁图斯有同感，好像不是为马塞卢斯请愿，而是为他们自己，如果他回不来，他们将要被流放。但是在布鲁图斯不忍离去、恺撒不忍看他被流放的时候，他收获的要多得多，因为两者都证明：布鲁图斯因抛下他而独自返回而伤心，而恺撒因惭愧而脸红。马塞卢斯这样伟大的人物会经常鼓励自己以平和的心态来忍受流放，这您会质疑吗？“没有国家并不会痛苦，通过深入的研究您已经明白，对于一个聪明的人来说，每个地方都是他的国家。另外，那个使你被流放的人不是连续十年都远离他的祖国吗？当然，他是为了拓展疆土——但他确实离开了自己的国家。看啊，他现在应征去了非洲，那里战事一触即发；去了西班牙，那里正重拾溃败的残部；到了危机四伏的埃及——简而言之，到了整个世界——那里的人虎视眈眈，伺机反抗千疮百孔的罗马帝国。他首先要面对什么问题？在什么地方立住脚？他自己的胜利进程使他奔波于世界各地。让列国都尊敬他、仰慕他吧，而你只要有布鲁图斯这样的仰慕者就可以心满意足地生活！”

马塞卢斯那时承受着流放生活，虽然穷困，但是他的心并未因易地而居而有所改变。穷困并非罪恶，任何一个人，只要还没贪婪、奢侈到疯狂的地步，就会认同这一点。贪婪和奢侈会毁掉一切。维持一个人的生活所需的是多么微不足道啊！如果他有什么德行的话谁会差这一点点？就我而言，我知道自己失去的不是财富而是那些分心的事。身体的需要微乎其微，只要不受冻，能吃饱喝足有营养就行。如果再渴望更多的东西就会增加我们的恶癖，而不是我们的所需。我们无须搜遍海洋，或屠宰动物来填充我们的肚腹，或到天涯海角那不知名的海滨捕捉贝类海产。愿神诅咒那些穷奢极欲的人，他们骄奢的触角已超出了帝国的疆界，引发了嫉恨。他们远去斐西斯狩猎以填储自己那自命不凡的厨房，他们不知羞耻地向帕提亚人索要禽类，而我们还未遭到这些人的报复。他们从各地搜寻那些刁嘴馋舌的家伙们喜闻乐见的食物。从天涯海角弄来食物，他们那被奢靡的饮食宠溺了的肠胃根本无法接受，吐是为了吃，吃是为了再吐，从世界各地搜刮来的美食大餐他们甚至无法消化。对此鄙夷的人，贫穷会对他有什么不好吗？对渴望这种生活的人来说，贫穷对他更有益：不情愿中他就得到了医治。即便受到强迫他也不吃药，一段时间内他无法得到那些东西，至少看起来也就和他不想要一样了。盖乌斯·恺撒这个人我认为是自然造就的职位最高、最邪恶的一个典型。他一天要吃掉价值一千万塞斯特斯[24]的食物，虽然所有人都费尽心思来帮他，他却仍想不出如何一顿饭耗掉三个行省进贡的钱财的办法。可怜虫，只有昂贵的菜肴才能引起他们的食欲。而之所以昂贵并非由于味道香、口感好，而是由于它们珍稀，得来不易。另外，如果这些人都改邪归正了，那些伺候肠胃的技艺哪儿还有用武之地呀？哪儿还需要进口贸易、砍伐森林、搜罗海洋呀？大自然已将制作食物的一切准备齐全分布于各地，但是人们视而不见，反而各国搜寻，不惜远渡重洋，本来花一点点钱就可以满足的口腹之欲，他们却不惜重金。我想对他们说：“为什么你们要乘船远航？为什么要用武力对付牲畜和人类？为什么总是惊恐万状、狼奔豕突？为什么财富堆积如山？你真的需要想想自己的身体有多小。明明只能容纳一点却总是想要很多，这难道不是疯狂或神经严重错乱吗？所以，虽然你可以提高收入扩大地产，但是你永远无法扩充身体的容量。虽然你的生意经营不错，打仗也能发横财，虽然你可以狩猎，到处掠取食物，你却没有地方储存这些给养。你为什么想要得到这么多东西？可以肯定，我们的祖先会不高兴，他们的德行至今还支撑着我们的恶习，他们用自己的双手获取食物，他们席地而睡，他们住的地方没有闪闪发光的金子，他们的庙宇没有镶嵌宝石——所以那时候他们在黏土做的神像前祈祷并庄严发誓，宁可回到敌阵去死也不会违背誓言[25]。可以肯定，我们的独裁者[26]在接见萨姆奈特使节时，还亲手做着最简单的饭（这手曾多次摧毁敌人，将月桂花环[27]放在卡彼托奈山丘的朱庇特膝上）——他不如我们时代的阿皮休斯[28]幸福，在阿皮休斯所在的那个城市里，哲学家曾被说成是腐蚀青年的人而被驱除，他作为烹调技师用他的教导亵渎了这个时代。”关于他的故事值得一听。当他在厨房花光了一亿塞斯特斯，当他在狂喝豪饮中耗尽了所有帝国的馈赠与巨额国家税收时，迫于债务的重压，他第一次查看了自己的账务，计算出账上只剩一千万塞斯特斯，而靠一千万塞斯特斯生活无异于要过食不果腹的日子，所以他服毒自尽了。有一千万塞斯特斯还认为是贫穷，多么奢侈！你又怎么会认为重要的是钱财的数量而不是心态呢？有人因为有一千万塞斯特斯而心生畏惧，别人求之不得的，他却躲之不及服毒而死。不过真的，对于一个心态反常的人来说，最后的豪饮乃最为风光之时，此时，他不仅是在享受，而且还在炫耀他那盛大的宴会，展示他的恶习，引起人们关注他那粗俗的表演，唆诱青年人效仿他（那些人即便没有坏人做榜样也会自然而然受到影响）——再后来，他就真的服食毒药。这就是这种人的命运，他们衡量财富不是用界限固定的理性标准，而是以放荡不羁、为所欲为、反复无常的有害的生活方式。任何东西都无法满足贪心欲壑，但是区区少量就可以让自然的天性知足。所以流放的贫困生活并非苦难，再贫困的流放地总还是可以让一个人丰衣足食。

“但是，”有人说，“流放地会让人怀念自己的服装和房子。”这些也只有在他需要时才会想念——而他既不缺房子又不缺衣服，因为身体对于遮蔽之物的需求和对食物的需求一样是很少的。而且自然也并未让人类生存的必需品难以获取。但是他非要将布料染上浓浓的紫色，用金线编织，并饰以五颜六色的图案。如果他感到穷困，那是他自己的问题。即便将所有他失掉的东西还给他，你也是枉费心机，因为一旦流放回来，他会更加失落，因为他想得到而得不到的东西远远多于他流放时失去的财富。但是他必须有家具，这些家具光彩照人，上面摆放着知名艺术家制作的金容器、古代的银盘、因只有几个疯子想要拥有而显得很值钱的铜器，挤满整个房子的奴隶，无论房子有多大，还有那些因拼命喂食而身体肥硕的驮畜，以及从各地采运来的大理石。虽然这些东西堆积成山，仍不能满足他那贪婪的灵魂：正如某人并非由于缺水而是由于极度内热对水产生渴求，那么他喝多少水都无济于事，因为那不是渴，而是一种病。不仅仅钱和食物是这样的，所有不是因为缺乏、而是因为贪婪这种恶癖而产生的欲望都具有同样的性质。无论堆积多少，都不能表示贪欲结束，而只不过是它的一个阶段。所以将自己限制在自然设定的范围内的人，不会自觉贫困，而那些越过限制的人无论多么富有却永远为贫穷所困扰。即便在流放地也能找到生活的必需品，相反即使身在王国中，也感受不到富足。是思想创造了财富，这样的财富与我们同往流放地，在荒无人烟的艰苦地方，它可以找到充足的食物来滋养我们的身体，尽享其物产。钱与神灵无关，同样也与心智无关。所有那些未受教化且受制于身体的心灵所崇拜的东西——大理石、金子、银子、光洁的大圆桌——都是世俗的负担，一个纯洁、深谙其本质的灵魂不会喜欢它们，因为它轻浮且不沉重，一旦从体内释放，便一定会飞扬直上。同时，由于不受四肢及裹挟我们的重负的阻碍，它能以带着翅膀快速飞翔的思想纵览神异之物。灵魂是自由的，类似于神的，与整个宇宙及所有的时间平等，它永远不会被流放，它的思想环绕整个天宇，行走于过去和未来的所有时间。这不幸的身体，灵魂的桎梏与囚牢，被抛来抛去，惩治、掠夺、疾病肆虐其上。然而，灵魂本身是圣洁的、永恒的、不受暴力攻击的。

如果您认为我仅仅是用哲学家的说教轻描淡写地讲述穷困的历练，把穷困说成除非本人认为，否则没人能感觉到的负担，那么首先想想：到目前为止大多数人都是穷困的，而您却看不到他们堪比富人的阴郁和焦虑。其实，我倒觉得他们更幸福，因为他们的心灵较少受到困扰。咱们接下来再谈富人，他们常常和穷人一样！他们出国时行李要受限制，每当要加快行程时，就得解散大批的随从。在军队服役时，由于军营纪律禁止奢侈，他们只能带多么少的行李！并非只有在特殊时间和场合他们才在需求方面被置于与穷人同等的水平，当他们一旦厌倦了富人的生活，他们会找出几天坐在地上吃饭，把那些金银容器搁置一旁，使用起陶制的器皿。真是疯了，有时竟然向往自己总是惧怕的那种生活状况。多阴暗的心理！多么无知盲目，他们畏惧贫困，却又以模仿贫困为乐！就我而言，每当我回顾往古那些范例，我都会为贫穷寻找慰藉而感到惭愧，因为奢侈竟已到了如此地步：一个流放者的津贴竟然比过去重要人物的遗产还多。众所周知，荷马有一个奴隶，柏拉图有三个，而芝诺，严格而富有生气的斯多葛哲学的创始人，却没有奴隶。如果不是本人亲口说出自己非常可怜的境遇，谁会从这些方面说他们很不幸呢？门尼涅斯·阿格里帕以调解贵族与平民之间的矛盾来维护社会的和平与安宁，他死后是公众捐款埋葬的。当阿提利乌斯·雷古勒斯在非洲追击迦太基人的时候，他给元老院写信说，他家的雇工走了，家里的田地无人照看了，元老院投票决定在雷古勒斯不在家的时候，他家的田地由国家照管。自家无奴隶而让罗马人民成了他家的佃户，这难道不值得吗？西庇奥女儿们的嫁妆来自国库，因为她们的老爸没给她们留下任何东西：罗马人民为西庇奥捐赠一次无疑也是对的，因为他不断强迫迦太基人进贡。女儿们的丈夫，有了罗马人民做他们的岳父是多么幸福！你认为那些把伶人的女儿以一百万塞斯特斯的嫁妆出聘的人会比自己孩子由元老院监护、收到实实在在的铜币作为嫁妆的西庇奥还快乐吗？有谁会蔑视家世如此显赫的贫穷？西庇奥置办不起女儿们的嫁妆，雷古勒斯缺少干活的人手，门尼涅斯无钱办葬礼时，倘若流放者知道这些，他们还会怨恨缺这少那吗？难道这些人要什么有什么，会更让我们尊敬？有这些人为贫穷辩护，贫穷不仅不是罪恶，反倒成了荣誉。

有人可能会回答：“有些事情单独发生尚可忍受，同时发生则难以忍受，你为什么非要分开来谈呢？易地而居如果仅是地点的改变，是可以忍受的。贫穷若不失体面也可忍受——丢掉体面这一件事就足以令人崩溃。”在回答这个想用一大堆不幸来吓唬我的人时，应该这样说：“如果你有力量对付某一方面的不幸，你就能对付所有方面的不幸。一旦道德使思想变得坚韧，它就会使各方面都变得刀枪不入。如果贪欲这一人类最难遏制的毛病不再能控制你，野心就不会挡道。如果你不把自己的末日看作惩罚而将它视为自然规律，把对死亡的恐惧从胸中驱逐，就不会再有恐惧胆敢进入。如果你认为性欲之于男人不是愉悦而是为了繁殖后代，一旦你能摆脱这种植根于身体命脉的强烈而有破坏作用的激情，那么其他的欲望就会悄悄离你而去。理智击溃恶习不是各个击破，而是一举全面击溃，胜利是最终的、全面的。”你认为耻辱会影响完全依靠自己、超然于大众信念的智者吗？可耻地死去比耻辱更糟糕，而苏格拉底走进监狱时的表情同他过去蔑视三十僭主时[29]的一样——他的到来甚至使监狱一扫耻辱，因为只要苏格拉底在，那里就不算监狱。谁能无视事实，认为马库斯·加图竞选地方长官和执政官而两次落选是耻辱？耻辱是属于地方长官和执政官的，而这两个职务因加图而光荣。没有人会被他人蔑视，除非他自己先蔑视自己。卑贱低下的心理对于这类侮辱是非常敏感的；而如果一个人能使自己面对最痛苦的灾难，并且能击败曾压倒别人的邪恶，那些苦难就像是一枚神圣的勋章佩戴在他身上。我们一般倾向于赞赏那些在逆境中表现刚毅的人，所以当阿里斯德岱斯[30]被带到雅典的法场，所有见到他的人都垂目低吟，好像受到惩罚的不仅是一名正义之士，而且是正义本身。然而一个家伙真的朝他的脸上吐唾沫。他本可以对此感到憎恶，因为他知道只有嘴巴肮脏的人才敢这样做。但是他没有，而是擦了擦脸，笑着对护送的地方官说：“警告那个家伙，让他下次不要再这么粗鲁地打哈欠了。”这就是用侮辱来回报侮辱。我知道有人会说，没有比鄙视更令人难以接受的了，连死亡都似乎比它舒服。对这些人的话，我的答复是，流放往往还能使人免遭任何鄙视。如果一个伟人倒下了仍能保持伟大，人们不会鄙视他，就像他们踏在倒塌的寺庙上，虔诚的人们照样对它顶礼膜拜，就像它耸立时候一样。

最亲爱的妈妈，既然您没有理由因为我而没完没了地流泪，那么应该是因为您自身的原因而伤心落泪了。这其中原因有二：您是因为自己似乎失去了某些保护而烦恼，或者因为一想到我不在您身边就感到无法忍受。

这第一点，我只少说几句，我知道您心中对亲人的爱只是为他们着想。让那些母亲想想吧，她们因为身为女人缺少权势就剥夺孩子的权势；由于自己没有职务，只能通过儿子来寻求权力，不仅花光了儿子的遗产，而且还企图从儿子那里获得遗产，她们假别人以口才而让自己的儿子疲于应对。而您为儿子们的所得感到高兴却几乎没有利用过它们；您的慷慨是无限的，却限制我们过分慷慨。当您父亲还健在的时候，您却给有钱的儿子们送礼物。您管理我们遗产的认真程度就像管理自己的，小心谨慎的程度就像管理别人的。您谨慎地利用我们的影响，就好像那是别人的；在我们履行职务期间，您除了高兴喜悦和吃穿用度，再没有掺和其中。您的爱从没有考虑个人利益。因而，即使您的儿子从您身边被带走，您也不会觉得缺少了什么东西，因为当儿子安全健康的时候，您从未觉得那些与您有关。

我必须完全从那个真正能使一位母亲感到悲哀的角度来安慰您。您说：“那么我被剥夺了拥抱我最亲爱的儿子的权利，我再也不能感受见到他或和他聊天的快乐了。那个一出现就能抚平我愁眉的人在哪儿？那个我可以倾诉悲哀的人在哪儿？我们那从未厌倦的聊天哪儿去了？我曾以超出女人的热忱，超出母亲的亲近与他分享的研究哪儿去了？我们的会面到哪儿去了？那个一见到自己母亲就总是像个孩子似的笑个不停的人哪儿去了？”除了这些，您还提到了我们愉快聚会和社交的具体地点，以及能够使我们想起最近一起生活的情形，这些必然都是最敏感的、促使您心情极其痛苦的缘由。命运甚至阴谋策划了这一对您的残酷打击，在我被贬黜的前两天，您才离开，心情平静，没有理由对这样的灾难担心、惧怕。如果我们以前就相隔遥远，如果多年不在您身边能使您对这一打击有所准备就好了。直到返回罗马，您都没有享受到儿子在跟前的快乐，却对他不在跟前感到很不习惯。如果您很早就离开，您就会更勇敢地面对这一缺憾，因为我们之间的距离可以淡化彼此的思念。如果您没有离开，至少还可以享受多看儿子两天的最后的快乐。现在的情况是，残酷的命运作出如此安排，使您没能看到我的不幸，又无法习惯我的不在。但是情况越是不利，您越要鼓起更大的勇气，更勇猛地战斗，像对付一个您了解并经常能打败的敌人一样。您的血现在不是从未受伤害的身体里淌出：您正受到打击，在旧伤之上。

您不能因为自己是女人就原谅自己，女人实际上有极度悲哀的权利，但不是无休止地悲哀。鉴于此，我们的前辈允许寡妇服丧十个月的时间，为的是采取折中的办法以公开的法令来限制女人们无法抑制的悲痛。他们不是禁止悲哀，只是限制。因为痛失亲人而无休止地悲哀使自己饱受折磨是愚蠢的自我放任，而没有任何表示又是无人性的冷酷无情。在爱与理智之间最好的折中办法就是既要思念又要克制这种情感。您不会对那种一旦悲痛便至死方休的妇人表示尊重吧——您知道有些人儿子死了就穿上丧服，从此不再脱下。您的一生从开始就比她们坚强，因而希望您会更坚强：一个没有任何女性弱点的女人，不应把自己是女人当作借口。当今时代最不能饶恕的罪恶就是淫荡，在这一点上，根本不能把您和大多数妇女放在一起来考量。宝石和珍珠对您都毫无影响，耀眼的财富在您眼里从不是赋予人类的最大恩惠。在严格的、旧式的家庭中成长的您从未误入歧途去模仿那些即使对良家妇女也颇具危险的坏女人。您从未因自己生儿育女而感到羞惭，似乎年长育子就会被嘲弄；您也没有像其他女人那样试图以美貌示人，而总是掩饰自己怀有身孕，似乎那是什么丢人的负担；您也从未以堕胎来摧毁生育的希望；您也没有用颜料和化妆品来惯纵您的容貌；您从来不喜欢那种穿着如同没穿的服装；人们从您身上看到的是无与伦比的服饰、岁月无痕的花容月貌和最光荣的品德——谦逊。所以您不能以妇女的名义来证明自己有理由悲伤，您已经以自己的美德与那个群体划清界限：您应该像拒绝一切女性恶习一样拒绝眼泪。甚至连女人们也不会允许您在伤痛中一蹶不振，她们会让您迅速度过必要的悲哀，然后在安抚后重新振作起来，您会乐意记住那些勇气过人不逊须眉的女士们。命运让科妮莉亚[31]的十二个孩子就剩下两个。如果您要计算她丧失的孩子，她丧失了十个；如果您想评价这些孩子，她失去了格拉古兄弟。但是当她周围的人痛哭着诅咒她的命运时，她不准他们诅咒命运之神，因为命运将格拉古兄弟赐予她，让他们成了她的儿子。一位无愧于这位母亲的儿子在群众大会上说：“你们想侮辱这位给了我生命的母亲吗？”而母亲的话听起来更是掷地有声。儿子因出生于格拉古家而自豪，母亲因儿子的献身也感到自豪。茹提莉亚跟随儿子考塔一起流放，她对儿子的爱如此真诚，宁可随儿子流放，也不愿意独自长相思，直到儿子回来时她才一同返回。可是当儿子官复原职重新得到重用，又成为一位杰出的公众人物时，却死了。她以当初和他一起流放的勇气承受他的离世，在他的葬礼之后，人们再没有看见她哭过。当他被流放，她显示了勇敢；当他死去，她显示了智慧。什么都不能阻止她表示自己的爱，什么都不能使她无休止地沉溺于无用、无益的悲哀之中。我希望您能与这样的女士为伍。您总在效仿她们的生活方式，也一定能以她们为榜样，控制、克服哀痛。

我知道这不是我们的力量所能掌控的，任何强烈的感情都不是我们能够控制的，尤其是悲哀之情更是无法抑制，因为这种感情是非常强烈的，而且对任何治愈措施都会强烈抵触。有时我们想要击垮它，强咽下痛苦的呻吟，表面上强装镇静，却止不住泪水滂沱。有时我们想去看看演出或角斗以分散注意力，但是就在这些娱乐活动的场景中，一点儿小小的事由就会使我们触景生情，使所有努力归于失败。因此最好是战胜悲痛，而不是自欺欺人。因为如果仅仅用娱乐和分散精力的方式来蒙骗自我，悲痛会撤离，然后又会卷土重来，用暂停期间积蓄的力量，向我们猛烈进攻。而以理智战胜的悲哀却会永远平静下来。因此我不打算给您开出别人用过的处方，让您分散精力，高兴起来，比如到国外长时间旅游，或用很多时间清理账目，管理财产，或经常参加一种新的活动。这些都短时间有效，它们不能治愈，只是干扰了伤痛。而我不是要转移它，而是要彻底终结它。所以我要引领您寻求那种慰藉，这是所有那些超越命运掌控的人的避难所：人文学科的研究。这些学习将为您疗伤，它们将驱除您所有的哀思，即便您从未通晓它们，现在也需要学习它们。就我父亲那种严格的旧式家教所能允许的，您对人文学科即使还没有通晓，也至少是比较熟悉的了。要是我父亲——他是最好的男人——不那么忠实于祖辈的传统，能让您专心于哲学教学，而不是只对它一知半解就好了——您现在就不需要通过学习获得抵御厄运的知识了，而只要拿来运用就行了。他之所以不太愿意让您从事研究，是因为那些女人不是用书上的知识来获得智慧，而只是当成奢侈的摆设。不过，好在您有一种积极求索的心态，能够在有限的时间内学到很多知识，正规研究的基础已经打好了，现在再去继续学习吧，那会使您有安全感。它会安慰您，让您高兴，如果它真的能沁入您的心里，悲痛以及那些毫无意义、不值一提的苦难引发的焦虑和苦恼就再也休想扰乱您的心，您的心里再也容不下这些，它早已将其他的不快拒之门外。学习是您最可靠的庇护，只有它可以使您摆脱厄运的禁锢。

不过，在您到达哲学为您提供的庇护所之前，您还必须有一些支持的力量可以依靠：所以我同时还想向您指出您本身就有的慰藉。想想我的兄弟们。只要他们活着，您就没有理由抱怨自己的命运。从他们身上，您会很高兴地发现反差很大的优点：一个以自己的能力获得官职，另一个以其智慧对官场不屑一顾。一个的优秀，另一个的退隐，为二人的挚爱而感到慰藉吧。我很了解我兄弟们内心深处的感情，一个建功立业是为了让您感到光荣，另一个退隐于平静安宁是为了让您享有闲适。命运为您作出了安排，让您的孩子既能对您有所帮助又能给您带来快乐。这个的显赫地位可以为您提供保护，那个的悠闲生活助您颐养天年。他们竞相侍奉您老人家，两个儿子的挚爱真情会填补一个儿子留下的空缺。我可以十分有把握地预先告诉您，除了儿子的数量，您不会失去任何东西。

这之后，再来想想您的孙子们吧：马尔库斯，这个最可爱的孩子——看到他您就不会再悲伤了，他的拥抱让再大再近的苦痛都会释然。有他的欢乐什么样的泪水不会止住？听到他快活的喋喋不休谁的焦虑心情能不得到舒缓？看到他嬉笑打趣的样子谁能不绽放出笑容？无论原先怎么专注于自己的心思，听着那些永远不会令人厌烦的稚嫩童音，谁的注意力能不被吸引、感染？我祈求神保佑他在我们都离去后活得更好！让命运的残酷行径自动消亡、止于我身。让我来代您承受作为母亲和祖母所要遭受的一切苦难吧。让其余的家人都免受侵扰，幸福生活吧。如果我能替全家遭罪而使家人免受一切痛苦，我决不会因为没有孩子或被流放而抱怨。拥抱诺瓦提拉吧，她很快就会给您生一个重外孙。我那么爱她，并收养了她，所以失去我，她就像个孤儿，尽管她的亲生父亲还活着。也替我好好爱护她吧。厄运最近夺走了她的母亲，但您的爱会让她仅仅因为母亲的去世而悲哀，而不会因为母亲的不在而遭罪。现在您得塑造和调理她的性格，在易受影响的年纪，教育会留下更深的印记。让她慢慢习惯您的谈话，按您认为正确的模式成长，即便您只是给她做做榜样，也会让她受益良多。如此神圣的责任对于您来说也是一种疗法，因为只有哲学或有意义的事情才能将痛苦从因爱而悲伤的心中转移出来。

如果您的父亲还在，我也会将他算作能给您带来莫大安慰的人。正如现在这样，您必须用您对他的爱来判断他对您的爱，这样您就会明白，您多么应该为了他而更多地保护自己而不是为了我而牺牲您自己。当过度的悲哀袭击您，逼您屈服时，想一想您的父亲。当然，给了他那么多子孙后代，您不再是他唯一的后代了，但是对于他来说，幸福生活的完美全靠您。当他还健在时，您抱怨自己活够了就不对了。

到现在为止我还没有谈到最能给您带来安慰的人，您的姐姐，她是最忠实于您的人，也是您可以毫无保留倾诉忧愁的人，还是我们所有孩子视为妈妈的人。您和她泪水交融，在她的怀抱中您才恢复了平静。确实，一直以来她都分享您的情感，但是在我的这件事上，她的悲哀却不全是为了您。她把我抱在怀里来到罗马，在我长期生病的时候，是她的爱和母亲般的呵护才使我恢复知觉。在我竞选检察官的时候，她支持我，虽然她平日连谈话和大声打招呼都不够自信，但对我的爱使她战胜了羞怯。她的隐居生活，她的谦逊（与现在很多妇女的厚颜相比显得有些保守），她的心平气和，还有她渴望平和安静的保守天性——所有这些都没有阻止她为了我而真正变得雄心勃勃。最亲爱的母亲啊，她是您恢复精神获得慰藉的源泉。尽您所能紧紧拥抱她吧。悲伤的人总是想回避他们最爱的人，想找个排解忧伤的地方，但是您一定要把您的想法告诉她。无论您是想保留这种情绪，还是想把它置于一旁，她都会使您不再难过，或者与您分担痛苦。但是，就我对这位优秀女性的智慧的了解，她一定不会让您在这种无益的困苦中消耗精力，她会给您讲述她生活中的一段颇有教育意义的插曲，那件事我也曾亲眼目睹。

在一次出海旅行途中，她失去了自己深爱的丈夫——我的姨夫，她还是个少女时就嫁给了他。她同时承受着悲哀和恐惧的巨大压力，虽然船失事了，她仍冒着风暴航行，最终安全地把丈夫的尸体运到岸上。啊，有多少妇女行为高尚却默默无闻被人们忘记！如果她有幸生活在过去，那时人们对英雄的行为都大加赞赏，那些才华横溢的人会怎样竞相赞美这样的女士。她不顾自己虚弱的身体，无视连最勇敢的人都会心生畏惧的大海，冒着生命危险以使丈夫能够入土为安。当她一心想的是丈夫的葬礼时，她对自己的处境是无所畏惧的。所有的诗人都盛赞要替丈夫献身的女人，但是冒着生命危险送丈夫的尸体去墓地的行为更高尚。经历同样的危险却鲜有人称赞，那是一种更伟大的爱。

这件事之后，人们对很多事情就不会感到惊奇了：在她丈夫担任埃及总督的十六年中，人们从未见她在公共场合露面，她从不在家里接待本地人，从未请求丈夫为她做什么，也从未允许别人求她办什么事。结果是，在一个盛行闲言碎语、对执政者讥讽辱骂的行省，连小心翼翼唯恐犯错误的人都难逃绯闻诟病，而她却被当成完美非凡的典范，让那些传播闲话的人三缄其口（这是很难做到的，因为这里连一些不着边际的闲话都会流传甚广），而直到如今，人们还在希望能再看到一个和她品行一样的人，虽然根本不可能。在一个省份生活十六年能够得到认可是很了不起的，在那里不为人们所注意更是了不起。我回顾这些事情不是为了说她品德多么高尚（讲述得这么概括，对她的美德是不公平的），而是让您了解一位高尚的女性，她没有被那些必然与权势相伴而来又因而为人们所诅咒的野心与贪婪所征服，她面对海难，在一只破船上无所畏惧地与死去的丈夫在一起，她不曾企图独自逃生，而一心想把丈夫带回家安葬。您也必须鼓起这样的勇气，驱除心中的悲伤，坚强起来，使人们看到您没有因为有这些孩子而后悔。

然而，无论您怎么做，都会经常不可避免地想到我，任何其他的孩子都不会这样经常地让您想念，并不是您不爱他们，而是因为越是疼痛的地方，人们自然会更多地要去触摸。所以您必须想到我现在是幸福而快乐的，就像生活在非常舒适的环境中。说环境舒适是因为现在我心无旁骛，可以自由地做自己想做的事情，眼下我正饶有兴趣地作一些一般性的研究，我的心正急切地想探索事物的真相以思考其自身的本质和宇宙的本质。首先想要了解的是陆地及其位置，然后是周边海洋的本质及潮落和海流。接下来还要研究天地之间那广袤无垠的空间——这离我们最近的空间因着雷鸣、电闪、阵风、大雪、冰雹而喧嚣。最终，我的心会从较低的地区倏忽而过，冲向苍穹，一览神奇壮美的景色，意识到自己的永生不朽，它将继续向所有年代延伸，饱览那些已经存在和将要存在的一切。

论心灵之安宁

塞雷努斯[32]：塞内加，当我审视自己的时候，我的一些不端行为便清晰地浮出表面，使我可以用手触摸。有些藏于较深之处，有些并不总在那里，只是不时往返。我想说，这最后一种是最麻烦的：它们就像潜伏的敌人，一旦时机成熟就对你突然袭击，让你既不能像战争年代那样时刻戒备，也不能像和平年代那样处之泰然。然而，我大多数时间所处的状态（我为什么不能像对医生一样向你承认真相呢？）是我并没有真正摆脱那些自己既怕又恨的恶行，但从另一方面讲，我也没有被它们所约束：这倒让我的状态并不太糟，但却极其易怒，动辄就想与人辩论——我没生病但也不健康。你没必要说，所有的美德开始时都很脆弱，随着时间的推移才变得坚实有力。我还知道那些竭力想获得好感的人，他们想爬上高职位，获得辩才方面的声誉，以及其他需要被人认可的东西，这些都需要时间来日趋成熟——那些真正有力量的，和那些为了名声涂脂抹粉将自己掩饰的，两者都需要等待数年，直到时间的流逝逐渐产生它们的色彩。但是，我唯恐那种使事情变得很牢固的习惯会将这种毛病更深地植根于我身——长期的交往会使人既对美好的也对丑恶的东西产生嗜好。心理脆弱的本质是在两种选择之间摇摆，没有明显地倾向于对或错。

我不能一次就把这一切表示清楚，不如一点一点地讲。我要把发生在我身上的事情告诉你，你就能给我的病症起个名字了。我得承认，我是极爱节俭的。我不喜欢把长椅装饰得那么华丽，也不喜欢把衣服从衣柜里取出，或用重物压上千百遍让它那么光彩耀人，我喜欢家常的、便宜的，不是那种珍藏着的，穿着时还要小心翼翼的衣服。我喜欢的饭菜不需要准备，也不需要在家奴的守护下用餐，不用提前几天就预定，也不用好多人伺候着，而是即时买，简单做，不需要跑远路也不需要花高价，而是到处都有的，钱包和身体都能负担得起的，不是怎么吃进去又怎么吐出来的。我要的佣人就是普普通通，没什么技能，家养的奴隶就行；我的银器呢，就用我乡下老爸的那种厚重且没什么特点的就行。我的桌子不需要有色彩斑斓俗不可耐的标记，也不需要因多次辗转于时尚名人之手而为全城所熟知，只要立着能用就行，不要让客人因高兴而分散目光，也不要引起他们的嫉妒。当我立下这些标准，我还是感到，自己的心被某个培训佣人的学校的华丽装饰搞得眩惑了，那些奴隶的服装上饰以金品，比要去参加游行的，打扮得还精致，还有一整队光鲜耀人的随从；我被一座房子搞得眩惑了，在那里面，你甚至可以在宝石上行走，财富撒在各个角落，房顶闪闪发光，所有的平民百姓都毕恭毕敬地侍候在家庭遗产的废墟上。还需要我提起那清澈见底、绕着就餐客人流淌的池水，以及那与周围环境相映成辉的宴席吗？长时间节俭惯了，我发现豪华奢靡的壮观场面将我包围，在我周围轰响。我的视觉有些游移，因为我发现用心去面对它，比用眼睛更容易。而这之后我回来，感到不是更糟了而是更悲哀了。行走于那些微不足道的财产中，我的头不再抬得那么高，一种隐秘而痛苦的疑惑折磨着我：这样的生活高尚吗？这些都没有改变我，但是却让我感到震撼。

我决定遵循老师的教导，投身于国家大事，担任一些公职——当然不是为了那身紫袍和执法官的棍棒，而是为了能更好地帮助我的朋友和亲戚，帮助所有的同胞，进而帮助全人类。我满腔热忱地追随芝诺、克里安提斯、克律西波斯，顺便说一下，他们都没有摄职从政，但是都劝导别人那样做。不过，当什么东西对我那已不习惯折腾的心发起进攻时，当什么事情发生在我身上时，无论是琐碎小事（每个人生都会经历的）还是难以对付的事，或当一些无关紧要的事要耗费很多精力时，我就会悠闲地躲避，就像疲惫的动物，匆匆赶回家。我决定将生活限制在自己的围墙之内，我会说：“给我造成损失却不想给予适当回报的人，别想从我这儿夺走哪怕一天的时间。让我的心安分守己，滋养自我，心无旁骛——决不仰人鼻息；让它珍惜宁静，远离公私事务。”然而，每当我看到令人心悦诚服的报道并为杰出的典范所激励，我又渴望站出来，为这个人说话，向那个人提供帮助，即便不能成功，也是助人的一种尝试，或去抑制某人因成功而恃才傲物的骄气。

我认为在自己的研究中，这样肯定比较好：专注于自己的课题，演讲时也以此为主题，同时以主题来决定用词，确立一种不矫揉造作的讲演风格。我问：“写出传世之作有必要吗？为什么不停止让后代对你歌功颂德的努力？人生来就会死的，无言的葬礼能省却很多麻烦。所以如果你想把时间利用起来，就写一些文风简朴的作品留给自己看，而不是为了发表——只为眼下学习就会省力多了。”再者，当我的精神被伟大的思想提高了，它在用词方面就会很有魄力，总是渴望用合适的语言来表达更高的灵感，这样就会产生一种给人很深印象的与主题相配的文风，那样我就会忘了自己一贯恪守的自我克制的规定和原则，而被一种已不属于自己的声音带到更高的高度。

咱们长话短说吧，我的善意中存在的这一弱点，还表现在各个方面，我觉得自己正在变坏，或者（这是更令人担忧的）我就好像被悬吊在边缘，总是命悬一线随时可能要掉下去，而且可能还有更错的我自己看不见的地方——我们对自己的性格总是投以太亲密的目光，而偏袒总会影响我们的判断力。我想，很多人要是没有想象自己已经很有智慧了，要是他们没有掩饰自己的某些性格而无视别人的某些性格，那么他们可能就已经获得了智慧。因为你没有理由设想我们的悲哀更多的是由于别人巴结我们，而不是我们巴结自己。谁敢跟自己说出真相？在成群的马屁精的包围中，最大的马屁精不是自己吗？所以我恳求你，如果你有治疗这种思想游移症的方法，看在我还是值得你施舍的人，给我心灵一个安宁吧，我明白这些心理上的不平静不会有什么危险，不会导致狂风暴雨。用一个真实的比喻来告诉你，我不是由于暴风雨而是由于晕船而苦恼。无论是什么病，根除掉吧，来帮帮一个已看到了陆地但仍在挣扎的人吧。

塞内加：确实，塞雷努斯，我一直在悄悄问自己，应该把这种心理状态比作什么，我找不到比这些人的状况更相似的了：他们曾长期生病，刚刚大病初愈，但仍常常会感到有点儿发烧或疼痛，而且最近的症状没了却仍会心烦意乱；虽然好多了，但有一点发热就把手伸给大夫，开始毫无必要地抱怨。塞雷努斯啊，这些人不是身体没有彻底治愈，而是他们还没有习惯于健康的状态，就好像在平静的海面上仍会有层层涟漪，尤其是暴风雨过后刚刚平静下来时。所以你不需要提供什么很彻底的治疗，因为刚刚进行过这样的治疗了——在这儿堵截自己，在那儿跟自己生气，在其他地方严正地恐吓自己——而最后阶段的治疗是，树立自信，相信自己的路是对的，不要误入那些纵横交错于自己路上的歧途，它们让很多人无可挽回地迷失方向，尽管有人离正确的道路还不远。但是你所期望的是伟大，至高无上、近于神圣的东西——决不动摇。希腊人把这种思想的恒稳坚定称为euthymia（情感正常），德谟克利特曾就此有过精辟的论述，而我却想称其为tranquilli-ty（平静），因为没有必要模仿或复制希腊文字的形式——关键是要找到一个术语，它能表达意思，而不是希腊词语的形式。因而，我们探索心灵如何能够保持平稳，恰当地面对自己，乐观地关注自己的处境，不会中断这种快乐，保持平和的状态，没有起伏忐忑：这就是宁静。让我们想想在一般情况下如何做到这些，然后你可以从通用的疗法中选出你喜欢的方法。在此期间，所有的过失必须放到光天化日之下，让每个人都从中看到自己也犯有的错误。同时你会感到，自我反感带给你的烦恼远比那些人带给你的要少得多，那些人被某些华而不实的宣言束缚，在显赫的头衔下操劳，他们一直虚伪地过日子，并非因为自己有此愿望，而是因为自惭形秽。

那些被变化无常、百无聊赖、朝三暮四所折磨的人，与那些怀念过去了的日子，因兴味索然而哈欠连天的人都是同一类人。还有一些人，他们像是患了失眠症，四处乱窜，朝秦暮楚，不到精疲力竭不会停歇。他们逐物心移，不断变换生活状况，最终安定下来也并非因为对继续变化的厌倦，而是年事太高对新奇事物已迟钝麻木。还有一些人并非由于道德上坚定不移，而是因为惰性十足，缺乏按自己的意愿来改变生活的动力，他们的日子还停留在最初的样子。其实这种病有无数种特征，但是只有一个结果——对自己不满意。这产生于精神上的不稳定，产生于可怕的、未满足的欲望。当人们不敢或没能得到他们渴望的东西时，他们能抓住的就是渴望。他们总是不平衡，总是躁动不安，结果就不可避免地总是生活在悬而未决的状态之中。他们不择手段，拼命想得到自己渴望的东西，他们说服自己、强迫自己去做不体面的事、难以成功的事，而当一切劳而无功的时候，那种徒劳无益的耻辱又让他们备受折磨，不是为自己的不端行为，而是为愿望受挫而懊悔。然后他们不断为已作的尝试悔恨，为再一次尝试而恐惧，心情躁动不安却又苦于无法排解，因为他们既不能控制又无法顺从自己的欲望，生活的不确定性让他们感到前途无望。精神的麻木不仁又让他们在无约束的希望面前止步不前。对劳而无功的憎恶使人们转而变得无所事事，或开始独自研究，而这是向往公共事业、热衷于社会活动、因缺少精神寄托而天性注定不安分的人所无法忍受的，所有的苦恼因而更加糟糕。结果，当那些忙碌的人从实际活动中所获得的乐趣消失不见的时候，他们无法忍受待在家里、四面围墙中的孤独寂寥，开始厌恶这种与世隔绝的孤寂。这样又会产生厌世和对自己的不满情绪，产生心绪不宁、郁郁寡欢、难耐闲适而导致的躁动，尤其是当我们羞于承认造成这种状况的原因，这种羞耻感又让痛苦深埋心中，我们的欲望陷于狭窄的界限中，无法逃逸，又无法呼吸。由此又会引发愁思与悲哀，以及不安分心灵无尽的踌躇。希望产生时振奋激动，希望破灭时萎靡不振，由此又引发了一些人对自己闲适的憎恶和对无所事事的抱怨，以及对别人升迁的极端嫉妒。游手好闲的安逸会衍生怨恨嫉妒，因为他们自己不能发迹就想让别人都遭殃。接下来，这种对别人成功的嫉恨和对自己的失望又使他们迁怒于命运，抱怨生不逢时命途多舛，进而退隐到阴暗角落思忖自己的遭遇，直到对自己产生腻烦和厌倦。由于人的心灵天生就是好动、喜欢享乐的，所以它对每个刺激和娱乐都是欢迎的，甚至欢迎那些疲于奔命而扬扬自得、层次不高的人。有些身体上的创伤欢迎有人用手来戳疼它们，渴望有人触摸它们，令人难受的瘙痒处希望能被抓挠：同样，我要说，心中的欲望已经破灭就如同可怕的伤痛，只想通过劳碌或病情恶化来获得乐趣。因为确实有些动作会让我们的身体很愉悦，即便它会引起疼痛，比如翻个身换到不感到累的那一侧，还会不断换来换去，让身体感到凉快。所以荷马史诗中的阿基里斯[33]一会儿趴下，一会儿仰面躺着，不断变换姿势，像个病人，哪种姿势都待不长，只能辗转变换来缓解痛楚。因此，人们四处旅行，在异国海滩上漫步，在陆地、海洋尝试各种不安分的生活，却总是对周围的东西感到厌恶。“咱们现在去坎帕尼亚。”不久，对奢华的生活厌倦了——“咱们去那些蛮荒地区吧，去布鲁蒂姆和卢卡尼亚的森林看看。”但在野外，他们那看惯奢华的双眼在这些肮脏乏味、毫无景致之地感到放松的乐趣也在消失。“咱们去塔林顿吧，那里有著名的港口，温暖的冬天，即便在古代也是人口众多繁华热闹的地区。”“咱们现在还是到城市去吧”——他们的耳朵早就向往喧嚣的掌声了，现在他们甚至想看人类杀戮流血。他们一次次地出游，不断变换着景点。正如卢克莱修[34]所说：“每个人都想以此种方式逃离自我。”但是如果他不能逃出自身，什么时候才是终点呢？他就像是自己最乏味的伴侣，尾随着自己。所以我们应该意识到，我们的难处不在于地点而在于我们自己，我们太脆弱了，不能忍受任何东西，不能忍受劳苦，不能忍受欢乐，不能忍受自己，不能长期忍受任何东西。这一弱点已经把有些人逼得走投无路，因为不断变换目标，他们又回到原来的地方，他们已经无力接受新奇的事物了，他们开始对生活、对世界感到腻烦，自我放纵让他们软弱，又产生了一种“这种同样的事情我还得忍受多久”的情绪。

你想知道我对这种厌倦的情绪建议采取的治疗方法吗？正如阿森诺德斯所说，最好的方法是使自己忙于摄职从政的实际活动。正如有些人愿意在白天进行日光浴、锻炼和其他保健活动，对于运动员来说，最切实、最重要的事情就是把大部分时间花在增强四肢力量上，对此他们是全力以赴的，所以对于你这样需要培训心智应对公共生活中的竞争的人，到目前为止最好的办法就是定期实践。当一个人打算让自己对公民和同胞有用，如果他能全身心地投入到为公众和个人服务中去，他就是同时在训练自己并做好事。但是，阿森诺德斯[35]说：“由于人类如此疯狂、野心勃勃，太多的陷害诬告颠倒黑白，使诚实正直的人处境危险，屡受阻挠而得不到帮助，所以我们确实应该从公共生活和政治生活中隐退。不过，一个伟大的思想即便是在私人生活中也还是有机会自由地活动。狮子和其他动物的能量可以被笼子限制住，而人的能量不会，人最伟大的成就往往在退隐之后才能看到。然而，如果一个人无论悠闲地隐居何处，他都能用自己的智慧、言辞和忠告来为个人和人类服务，那么就让他隐居起来吧。为国家服务不只限于那些竞争公职的候选人、法庭上的辩护人，以及为战争与和平而投票的人。教育年轻人，向他们心中灌输美德的人（出色的教师异常匮乏），还有那遏制、制止人们疯狂追逐财富和奢靡，&nbsp；即使制止不了，至少也能拖延他们步伐的人——这样的人也是在为公众服务，尽管在私人生活中。那些处理外国人与本国人之间的案子，向起诉人宣布财产评估人的裁决结果的执政官，与宣讲正义、虔诚、忍耐、勇敢、蔑视死亡、有关诸神的知识，宣讲发自善良之心的祝福是多么自由等问题的本质的人相比，你觉得前者比后者对社会更有益吗？所以如果你从履行公共责任的时间中抽出来一部分用来研究，你就不算放弃或逃避工作。因为士兵不仅要站在前线防御左右两翼，还要从事守护大门和保卫兵工厂这样虽不是很危险但也是不可掉以轻心的岗位，尽管不流血，但也是军事职责。如果你致力于研究，你就不会再厌倦生活，不会因厌恶白天而渴望夜晚，你就会感到你既不是自己的负担，对他人也不是无用的，你将吸引很多人成为你的朋友，很多优秀人物会聚集在你的周围。即便是最不起眼的美德也不可能永远隐身，而总会清楚地表露出来：任何值得拥有这种美德的人都会寻到她的踪迹。但是如果我们脱离整个社会，远离人群，只为自己活着，这种没有任何趣味的与世隔绝的生活就会引来毫无价值的活动。我们会开始盖一些房子，推倒另一些；拦截海水，再从人工渠道取水，把自然赋予我们可供利用的时间挥霍掉。我们中有些人能够非常节俭地利用时间，而另一些人却浪费它；有些人可以开出时间账户，另一些人就没有任何结余——这真是最可耻的结局。老年人往往除了年龄再无其他证据证明自己漫长的生命了。”

亲爱的塞雷努斯，我觉得阿森诺德斯太轻易就顺应时代了，太迅速地退隐了。我不否认人有时确实应该让步——但是，应该一点儿一点儿逐渐隐退，应该坚持我们的标准，保持我们战斗者的荣誉。那些与敌人达成协议时并未解除武装的军人更安全，更受人敬重。我想，这是美德及追求美德者应该做的：如果命运将某人击败，剥夺了他行动的手段，他不应该转身就走，扔下武器找个地方躲起来（好像真有命运找不到的地方似的），而是应该更慎重地履行职责，谨慎地寻找能够为国家服务的机会。假如不能成为战士，就担任公职；假如他要以平民身份生活，就让他当个辩护人；假如情况迫使他保持沉默，就让他以无言的方式帮助他的同胞；假如他在讲坛上露面有危险，就让他在私人住处、演出中、宴会上当个好的伴侣、忠诚的朋友、温文尔雅的赴宴者；假如他没有了一个公民的责任，就让他履行做人的责任。如果我们精神崇高，就不会将自己禁锢在一城之内，我们应走出去与整个地球打交道，把整个世界当成自己的国家，为此，我们就可以让自己的德行在更广阔的领域发挥作用。假设你被禁止在法院工作、在公众场合讲演、参加选举，那么想想身后向你开放的大片地区和欢迎你的各国人民吧——对你紧闭的领域再大，也大不过对你开放的天地。但是注意，这不全是你的错——如，除了当执政官、议长、传令官或萨菲斯[36]，你不想担任别的官职。但是假如除了将军或司令官外，你就不想在军队担任其他职务呢？即便其他人担当最高级别的官职，而命运让你就当个三等兵，你也必须用你的声音、你的鼓励、你的示范、你的精神来承担士兵的责任。如果一个人的手被砍下，他还能发现自己可以毅然挺立履行自己的职责为他人助威。你也应该像他这样做：如果命运免去了你在公共事业中的显要职位，你也要坚定地挺住，鼓励其他人工作；而如果有人扼住你的喉咙，你要继续挺立，默默地助他人一臂之力。一个好公民的服务从来就不会没有作用：人们可以听到，可以看到他通过表情、点头、缄口不语，甚至步态提供帮助。就如一些有益健康的食品，即便没有品尝，没有触摸，仅从它们散发出的气味我们就能受益，美德即使藏身于很远的地方也能显露其优点。无论她是出国办理正当业务，或经默许露面，或被迫卷起船帆，无论她是被禁锢的、静止不动的，还是一言不发的，是局限在狭小空间里，还是显而易见的，在任何条件下她都能够有所帮助。你为什么认为一个体面退休了的人就不能做有价值的榜样？如果由于时运不济或国家状况不允许，不能将全部精力投入于一种生活，那么最理想的方式就是将休闲与某种活动结合起来，因为你总会找到一条途径参与某种高尚的活动。

当三十僭主将雅典搞得四分五裂的时候，你见过比那更糟糕的城市吗？他们杀死了一千三百个最优秀的公民还不罢休，十足的野性刺激他们继续倒行逆施。这个城市设有亚略巴古——最神圣的高级法院和元老院，以及与元老院同级别的公民大会，每天，一伙邪恶的刽子手聚集在这里，而不幸的元老院议厅中集聚着众位僭主。一个国家中如果僭主与侍从的人数相差无几，这样的国家还能太平吗？连恢复自由的希望都很渺茫，更没有合适的机会处治这些掌有实权的恶棍。这可怜的国家到哪儿找足够多的像哈默迪乌斯[37]这样的人呢？而苏格拉底深陷这场激战中，他安慰郁闷沮丧的元老，鼓励那些对国家绝望的人，谴责那些为自己财富担惊受怕的富豪，这些人为当初不顾死活的贪婪感到悔之晚矣，而对于那些乐意效仿他的人来说，他是活生生的鼓励，是三十僭主身边自由的灵魂。然而，他就是这个人，这个被雅典亲手处死于深牢大狱的人，这个公开嘲弄一群暴君的人，这个自由之神不能容忍其自由的人。所以你能明白这两点了：在一个灾难深重的国度，智者有机会显示其影响力；而在一个繁荣昌盛的国家，不择手段地攫取、嫉妒，及上千种卑怯的恶行会大行其道。因而，我们应该按照国家的安排和命运所赋予我们的自由，扩展或缩小我们的活动，但是无论如何，我们都应该振奋精神，不要陷于恐惧之中萎靡不振。尽管受到来自四面八方的威胁，尽管武器、镣铐的哗啦声不绝于耳，他的勇气丝毫不减也绝不会收敛，这样的人才是真正的男子汉。因为自我保护并非意味着要压抑自我。确实，我相信，库里乌斯·丹塔图斯曾说过他宁可真的去死，也不愿意像具行尸走肉似地活着，因为最可怕的事情莫过于死前只留下活过的岁数。但是如果你恰巧活在一个为国效力非常不易的时代，你就要把时间更多地用于休闲和文学作品，就像在惊险的航海中不时寻找一个安全的港湾，不要让公共生活先放逐了你，而要先主动摆脱出来。

无论如何，我们必须先要谨慎地审视自己，其次要审视我们想要参与的活动，然后弄明白为了谁、和谁一起进行这些活动。

这其中最重要的就是要正确地评价自己，因为我们总是过高地估计自己的能力。某人因对自己的口才太自信而受到伤害；某人因对命运奢求太多超过了他的承受能力；某人超负荷工作使羸弱的身体不堪重负。有的人太羞涩而不适于搞政治，因为搞政治需要大胆地抛头露面；有的人总是率性而为所以不适于司法工作；有的人不能抑制怒火中烧和其他不快情绪以致出言不逊；有的人不能控制自己的才智，抑制那些巧妙却危险的进攻。对于所有这些人，退隐较之公共活动更适于他们——易怒易躁的性格要避免刺激，直言不讳会引出麻烦。

其次，我们必须评估正在做的实事，使自己的力量足以承担起这项工作。执行任务的人永远要比任务本身更强势——负荷太重就会将负重的人压垮。此外，某些任务与其说是伟大，不如说会衍生出很多其他的任务。我们必须避免那些将会产生各种新花样的次生活动，不要染指那些一旦触及就很难抽身的事情。你要去作那些自己可以完成或至少是希望完成的任务，而回避那些在进行过程中会变得越来越多、想停也停不下来的工作。

在对人的选择上，我们也必须非常审慎，必须确定他们是否值得我们为其贡献生命的一部分，牺牲我们的时间是否能使其有所变化。因为有些人确实会以怨报德。阿森诺德斯说他不会陪一个不知心怀感激的人进餐。我想你能理解，他更不喜欢拜访那些以一顿饭来报答朋友相助的人，这些人把一道道菜看作慷慨的给予，好像他们给他的荣耀超过了给予别人的。没有人见证和观看，私下里大快朵颐也是了无生趣的。

你必须了解你的性格更适合实际的活动还是安静的研究与思考，向适合你天生的才能与禀赋的方向发展。伊索克拉底[38]强行将埃弗罗斯[39]从广场上拉走，因为他认为埃弗罗斯更适合去撰写历史。强其所难，天性便不能充分发挥；与自然作对，我们便会徒劳无功。

但是没有比深厚、诚挚的友谊更令人欣喜的了。有人随时乐意聆听你倾诉的秘密，是多么幸福的事情！和他们分享你的所知，你会觉得比个人独享还轻松，和他们叙谈能够抚平你心中的苦闷，他们的忠告促使你作出决定，他们的欢乐化解了你的忧愁，他们只要一露面就会让你高兴！诚然，我们要选择那些最大限度地摆脱了强烈欲望的人，因为恶行都是不露声色地散布的，和近在咫尺的恶人接触我们也会遭到攻击和侵害。这正如传染病流行时我们必须小心，不要坐在已经出现发烧症状的病人旁边，因为这样对我们很危险，他们对着我们呼吸会使我们染病。所以在选择朋友时，我们要谨慎选择那些人品没有问题的。健康的人和有病的人混杂在一起，是传播疾病的开始。但是我并不是让你只追随智者，并与他们联系。我们到哪儿才能找到那位我们已苦寻良久的智者？理想情况下我们只能在坏人里挑最不坏的。如果你能在柏拉图、色诺芬或苏格拉底的其他门徒中寻找好人，或者如果你可以进入加图时代——这个时代产生了不愧为加图时代的人（还产生了很多有史以来最邪恶的人，这些人犯有骇人听闻的罪行：加图对这两种人都有必要赏识一番，他需要赢得好人们的首肯，也需要坏蛋来证明自己的力量），那就再好不过了。但在当下好人稀缺的时候，你在选择时不能太挑剔。还有，你要特别注意别选那些阴郁伤感的人，这种人找个茬儿就发牢骚，虽然人毫无疑问是忠诚善良的，但是如果身边有个人对每件事情都焦虑不安，动不动就哼哼唧唧发牢骚，那就会破坏你平和的心境。

让我们再来谈谈私有财产这一人类痛苦的最大根源。如果将我们所遭受的其他苦难，如死亡、疾病、恐惧、欲望、对痛苦与艰辛的忍受，与金钱所带来的罪恶相比较，后者要严重得多。所以我们必须记住，没有钱要比有钱后又失去的痛苦轻得多，而且我们应该认识到，可以失去的东西越少，给我们带来的痛苦就越小。如果你认为富人更能忍受痛苦，你就错了，最高大和最矮小的身体上的伤口是一样痛的。比翁对此作了一个恰当的比喻：从一个秃头上拔头发和从长满头发的头上拔都是一样疼。你可以得出同样的结论，即富人和穷人会感到同样的痛苦，不管贫富，都把钱看得很紧，一旦钱被攫走，都会痛苦。但是，正如我所说的，未曾得到金钱比得而后失更容易忍受，也更简单，所以你会发现那些命运女神从未示爱的人比被她抛弃的人要快活得多。灵魂高尚的第欧根尼[40]因为认识到这点，所以他把一切安排好，从他那里什么东西都拿不走。你可以称这种状况为贫穷、匮乏、亟须，给这种无忧无虑的自由起个任何难听的名字。只有他没有什么可以失去，否则我不会说他是幸福的。如果我没弄错的话，置身吝啬鬼、骗子、抢劫犯、绑匪这些人之中而不受其害，这样的地位堪比帝王。如果有人怀疑第欧根尼的快活，他也同样会对不朽诸神的状况产生怀疑——他们是否因为没有房产、公园、出租给外籍佃户的昂贵的农庄，没能从市场上得到巨额生息的进项而生活得不愉快。你们这些被财富击垮的人，你们不感到羞愧吗？来，看看天空，你会看到财产全无的众神，尽管一无所有却能贡献一切。一个人抛弃了命运的恩赐，你认为他贫穷，还是类似于不朽的神？德米特里厄斯是庞培的释奴，并不因为比庞培富有就感到羞愧，你说他就因而感到更幸福吗？他曾每天给奴隶记数，就像一位将军检阅自己的军队，而之前，他会认为有两个下等奴隶和稍宽敞一些的小屋就是富有了。当有人告诉第欧根尼说他唯一的奴隶逃跑了，他觉得不值得把他找回来。“如果曼斯没有第欧根尼可以活，而第欧根尼没有曼斯就活不下去，那是很可耻的。”他说。我想他的意思是：“管好自己的事吧，命运之神，第欧根尼现在没有属于你的东西了。我的奴隶跑了，不，是我解脱了，获得了自由。”一家子的奴隶需要穿衣、吃饭，这么多贪吃的家伙要填饱肚子，要给他们买衣服，还得提防他们偷偷摸摸，接受他们边哭边骂的服务，人如果不欠任何人任何东西，除了一个他可以轻易就拒绝的人——他自己，该是多么幸福！但是，由于我们没有这样的意志力，所以我们至少得缩减自己的财产，以尽可能少地遭受命运的打击。战争中，那些将身体全都缩进盔甲里的人要比盔甲遮拦不住而使身体暴露在外容易受伤的人更适合打仗。所以钱的最理想的数额应是既不低于贫困线也不要超出太多。

而且，如果我们以前就很节俭，就会满足于这样的限度，不力行节俭，多少财富都不够用，多少财富都不算富足。尤其是补救的方法近在咫尺，贫穷本身可以通过节俭变得富有。让我们习惯于戒除浮夸的生活方式，以功能性质来考量事物，而不是炫耀作秀。让食物来解饿，饮水来解渴，性生活满足需要，让我们学着依靠自己的四肢，懂得调整我们的穿着风格和生活方式，不要一味追求时髦，而要承袭我们祖先的风俗习惯。让我们学会提高自我约束力，戒除奢靡之风，不要好高骛远，不要动辄生气，不要对贫困抱有成见，要勤俭节约，即便很多人羞于如此，我们也要按照自然的需要采取廉价可行的补救方法，遏制自己放纵的希求和对未来着迷的心灵，好像给它戴上脚镣，立志自力更生获取财富而不是靠运气。如此这般，并非人生中各种各样不应有的灾祸就可全部免除，暴风雨就不会频繁袭击那些勇敢扬帆远航的人。我们必须约束自己的活动，这样，命运的武器就找不到攻击的目标，因此流放和灾难就会变害为利，更重大的灾祸就会被比较小的不幸所弥补。当心灵不肯接受教诲，不能用温和的方法治疗，为什么不能服一剂贫困，或耻辱，或一般性损伤的药，采取以毒攻毒的方法？所以让我们习惯于在没有大群人的簇拥下用餐，使唤少一些奴隶，适当购置服装，再限制一下住房面积。不仅是在赛跑和马戏场的竞赛中，而且在人生的赛程中，都要沿着跑道的内圏跑。

甚至是我们的学习也是这样，虽然学习上的支出是最值得的，但支出的正当与否取决于是否适度。拥有无数本书有什么意义呢？书的主人一生几乎连题目都没有看过。没有得到书的指导，大量的书就成了学习者的负担，而且专注于几位作家比迷失于众多作者要有益得多。四万册图书在亚历山大图书馆[41]的火灾中化为灰烬，外人曾盛赞其为王室财富的豪华见证，如提图斯·李维[42]称其为国王高雅品位和奉献精神的卓越表现。这根本不是高雅品位和奉献精神，而是学究气的自我放纵——其实，也谈不上学究气，因为他们收集书不是为了学识，而是为了炫耀。同样你能发现，很多人连最基本的文化都没有，他们藏书不是用作学习的工具，而是为了装点自家的餐厅。所以我们应该买足够多的实用书籍来读，而不要买来装饰门面。“不过，”你会说，“这总比把钱浪费在买科林斯式青铜器或画儿上体面多了。”但是，在任何领域的过度消费都是应该受到谴责的。你怎么能容忍这样的人，他收集香橼木和象牙的书柜，收藏了不知名的或三流作家的作品，然后就坐在他那几千本书中，打着哈欠，更多的是为书的封面和标签感到得意？于是，你就会看到最无所事事的人竟拥有好多套演讲词和历史书籍，装书的板条箱一直摞到天花板——如今，精美的藏书室也和冷热浴室一样成了家中必不可少的装饰物。当然，我可以原谅那些人由于酷爱学习而犯错，但是这些贤哲的著作及其多幅画像收集起来仅仅只是为装点一堵墙以显示自命不凡而已。

不过你也许在生活中陷入了某种困难的境地，公务或私事在你神不知鬼不觉时就收紧了绳套，使你既不能解开又不能弄断。想想戴着脚镣的囚徒，他们只是在最开始的时候感到腿上镣铐的重量，当他们决定放弃挣扎强忍下去时，他们就从事情的必然性中学到了要以坚韧的精神来忍受，而且习与性成，逐渐学会了要以放松的态度来忍受。如果你有藐视困难的精神，不为困难所烦扰，那么在任何生活状况中，你都可以找到乐趣、消遣和快活。没有比这更应该让我们感谢自然的了，由于了解我们生于何种苦难之中，她为人类设计了在灾祸面前可以得到慰藉的习性，以使人类可以尽快在最恶劣的祸事面前泰然处之。如果灾祸以一成不变的力度持续向我们进攻，那么没有人能够忍受长久的不幸。我们都被命运所束缚，有些人是被较松的金锁链所束缚，而另一些人则被较紧的劣质金属锁链所束缚，但是这又有什么关系呢？我们都被禁锢着，那些束缚着别人的人，自己也被束缚着——除非你也许能感觉左手的锁链轻一些[43]。有的人被高官束缚，有的人被财富束缚；高贵的出身压倒一些人，卑贱的出身又压倒另一些人；有些人屈从于别人的管制，另一些人屈从于自己的管制；有的人因为被流放而限居于一处，另一些人则因为履行神职而不得不住在某个地方。所有的生活都是苦役。所以你要习惯自己的环境，尽可能不要抱怨，抓住它们赋予你的任何优势：一个稳健的心智若是找不到其中的慰藉，那就是最大的悲苦。如果规划巧妙，即使很小的面积也能分成具有多种用途的空间；倘若安排合理，狭小的地方也能居住。想出战胜困难的办法，条件艰苦的可以改善，条件有限的可以拓宽，如果知道如何承担，沉重的负担便可减轻。此外，我们绝对不能好高骛远，而是应该探究那些触手可及的东西，因为欲望不能被完全控制。放弃那些不可能或很难得到的东西，努力获取那些容易得到的和极想得到的，而且要认识到所有东西都是微不足道的，表面上不同，内里全都一样无用。不要羡慕那些比自己地位高的人，高高耸立的是悬崖绝壁。另外，被命运不公地置于危险境地的人反倒安全，因为那种状况有利于他们戒骄戒躁、处事低调。确实有很多人被迫固守于高处，如果不是自己坠落，他们不会下来，但是他们必须要认清这样的事实：他们不得已成为别人的负担，这本身就是最大的负担，而且他们并不是上升到那样的高度，而是被钉到了高处。让这些人以公正、温和、善良、慷慨作为安全措施来抵御今后的灾难，并寄希望于更安全的处境吧。但是，将我们从精神游移不定的状态中拯救出来的最有效的方法，是对前进设置一些限制。当需要停止时，不要让命运来作决定，而应由我们自己早早决定罢手不干。这样，当我们的心灵被欲望刺激时，就会被限制住，就不会将我们引入无法控制的无常境地。

我所讲的这些适合那些有缺点的、普通的、不健全的人，而不是智者。智者不必神色紧张、小心翼翼地走动，因为他能很自信地毫不犹豫地对抗命运，而且决不妥协。他没有理由惧怕她，因为他不仅将他的东西、财产和地位，甚至连他的身体，他的眼睛和手，以及那些使生命更珍贵的东西，还有他本身，都看成是命运默许给他的。他活着就如同自己是借来的，必定要按要求偿还的，没什么可抱怨的。他并没有因此在自己眼中变得廉价，因为他知道他不是自己的，但是他会在做所有事情时都小心、谨慎，就像一个虔诚圣洁的人守卫着托付给他的东西一样。而无论何时命令他偿还债务，他都不会抱怨命运，而会说：“我为自己所持有和保留的一切而感谢你。我照看了你的财产获取了巨大利益，但是应你的要求，我怀着感激的心情和良好的意愿交给你。如果你想让我仍旧拥有你的任何东西，我会妥善保存，如果你不同意我保有这些东西，我会把银币、银盘、房子、我的家全都还给你。”如果自然要求将她原先托付给我们的东西归还，我们会对她说：“把我的灵魂收回吧，它现在比当初你赋予我时好得多，我不会推托，不会退缩，在我清醒之前，把你给我的东西都拿走——拿走吧，我很乐意这么做。”回到你来的地方有什么害处吗？如果不能正确对待死亡，就会活得一团糟，所以我们必须首先摒弃我们在这件事上所确立的价值观，把生命的气息看作一种廉价的东西。用西塞罗的话说，我们厌恶那些不惜一切手段急于保住自己生命的角斗士，我们赏识那些公开藐视生命的角斗士。你要知道，同样的事也适合我们：死亡的原因往往是因为惧怕死亡。命运女神戏弄我们说：“为什么我要让你们这些胆怯的贱民活着。既然你们不知道怎么把喉咙伸出来，就让你们尝尝更厉害的创伤和刀刺的滋味。但是如果你们能勇敢地面对刀锋，没有缩脖，没有用手挡，那么你们将活得更长，死得更安逸。”那些惧怕死亡的人永远不会做一个活人值得做的事。但是知道这是在自己孕育母腹那一刻就设定好条件的人，将依这些条款生活，同时他将以同样心灵的力量来保证任何事都不会令其感到意外吃惊。他把可能发生的都看成将要发生的，他能减轻那些麻烦的杀伤力，那些有所准备拭目以待的人不会对它们感到惊讶，但它们对那些疏忽大意、期望一切都会顺利的人却是沉重打击。疾病、坐牢、灾害、火灾，所有这些都是可以预知的——我不知道自然将我归于哪个烦扰的行列。有那么多回邻居哀悼死去的亲人，那么多回人们手举火把和蜡烛为早逝的亲人举行葬礼，他们的队伍从我们家门口走过。建筑物倒塌的轰隆声时常在我的耳边回响。很多在广场、元老院和通过聊天与我建立了联系的人一夜之间溘然长逝，将友谊之手撒开。这些时时在我周围游荡的险情如果某一天降临到我头上，会让我惊慌失措吗？有多少人计划海上远航却没有考虑到会有暴风雨的袭击！我从来没觉得，从一位蹩脚作者的著作中引用一句经典的句子有什么不体面的。只要普布利柳斯[44]不写荒唐的笑剧，也不考虑低层观众，他所显示的智慧远远超过悲喜剧作家，他作品中的很多思想光芒远比那些悲剧作家的更耀眼，更别说滑稽剧了，其中包括这句：“发生在一个人身上的事情也可以发生在所有人身上。”如果你让此意沦肌浃髓，而且将别人的灾难（每天都会有大量不幸事情发生）看作一条通向你的清晰路径，你就会在灾祸袭击前早早装备防御好。当危险已至，才开始武装自己的思想来对抗它就为时太晚了。“我觉得不会发生这样的事呀？”“你曾想到竟然会是这样的吗？”为什么不会呢？有哪些财富身后没跟着贫穷、饥饿和乞讨？什么官职的紫袍上、占卜官的器物上、贵族们的鞋带上没有沾染污点、耻辱的烙印、上千个不检点和令人不齿的痕迹？哪个王权没有面临过毁灭、垮台、僭主和刽子手？而且这些事相隔不久就会发生：威坐于王位之上与匍匐于另一王位之前只是转瞬之间。那么就要明白任何情况都会改变，发生在任何人身上的事也能发生在你身上。你富有，难道你比庞培还富有？但是当盖乌斯——他原来的亲戚、现在的主子向他打开恺撒的大门以使他能关上自己的大门时，他甚至连面包和水都没有。虽然庞培拥有那么多源头和河口都在他领地之内的河流，但现在他却要为几滴水而折腰。他又饿又渴，最后死于一个亲戚的宫殿里，而就在他忍饥挨饿之际，他的继承人却在为他安排国葬。你曾位居高官，但你的职位有塞扬努斯[45]那么高，有他那么难以企及，有他那么无所不有吗？然而，就在元老院将他送入监狱的同一天，人们把他撕成碎片，就是这个曾经将诸神与人类所能赋予的一切财富集于一己之身的人，刽子手竟找不到能拖走的尸首。你是国王，我不想对你说库罗伊索斯[46]，那个活着目睹了要火葬自己的柴堆被点燃又熄灭的国王，他不仅在国家灭亡后，而且在自己死过一次后还保留了一条命。我也不想对你说朱古达[47]，他曾令罗马人闻风丧胆，但是不到一年就被缚到罗马人面前示众。我们曾目睹非洲国王托勒密[48]和亚美尼亚国王米特里达特[49]被盖乌斯投进监狱，其中一人被流放，另一位更诚心诚意地祈望去流放。在这接连不断的天翻地覆的事件中，除非你认为能发生的必定会发生，否则你会屈服于灾难的压力之下，这灾难会让首次目睹的人崩溃。

下一个问题是确保我们不要毫无意义地浪费自己的精力，或者说不要做无意义的事，就是说不要希求我们无法得到的东西，或不要希求那些一旦得到就会让我们感觉不值得为之花费很多时间很大力气的愿望。换句话说，我们不能徒劳无益、劳而无功，也不能事倍功半，一般来说，如果我们不能取胜或者对获胜的过程感到愧疚，那么痛苦就会接踵而至。我们必须戒除那种东奔西跑、好凑热闹的浮躁风气，很多人热衷于这样的生活，他们聚集在宅邸、剧院或讲坛的周围，好管别人的闲事，总是给人一种忙忙碌碌的印象。如果其中一位从房子里走出来，你可以问他：“你要去哪儿？你想什么呢？”他会回答：“我真的不知道，不过我要见一些人，我要做一些事。”他们四处游荡，漫无目的地找事干，不是做想要做的事，而是碰到什么做什么。他们百无聊赖、毫无目的地闲逛，就像蚂蚁爬到灌木丛上，漫无目的地一直爬到树枝的最上端，然后又原路爬下来。很多人过着和这些动物一样的生活，将其称为无事忙绝非不公。当你看到那些人匆匆忙忙擦身而过像是去救火，就会不免心生遗憾，他们常常会在路上迎头撞到别人，不是自己就是对方摔个四仰八叉，这时他们往往都是去匆忙拜访某个从不会回访的人，或是去参加某个陌生人的葬礼，或去旁听某个不断惹官司的人的庭审，要么就去参加一个结过多次婚的女人的订婚仪式，照看一下轿子，有时甚至抬着它。然后他们回家，筋疲力尽，不知目的何在，诅咒说他们不知道为什么要往外跑，跑到哪儿去——而第二天他们故态复萌，继续闲逛游荡。所以，要让所有的活动都在某一目标指引下进行，让其目的清晰可见。并非那些活动让人们焦躁不安，而是事情虚假的表象让人们发狂，因为连狂人也需要希望来刺激他们，而某些东西的外表对他们会产生刺激，因为他们被蒙蔽的心识别不出那些毫无价值的事情。那些闲逛的人不断扩充着这一群体，他们中的每个人都以同样的方式以各种空虚琐屑的理由在城市转悠。天一亮，他没事可做，就往外走，在很多人家的大门口碰了钉子，只和通报来客的奴仆打个招呼就被关在了门外，这时他才发现，没有谁比他本人更难在家中找到的了。这种劣行又引发另一种最可鄙的恶习：偷听打探公开的和秘密的消息，了解那些讲出去和听起来都不靠谱的事情。

我猜德谟克利特一定是注意到这种现象才开始这样说的：“任何人如果想过安静日子就不要参与很多活动，无论是公共的还是私人的活动。”——他说的当然是指无意义的活动。如果是必要的活动，那么不仅是很多，而且是无数的公事或私事都要做。但是如果没有义务和责任需要我们去做，我们最好克制自己。因为一个人如果要干很多事，往往就会将自己置于命运的掌控下，而最安全的方针是少去引起她的注意，虽然还要时时把她记挂，但任何事情都不能相信她。于是会有人说：“我要出航，除非有什么事发生”“我要当执政官，除非有什么事阻止我”“我的生意要成功了，除非有什么干扰。”这就是为什么我们说智者身上不会发生违背其期望的事情。并不是说，发生在所有人身上的概率不会发生在他身上，而是说他不会在概率上犯错误。事情的结果未必如他所愿，但他可以估计得到——而首先，他应该估计到会有什么事妨碍他实现自己的计划。如果没有许诺必然会成功，那么热望变失望所产生的烦心肯定就容易对付了。

我们还应该让自己通权达变，这样就不会过分寄希望于制订好的计划上，而可以转移到有机会可以做成的事情上，假定变化无常这种最不利于心态平和的不利因素无法掌控我们，我们就不必对目的或条件发生变化感到恐惧。固执己见常常会让命运勒索某些东西，因而一定会带来不幸和焦虑，而更严重的是反复无常，这是任何地方都无法抑制的。这两方面都是心态平和的大敌，而且你会发现它们既不能改变，也难以容忍。任何情况下都必须将思想从外部召唤到本身：它必须信任自己，自得其乐，自我欣赏，必须尽可能多地从别人的事情中抽身，关注自身，不要患得患失，即便是灾祸，也要仁心相待。有一次，海难消息传来，我们斯多葛派的创始人芝诺听说他所有的财产都沉到海里后说：“命运让我做一个少有拖累的哲人。”当一个暴君威胁要杀死哲学家色俄多鲁斯并且真的要让他暴尸街头时，他回答：“只要你高兴，我的半品脱的血由你处置，至于说埋葬，如果你觉得我在地上还是在地下腐烂对我来说很重要，你就太愚蠢了。”尤里乌斯·卡那斯[50]，一位杰出的优秀人士，即使他出生在我们这个时代，我们也非常钦佩他，他与盖乌斯进行了长时间的争论，当他要离开时，法拉里斯[51]对他说：“为了让你不再为自己愚蠢的希望所迷惑，我已命令将你带走处决。”他的回答是：“我谢谢你，高贵的君主。”我不能确定他这话的意思，但我可以想出几种可能。他的意思是说，对方的残忍已经使死亡成了祝福，以此来侮辱对方吗？他是嘲弄对方每天都发疯（因为那些孩子被杀、财产被没收的人一向都得向他表示感谢）吗？他是把对他的宣判当成乐于接受的解脱吗？无论他是什么意思，都是勇敢无畏的应答。有些人会说：“这之后盖乌斯可能会命令让他活下来。”卡那斯不惧这些：盖乌斯对此类命令从不食言。你相信卡那斯在行刑前的十天里过得无忧无虑吗？这个人的言行简直令人难以置信，他保持得多么平静。当拉着一队死刑犯的百夫长命令他也站出来时，他正在下国际跳棋。听到有人叫他，他数了数棋子然后对他的棋友说：“听着，我死了以后你不许谎称自己赢了。”然后对百夫长点点头说：“你得做证，我多赢了一个棋子。”你以为卡那斯只是享受棋盘上的游戏吗？他是享受这场充满讽刺意味的游戏。他的朋友为将要失去这样一个人而感到伤心，而他却对他们说：“你们为什么悲伤？你们还弄不明白灵魂为什么不朽，而我很快就知道了。”他直到死都没有停止探索真理，使自己的死成为人们讨论的话题。他的哲学导师陪他共赴刑场，当他们离我们高高在上的恺撒每天接受供品的土丘不远的时候，他说：“卡那斯，你现在在想什么呢？你感觉如何？”卡那斯回答：“我决定作笔记，记录一下瞬间之内灵魂是否意识到自己离开了身躯。”他还许诺说，如果有什么发现他会依次拜访他的朋友，向他们透露灵魂的状况。看看在飓风中的平静吧，这样的灵魂是值得不朽的，以自己的命运来证明真相，在生命的最后时刻还盘问即将离去的灵魂，不仅到死都在探索研究，而且还从死亡的经历本身来探究，没有人对哲学的探究比这更长久。如此伟大的人不会就此立刻撒手人寰，他将受到人们的尊重，被称为高尚的灵魂，他是盖乌斯的又一受害者，我们确信你将永垂不朽。

但是，要驱除个人伤痛的原因是没有意义的，因为我们有时会陷入对整个人类的仇恨中。当你想到单纯多么稀罕，天真多么无人知晓，除了极其短暂的机会，忠诚又是多么少见，你碰见过多少罪行得逞，人们由于贪财好色干出的事，无论是得是失，都同样可恶，还有，从不给自己设限的野心，现在如何从恶习中获得荣耀——所有这些使心灵坠入了黑暗之中，笼罩于阴影之下，似乎那些美德都被打翻，希求美德成了无稽之谈，拥有美德也毫无用处。所以我们必须教育自己，不要认为那些普遍存在的恶习可恨，而要看作可笑，我们应该仿效德谟克利特，而不要仿效赫拉克利特。因为当他们走到大庭广众之中，后者总是哭，而前者总是笑，后者认为我们所有的活动都可悲，而前者则认为都愚蠢。所以我们不要把这些事情看得太严重，而应该宽容它们，嘲弄生活总比哀叹生活要开化多了。还要记住：对生活付之一笑的人比对生活充满忧伤的人更优秀，因为笑对人生的人对生活留有美好的希望，而另一种人对那些无望纠正的事情只是愚蠢地悲叹。而且，全盘考虑这些事情，会发现开怀大笑是比涕泗滂沱更博大的思想表现，因为笑表达的是我们最温柔的情感，而且笑也体现了我们承认，用以生存的一切外物都无所谓好，无所谓坏，甚至无所谓不幸。每个人如果都好好考虑给我们带来喜与悲的每件事情，他就会领会比翁箴言的真谛：人类所做的一切都和他起始时一样，他们的生命并没有比孕育时更高尚更恶劣，生时一无所有，最终回归于一无所有。不过，能够平静地接受大众的行为方式和人类的缺陷则更为妥当，不要失控于大笑或哭泣。因为为别人的痛苦而苦恼意味着永恒的烦扰，而从别人的痛苦中获取快乐则是一种缺少人性的快乐，就如看到别人埋葬自己儿子时你也哭泣或表情庄重都是没必要表达的慈悲。对于自己的烦恼也是一样，得体的举止应是悲伤宣泄得合乎自然，而不是合乎旧俗。很多人哭是给别人看的，只要没人看，眼睛就是干的，因为他们觉得，当每个人都在哭的时候自己不哭是不得体的。这种跟在别人后面亦步亦趋的恶习如此根深蒂固，连人最基本的感情——悲痛——的表达也沦为一种模仿。

我们接着还必须看看一种有足够理由引起我们悲哀和焦虑的情况。当好人没有落得好下场时，当苏格拉底被迫死于狱中，当茹提利乌斯被流放，当庞培和西塞罗不得不在自己的门客面前引颈受戮，当加图这位道德的典范挥剑自刎以向世界表明自己和国家已是大难临头时，我们会为命运如此不公平地给予回报而感到愤愤不平。那么，在看到这些最出色的人遭到最悲惨的下场时，我们每个人对自己会有怎样的祈望呢？接下来会怎样呢？好好看看这些人是怎么忍受自己的命运的。如果他们是勇敢的，就以你的精神来希求得到他们那种精神；如果他们像女人似的懦弱死去，那么就死得全无价值。他们或因勇敢而值得你赞赏或因懦弱不值得你想念。崇高伟大的人勇敢赴死而使别人感到恐惧，还有比这更耻辱的吗？让我们反复夸奖那些值得夸奖的人，让我们说：“人越勇敢，就越幸福！你已经逃过了所有的劫难、嫉恨和疾病，你已经出狱——并非因为对诸神来说你就该命途多舛，而是因为命运再掌控你已没有价值。”但对那些在赴死之前退缩不舍，回望生活的人，我们应该嗤之以鼻。我不会为幸福的人哭泣，也不会为哭泣的人哭泣，前者会亲手拭去我的泪水，后者因其泪水而不配我为之洒下热泪。我应该为被活活烧死的赫拉克勒斯哭泣吗？或者为瑞古拉斯，因为那么多钉子都戳进他的身体？或者为加图，因为他刺痛了自己的旧伤？所有这些人因为放弃短暂而获得永生，因为死亡而成就不朽。如果你太在意自己的模样而不向任何人公开表露自己，就像很多人过着虚伪的生活，只想以外表示人一样，那么就会有产生焦虑的另一大缘由。总是小心翼翼，唯恐自己平日的面具滑脱而被人看到，这亦令人苦恼不安。当我们想到每当被人看到时总会被人评头品足，这也会使我们不无忧虑，有很多事情是在我们不情愿的时候揭掉了假象，即便这种对自己的关注是正面的，那种总在面具后面的日子也是不开心甚至令人堪忧的。相反，诚实、自然、无修饰的质朴以及毫不掩饰自我个性的生活是多么快乐无忧啊！一旦所有的事情向所有的人曝光，这种生活还难免会有被人鄙视的危险，因为对于某些人来说，熟悉就会产生轻蔑。但是，近距离观察，道德也不会有贬值的危险，质朴而被轻视总比长久伪装而苦恼好吧。让我们在这里仍采取中庸之道吧，简朴生活与马马虎虎过日子是有很大区别的。

我们还应该多多回归自我，因为和与自己不同的人接触会扰乱平静的天性，又会触动激情，加重尚未治愈的心理缺陷。然而独处与合群这两种方式必须中和与变通，第一种使我们渴望与人们接触，另一种又使我们渴望自己的空间，每一种对于另一种都是一种补救：独处缓解了我们对人多的厌烦，而从众又会消除因独处而产生的乏味。

人的思想不会一直专注于同一件事，而是要进行一些有趣的消遣。苏格拉底不会因与孩子在一起玩耍而脸红；加图在料理国事感到疲倦的时候也会以酒来放松自己的心情；西庇奥过去常常以跳舞来放松他那常胜军人的身躯，不是跳现在那种缓慢娇柔的舞蹈，那种让现代男人走路都效仿、扭摆起来比女人还性感的风格，而是过去那种男人在娱乐和节日时跳的充满阳刚之气的舞蹈，这种舞蹈即使在敌人的注视下也不会失去尊严。我们的心情必须放松，休憩之后精神会更饱满、机敏，就如同我们不能强求农田不断高产，因为那样会使田地很快耗竭，而长时间努力工作也会耗尽我们的精力，短时间的休息和放松则会使能量恢复。长期不间断地工作会使大脑迟钝、疲惫。如果运动和游戏不能带来一种自然而然的快乐，人们是不会乐于从事的，虽然反复沉迷于这些娱乐活动也会使人的思想失重，脑力受到损害。还要谨记的是，睡眠对于恢复体力也是非常必要的，但是如果睡眠时间太长，白天黑夜地睡，那无异于死亡。松弛和放任是有很大区别的。法律制定者规定了假期以使人们按公家要求享有放松的假日，他们认为这样可以使工作达到一种平衡，而如我所说，某些重要人物每个月给自己规定固定的日子作为假日，而另一些人把每一天分为休息和工作几个时间段。我记得伟大的演说家阿西尼乌斯·波利奥的习惯是每天工作十小时[52]后就休息，十小时后连信件都不看了，以免出现新的问题需要处理，他可以在余下的两个小时内摆脱一天的疲劳。有的人中午休息一会儿，把不太要紧的工作留在下午做。我们的前辈还禁止元老院工作十小时后提出任何新的动议。军队将警卫工作分班轮流做，那些刚刚返回的长途巡警不再安排夜间值班。我们必须照顾好我们的思想，不时地让思想休息一下，这是给它补充营养和力量。我们必须到户外去散步，晴朗的天空、新鲜的空气会给我们增添能量与活力。有时，我们的心灵需要从乘车出游、景色的变换、社交活动和无拘无束的畅饮中获取能量。我们甚至偶尔要沉浸在酒中陶醉一下，但不是酩酊大醉，这样确实可以冲走烦恼，彻底触动心灵，治愈哀愁，就如治愈某些疾病一般。酒的发明者之所以被称为“解放者”，并非因为酒给了舌头自由让饮者畅所欲言，而是因为他使心灵从被禁锢的状态解脱出来，受到关爱，得到自由，增添活力，并鼓励它大胆从事自己所有的事业。然而，饮酒有一个从健康考虑的适度问题，就如自由也要有度一般。人们认为梭伦和阿尔凯西劳斯很喜欢喝酒，而有人指责加图酗酒，可任何指责他的人会更容易使加图令人景仰，而不是让他名誉扫地。但我们不能总是饮酒，以免养成坏习惯，但有时可以刺激一下，让心情无拘束地快活一下，暂时收起那一本正经的严肃。无论我们是否认同希腊诗人所说的“有时癫狂也很可爱”，或柏拉图说的“一个理智健全的人要想敲开诗歌王国的大门是徒劳的”，或亚里士多德所说的“智力超群的人没有不带一点儿癫狂的”，事实是，只有心灵被深深触动之后才能写出不同凡响、他人难以企及的作品。只有当它对平庸陈腐的思想不屑一顾，凭借神性的想象力振翮高飞时，才能发出超凡脱俗的高雅心声。只要它停留在自己原有的感觉中，它就不可能达到高难的程度，它必须舍弃惯常的跑道向前驶去，迫不及待地催促驾驭者沿着自己的路线到达一个它自身不敢攀登的高度。

所以，亲爱的塞雷努斯，你现在有了保持心灵宁静的方法、恢复心灵宁静的方法，以及克服那些无意中渐渐染上的缺点的方法。但是可以肯定，除非那摇摆不定的心灵能时时刻刻得到精心呵护，否则这些方法仍不足以维护一个如此脆弱的东西。

[1]保利努斯：塞内加的朋友，是主管罗马粮食供养的官员。

[2]这是医学之父希波克拉底的名言。

[3]这句诗的作者姓名不详。

[4]奥古斯都大帝：罗马帝国的开国君主屋大维，又名奥古斯都，生于公元前63年9月23日死于公元14年8月19日，统治罗马四十三年。当他死去时，罗马元老院决定将他列入“神”的行列，并且将8月称为“奥古斯都”月。

[5]指朱莉亚，因通奸罪被奥古斯都流放到潘达塔里亚岛。

[6]马尔库斯·西塞罗（公元前106—前43）曾担任执政官、元老院元老、总督，是古罗马最有才华的思想家、政治家、哲学家、散文家、演说家之一。

[7]喀提林曾与西塞罗竞争执政官的职位，失败后纠集了一帮对西塞罗不满的人企图武力推翻政府。西塞罗得知后向元老院揭露了他的阴谋并成功地敦促元老院宣布他为公敌，继而一举粉碎了他的阴谋。

[8]克劳狄乌斯公元前58年为古罗马保民官，是西塞罗的政敌，曾提出针对西塞罗的放逐法案。

[9]西塞罗因拒绝参加庞培、克劳苏、恺撒组成的前三头联盟而得罪了他们。

[10]李维乌斯·杜路苏斯是公元前91年的保民官，曾提出谷物法并倡议给予意大利人公民权。

[11]在当时古罗马公众娱乐活动的管理权归执政官。

[12]古罗马奥古斯都时期最重要的诗人维吉尔（公元前70—前19）《田园诗》中的诗句。

[13]法比亚诺斯：古罗马的一位哲学家，是塞内加非常敬佩的一位老师。

[14]指每天天快黑时放进法院的看门狗，它们会向仍在工作的律师扑去，把他们赶回家。

[15]指在当时被当作公共拍卖的标记插在地上的矛，这样的拍卖市场一般是拍卖战争中的缴获品或充公物品。

[16]古代的法律抄本由固定在一处的木块组成。

[17]指波斯帝国国王薛西斯，他于公元前480年入侵希腊。他在色雷斯的多里司科斯的平原上摆下他庞大的陆军，因人数太多，只能通过计算一块可容纳一万人的面积，然后乘以面积的倍数来估计。

[18]意思是他们就像儿童一样，因为儿童的葬礼是在晚上举行，因而需要举着火把和蜡烛。

[19]塞内加于公元41年被克劳狄皇帝判处死刑，后改判流放科西嘉岛，直到公元49年才被召回。这封信是塞内加到流放地不久写给母亲赫尔维亚的，试图安慰母亲不要为他悲伤。

[20]相传罗慕路斯是母狼哺育的两个男婴之一，罗马城的奠基者和第一个皇帝。

[21]马可斯·布鲁图斯（公元前85—前42）是晚期罗马共和国的一名元老院议员，他组织并参与了对恺撒的谋杀。

[22]马塞卢斯曾于公元前51年任执政官，他是恺撒的死敌。

[23]布鲁图斯和加图是亲戚，很受加图的尊崇。

[24]古罗马的货币。

[25]指的是古罗马的将军雷古勒斯。他在公元前255年被迦太基人俘获，按传统，应被囚禁于迦太基，除非按“凭誓获释”的规定，作为和谈的代表他才可以回罗马。据说，雷古勒斯回到罗马后力劝元老院拒绝迦太基人的提议，而后遵守自己的誓言又回到迦太基受死。

[26]指马尼乌斯·克里乌斯，他因打败萨姆奈特人、萨宾人和皮洛士人而出名。

[27]这是胜利者的特权。

[28]阿皮休斯是一个声名狼藉的美食家。

[29]公元前404年，斯巴达人打败雅典人，结束了长达二十七年的伯罗奔尼撒战争。这时曾是苏格拉底学生的克里底亚和查米迪斯成立了三十僭主集团。豪权政治代替了民主，这个集团在执政的八个月中就处死了一千五百人。八个月后，三十僭主集团垮台，民主制度恢复，克里底亚和查米迪斯被处死，苏格拉底也因此受到牵连，也被处以死刑。

[30]阿里斯德岱斯是雅典稳重派领袖，以廉洁无私著称。

[31]格拉古兄弟的母亲。格拉古兄弟的父亲老提比略·格拉古曾在公元前177年和前163年出任罗马执政官。母亲科妮莉亚·阿菲莉加娜来自显赫的西庇阿家族。她的父亲就是大名鼎鼎的阿非利加征服者。据说科妮莉亚·阿菲莉加娜曾拒绝了埃及法老托勒密的求婚，悉心教子并聘请了有名的希腊学者来做家庭教师，使兄弟两人受到了良好的教育。

[32]塞雷努斯：塞内加的一个好朋友，是尼禄时代的一个高级官员，塞内加流传下来的好几封信都是写给他的。

[33]阿基里斯：荷马史诗《伊里亚特》中的人物，他因为朋友帕特洛克罗斯的死而痛不欲生，因而辗转反侧，坐立不安。

[34]卢克莱修（约公元前99—前55）：古罗马哲学家。他继承古代原子学说，特别阐述并发展了伊壁鸠鲁的哲学观点。他认为物质的存在是永恒的，提出了“无物能由无中生，无物能归于无”的唯物主义观点。著有哲学长诗《物性论》。

[35]阿森诺德斯：奥古斯都的老师，任其军师二十九年，斯多葛派哲学家。

[36]迦太基政府的一个高级职位。

[37]哈默迪乌斯曾与阿里斯托杰顿一起带头推翻雅典的僭主佩西司特拉提达伊。

[38]伊索克拉底：古代雅典著名的演说家、教师和修辞学家。

[39]埃弗罗斯：公元前4世纪著名的历史学家。

[40]第欧根尼（公元前404—前323）：出生于一个银行家家庭，是古希腊犬儒学派哲学家。他认为除了自然的需要必须满足外，其他的任何东西，都是不自然的。他强调禁欲主义的自我满足，鼓励放弃舒适环境。作为一个苦行主义的身体力行者，他居住在一只木桶内，过着乞丐一样的生活。

[41]位于埃及亚历山大里亚城，是最著名的古代图书馆之一。它始建于公元前259年，由埃及的托勒密王朝相继建立与管理。据说当初建亚历山大图书馆唯一的目的就是“收集全世界的书”，实现“世界知识总汇”的梦想。据说当时尽管有战乱，亚历山大图书馆仍藏书约五万四千万卷。极盛时据说馆藏各类手稿逾五十万卷（纸草卷）。不少历史名人都曾出任过亚历山大图书馆的馆长，很多圣贤也均在此讲学或求学，使图书馆享有“世界上最好的学校”的美名，并在整个地中海世界传播文明长达二百至八百年。传说它先后毁于两场大火。现在的亚历山大图书馆是1995年后重建的，占地四万平方米，它不仅是埃及的重点建筑项目，也是联合国教科文组织在世界范围内的重大科研和建筑项目。

[42]提图斯·李维（公元前59—公元17）：古罗马历史学家。生于意大利北部的帕塔维乌姆（今帕多瓦）。他学习了文学、史学、修辞学、演说术等，是罗马共和后期学问渊博、几乎无所不知的大学问家。后李维奉命教授屋大维的继孙克劳狄，即后来的皇帝。李维著述丰富，但流传下来的只有《罗马自建城以来的历史》一书。他用四十年左右时间写成的这部罗马史巨著，共一百四十二卷，记述自传说中的埃涅阿斯到达意大利至公元前9年的史事，著作中保存了丰富和宝贵的历史资料，不失为研究罗马早期及罗马共和国历史的重要文献。

[43]指监守吏，他们有时押解犯人时需要将犯人铐在自己的左手上。

[44]普布利柳斯·西鲁斯（公元前42—前1）：古罗马作家。

[45]塞扬努斯：曾为执政官，在一次元老院的会议上被押解到监狱，并在同一天被处决。

[46]库罗斯索斯：吕底亚国王，被波斯王打败，即将遭到火焚处死时，他流泪高呼索伦之名，波斯王问明情况，了解了索伦的警语，动了慈悲之心，免他一死。

[47]朱古达：努米底亚国王，从公元前111年到前105年与古代罗马长期战争。努米底亚拥有精锐骑兵，而罗马军队士气涣散，连遭失败。前107年，马略当选为执政官，受权指挥北非作战，接连获胜。朱古达陷入困境，退至邻国毛里塔尼亚避难。前105年，毛里塔尼亚国王把朱古达引渡给罗马军副，马略凯旋罗马。翌年，朱古达死于狱中，努米底亚被分割。

[48]托勒密：毛里塔尼亚的国王，被流放到罗马处死。

[49]米特里达特：亚美尼亚国王，后来重新登上王位。

[50]尤里乌斯·卡那斯：斯多葛派哲学家，被暴君卡里古拉处死。

[51]法拉里斯：公元前6世纪西西里岛上的暴君。最臭名昭著的是他叫工匠制作了一头铜牛，将犯人关进牛肚子，然后用火烧，被关在里面的人的惨叫声可以通过缚在牛鼻子上的长笛传出来，长笛可以将惨叫声转化为音乐。

[52]古罗马人将每天日出和日落之间的时间分为十二个小时。阿西尼乌斯·波利奥在这十二小时中，前十小时工作，然后就休息。

On the Shortness of Life

Most human beings, Paulinus,[〔1〕] complain about the meanness of nature, because we are born for a brief span of life, and because this spell of time that has been given to us rushes by so swiftly and rapidly that with very few exceptions life ceases for the rest of us just when we are getting ready for it. Nor is it just the man in the street and the unthinking mass of people who groan over this — as they see it — universal evil: the same feeling lies behind complaints from even distinguished men. Hence the dictum of the greatest of doctors:[〔2〕] 'Life is short, art is long.' Hence too the grievance, most improper to a wise man, which Aristotle expressed when he was taking nature to task for indulging animals with such long existences that they can live through five or ten human lifetimes, while a far shorter limit is set for men who are born to a great and extensive destiny. It is not that we have a short time to live, but that we waste a lot of it. Life is long enough, and a sufficiently generous amount has been given to us for the highest achievements if it were all well invested. But when it is wasted in heedless luxury and spent on no good activity, we are forced at last by death's final constraint to realize that it has passed away before we knew it was passing. So it is: we are not given a short life but we make it short, and we are not ill-supplied but wasteful of it. Just as when ample and princely wealth falls to a bad owner it is squandered in a moment, but wealth however modest, if entrusted to a good custodian, increases with use, so our lifetime extends amply if you manage it properly.

Why do we complain about nature? She has acted kindly: life is long if you know how to use it. But one man is gripped by insatiable greed, another by a laborious dedication to useless tasks. One man is soaked in wine, another sluggish with idleness. One man is worn out by political ambition, which is always at the mercy of the judgement of others. Another through hope of profit is driven headlong over all lands and seas by the greed of trading. Some are tormented by a passion for army life, always intent on inflicting dangers on others or anxious about danger to themselves. Some are worn out by the self-imposed servitude of thankless attendance on the great. Many are occupied by either pursuing other people's money or complaining about their own. Many pursue no fixed goal, but are tossed about in ever-changing designs by a fickleness which is shifting, inconstant and never satisfied with itself. Some have no aims at all for their life's course, but death takes them unawares as they yawn languidly — so much so that I cannot doubt the truth of that oracular remark of the greatest of poets: 'It is a small part of life we really live.' Indeed, all the rest is not life but merely time. Vices surround and assail men from every side, and do not allow them to rise again and lift their eyes to discern the truth, but keep them overwhelmed and rooted in their desires. Never can they recover their true selves. If by chance they achieve some tranquillity, just as a swell remains on the deep sea even after the wind has dropped, so they go on tossing about and never find rest from their desires. Do you think I am speaking only of those whose wickedness is acknowledged? Look at those whose good fortune people gather to see: they are choked by their own blessings. How many find their riches a burden! How many burst a blood vessel by their eloquence and their daily striving to show off their talents! How many are pale from constant pleasures! How many are left no freedom by the crowd of clients surrounding them! In a word, run through them all, from lowest to highest: one calls for legal assistance, another comes to help; one is on trial, another defends him, another gives a judgment; no one makes his claim to himself, but each is exploited for another's sake. Ask about those whose names are learned by heart, and you will see that they have these distinguishing marks: X cultivates Y and Y cultivates Z — no one bothers about himself. Again, certain people reveal the most stupid indignation: they complain about the pride of their superiors because they did not have time to give them an audience when they wanted one. But can anyone dare to complain about another's pride when he himself never has time for himself? Yet whoever you are, the great man has sometimes gazed upon you, even if his look was patronizing, he has bent his ears to your words, he has let you walk beside him. But you never deign to look at yourself or listen to yourself. So you have no reason to claim credit from anyone for those attentions, since you showed them not because you wanted someone else's company but because you could not bearyour own.

Even if all the bright intellects who ever lived were to agree to ponder this one theme, they would never sufficiently express their surprise at this fog in the human mind. Men do not let anyone seize their estates, and if there is the slightest dispute about their boundaries they rush to stones and arms; but they allow others to encroach on their lives — why, they themselves even invite in those who will take over their lives. You will find no one willing to share out his money; but to how many does each of us divide up his life! People are frugal in guarding their personal property; but as soon as it comes to squandering time they are most wasteful of the one thing in which it is right to be stingy. So, I would like to fasten on someone from the older generation and say to him: 'I see that you have come to the last stage of human life; you are close upon your hundredth year, or even beyond: come now, hold an audit of your life. Reckon how much of your time has been taken up by a money-lender, how much by a mistress, a patron, a client, quarrelling with your wife, punishing your slaves, dashing about the city on your social obligations. Consider also the diseases which we have brought on ourselves, and the time too which has been unused. You will find that you have fewer years than you reckon. Call to mind when you ever had a fixed purpose; how few days have passed as you had planned; when you were ever at your own disposal; when your face wore its natural expression; when your mind was undisturbed; what work you have achieved in such a long life; how many have plundered your life when you were unaware of your losses; how much you have lost through groundless sorrow, foolish joy, greedy desire, the seductions of society; how little of your own was left to you. You will realize that you are dying prematurely.'

So what is the reason for this? You are living as if destined to live for ever; your own frailty never occurs to you; you don't notice how much time has already passed, but squander it as though you had a full and overflowing supply — though all the while that very day which you are devoting to somebody or something may be your last. You act like mortals in all that you fear, and like immortals in all that you desire. You will hear many people saying: 'When I am fifty I shall retire into leisure; when I am sixty I shall give up public duties.' And what guarantee do you have of a longer life? Who will allow your course to proceed as you arrange it? Aren't you ashamed to keep for yourself just the remnants of your life, and to devote to wisdom only that time which cannot be spent on any business? How late it is to begin really to live just when life must end! How stupid to forget our mortality, and put off sensible plans to our fiftieth and sixtieth years, aiming to begin life from a point at which few have arrived!

You will notice that the most powerful and highly stationed men let drop remarks in which they pray for leisure, praise it, and rate it higher than all their blessings. At times they long to descend from their pinnacles if they can in safety; for even if nothing external assails or agitates it, high fortune of itself comes crashing down.

The deified Augustus, to whom the gods granted more than to anyone else, never ceased to pray for rest and to seek a respite from public affairs. Everything he said always reverted to this theme — his hope for leisure. He used to beguile his labours with this consolation, sweet though false, that one day he would live to please himself. In a letter he wrote to the senate, after he promised that his rest would not be lacking in dignity nor inconsistent with his former glory, I find these words: 'But it is more impressive to carry out these things than to promise them. Nevertheless, since the delightful reality is still a long way off, my longing for that much desired time has led me to anticipate some of its delight by the pleasure arising from words.' So valuable did leisure seem to him that because he could not enjoy it in actuality, he did so mentally in advance. He who saw that everything depended on himself alone, who decided the fortune of individuals and nations, was happiest when thinking of that day on which he would lay aside his own greatness. He knew from experience how much sweat those blessings gleaming through every land cost him, how many secret anxieties they concealed. He was forced to fight first with his fellow-countrymen, then with his colleagues, and finally with his relations, shedding blood on land and sea. Driven to fight in Macedonia, Sicily, Egypt, Syria, Asia — almost every country — he turned his armies against foreign enemies when they were tired of shedding Roman blood. While he was establishing peace in the Alps and subduing enemies established in the middle of his peaceful empire; while he was extending his boundaries beyond the Rhine, the Euphrates and the Danube, at Rome itself Murena, Caepio, Lepidus, Egnatius and others were sharpening their swords against him. Nor had he yet escaped their plots when his daughter and all the noble youths bound to her by adultery as though by an oath kept alarming his feeble old age, as did Iullus and a second formidable woman linked to an Antony. He cut away these ulcers, limbs and all, but others took their place: just like a body with a surfeit of blood which is always subject to a haemorrhage somewhere. So he longed for leisure, and as his hopes and thoughts dwelt on that he found relief for his labours: this was the prayer of the man who could grant the prayers of mankind.

When Marcus Cicero was cast among men like Catiline and Clodius and Pompey and Crassus — some of them undisguised enemies and some doubtful friends — when he was tossed about in the storm that struck the state, he tried to hold it steady as it went to its doom; but at last he was swept away. He had neither peace in prosperity nor patience in adversity, and how often does he curse that very consulship, which he had praised without ceasing though not without good reason! What woeful words he uses in a letter to Atticus when the elder Pompey had been conquered, and his son was still trying to revive his defeated forces in Spain! 'Do you want to know,' he said, 'what I am doing here? I am staying a semi-prisoner in my Tusculan villa.' He then goes on to bewail his former life, to complain of the present, and to despair of the future. Cicero called himself a semi-prisoner, but really and truly the wise man will never go so far as to use such an abject term. He will never be a semi-prisoner, but will always enjoy freedom which is solid and complete, at liberty to be his own master and higher than all others. For what can be above the man who is above fortune?

Livius Drusus, a bold and vigorous man, had proposed laws which renewed the evil policy of the Gracchi, and he was supported by a huge crowd from all over Italy. But he could see no successful outcome for his measures, which he could neither carry through nor abandon once embarked upon; and he is said to have cursed the turbulent life he had always lived, saying that he alone had never had a holiday even as a child. For while still a ward and dressed as a youth he ventured to speak to a jury in favour of some accused men, and to acquire influence in the law courts, with so much effect that, as we all know, he forced certain verdicts favourable to his clients. To what lengths would so precocious an ambition not go? You might have known that such premature boldness would result in terrible trouble, both public and private. So he was too late in complaining that he had never had a holiday, since from his boyhood he had been a serious trouble-maker in the Forum. It is uncertain whether he died by his own hand, for he collapsed after receiving a sudden wound in the groin, some people doubting whether his death was self-inflicted, but no one doubting that it was timely.

It would be superfluous to mention any more who, though seeming to others the happiest of mortals, themselves bore true witness against themselves by their expressed hatred of every action of their lives. Yet they did not change themselves or anyone else by these complaints, for after their explosion of words their feelings reverted to normal.

Assuredly your lives, even if they last more than a thousand years, will shrink into the tiniest span: those vices will swallow up any space of time. The actual time you have — which reason can prolong though it naturally passes quickly — inevitably escapes you rapidly: for you do not grasp it or hold it back or try to delay that swiftest of all things, but you let it slip away as though it were something superfluous and replaceable.

But among the worst offenders I count those who spend all their time in drinking and lust, for these are the worst preoccupations of all. Other people, even if they are possessed by an illusory semblance of glory, suffer from a respectable delusion. You can give me a list of miserly men, or hot-tempered men who indulge in unjust hatreds or wars: but they are all sinning in a more manly way. It is those who are on a headlong course of gluttony and lust who are stained with dishonour. Examine how all these people spend their time — how long they devote to their accounts, to laying traps for others or fearing those laid for themselves, to paying court to others or being courted themselves, to giving or receiving bail, to banquets (which now count as official business): you will see how their activities, good or bad, do not give them even time to breathe.

Finally, it is generally agreed that no activity can be successfully pursued by an individual who is preoccupied — not rhetoric or liberal studies — since the mind when distracted absorbs nothing deeply, but rejects everything which is, so to speak, crammed into it. Living is the least important activity of the preoccupied man; yet there is nothing which is harder to learn. There are many instructors in the other arts to be found everywhere: indeed, some of these arts mere boys have grasped so thoroughly that they can even teach them. But learning how to live takes a whole life, and, which may surprise you more, it takes a whole life to learn how to die. So many of the finest men have put aside all their encumbrances, renouncing riches and business and pleasure, and made it their one aim up to the end of their lives to know how to live. Yet most of these have died confessing that they did not yet know — still less can those others know. Believe me, it is the sign of a great man, and one who is above human error, not to allow his time to be frittered away: he has the longest possible life simply because whatever time was available he devoted entirely to himself. None of it lay fallow and neglected, none of it under another's control; for being an extremely thrifty guardian of his time he never found anything for which it was worth exchanging. So he had enough time; but those into whose lives the public have made great inroads inevitably have too little.

Nor must you think that such people do not sometimes recognize their loss. Indeed, you will hear many of those to whom great prosperity is a burden sometimes crying out amidst their hordes of clients or their pleadings in law courts or their other honourable miseries. 'It's impossible to live.' Of course it's impossible. All those who call you to themselves draw you away from yourself. How many days has that defendant stolen from you? Or that candidate? Or that old lady worn out with burying her heirs? Or that man shamming an illness to excite the greed of legacy-hunters? Or that influential friend who keeps people like you not for friendship but for display? Mark off, I tell you, and review the days of your life: you will see that very few — the useless remnants — have been left to you. One man who has achieved the badge of office he coveted longs to lay it aside, and keeps repeating, 'Will this year never end?' Another man thought it a great coup to win the chance of giving games, but, having given them, he says, 'When shall I be rid of them?' That advocate is grabbed on every side throughout the Forum, and fills the whole place with a huge crowd extending further than he can be heard: but he says, 'When will vacation come?' Everyone hustles his life along, and is troubled by a longing for the future and weariness of the present. But the man who spends all his time on his own needs, who organizes every day as though it were his last, neither longs for nor fears the next day. For what new pleasures can any hour now bring him? He has tried everything, and enjoyed everything to repletion. For the rest, Fortune can dispose as she likes: his life is now secure. Nothing can be taken from this life, and you can only add to it as if giving to a man who is already full and satisfied food which he does not want but can hold. So you must not think a man has lived long because he has white hair and wrinkles: he has not lived long, just existed long. For suppose you should think that a man had had a long voyage who had been caught in a raging storm as he left harbour, and carried hither and thither and driven round and round in a circle by the rage of opposing winds? He did not have a long voyage, just a long tossing about.

I am always surprised to see some people demanding the time of others and meeting a most obliging response. Both sides have in view the reason for which the time is asked and neither regards the time itself — as if nothing there is being asked for and nothing given. They are trifling with life's most precious commodity, being deceived because it is an intangible thing, not open to inspection and therefore reckoned very cheap — in fact, almost without any value. People are delighted to accept pensions and gratuities, for which they hire out their labour or their support or their services. But nobody works out the value of time: men use it lavishly as if it cost nothing. But if death threatens these same people, you will see them praying to their doctors; if they are in fear of capital punishment, you will see them prepared to spend their all to stay alive. So inconsistent are they in their feelings. But if each of us could have the tally of his future years set before him, as we can of our past years, how alarmed would be those who saw only a few years ahead, and how carefully would they use them! And yet it is easy to organize an amount, however small, which is assured; we have to be more careful in preserving what will cease at an unknown point.

But you are not to think that these people do not know how precious time is. They commonly say to those they are particularly fond of that they are ready to give them some of their years. And they do give them without being aware of it; but the gift is such that they themselves lose without adding anything to the others. But what they actually do not know is whether they are losing; thus they can bear the loss of what they do not know has gone. No one will bring back the years; no one will restore you to yourself. Life will follow the path it began to take, and will neither reverse nor check its course. It will cause no commotion to remind you of its swiftness, but glide on quietly. It will not lengthen itself for a king's command or a people's favour. As it started out on its first day, so it will run on, nowhere pausing or turning aside. What will be the outcome? You have been preoccupied while life hastens on. Meanwhile death will arrive, and you have no choice in making yourself available for that.

Can anything be more idiotic than certain people who boast of their foresight? They keep themselves officiously preoccupied in order to improve their lives; they spend their lives in organizing their lives. They direct their purposes with an eye to a distant future. But putting things off is the biggest waste of life: it snatches away each day as it comes, and denies us the present by promising the future. The greatest obstacle to living is expectancy, which hangs upon tomorrow and loses today. You are arranging what lies in Fortune's control, and abandoning what lies in yours. What are you looking at? To what goal are you straining? The whole future lies in uncertainty: live immediately. Listen to the cry of our greatest poet, who as though inspired with divine utterance sings salutary verses:

Life's finest day for wretched mortals here

Is always first to flee.

'Why do you linger?' he means. 'Why are you idle? If you don't grasp it first, it flees.' And even if you do grasp it, it will still flee. So you must match time's swiftness with your speed in using it, and you must drink quickly as though from a rapid stream that will not always flow. In chastising endless delay, too, the poet very elegantly speaks not of the 'finest age' but 'finest day'. However greedy you are, why are you so unconcerned and so sluggish (while time flies so fast), extending months and years in a long sequence ahead of you? The poet is telling you about the day — and about this very day that is escaping. So can it be doubted that for wretched mortals — that is, the preoccupied — the finest day is always the first to flee? Old age overtakes them while they are still mentally childish, and they face it unprepared and unarmed. For they have made no provision for it, stumbling upon it suddenly and unawares, and without realizing that it was approaching day by day. Just as travellers are beguiled by conversation or reading or some profound meditation, and find they have arrived at their destination before they knew they were approaching it; so it is with this unceasing and extremely fast-moving journey of life, which waking or sleeping we make at the same pace — the preoccupied become aware of it only when it is over.

If I wanted to divide my theme into different headings and offer proofs, I would find many arguments to prove that the preoccupied find life very short. But Fabianus, who was not one of today's academic philosophers but the true old-fashioned sort, used to say that we must attack the passions by brute force and not by logic; that the enemy's line must be turned by a strong attack and not by pinpricks; for vices have to be crushed rather than picked at. Still, in order that the people concerned may be censured for their own individual faults, they must be taught and not just given up for lost.

Life is divided into three periods, past, present and future. Of these, the present is short, the future is doubtful, the past is certain. For this last is the one over which Fortune has lost her power, which cannot be brought back to anyone's control. But this is what preoccupied people lose: for they have no time to look back at their past, and even if they did, it is not pleasant to recall activities they are ashamed of. So they are unwilling to cast their minds back to times ill spent, which they dare not relive if their vices in recollection become obvious — even those vices whose insidious approach was disguised by the charm of some momentary pleasure. No one willingly reverts to the past unless all his actions have passed his own censorship, which is never deceived. The man who must fear his own memory is the one who has been ambitious in his greed, arrogant in his contempt, uncontrolled in his victories, treacherous in his deceptions, rapacious in his plundering, and wasteful in his squandering. And yet this is the period of our time which is sacred and dedicated, which has passed beyond all human risks and is removed from Fortune's sway, which cannot be harassed by want or fear or attacks of illness. It cannot be disturbed or snatched from us: it is an untroubled, everlasting possession. In the present we have only one day at a time, each offering a minute at a time. But all the days of the past will come to your call: you can detain and inspect them at your will — something which the preoccupied have no time to do. It is the mind which is tranquil and free from care which can roam through all the stages of its life: the minds of the preoccupied, as if harnessed in a yoke, cannot turn round and look behind them. So their lives vanish into an abyss; and just as it is no use pouring any amount of liquid into a container without a bottom to catch and hold it, so it does not matter how much time we are given if there is nowhere for it to settle; it escapes through the cracks and holes of the mind. The present time is extremely short, so much so that some people are unaware of it. For it is always on the move, flowing on in a rush; it ceases before it has come, and does not suffer delay any more than the firmament or the stars, whose unceasing movement never pauses in the same place. And so the preoccupied are concerned only with the present, and it is so short that it cannot be grasped, and even this is stolen from them while they are involved in their many distractions.

In a word, would you like to know how they do not live long? See how keen they are to live long. Feeble old men pray for a few more years; they pretend they are younger than they are; they comfort themselves by this deception and fool themselves as eagerly as if they fooled Fate at the same time. But when at last some illness has reminded them of their mortality, how terrified do they die, as if they were not just passing out of life but being dragged out of it. They exclaim that they were fools because they have not really lived, and that if only they can recover from this illness they will live in leisure. Then they reflect how pointlessly they acquired things they never would enjoy, and how all their toil has been in vain. But for those whose life is far removed from all business it must be amply long. None of it is frittered away, none of it scattered here and there, none of it committed to fortune, none of it lost through carelessness, none ofit wasted on largesse, none of it superfluous: the whole of it, so to speak, is well invested. So, however short, it is fully sufficient, and therefore whenever his last day comes, the wise man will not hesitate to meet death with a firm step.

Perhaps you want to know whom I would call the preoccupied? You must not imagine I mean just those who are driven from the law court only by the arrival of the watchdogs; or those whom you see crushed either honourably in their own crowd of supporters or contemptuously in someone else's; or those whose social duties bring them forth from their own homes to dash them against someone else's doors; or those whom the praetor's auction spear occupies in acquiring disreputable gain which will one day turn rank upon them. Some men are preoccupied even in their leisure: in their country house, on their couch, in the midst of solitude, even when quite alone, they are their own worst company. You could not call theirs a life of leisure, but an idle preoccupation. Do you call that man leisured who arranges with anxious precision his Corinthian bronzes, the cost of which is inflated by the mania of a few collectors, and spends most of the day on rusty bits of metal? Who sits at a wrestling ring (for shame on us! We suffer from vices which are not even Roman), keenly following the bouts between boys? Who classifies his herds of pack-animals into pairs according to age and colour? Who pays for the maintenance of the latest athletes? Again, do you call those men leisured who spend many hours at the barber's simply to cut whatever grew overnight, to have a serious debate about every separate hair, to tidy up disarranged locks or to train thinning ones from the sides to lie over the forehead? How angry they get if the barber has been a bit careless — as if he were trimming a real man! How they flare up if any of their mane is wrongly cut off, if any of it is badly arranged, or if it doesn't all fall into the right ringlets! Which of them would not rather have his country ruffled than his hair? Which would not be more anxious about the elegance of his head than its safety? Which would not rather be trim than honourable? Do you call those men leisured who divide their time between the comb and the mirror? And what about those who busy themselves in composing, listening to, or learning songs, while they distort their voice, whose best and simplest tone nature intended to be the straight one, into the most unnatural modulations; who are always drumming with their fingers as they beat time to an imagined tune; whom you can hear humming to themselves even when they are summoned on a serious, often even sorrowful, affair? Theirs is not leisure but indolent occupation. And, good heavens, as for their banquets, I would not reckon on them as leisure times when I see how anxiously they arrange their silver, how carefully they gird up the tunics of their page-boys, how on tenterhooks they are to see how the cook has dealt with the boar, with what speed smooth-faced slaves rush around on their duties, with what skill birds are carved into appropriate portions, how carefully wretched little slaves wipe up the spittle of drunkards. By these means they cultivate a reputation for elegance and good taste, and to such an extent do their failings follow them into all areas of their private lives that they cannot eat or drink without ostentation.

I would also not count as leisured those who are carried around in a sedan chair and a litter, and turn up punctually for their drives as if it was forbidden to give them up; who have to be told when to bathe or to swim or to dine: they are so enervated by the excessive torpor of a self-indulgent mind that they cannot trust themselves to know if they are hungry. I am told that one of these self-indulgent people — if self-indulgence is the right word for unlearning the ordinary habits of human life — when he had been carried out from the bath and put in his sedan chair, asked, 'Am I now sitting down?' Do you think that this man, who doesn't know if he is sitting down, knows whether he is alive, whether he sees, whether he is at leisure? It is difficult to say whether I pity him more if he really did not know this or if he pretended not to know. They really experience forgetfulness of many things, but they also pretend to forget many things. They take delight in certain vices as proofs of their good fortune: it seems to be the lowly and contemptible man who knows what he is doing. After that see if you can accuse the mimes of inventing many details in order to attack luxury! In truth, they pass over more than they make up, and such a wealth of incredible vices have appeared in this generation, which shows talent in this one area, that we could now actually accuse the mimes of ignoring them. To think that there is anyone so lost in luxuries that he has to trust another to tell him if he is sitting down! So this one is not at leisure, and you must give him another description — he is ill, or even, he is dead: the man who is really at leisure is also aware of it. But this one who is only half alive, and needs to be told the positions of his own body — how can he have control over any of his time?

It would be tedious to mention individually those who have spent all their lives playing draughts or ball, or carefully cooking themselves in the sun. They are not at leisure whose pleasures involve a serious commitment. For example, nobody will dispute that those people are busy about nothing who spend their time on useless literary studies: even among the Romans there is now a large company of these. It used to be a Greek failing to want to know how many oarsmen Ulysses had, whether the Iliad or the Odyssey was written first, and whether too they were by the same author, and other questions of this kind, which if you keep them to yourself in no way enhance your private knowledge, and if you publish them make you appear more a bore than a scholar. But now the Romans too have been afflicted by the pointless enthusiasm for useless knowledge. Recently I heard somebody reporting which Roman general first did this or that: Duilius first won a naval battle; Curius Dentatus first included elephants in a triumph. So far these facts, even if they do not contribute to real glory, at least are concerned with exemplary services to the state: such knowledge will not do us any good, but it interests us because of the appeal of these pointless facts. We can also excuse those who investigate who first persuaded the Romans to embark on a ship. That was Claudius, who for this reason was called Caudex because a structure linking several wooden planks was called in antiquity a caudex. Hence too the Law Tables are called codices, and even today the boats which carry provisions up the Tiber are called by the old-fashioned name codicariae. Doubtless too it is of some importance to know that Valerius Corvinus first conquered Messana, and was the first of the family of the Valerii to be surnamed Messana from the name of the captured city — the spelling of which was gradually corrupted in everyday speech to Messalla. Perhaps you will also allow someone to take seriously the fact that Lucius Sulla first exhibited lions loose in the Circus, though at other times they were shown in fetters, and that javelin-throwers were sent by King Bocchus to kill them. This too may be excused — but does it serve any good purpose? — to know that Pompey first exhibited in the Circus a fight involving eighteen elephants, pitting innocent men against them in a staged battle. A leader of the state and, as we are told, a man of notable kindliness among the leaders of old, he thought it would be a memorable spectacle to kill human beings in a novel way. 'Are they to fight to the death? Not good enough. Are they to be torn to pieces? Not good enough. Let them be crushed by animals of enormous bulk.' It would be better for such things to be forgotten, lest in the future someone in power might learn about them and not wish to be outdone in such a piece of inhumanity. Oh, what darkness does great prosperity cast over our minds! He thought himself beyond nature's laws at the time that he was throwing so many crowds of wretched men to wild creatures from abroad, when he was setting such disparate creatures against each other, when he was shedding so much blood in front of the Roman people, who themselves were soon to be forced by him to shed their own blood. But later he himself, betrayed by Alexandrian treachery, offered himself to be stabbed by the lowest slave, only then realizing that his surname ('Great') was an empty boast.

But to return to the point from which I digressed, and to illustrate how some people spend useless efforts on these same topics, the man I referred to reported that Metellus in his triumph, after conquering the Carthaginians in Sicily, alone among all the Romans had 120 elephants led before his chariot, and that Sulla was the last of the Romans to have extended the pomerium,[〔3〕] which it was the ancient practice to extend after acquiring Italian, but never provincial, territory. Is it better to know this than to know that the Aventine Hill, as he asserted, is outside the pomerium for one of two reasons, either because the plebs withdrew to it or because when Remus took the auspices there the birds had not been favourable — and countless further theories that are either false or very close to lies? For even if you admit that they say all this in good faith, even if they guarantee the truth of their statements, whose mistakes will thereby be lessened? Whose passions restrained? Who will be made more free, more just, more magnanimous? Our Fabianus used to say that sometimes he wondered whether it was better not to be involved in any researches than to get entangled in these.

Of all people only those are at leisure who make time for philosophy, only those are really alive. For they not only keep a good watch over their own lifetimes, but they annex every age to theirs. All the years that have passed before them are added to their own. Unless we are very ungrateful, all those distinguished founders of holy creeds were born for us and prepared for us a way of life. By the toil of others we are led into the presence of things which have been brought from darkness into light. We are excluded from no age, but we have access to them all; and if we are prepared in loftiness of mind to pass beyond the narrow confines of human weakness, there is a long period of time through which we can roam. We can argue with Socrates, express doubt with Carneades, cultivate retirement with Epicurus, overcome human nature with the Stoics, and exceed its limits with the Cynics. Since nature allows us to enter into a partnership with every age, why not turn from this brief and transient spell of time and give ourselves whole-heartedly to the past, which is limitless and eternal and can be shared with better men than we?

Those who rush about on social duties, disturbing both themselves and others, when they have duly finished their crazy round and have daily crossed everyone's threshold and passed by no open door, when they have carried around their self-interested greetings to houses that are miles apart, how few will they be able to see in a city so enormous and so distracted by varied desires? How many will there be who through sleepiness or self-indulgence or ungraciousness will exclude them? How many, after keeping them in an agony of waiting, will pretend to be in a hurry and rush past them? How many will avoid going out through a hall crowded with dependants, and escape through a secret door — as if it were not even more discourteous to deceive callers than to exclude them? How many, half asleep and sluggish after yesterday's drinking, will yawn insolently and have to be prompted a thousand times in a whisper before, scarcely moving their lips, they can greet by name the poor wretches who have broken their own slumbers in order to wait on another's?

You should rather suppose that those are involved in worthwhile duties who wish to have daily as their closest friends Zeno, Pythagoras, Democritus and all the other high priests of liberal studies, and Aristotle and Theophrastus. None of these will be too busy to see you, none of these will not send his visitor away happier and more devoted to himself, none of these will allow anyone to depart empty-handed. They are at home to all mortals by night and by day.

None of these will force you to die, but all will teach you how to die. None of them will exhaust your years, but each will contribute his years to yours. With none of these will conversation be dangerous, or his friendship fatal, or attendance on him expensive. From them you can take whatever you wish: it will not be their fault if you do not take your fill from them. What happiness, what a fine old age awaits the man who has made himself a client of these! He will have friends whose advice he can ask on the most important or the most trivial matters, whom he can consult daily about himself, who will tell him the truth without insulting him and praise him without flattery, who will offer him a pattern on which to model himself.

We are in the habit of saying that it was not in our power to choose the parents who were allotted to us, that they were given to us by chance. But we can choose whose children we would like to be. There are households of the noblest intellects: choose the one into which you wish to be adopted, and you will inherit not only their name but their property too. Nor will this property need to be guarded meanly or grudgingly: the more it is shared out, the greater it will become. These will offer you a path to immortality and raise you to a point from which no one is cast down. This is the only way to prolong mortality — even to convert it to immortality. Honours, monuments, whatever the ambitious have ordered by decrees or raised in public buildings are soon destroyed: there is nothing that the passage of time does not demolish and remove. But it cannot damage the works which philosophy has consecrated: no age will wipe them out, no age diminish them. The next and every following age will only increase the veneration for them, since envy operates on what is at hand, but we can more openly admire things from a distance. So the life of the philosopher extends widely: he is not confined by the same boundary as are others. He alone is free from the laws that limit the human race, and all ages serve him as though he were a god. Some time has passed: he grasps it in his recollection. Time is present: he uses it. Time is to come: he anticipates it. This combination of all times into one gives him a long life.

But life is very short and anxious for those who forget the past, neglect the present, and fear the future. When they come to the end of it, the poor wretches realize too late that for all this time they have been preoccupied in doing nothing. And the fact that they sometimes invoke death is no proof that their lives seem long. Their own folly afflicts them with restless emotions which hurl themselves upon the very things they fear: they often long for death because they fear it. Nor is this a proof that they are living for a long time that the day often seems long to them, or that they complain that the hours pass slowly until the time fixed for dinner arrives. For as soon as their preoccupations fail them, they are restless with nothing to do, not knowing how to dispose of their leisure or make the time pass. And so they are anxious for something else to do, and all the intervening time is wearisome: really, it is just as when a gladiatorial show has been announced, or they are looking forward to the appointed time of some other exhibition or amusement — they want to leap over the days in between. Any deferment of the longed-for event is tedious to them. Yet the time of the actual enjoyment is short and swift, and made much shorter through their own fault. For they dash from one pleasure to another and cannot stay steady in one desire. Their days are not long but odious: on the other hand, how short do the nights seem which they spend drinking or sleeping with harlots! Hence the lunacy of the poets, who encourage human frailty by their stories in which Jupiter, seduced by the pleasures of love-making, is seen to double the length of the night. What else is it but to inflame our vices when they quote the gods to endorse them, and as a precedent for our failings they offer — and excuse — the wantonness of the gods? Can the nights, which they purchase so dearly, not seem much too short to these people? They lose the day in waiting for the night, and the night in fearing the dawn.

Even their pleasures are uneasy and made anxious by various fears, and at the very height of their rejoicing the worrying thought steals over them: 'How long will this last?' This feeling has caused kings to bewail their power, and they were not so much delighted by the greatness of their fortune as terrified by the thought of its inevitable end. When that most arrogant king of Persia[〔4〕] was deploying his army over vast plains, and could not number it but had to measure it, he wept because in a hundred years out of that huge army not a soul would be alive. But he who was weeping was the very man who would bring their fate upon them, and would destroy some on the sea, some on land, some in battle, some in flight, and in a very short time would wipe out all those for whose hundredth year he was afraid.

And what of the fact that even their joys are uneasy? The reason is that they are not based on firm causes, but they are agitated as groundlessly as they arise. But what kind of times can those be, do you think, which they themselves admit are wretched, since even the joys by which they are exalted and raised above humanity are pretty corrupt? All the greatest blessings create anxiety, and Fortune is never less to be trusted than when it is fairest. To preserve prosperity we need other prosperity, and to support the prayers which have turned out well we have to make other prayers. Whatever comes our way by chance is unsteady, and the higher it rises the more liable it is to fall. Furthermore, what is doomed to fall delights no one. So it is inevitable that life will be not just very short but very miserable for those who acquire by great toil what they must keep by greater toil. They achieve what they want laboriously; they possess what they have achieved anxiously; and meanwhile they take no account of time that will never more return. New preoccupations take the place of the old, hope excites more hope and ambition more ambition. They do not look for an end to their misery, but simply change the reason for it. We have found our own public honours a torment, and we spend more time on someone else's. We have stopped labouring as candidates, and we start canvassing for others. We have given up the troubles of a prosecutor, and taken on those of a judge. A man stops being a judge and becomes president of a court. He has grown old in the job of managing the property of others for a salary, and then spends all his time looking after his own. Marius was released from army life to become busy in the consulship. Quintius hastens to get through his dictatorship, but he will be summoned back to it from the plough. Scipio will go against the Carthaginians before he is experienced enough for such an undertaking. Victorious over Hannibal, victorious over Antiochus, distinguished in his own consulship and a surety for his brother's, if he had not himself forbidden it he would have been set up beside Jupiter. But discord in the state will harass its saviour, and after as a young man he has scorned honours fit for the gods, at length when old he will take delight in an ostentatiously stubborn exile. There will always be causes for anxiety, whether due to prosperity or to wretchedness. Life will be driven on through a succession of preoccupations: we shall always long for leisure, but never enjoy it.

And so, my dear Paulinus, extract yourself from the crowd, and as you have been storm-tossed more than your age deserves, you must at last retire into a peaceful harbour. Consider how many waves you have encountered, how many storms — some of which you have sustained in private life and some you have brought upon yourself in public life. Your virtue has for long enough been shown, when you were a model of active industry: try how it will manage in leisure. The greater part of your life, certainly the better part, has been devoted to the state: take some of your own time for yourself too. I am not inviting you to idle or purposeless sloth, or to drown all your natural energy in sleep and the pleasures that are dear to the masses. That is not to have repose. When you are retired and enjoying peace of mind, you will find to keep you busy more important activities than all those you have performed so energetically up to now. Indeed, you are managing the accounts of the world as scrupulously as you would another person's, as carefully as your own, as conscientiously as the state's. You are winning affection in a job in which it is hard to avoid ill-will; but believe me it is better to understand the balance-sheet of one's own life than of the corn trade. You must recall that vigorous mind of yours, supremely capable of dealing with the greatest responsibilities, from a task which is certainly honourable but scarcely suited to the happy life; and you must consider that all your youthful training in the liberal studies was not directed to this end, that many thousands of measures of corn might safely be entrusted to you. You had promised higher and greater things of yourself. There will not be wanting men who are completely worthy and hard-working. Stolid pack-animals are much more fit for carrying loads than thoroughbred horses: who ever subdued their noble speed with a heavy burden? Consider too how much anxiety you have in submitting yourself to such a weight of responsibility: you are dealing with the human belly. A hungry people neither listens to reason nor is mollified by fair treatment or swayed by any appeals. Quite recently, within a few days after Gaius Caesar died — still feeling very upset (if the dead have feelings) because he saw that the Roman people were still surviving, with a supply of food for seven or at most eight days, while he was building bridges with boats and playing with the resources of the empire — we faced the worst of all afflictions, even to those under siege, a shortage of provisions. His imitation of a mad foreign king doomed in his pride, nearly cost the city destruction and famine and the universal collapse that follows famine. What then must those have felt who had charge of the corn supply, when they were threatened with stones, weapons, fire — and Gaius? With a huge pretence they managed to conceal the great evil lurking in the vitals of the state — and assuredly they had good reason. For certain ailments must be treated while the patient is unaware of them: knowing about their disease has caused the death of many.

You must retire to these pursuits which are quieter, safer and more important. Do you think it is the same thing whether you are overseeing the transfer of corn into granaries, unspoilt by the dishonesty and carelessness of the shippers, and taking care that it does not get damp and then ruined through heat, and that it tallies in measure and weight; or whether you take up these sacred and lofty studies, from which you will learn the substance of god, and his will, his mode of life, his shape; what fate awaits your soul; where nature lays us to rest when released from our bodies; what is the force which supports all the heaviest elements of this world at the centre, suspends the light elements above, carries fire to the highest part, and sets the stars in motion with their proper changes — and learn other things in succession which are full of tremendous marvels? You really should leave the ground and turn your thoughts to these studies. Now while the blood is hot you should make your way with vigour to better things. In this kind of life you will find much that is worth your study: the love and practice of the virtues, forgetfulness of the passions, the knowledge of how to live and die, and a life of deep tranquillity.

Indeed the state of all who are preoccupied is wretched, but the most wretched are those who are toiling not even at their own preoccupations, but must regulate their sleep by another's, and their walk by another's pace, and obey orders in those freest of all things, loving and hating. If such people want to know how short their lives are, let them reflect how small a portion is their own.

So, when you see a man repeatedly wearing the robe of office, or one whose name is often spoken in the Forum, do not envy him: these things are won at the cost of life. In order that one year may be dated from their names they will waste all their own years. Life has left some men struggling at the start of their careers before they could force their way to the height of their ambition. Some men, after they have crawled through a thousand indignities to the supreme dignity, have been assailed by the gloomy thought that all their labours were but for the sake of an epitaph. Some try to adjust their extreme old age to new hopes as though it were youth, but find its weakness fails them in the midst of efforts that overtax it. It is a shameful sight when an elderly man runs out of breath while he is pleading in court for litigants who are total strangers to him, and trying to win the applause of the ignorant bystanders. It is disgraceful to see a man collapsing in the middle of his duties, worn out more by his life-style than by his labours. Disgraceful too is it when a man dies in the midst of going through his accounts, and his heir, long kept waiting, smiles in relief. I cannot resist telling you of an instance that occurs to me. Sextus Turannius was an old man known to be scrupulous and diligent, who, when he was ninety, at his own request was given retirement from his office by Gaius Caesar. He then ordered himself to be laid out on his bed and lamented by the assembled household as though he were dead. The house bewailed its old master's leisure, and did not cease its mourning until his former job was restored to him. Is it really so pleasant to die in harness? That is the feeling of many people: their desire for their work outlasts their ability to do it. They fight against their own bodily weakness, and they regard old age as a hardship on no other grounds than that it puts them on the shelf. The law does not make a man a soldier after fifty or a senator after sixty: men find it more difficult to gain leisure from themselves than from the law. Meanwhile, as they rob and are robbed, as they disturb each other's peace, as they make each other miserable, their lives pass without satisfaction, without pleasure, without mental improvement. No one keeps death in view, no one refrains from hopes that look far ahead; indeed, some people even arrange things that are beyond life — massive tombs, dedications of public buildings, shows for their funerals, and ostentatious burials. But in truth, such people's funerals should be conducted with torches and wax tapers, as though they had lived the shortest of lives.

注释

〔1〕 A friend of Seneca's.

〔2〕 Hippocrates.

〔3〕 The religious boundary of a city.

〔4〕 Xerxes.

Consolation to Helvia

Dearest mother, I have often had the urge to console you and often restrained it. Many things encouraged me to venture to do so. First, I thought I would be laying aside all my troubles when I had at least wiped away your tears, even if I could not stop them coming. Then, I did not doubt that I would have more power to raise you up if I had first risen myself. Moreover, I was afraid that though Fortune was conquered by me she might conquer someone close to me. So, staunching my own cut with my hand I was doing my best to crawl forward to bind up your wounds. There were, on the other hand, considerations which delayed my purpose. I realized that your grief should not be intruded upon while it was fresh and agonizing, in case the consolations themselves should rouse and inflame it: for an illness too nothing is more harmful than premature treatment. So I was waiting until your grief of itself should lose its force and, being softened by time to endure remedies, it would allow itself to be touched and handled. Moreover, although I consulted all the works written by the most famous authors to control and moderate grief, I couldn't find any example of someone who had comforted his own dear ones when he himself was the subject of their grief. So in this unprecedented situation I hesitated, fearing that I would be offering not consolation but further irritation. Consider, too, that a man lifting his head from the very funeral pyre must need some novel vocabulary not drawn from ordinary everyday condolence to comfort his own dear ones. But every great and overpowering grief must take away the capacity to choose words, since it often stifles the voice itself. Anyway, I'll try my best, not trusting in my cleverness, but because being myself the comforter I can thereby be the most effective comfort. As you never refused me anything I hope you will not refuse me this at least (though all grief is stubborn), to be willing that I should set a limit to your desolation.

Consider how much I have promised myself from your indulgence. I don't doubt that I shall have more influence over you than your grief, than which nothing has more influence over the wretched. So in order not to join battle with it at once, I'll first support it and offer it a lot of encouragement: I shall expose and reopen all the wounds which have already healed. Someone will object: 'What kind of consolation is this, to bring back forgotten ills and to set the mind in view of all its sorrows when it can scarcely endure one?' But let him consider that those disorders which are so dangerous that they have gained ground in spite of treatment can generally be treated by opposite methods. Therefore I shall offer to the mind all its sorrows, all its mourning garments: this will not be a gentle prescription for healing, but cautery and the knife. What shall I achieve? That a soul which has conquered so many miseries will be ashamed to worry about one more wound in a body which already has so many scars. So let those people go on weeping and wailing whose self-indulgent minds have been weakened by long prosperity, let them collapse at the threat of the most trivial injuries; but let those who have spent all their years suffering disasters endure the worst afflictions with a brave and resolute staunchness. Everlasting misfortune does have one blessing, that it ends up by toughening those whom it constantly afflicts.

Fortune has given you no respite from the most woeful sorrows, not even excepting the day of your birth. As soon as you were born, no, even while being born, you lost your mother, and on the threshold of life you were in a sense exposed. You grew up under the care of a stepmother, and you actually forced her to become a real mother by showing her all the deference and devotion which can be seen even in a daughter. Yet even having a good stepmother costs every child a good deal. You lost your uncle, kindest, best and bravest of men, when you were awaiting his arrival; and lest Fortune should lessen her cruelty by dividing it, within a month you buried your dearest husband by whom you had three children. This sorrow was announced to you when you were already grieving, and when indeed all your children were away, as if your misfortunes were concentrated on purpose into that time so that your grief would have nowhere to turn for relief. I pass over all the dangers, all the fears you endured as they assailed you unceasingly. But recently into the same lap from which you had let go three grandchildren you received back the bones of three grandchildren. Within twenty days of burying my son, who died as you held and kissed him, you heard that I had been taken away. This only you had lacked — to grieve for the living.

Of all the wounds which have ever pierced your body this last one is, I admit, the worst. It has not simply broken the skin but cut into your breast and vital parts. But just as recruits, even when superficially wounded, cry aloud and dread being handled by doctors more than the sword, while veterans, even if severely wounded, patiently and without a groan allow their wounds to be cleaned as though their bodies did not belong to them; so you must now offer yourself bravely for treatment. Come, put away wailings and lamentations and all the other usual noisy manifestations of feminine grief. For all your sorrows have been wasted on you if you have not yet learned how to be wretched. Do I seem to have dealt boldly with you? I have kept away not one of your misfortunes from you, but piled them all up in front of you.

I have done this courageously for I decided to conquer your grief, not to cheat it. But I shall do this, I think, first of all if I show that I am suffering nothing for which I could be called wretched, let alone make my relations wretched; then if I turn to you and show that your fortune, which is wholly dependent on mine, is also not painful.

First I shall deal with the fact, which your love is longing to hear, that I am suffering no affliction. I shall make it clear, if I can, that those very circumstances which you think are crushing me can be borne; but if you cannot believe that, at least I shall be more pleased with myself for being happy in conditions which normally make men wretched. There is no need to believe others about me: I am telling you firmly that I am not wretched, so that you won't be agitated by uncertainty. To reassure you further, I shall add that I cannot even be made wretched.

We are born under circumstances that would be favourable if we did not abandon them. It was nature's intention that there should be no need of great equipment for a good life: every individual can make himself happy. External goods are of trivial importance and without much influence in either direction: prosperity does not elevate the sage and adversity does not depress him. For he has always made the effort to rely as much as possible on himself and to derive all delight from himself. So what? Am I calling myself a sage? Certainly not. For if I could claim that, not only would I be denying that I was wretched but I would be asserting that I was the most fortunate of all men and coming close to god. As it is, doing what is sufficient to alleviate all wretchedness, I have surrendered myself to wise men, and as I am not yet strong enough to help myself I have gone over to another camp — I mean those who can easily protect themselves and their followers. They have ordered me to take a firm stand, like a sentry on guard, and to foresee all the attacks and all the onslaughts of Fortune long before they hit me. She falls heavily on those to whom she is unexpected; the man who is always expecting her easily withstands her. For an enemy's arrival too scatters those whom it catches off guard; but those who have prepared in advance for the coming conflict, being properly drawn up and equipped, easily withstand the first onslaught, which is the most violent. Never have I trusted Fortune, even when she seemed to offer peace. All those blessings which she kindly bestowed on me — money, public office, influence — I relegated to a place whence she could claim them back without bothering me. I kept a wide gap between them and me, with the result that she has taken them away, not torn them away. No man has been shattered by the blows of Fortune unless he was first deceived by her favours. Those who loved her gifts as if they were their own for ever, who wanted to be admired on account of them, are laid low and grieve when the false and transient pleasures desert their vain and childish minds, ignorant of every stable pleasure. But the man who is not puffed up in good times does not collapse either when they change. His fortitude is already tested and he maintains a mind unconquered in the face of either condition: for in the midst of prosperity he has tried his own strength against adversity. So I have never believed that there was any genuine good in the things which everyone prays for; what is more, I have found them empty and daubed with showy and deceptive colours, with nothing inside to match their appearance. And now in these so-called evils I find nothing so terrible and harsh as the general opinion threatened. Certainly the word 'exile' itself now enters the ears more harshly through a sort of conviction and popular belief, and strikes the listener as something gloomy and detestable. For that is the people's verdict, but wise men on the whole reject the people's decrees.

So, putting aside this judgement of the majority who are carried away by the surface appearance of things, whatever the grounds for believing in it, let us examine the reality of exile. Clearly a change of place. I must not seem to restrict its force and remove its worst feature, so I agree that this change of place brings with it the disadvantages of poverty, disgrace and contempt. I shall deal with these later; meanwhile I wish first to examine what distress the change of place itself involves.

'It is unbearable to be deprived of your country.' Come now, look at this mass of people whom the buildings of huge Rome can scarcely hold: most of that crowd are deprived of their country. They have flocked together from their towns and colonies, in fact from the whole world, some brought by ambition, some by the obligation of public office, some by the duties of an envoy, some by self-indulgence seeking a place conveniently rich in vice, some by a love of liberal studies, some by the public shows; some have been attracted by friendship, some by their own energy which has found a wide field for displaying its qualities; some have come to sell their beauty, others their eloquence. Absolutely every type of person has hastened into the city which offers high rewards for both virtues and vices. Take a roll-call of all of them and ask each where he comes from: you will see that most of them have left their own homes and come to a very great and beautiful city, but not their own. Then move away from this city, which in a way can be said to belong to all, and go around all the others: in every one a large proportion of the population is immigrant. Pass on from those whose lovely and convenient position attracts large numbers, and review deserted places and rocky islands, Sciathus and Seriphus, Gyara and Cossura: you will find no place of exile where somebody does not linger because he wants to. What could be found so bare and with such a steep drop on every side as this rock? What more barren regarding its resources? What more savage regarding its people? What more rugged regarding its geography? What more intemperate regarding its climate? Yet more foreigners than natives live here. Thus, so far is change of locality itself from being a hardship that even this place has enticed some people from their homeland. I've come across people who say that there is a sort of inborn restlessness in the human spirit and an urge to change one's abode; for man is endowed with a mind which is changeable and unsettled: nowhere at rest, it darts about and directs its thoughts to all places known and unknown, a wanderer which cannot endure repose and delights chiefly in novelty. This will not surprise you if you consider its original source. It was not made from heavy, earthly material, but came down from that heavenly spirit: but heavenly things are by nature always in motion, fleeing and driven on extremely fast. Look at the planets which light up the world: not one is at rest. The sun glides constantly, moving on from place to place, and although it revolves with the universe its motion is nevertheless opposite to that of the firmament itself: it races through all the signs of the zodiac and never stops; its motion is everlasting as it journeys from one point to another. All the planets forever move round and pass by: as the constraining law of nature has ordained they are borne from point of point. When through fixed periods of years they have completed their courses they will start again upon their former circuits. How silly then to imagine that the human mind, which is formed of the same elements as divine beings, objects to movement and change of abode, while the divine nature finds delight and even self-preservation in continual and very rapid change.

Well, now, turn your attention from heavenly to human matters and you will see that whole nations and peoples have changed their abode. What are Greek cities doing in the midst of barbarian territories? Why do we hear the Macedonian language among Indians and Persians? Scythia and all that wide region of fierce and untamed tribes reveal Achaean cities established on the shores of the Pontus. People were not put off from migrating there by the endlessly severe winter or the savage character of the natives which matched their climate. There is a crowd of Athenians in Asia; Miletus has sent out all over the place enough people to colonize seventy-five cities; the whole of the Italian coast which is washed by the lower sea was once Greater Greece. Asia claims the Etruscans as her own; Tyrians live in Africa, Phoenicians in Spain; Greeks penetrated into Gaul and Gauls into Greece; the Pyrenees did not block the passage of the Germans — through trackless, through unknown territory has ventured the restlessness of men, and behind them came their wives and children and parents stricken in years. Some of them, driven about in their long wanderings, did not choose their goal deliberately, but through weariness settled at the nearest place; others by force of arms established their right in a foreign country. Some tribes were drowned while they sought unknown regions; others settled where they were stranded by running out of supplies. They did not all have the same reason for abandoning one homeland for another. Some, escaping the destruction of their cities by enemy attack, were driven to other territory when they lost their own; some were banished by civil strife; others were sent out to relieve the burden of overpopulation; others fled from disease or constant earthquakes or some intolerable deficiencies in their barren soil; others were tempted by the exaggerated report of a fertile shore. Different reasons roused different peoples to leave their homes; but this at least is clear, nothing has stayed where it was born. The human race is always on the move: in so large a world there is every day some change — new cities are founded, and new names of nations are born as former ones disappear or are absorbed into a stronger one. But what else are all these national migrations than banishments of a people? Why should I drag you through the whole cycle? Why bother to mention Antenor who founded Patavium, and Evander who settled the Arcadian kingdom on the banks of the Tiber? What about Diomedes and the others, both conquerors and conquered, who were scattered over alien lands by the Trojan War? Why, the Roman empire itself looks back to an exile as its founder, a man who was driven out when his homeland was captured and, taking a few survivors, was forced by fear of the victor to make a long journey which brought him to Italy. What a number of colonies this people in turn has sent out to every province! — wherever the Romans have conquered they dwell. People volunteered for this kind of emigration, and even old men leaving their altars followed the settlers overseas. The point does not need any more illustration, but I will just add one which hits you in the eye: this island itself has often changed its inhabitants. To leave aside earlier events which are obscured by antiquity, the Greeks who now live in Massilia after leaving Phocis first settled in this island. It is not clear what drove them from it, whether the harsh climate, or being in sight of the superior power of Italy, or the lack of harbours. For clearly the reason was not the savagery of the inhabitants, since they settled among what were then the fiercest and most uncivilized peoples in Gaul. Subsequently the Ligurians crossed over to the island, and the Spaniards too, as is clear from the similarity of their customs: for the Corsicans wear the same kind of head-covering and shoes as the Cantabrians, and some of their words are the same — only some, for their language as a whole, through association with Greeks and Ligurians, has lost its native elements. Next, two colonies of Roman citizens were brought there, one by Marius and one by Sulla: so often has the population of this barren and thorny rock changed! In a word, you will hardly find a single country still inhabited by its original natives: everywhere the people are of mixed and imported stock. One group has followed another: one longed for what another scorned; one was driven out from where he had expelled others. So fate has decreed that nothing maintains the same condition forever.

To compensate for the actual change of place and forgetting about the other inconveniences attached to exile, Varro, most learned of Romans, considers we have this sufficient remedy, that wherever we come we have the same order of nature to deal with. Marcus Brutus thinks this is enough, that exiles can carry with them their own virtues. Even if anyone thinks that these points taken separately are insufficient to console the exile, he will admit that in combination they carry great weight. For how little have we lost, when the two finest things of all will accompany us wherever we go, universal nature and our individual virtue. Believe me, this was the intention of whoever formed the universe, whether all-powerful god, or incorporeal reason creating mighty works, or divine spirit penetrating all things from greatest to smallest with even pressure, or fate and the unchanging sequence of causation — this, I say, was the intention, that only the most worthless of our possessions should come into the power of another. Whatever is best for a human being lies outside human control: it can be neither given nor taken away. The world you see, nature's greatest and most glorious creation, and the human mind which gazes and wonders at it, and is the most splendid part of it, these are our own everlasting possessions and will remain with us as long as we ourselves remain. So, eager and upright, let us hasten with bold steps wherever circumstances take us, and let us journey through any countries whatever: there can be no place of exile within the world since nothing within the world is alien to men. From whatever point on the earth's surface you look up to heaven the same distance lies between the realms of gods and men. Accordingly, provided my eyes are not withdrawn from that spectacle, of which they never tire; provided I may look upon the sun and the moon and gaze at the other planets; provided I may trace their risings and settings, their periods and the causes of their travelling faster or slower; provided I may behold all the stars that shine at night — some fixed, others not travelling far afield but circling within the same area; some suddenly shooting forth, and others dazzling the eye with scattered fire, as if they are falling, or gliding past with a long trail of blazing light; provided I can commune with these and, so far as humans may, associate with the divine, and provided I can keep my mind always directed upwards, striving for a vision of kindred things — what does it matter what ground I stand on?

'But this country is not fertile in lush or fruitful trees; no large and navigable rivers irrigate it with their channels; it produces nothing which other nations want, being scarcely fertile enough to support its own inhabitants. No valuable marble is quarried here, no veins of gold and silver are mined.' Petty is the mind which delights in earthly things: it should be led away to those things which appear everywhere equally, everywhere equally lustrous. There is this too to consider, that earthly things stand in the way of genuine goods through a wayward belief in false goods. The longer people extend their colonnades, the higher they build their towers, the wider they stretch their walks, the deeper they dig their summer grottoes, the more massively they raise the roofs of their dining-halls, so much the more will there be to cut off the sight of heaven. Fate has cast you into a land where the most luxurious shelter is a hut. Truly you have a petty spirit which meanly comforts itself, if you put up with this bravely because you know about the hut of Romulus. Say rather 'This humble shack gives shelter, I suppose, to the virtues. Soon it will be more elegant than any temple when justice is seen to be there, and temperance, wisdom, piety, a system for the right allotment of all duties, and the knowledge of man and god. No place is narrow which can hold this assembly of such great virtues; no exile is burdensome when you can have this company with you.'

In his treatise 'On Virtue' Brutus says that he saw Marcellus in exile at Mytilene, living as happily as human nature allows, and never more keen on liberal studies than at that time. And so he adds that when he was about to return without Marcellus, he himself seemed to be going into exile rather than leaving the other in exile. How much more fortunate was Marcellus at that time when he won the favour of Brutus for his exile than when he won the favour of the state for his consulship! What a man that was who caused someone to feel himself an exile because he was leaving an exile behind! What a man he was to have won the admiration of a man whom even his kinsman Cato had to admire! Brutus also says that Gaius Caesar had sailed past Mytilene because he could not bear the sight of a great man in disgrace. Indeed, the senate obtained his recall by public petition: they were so anxious and sorrowful that they all seemed to share Brutus' feelings on that day, and to be pleading not for Marcellus but for themselves, in case they would be exiled if deprived of him. But he achieved much more on that day when Brutus could not bear to leave, nor Caesar to see, him in exile. For both gave him testimony: Brutus grieved to return without Marcellus, and Caesar blushed. Can you doubt that Marcellus, being the great man he was, often encouraged himself thus to endure his exile with equanimity? 'Being without your country is not misery: you have thoroughly taught yourself by your studies to know that to a wise man every place is his country. Besides, was not the man who caused your exile himself absent from his country for ten consecutive years? No doubt the reason was to enlarge his domains — yet he certainly was absent. See, now he is summoned to Africa which is full of threats of further war; to Spain which is reviving its forces shattered by defeat; to treacherous Egypt — in short to the whole world which is watchful for an opportunity against the stricken empire. Which problem shall he face first? To which quarter take his stand? His own victorious course will drive him throughout the world. Let the nations honour and worship him; live yourself content with Brutus as your admirer.'

Well did Marcellus, then, endure his exile, nor did his change of abode cause any change at all in his mind though poverty attended it. But there is no evil in poverty, as anyone knows who has not yet arrived at the lunatic state of greed and luxury, which ruin everything. For how little is needed to support a man! And who can lack this if he has any virtue at all? As far as I am concerned, I know that I have lost not wealth but distractions. The body's needs are few: it wants to be free from cold, to banish hunger and thirst with nourishment; if we long for anything more we are exerting ourselves to serve our vices, not our needs. We do not need to scour every ocean, or to load our bellies with the slaughter of animals, or to pluck shellfish from the unknown shores of the furthest sea. May gods and goddesses destroy those whose luxury passes the bounds of an empire that already awakens envy. They seek to stock their pretentious kitchens by hunting beyond the Phasis, and they aren't ashamed to ask for birds from the Parthians, from whom we have not yet exacted vengeance. From all sides they collect everything familiar to a fastidious glutton. From the furthest sea is brought food which their stomachs, weakened by a voluptuous diet, can scarcely receive. They vomit in order to eat, and eat in order to vomit, and banquets for which they ransack the whole world they do not even deign to digest. If someone despises all that, what harm can poverty do him? If he longs for it, poverty even does him good: for against his will he is being cured, and if even under compulsion he does not take his medicine, for a time at least his inability to have those things looks like unwillingness. Gaius Caesar, whom I think nature produced as an example of the effect of supreme wickedness in a supreme position, dined in one day at a cost of ten million sesterces; and though helped in this by everyone's ingenuity he could scarcely discover how to spend the tribute from three provinces on one dinner. Poor wretches, whose appetite is only tempted by expensive foods! Yet it is not an exquisite taste or some delightful effect on the palate that makes them expensive, but their scarcity and the difficulty of procuring them. Otherwise, if these people would agree to return to good sense, where is the need for all these skills that serve the belly? What need for importing, or laying waste the woodlands, or ransacking the ocean? All around food lies ready which nature has distributed in every place; but men pass it by as though blind to it, and they scour every country, they cross the seas, and they whet their appetite at great expense when at little cost they could satisfy it. I want to say to them: 'Why do you launch your ships? Why do you arm your bands against both beasts and men? Why do you tear around in such a panic? Why do you pile wealth upon wealth? You really must consider how small your bodies are. Is it not madness and the worst form of derangement to want so much though you can hold so little? Therefore, though you may increase your income and extend your estates, you will never increase the capacity of your bodies. Though your business may do well and warfare bring you profit, though you hunt down and gather your food from every side, you will not have anywhere to store your supplies. Why do you seek out so many things? To be sure, our ancestors were unhappy, whose virtue even now props up our vices, who procured their food with their own hands, who slept on the ground, whose dwellings did not yet glitter with gold nor their temples with precious stones — and so in those days they swore solemn oaths by gods of clay and, having invoked them, returned to the enemy to certain death rather than break their word. To be sure, our dictator who gave audience to the Samnite envoys while with his own hand he cooked the simplest sort of food (the hand which already had frequently smitten the enemy and placed a laurel wreath on the lap of Capitoline Jupiter) — he lived less happily than Apicius in our time, who in the city from which philosophers were once banished as corrupters of the youth, polluted the age by his teaching as professor of cookery.' It is worth hearing what happened to him. When he had spent a hundred million sesterces in his kitchen, when he had drunk up at every one of his carousals all those imperial gifts and the enormous revenue of the Capitol, then for the first time he was forced by the weight of his debts to look into his accounts. He reckoned he would have ten million sesterces left, and that living on ten million would be starvation: so he poisoned himself. What luxury, if ten million meant poverty! How then can you think that it is the amount of money that matters and not the attitude of mind? Someone dreaded having ten million, and what others pray for he escaped by poison. But indeed for a man of such perverted mentality that last drink was the best thing for him. It was when he was not merely enjoying but boasting of his huge banquets, when he was making a display of his vices, when he was drawing public attention to his vulgar displays, when he was tempting young people to imitate him (who even without bad examples are naturally impressionable) — then it was that he was really eating and drinking poisons. Such is the fate of those who measure wealth not by the standard of reason, whose limits are fixed, but by that of a vicious life-style governed by boundless, uncontrollable caprice. Nothing satisfies greed, but even a little satisfies nature. So an exile's poverty brings no hardship; for no place of exile is so barren that it cannot abundantly support a man.

'But,' says someone, 'the exile is going to miss his clothes and home.' These too he will miss only as far as he needs them — and he will lack neither house nor covering; for the body needs as little for protection as for food. Nature has not made any of man's essentials laborious as well. But he must have richly dyed purple clothes, woven with gold thread and decorated with multicoloured patterns: it is his fault, not nature's, if he feels poor. Even if you give him back all he has lost, you'll be wasting your time; for once he is back from exile he will feel a greater lack compared with his desires than he felt as an exile compared with his former possessions. But he must have furniture gleaming with gold vessels and antique silver plate wrought by famous artists, bronze made valuable because a few lunatics want it, a crowd of slaves which would throng a house however large, beasts of burden with bodies bloated with force-feeding, marbles from every land: though he piles all these up, they will never sate his insatiable soul; just as no amount of fluid will satisfy one whose craving arises not from lack of water but from burning internal fever: for that is not a thirst but a disease. Nor is this true only of money or food: the same feature is found in every desire which arises not from a lack but from a vice. However much you heap up for it will not mark the end of greed, only a stage in it. So the man who restrains himself within the bounds set by nature will not notice poverty; the man who exceeds these bounds will be pursued by poverty however rich he is. Life's necessities are found even in places of exile, superfluities not even in kingdoms. It is the mind that creates our wealth, and this goes with us into exile, and in the harshest desert places it finds sufficient to nourish the body and revels in the enjoyment of its own goods. Money in no way concerns the mind any more than it concerns the gods. All those things which are revered by minds untaught and enslaved to their bodies — marble, gold, silver, great round polished tables — are earthly burdens which a soul pure and conscious of its nature cannot love: for it is light and unencumbered, and destined to soar aloft whenever it is released from the body. Meanwhile, so far as it is not hampered by our limbs and this heavy burden that envelops us, it surveys things divine with swift and winged thought. So the soul can never suffer exile, being free and akin to the gods and equal to all the universe and all time. For its thought encompasses the whole of heaven, and journeys into all past and future time. This wretched body, the chain and prison of the soul, is tossed hither and thither; upon it punishment and pillage and disease wreak havoc: but the soul itself is holy and eternal, and it cannot be assailed with violence.

In case you think I am simply using the teaching of philosophers to make light of the trials of poverty, which no one feels to be a burden unless he thinks it that, first consider that by far the greater proportion of men are poor, but you will not see them looking at all more gloomy and anxious than the rich. In fact, I rather suspect that they are happier in proportion as their minds have less to harry them. Let us pass on to the rich: how frequently are they just like the poor! When they travel abroad their luggage is restricted, and whenever they are forced to hasten their journey they dismiss their retinue of attendants. When they are serving in the army, how little of their belongings do they keep with them, since camp discipline forbids any luxury! Nor is it only special conditions of time and place which put them on a level with the poor in their needs: when on occasion they get tired of their riches they choose certain days on which they dine on the ground and, putting aside their gold and silver vessels, use earthenware ones. What lunatics, to covet sometimes a condition they always dread! What mental darkness, what ignorance of the truth blinds those who, though afflicted by the fear of poverty, yet take pleasure in imitating it! For my part, whenever I look back at the fine examples of antiquity, I am ashamed to find consolations for poverty, since the luxury of the times has reached the point where an exile's allowance is more than the inheritance of leading men of old. We all know that Homer had one slave, Plato had three, and Zeno, the founder of the strict and manly Stoic philosophy, had none. Will anyone on that account say that they lived wretchedly without himself seeming to all by his words to be utterly wretched? Menenius Agrippa, who kept the public peace by acting as mediator between patricians and plebeians, was buried by public subscription. Atilius Regulus, while he was routing the Carthaginians in Africa, wrote to tell the senate that his hired worker had gone off and abandoned his farm: the senate voted that during Regulus' absence the farm should be managed by the state. Was it not worth being without a slave so that the Roman people might become his tenant? Scipio's daughters received a dowry from the state treasury because their father had left them nothing: assuredly it was right for the Roman people to offer tribute to Scipio once, since he was always exacting it from Carthage. Happy were the girls' husbands whose father-in-law was the Roman people! Do you think those whose pantomime actresses marry with a dowry of a million sesterces are happier than Scipio, whose children had the senate for their guardian and received solid copper money as a dowry? Could anyone despise poverty with a pedigree so distinguished? Could an exile resent lacking anything, when Scipio lacked a dowry, Regulus a hired worker, Menenius a funeral: when for all of them supplying their need was all the more honourable simply because they had the need? And so, with these men pleading her cause poverty wins not only acquittal but high esteem.

One might reply, 'Why do you make an artificial separation of those things which can be borne separately but not in combination? You can put up with a change of place if only the place is changed. You can put up with poverty if there is no disgrace, which even alone usually crushes the spirit.' In answer to this man who aims to frighten me by an accumulation of ills, this must be said: 'If you have the strength to tackle any one aspect of misfortune you can tackle all. When once virtue has toughened the mind it renders it invulnerable on every side. If greed, the most overmastering plague of the human race, has relaxed its grip, ambition will not stand in your way. If you regard your last day not as a punishment but as a law of nature, the breast from which you have banished the dread of death no fear will dare to enter. If you consider that sexual desire was given to man not for enjoyment but for the propagation of the race, once you are free of this violent and destructive passion rooted in your vitals, every other desire will leave you undisturbed. Reason routs the vices not one by one but all together: the victory is final and complete.' Do you think that any wise man can be affected by disgrace, one who relies entirely on himself and holds aloof from common beliefs? A disgraceful death is worse than disgrace: yet Socrates went to prison with the same expression he wore when he once snubbed the Thirty Tyrants — and his presence robbed even prison of disgrace, for where Socrates was could not seem a prison. Who is so blind to the truth that he thinks it was a disgrace to Marcus Cato that he was twice defeated in his bid for the praetorship and consulship? The disgrace belonged to the praetorship and consulship which were being honoured by Cato. No man is despised by another unless he is first despised by himself. An abject and debased mind is susceptible to such insult; but if a man stirs himself to face the worst of disasters and defeats the evils which overwhelm others, then he wears those very sorrows like a sacred badge. For we are naturally disposed to admire more than anything else the man who shows fortitude in adversity. When Aristides was being led to execution at Athens, everyone who met him cast down his eyes and groaned, as though it was not merely a just man but Justice herself who was being punished. Yet one man actually spat in his face. He could have resented this because he knew that only a foul-mouthed man would dare to do it. Instead he wiped his face, and with a smile he said to the magistrate escorting him: 'Warn that fellow not to give such a vulgar yawn another time.' This was to retaliate insult upon insult. I know some people say that nothing is worse than scorn and that even death seems preferable. To these I shall reply that exile too is often free from any kind of scorn. If a great man falls and remains great as he lies, people no more despise him than they stamp on a fallen temple, which the devout still worship as much as when it was standing.

Dearest mother, since you have no cause on my account to drive you to endless tears it follows that reasons regarding yourself are urging you to weep. Well, there are two: you are bothered either because you seem to have lost some protection, or because you cannot endure the very thought of doing without me.

The first point I must touch upon only slightly, for I know that your heart loves your dear ones for themselves alone. Let those mothers reflect on this who exploit their children's influence with a woman's lack of influence; who, because women cannot hold office, seek power through their sons; who both drain their sons' inheritances and try to get them; who exhaust their sons by lending their eloquence to others. Whereas you have taken the greatest pleasure in your sons' gifts and made the least use of them; you have always set a limit to our generosity without limiting your own; while your father was still alive you actually gave gifts to your wealthy sons; you administered our inheritances as though you were earnestly looking after your own and being scrupulously provident with another's; you were cautious in using our influence, as if it were someone else's, and in our spells in office you had no part except your pleasure and the expenses. Your love never had regard for self-interest: therefore, now that your son has been taken from you, you cannot feel the lack of those things which you never thought concerned you when he was safe and sound.

I must direct my consolation entirely to that point from which arises the true force of a mother's grief. You say, 'So I am deprived of my dearest son's embrace; I can't enjoy seeing him or talking to him. Where is he whose appearance smoothed my troubled brow, to whom I confided all my woes? Where are our conversations of which I never tired? Where are his studies which I shared with more than a feminine eagerness and more than a mother's intimacy? Where are our meetings? Where is the unfailing boyish glee at the sight of his mother?' To all this you add the actual places where we rejoiced together and socialized, and the reminders of our recent life together which are inevitably the most acute source of mental anguish. For Fortune plotted even this cruel blow against you, that only two days before I was struck down she contrived that you should depart tranquil in mind and fearing no such disaster. It was well that we had lived far apart, and that an absence of some years had prepared you for this blow. By returning you did not gain the pleasure of your son's presence, but you lost the habit of bearing his absence. If you had been away long before you would have borne the loss more bravely, as the very distance between us would have softened the longing. If you had not gone away you would at least have had the final pleasure of seeing your son for two days longer. As it was, cruel fate so arranged it that you could neither be present at my misfortune nor get used to my absence. But the harsher these circumstances are, the greater the courage you must summon up and the more fiercely you must fight, as with an enemy you know and have often defeated. Your blood has not now flowed from an undamaged body: you have been struck exactly where the old scars are.

You must not excuse yourself as being a woman, who has been virtually given the right to indulge excessively, but not endlessly, in tears. With this in view our ancestors allowed widows to mourn their husbands for ten months, in order to compromise by public decree with the stubbornness of female grief. They did not prohibit mourning but they limited it. For to be afflicted with endless sorrow at the loss of someone very dear is foolish self-indulgence, and to feel none is inhuman callousness. The best compromise between love and good sense is both to feel longing and to conquer it. You must not pay regard to certain women whose grief, once assumed, was ended only by death — you know some who never removed the mourning dress they put on when they lost their sons. Your life was braver from its start and expects more from you: the excuse of being a woman does not apply to one from whom all womanly faults have been absent. That worst evil of our time, unchastity, has not numbered you among the majority of women; neither jewels nor pearls have influenced you; the glitter of wealth has not struck you as the greatest blessing of the human race; you were brought up in a strict, old-fashioned home and never deviated into the imitation of worse women which is dangerous even to good ones; you were never ashamed of your fertility as if it taunted you with your advancing years; never did you follow other women who seek only to impress by their looks, and hide your pregnancy as if it were an indecent burden, nor did you destroy the hopes of giving birth by abortion; you did not spoil your complexion by paints and cosmetics; you never liked the sort of garment which revealed no more when it was taken off; in you has been seen that matchless ornament, that loveliest beauty which is not dependent on any time of life, that greatest glory of all — modesty. So you cannot, in order to justify your grief, claim the name of woman from which your virtues have set you apart: you ought to be as immune to female tears as to female vices. Not even women will allow you to waste away from your wound, but they will tell you to get your necessary mourning speedily over with and rise again comforted, by willing yourself to keep in mind those women whose conspicuous courage has ranked them with great men. Fortune reduced Cornelia's twelve children to two: if you wanted to count Cornelia's bereavements, she had lost ten; if you wanted to appraise them, she had lost the Gracchi. But when those around her were weeping and cursing her fate she forbad them to accuse Fortune, which had given her the Gracchi as her sons. It was a fitting son of this mother who said in the assembly, 'Would you insult the mother who gave me birth?' Yet his mother's words seem to me much more spirited: the son was proud of the parentage of the Gracchi, the mother of their deaths as well. Rutilia followed her son Cotta into exile, and was so single-minded in her devotion that she preferred exile to missing him, and returned home only when he did. And when, restored to favour and a distinguished public figure, he died, she bore his loss as bravely as she had shared his exile, nor was she ever seen to weep after his funeral. She showed courage when he was exiled and wisdom when he died; for nothing stopped her showing her love and nothing induced her to persist in useless and unavailing grief. It is with women like these that I want you to be numbered. You always imitated their way of life, and you will best follow their example in controlling and conquering your sorrow.

I know that this is not something which is in our power and that no strong feeling is under our control, least of all that which arises from sorrow: for it is violent and violently resists every remedy. Sometimes we want to crush it and swallow down our groans, but through the pretended composure of our features the tears pour down. Sometimes we divert our mind with public shows or gladiatorial contests, but in the very midst of the distractions of the spectacles it is undermined by some little reminder of its loss. Therefore it is better to conquer our grief than to deceive it. For if it has withdrawn, being merely beguiled by pleasures and preoccupations, it starts up again and from its very respite gains force to savage us. But the grief that has been conquered by reason is calmed for ever. I am not therefore going to prescribe for you those remedies which I know many people have used, that you divert or cheer yourself by a long or pleasant journey abroad, or spend a lot of time carefully going through your accounts and administering your estate, or constantly be involved in some new activity. All those things help only for a short time; they do not cure grief but hinder it. But I would rather end it than distract it. And so I am leading you to that resource which must be the refuge of all who are flying from Fortune, liberal studies. They will heal your wound, they will withdraw all your melancholy. Even if you had never been familiar with them you would have need of them now. But, so far as the old-fashioned strictness of my father allowed, you have had some acquaintance with the liberal arts, even if you have not mastered them. If only my father, best of men, had been less devoted to ancestral tradition, and had been willing that you be steeped in the teaching of philosophy and not just gain a smattering of it: you would not now have to acquire your defence against Fortune but just bring it forth. He was less inclined to let you pursue your studies because of those women who use books not to acquire wisdom but as the furniture of luxury. Yet thanks to your vigorously inquiring mind you absorbed a lot considering the time you had available: the foundations of all formal studies have been laid. Return now to these studies and they will keep you safe. They will comfort you, they will delight you; and if they genuinely penetrate your mind, never again will grief enter there, or anxiety, or the distress caused by futile and pointless suffering. Your heart will have room for none of these, for to all other failings it has long been closed. Those studies are your most dependable protection, and they alone can snatch you from Fortune's grip.

But until you arrive at this haven which philosophy holds out to you, you must have supports to lean on: so I want meanwhile to point out your own consolations. Consider my brothers: while they live you have no reason to complain of your fortune. In both you have contrasting virtues to cheer you up: the one achieved public office by his energy, the other in his wisdom despised it. Take comfort in the distinction of the one, the retirement of the other, and the devotion of both. I know the innermost feelings of my brothers. The one fosters his distinction really in order to bring honour to you, while the other has retired into peace and tranquillity in order to have leisure for you. Fortune has done you a service in arranging that your children should bring you both assistance and delight: you can be protected by the distinction of the one and you can enjoy the leisure of the other. They will be rivals in their services to you, and the devotion of two will fill the blank space left by one. I promise you with complete confidence that you will miss nothing but the number of sons.

After these consider too your grandchildren: Marcus, a most charming child — you could not remain sorrowful while looking at him, and no one's heart could suffer anguish too great or too recent not to be soothed by his embrace. Whose tears would his merriment not allay? Whose heart gripped by anxious care would not relax at his lively chatter? Who will not smile at his playfulness? Whose attention, however fixed on his own thoughts, will not be attracted and held by that prattling which no one could tire of? I pray to the gods that he may survive us! May all the cruelty of fate wear itself out and stop at me. Whatever you were destined to suffer as a mother and as a grandmother may I represent. Let the rest of my family flourish undisturbed. I shall not complain of my childlessness or my exile, if only I prove to be the scapegoat for a family that will suffer no more. Embrace Novatilla, who will soon give you great-grandchildren; I had so attached her to myself and adopted her that in losing me she could seem an orphan, though her father is alive. Cherish her for me too. Fortune recently took away her mother, but your love will mean that she will only grieve over her mother's loss but not suffer for it. Now you must shape and compose her character: teaching sinks more deeply into those of impressionable years. Let her grow used to your conversation and be moulded as you think right; you will be giving her a great deal even if you give her only your example. Such a sacred duty as this will act as a cure for you, for only philosophy or honourable occupation can divert from its anguish a heart whose grief springs from love.

I would reckon your father too among your great comforts if he were not absent. As it is, you must now judge his love for you by your love for him, and you will realize how much more just it is for you to preserve yourself for him than sacrifice yourself for me. Whenever excessive grief attacks you and urges you to give way to it, think of your father. Certainly, by giving him so many grandchildren and great-grandchildren you ceased to be his only offspring; but for him the completion of a happy life depends on you. While he lives it is wrong for you to complain that you have lived.

Up to now I have said nothing about your greatest comfort, your sister, that heart most faithful to you into which are poured unreservedly all your anxieties, that soul which has been a mother to us all. You mingled your tears with hers; on her bosom you first began to breathe again. Always indeed she shares your feelings, but in my case she grieves not only for you. She carried me in her arms to Rome. During my long illness it was her loving and motherly nursing that brought me round. When I was a candidate for the quaestorship she supported me and, though she normally lacked the confidence even for conversation or a loud greeting, for my sake love conquered shyness. Neither her sheltered manner of living, nor her modesty (old-fashioned when compared with the prevalent brazenness of women), nor her tranquillity, nor her reserved nature which wanted peace and quiet — none of these prevented her from actually becoming ambitious on my behalf. She, dearest mother, is the source of comfort from which you can revive yourself: cling to her as much as you can in the closest embraces. Sorrowers tend to avoid what they are most fond of and try to give vent to their grief; but you must share all your thoughts with her. Whether you wish to keep this mood or lay it aside, you will find in her either the end of your sorrow or one who will share it. But if I know the wisdom of this paragon of women, she will not allow you to be consumed in profitless anguish, and she will tell you of an edifying episode in her life which I also witnessed.

While actually on a sea voyage she lost her beloved husband, my uncle, whom she had married as a maiden; yet she bore simultaneously the burdens of grief and fear and, though shipwrecked, she rode out the storms and brought his body safely ashore. O how many noble deeds of women are lost in obscurity! If she had chanced to live in the days of old when people frankly admired heroism, how men of genius would have competed to sing the praises of a wife who ignored her physical weakness, ignored the sea which even the bravest must fear, and risked her life to give her husband burial; and while her thoughts were on his funeral had no fears about her own! All the poets have given renown to the woman who offered to die in place of her husband. But this is nobler, to risk one's life to bury one's husband: for that love is greater which wins less through equal danger.

After this it can surprise no one that during the sixteen years her husband governed Egypt she was never seen in public, she received no provincial into her home, she never petitioned her husband for a favour, and she never allowed herself to be petitioned. The result was that a province given to gossip and clever at insulting its rulers, where even those who had avoided wrongdoing did not escape scandal, respected her as a singular pattern of integrity, restrained all licence in its speech (a very difficult achievement where even dangerous witticisms are popular), and even to this day keeps hoping, though it never expects, to see another like her. It would have been a great achievement if she had won the approval of the province for sixteen years; it was even better not to have been noticed there. I do not recall these things in order to list her good qualities (to rehearse them so sketchily is to be unfair to them), but to give you an idea of the high-mindedness of the woman who was not conquered by ambition or greed, those inevitable companions and curses of power; who, facing shipwreck on a disabled boat, was not deterred by the fear of death from clinging to her dead husband and seeking not the means of her own escape but the means of getting his body off for burial. This is the sort of courage you must match, by withdrawing your mind from grief and resolving that no one shall think you regret having had children.

However, whatever you do, inevitably your thoughts will turn to me constantly, and none of your other children will come to your mind more often, not because they are less dear to you but because it is natural to touch more often the part that hurts. So this is how you must think of me — happy and cheerful as if in the best of circumstances. For they are best, since my mind, without any preoccupation, is free for its own tasks, now delighting in more trivial studies, now in its eagerness for the truth rising up to ponder its own nature and that of the universe. It seeks to know first about lands and their location, then the nature of the encompassing sea and its tidal ebb and flow. Then it studies all the awesome expanse which lies between heaven and earth — this nearer space turbulent with thunder, lightning, gales of wind, and falling rain, snow and hail. Finally, having scoured the lower areas it bursts through to the heights and enjoys the noblest sight of divine things and, mindful of its own immortality, it ranges over all that has been and will be throughout all ages.

On Tranquillity of Mind

SERENUS:[〔1〕] When I looked into myself, Seneca, some of my vices appeared clearly on the surface, so that I could lay my hand on them; some were more hidden away in the depths; some were not there all the time but return at intervals. These last I would say are the most troublesome: they are like prowling enemies who pounce on you when occasion offers, and allow you neither to be at the ready as in war nor at ease as in peace. However, the state I most find myself in (for why should I not admit the truth to you as to a doctor?) is that I am not really free of the vices which I feared and hated, though not, on the other hand, subject to them: this puts me in a condition which is not the worst, but an extremely peevish and quarrelsome one — I am neither ill nor well. There is no need for you to say that all virtues are fragile to start with and acquire firmness and strength with time. I know too that those which toil to make a good impression, seeking high rank, for example, and a reputation for eloquence, and whatever depends on the approval of others, take time to mature — both those which offer real strength and those which are tricked out in some sort of dye aimed at popularity have to wait years until the passage of time gradually produces their colour. But I'm afraid that habit, which induces firmness in things, may drive this fault more deeply into me: long association brings love of evil as well as good.

I cannot show all at once so much as bit by bit the nature of this mental weakness, which wavers between two choices and does not incline strongly either to right or to wrong: I'll tell you what happens to me and you can find a name for the malady. I have a tremendous love of frugality, I must admit. I don't like a couch decked out ostentatiously; or clothes brought out from a chest or given a sheen by the forceful pressure of weights and a thousand mangles, but homely and inexpensive, and not hoarded to be donned with fuss and bother. I like food which is not prepared and watched over by the household slaves, not ordered many days in advance nor served by a multitude of hands, but readily obtainable and easy to deal with, nothing in it out of the way or expensive, available everywhere, not heavy on the purse or the body, and not destined to come back by the same way it entered. I want my servant to be an ordinary, unskilled, home-born slave; my silver to be the heavy ware of my rustic father without any hallmark; and my table to be without flashy variegated markings and not familiar to the whole town through its many changes of fashionable owners, but set up to be used and not to distract any guest's eyes with pleasure or kindle them with envy. But when I have set up these standards I find my mind dazzled by the fine trappings of some training-school for servants, with the slaves more carefully clothed and decked with gold than if they were in a public parade, and a whole army of glittering flunkies; by a house where you even walk on precious stones, where wealth is scattered in every corner, where the roof itself glitters, and the whole populace deferentially attends the ruin of a family heritage. Need I mention pools clear to their depths which flow around the dinner guests, or banquets worthy of their surroundings? After being long given up to frugality I have found myself surrounded by the lavish splendour of luxury echoing all about me. My vision wavers somewhat, for I can raise my mind to face it more easily than my eyes. And so I come back not a worse but a sadder man; I don't move with my head so high among my trivial possessions; and a secret gnawing doubt undermines me whether that life is superior. None of these things is changing me, but none of them fails to shake me.

I decide to follow my teacher's precepts and busy myself in state affairs; I decide to achieve public office — not, of course, because of the purple robe and the lictors' rods, but so that I can be more ready with help for my friends and relations, for all my fellow-citizens, and then for all mankind. Enthusiastically I follow Zeno, Cleanthes, Chrysippus, of whom, by the way, none entered public life and all urged others to do so. But when something has assailed my mind, which is not used to being battered; when something has happened which either is unworthy of me (a common experience in every human life) or cannot easily be dealt with; when unimportant things become time-consuming; I take refuge in leisure and, just like weary flocks of animals, I make my way more quickly home. I decide to restrict my life within its walls, saying, 'Let no one rob me of a single day who is not going to make me an adequate return for such a loss. Let my mind be fixed on itself, cultivate itself, have no external interest — nothing that seeks the approval of another; let it cherish the tranquillity that has no part in public or private concerns.' But when my mind is excited by reading a convincing account of something and spurred on by noble examples, I long to rush into the forum, to speak on behalf of one man and offer help to another, which will at least be an attempt to assist even if it does not succeed, or to curb the pride of someone else grown arrogant by success.

In my studies I suppose it must indeed be better to keep my theme firmly in view and speak to this, while allowing the theme to suggest my words and so dictate the course of an unstudied style of speech. 'Where is the need,' I ask, 'to compose something to last for ages? Why not stop trying to prevent posterity being silent about you? You were born to die, and a silent funeral is less bothersome. So if you must fill your time, write something in a simple style for your own use and not for publication: less toil is needed if you study only for the day.' Again, when my mind is lifted up by the greatness of its thoughts, it becomes ambitious for words and longs to match its higher inspiration with its language, and so produces a style that conforms to the impressiveness of the subject matter. Then it is that I forget my rule and principle of restraint, and I am carried too far aloft by a voice no longer my own.

To cut the matter short, this weakness in my good intentions pursues me in every sphere. I fear that I am gradually getting worse, or (which is more worrying) that I am hanging on an edge like someone always on the point of falling, and that perhaps there is more wrong than I myself can see: for we take too intimate a view of our own characteristics and bias always affects our judgement. I imagine many people could have achieved wisdom if they had not imagined they had already achieved it, if they had not dissembled about some of their own characteristics and turned a blind eye to others. For you have no reason to suppose that we come to grief more through the flattery of others than through our own. Who has dared to tell himself the truth? Who even when surrounded by crowds of toadying sycophants is not his own greatest flatterer? So, I am appealing to you, if you have any cure for this vacillation of mind, to consider me worthy of owing tranquillity to you. I realize that these mental agitations of mine are not dangerous and won't produce a storm. To express my complaint for you in a realistic metaphor, I am harried not by a tempest but by sea-sickness. Whatever my ailment, then, root it out and come to the help of one who is struggling in sight of land.

SENECA: Indeed, Serenus, I have long been silently asking myself to what I should compare such a mental state, and I could find no closer analogy than the condition of those people who have got over a long and serious illness, but are still sometimes mildly affected by onsets of fever and pain, and even when free of the last symptoms are still worried and upset; and, though quite better, offer their hands to doctors and needlessly complain if they feel at all hot. With these people, Serenus, it is not that their bodies are insufficiently healed but that they are insufficiently used to health, just as even a calm sea will show some ripples, especially when it has subsided following a storm. So what you need is not those more radical remedies which we have now finished with — blocking yourself here, being angry with yourself there, threatening yourself sternly somewhere else — but the final treatment, confidence in yourself and the belief that you are on the right path, and not led astray by the many tracks which cross yours of people who are hopelessly lost, though some are wandering not far from the true path. But what you are longing for is great and supreme and nearly divine — not to be shaken. The Greeks call this steady firmness of mind 'euthymia' (Democritus wrote a good treatise about it), but I call it tranquillity, as there is no need to imitate and reproduce the form of Greek words: the point at issue must be indicated by some term which should have the sense but not the form of the Greek name. We are, therefore, seeking how the mind can follow a smooth and steady course, well disposed to itself, happily regarding its own condition and with no interruption to this pleasure, but remaining in a state of peace with no ups and downs: that will be tranquillity. Let us consider in general how this can be achieved: you will then extract what you like from the communal remedy. Meanwhile the whole failing must be dragged out into the open, where everyone will recognize his own share in it. At the same time you will realize how much less trouble you have with your self-revulsion than those people who, tied to some specious declaration and labouring under an impressive title, are stuck with their own pretence more by shame than by desire.

They are all in the same category, both those who are afflicted with fickleness, boredom and a ceaseless change of purpose, and who always yearn for what they have left behind, and those who just yawn from apathy. There are those too who toss around like insomniacs, and keep changing their position until they find rest through sheer weariness. They keep altering the condition of their lives, and eventually stick to that one in which they are trapped not by weariness with further change but by old age which is too sluggish for novelty. There are those too who suffer not from moral steadfastness but from inertia, and so lack the fickleness to live as they wish, and just live as they have begun. In fact there are innumerable characteristics of the malady, but one effect — dissatisfaction with oneself. This arises from mental instability and from fearful and unfulfilled desires, when men do not dare or do not achieve all they long for, and all they grasp at is hope: they are always unbalanced and fickle, an inevitable consequence of living in suspense. They struggle to gain their prayers by every path, and they teach and force themselves to do dishonourable and difficult things; and when their efforts are unrewarded the fruitless disgrace tortures them, and they regret not the wickedness but the frustration of their desires. Then they are gripped by repentance for their attempt and fear of trying again, and they are undermined by the restlessness of a mind that can discover no outlet, because they can neither control nor obey their desires, by the dithering of a life that cannot see its way ahead, and by the lethargy of a soul stagnating amid its abandoned hopes. All these afflictions are worse when, through hatred of their toilsome failure, men have retreated into idleness and private studies which are unbearable to a mind aspiring to public service, keen on activity, and restless by nature because of course it is short of inner resources. In consequence, when the pleasures have been removed which busy people derive from their actual activities, the mind cannot endure the house, the solitude, the walls, and hates to observe its own isolation. From this arises that boredom and self-dissatisfaction, that turmoil of a restless mind and gloomy and grudging endurance of our leisure, especially when we are ashamed to admit the reasons for it and our sense of shame drives the agony inward, and our desires are trapped in narrow bounds without escape and stifle themselves. From this arise melancholy and mourning and a thousand vacillations of a wavering mind, buoyed up by the birth of hope and sickened by the death of it. From this arises the state of mind of those who loathe their own leisure and complain that they have nothing to do, and the bitterest envy at the promotion of others. For unproductive idleness nurtures malice, and because they themselves could not prosper they want everyone else to be ruined. Then from this dislike of others' success and despair of their own, their minds become enraged against fortune, complain about the times, retreat into obscurity, and brood over their own sufferings until they become sick and tired of themselves. For the human mind is naturally mobile and enjoys activity. Every chance of stimulation and distraction is welcome to it — even more welcome to all those inferior characters who actually enjoy being worn out by busy activity. There are certain bodily sores which welcome the hands that will hurt them, and long to be touched, and a foul itch loves to be scratched: in the same way I would say that those minds on which desires have broken out like horrid sores take delight in toil and aggravation. For some things delight our bodies even when they cause some pain, like turning over to change a side that is not yet tired and repeatedly shifting to keep cool: so Achilles in Homer lay now on his face, now on his back, trying to settle in different positions, and like an invalid could endure nothing for long but used his restlessness as a cure. Hence men travel far and wide, wandering along foreign shores and making trial by land and sea of their restlessness, which always hates what is around it. 'Let's now go to Campania.' Then when they get bored with luxury — 'Let's visit uncultivated areas; let's explore the woodlands of Bruttium and Lucania.' And yet amid the wilds some delight is missing by which their pampered eyes can find relief from the tedious squalor of these unsightly regions. 'Let's go to Tarentum, with its celebrated harbour and mild winters, an area prosperous enough for a large population even in antiquity.' 'Let's now make our way to the city' — too long have their ears missed the din of applause: now they long to enjoy even the sight of human blood. They make one journey after another and change spectacle for spectacle. As Lucretius says, 'Thus each man ever flees himself.' But to what end, if he does not escape himself? He pursues and dogs himself as his own most tedious companion. And so we must realize that our difficulty is not the fault of the places but of ourselves. We are weak in enduring anything, and cannot put up with toil or pleasure or ourselves or anything for long. This weakness has driven some men to their deaths; because by frequently changing their aims they kept falling back on the same things and had left themselves no room for novelty. They began to be sick of life and the world itself, and out of their enervating self-indulgence arose the feeling 'How long must I face the same things?'

You want to know what remedy I can recommend against this boredom. The best course, as Athenodorus says, would be to busy oneself in the practical activity of political involvement and civic duties. For just as some people spend the day in sun-bathing, exercise and the care of their bodies, and for athletes it is of the highest practical importance to spend most of their time cultivating the strength of their limbs, to which alone they have devoted themselves, so for you, who are training your mind for the contests of public life, by far the finest approach is regular practice. For when one intends to make himself useful to his fellow-citizens and fellowmen, he is at the same time getting practice and doing good if he throws himself heart and soul into the duty of looking after both the community and the individual. 'But,' says Athenodorus, 'since mankind is so insanely ambitious and so many false accusers twist right into wrong, making honesty unsafe and bound to meet resistance rather than help, we should indeed retire from public and political life, though a great mind has scope for free activity even in private life. The energies of lions and other animals are restricted by cages, but not of men, whose finest achievements are seen in retirement. However, let a man seclude himself on condition that, wherever he conceals his leisure, he is prepared to serve both individuals and all mankind by his intellect, his words and his counsel. Service to the state is not restricted to the man who produces candidates for office, defends people in court, and votes for peace and war: the man who teaches the young, who instils virtue into their minds (and we have a great shortage of good teachers), who grips and restrains those who are rushing madly after wealth and luxury, and if nothing more at least delays them — he too is doing a public service, though in private life. Do you imagine that more benefit is provided by the praetors, who settle cases between foreigners and citizens by pronouncing to appellants the verdict of the assessor, than by those who pronounce on the nature of justice, piety, endurance, bravery, contempt of death, knowledge of the gods, and how free a blessing is that of a good conscience? So if you devote to your studies the time you have taken from your public duties you will not have deserted or evaded your task. For the soldier is not only the man who stands in the battle line, defending the right and left wings, but also the one who guards the gates and has the post, less dangerous but not idle, of keeping the watch and guarding the armoury: these duties, though bloodless, count as military service. If you apply yourself to study you will avoid all boredom with life, you will not long for night because you are sick of daylight, you will be neither a burden to yourself nor useless to others, you will attract many to become your friends and the finest people will flock about you. For even obscure virtue is never concealed but gives visible evidence of herself: anyone worthy of her will follow her tracks. But if we shun all society and, abandoning the human race, live for ourselves alone, this isolation, devoid of any interest, will be followed by a dearth of worthwhile activity. We shall begin to put up some buildings, to pull down others, to push back the sea, to draw waters through unnatural channels, and to squander the time which nature gave us to be used. Some of us use it sparingly, others wastefully; some spend it so that we can give an account of it, others so that we have no balance left — a most shameful result. Often a very old man has no other proof of his long life than his age.'

It seems to me, my dear Serenus, that Athenodorus has too easily submitted to the times and too quickly retreated. I would not deny that one has to yield sometimes — but by a gradual retreat, and holding on to our standards and our soldier's honour. Those who are still armed when they agree terms with their enemies are safer and more highly regarded. This, I think, is what Virtue and Virtue's disciple should do: if Fortune gets the better of someone and deprives him of the means of action, he should not immediately turn his back and bolt, dropping his weapons and looking for a place to hide (as if there were any place where Fortune could not find him), but he should apply himself more sparingly to his duties and choose something carefully in which he can serve the state. Suppose he cannot be a soldier: let him seek public office. Suppose he has to live in a private capacity: let him be an advocate. Suppose he is condemned to silence: let him help his fellow-citizens by unspoken support. Suppose it is dangerous for him to be seen in the forum: in private homes, at the shows, at banquets let him play the part of a good companion, a loyal friend, a temperate banqueter. Suppose he has lost the duties of a citizen: let him practise those of a man. With a lofty spirit we have refused to confine ourselves within the walls of one city, and we have gone out to have dealings with the whole earth and claimed the world as our country, for this reason, that we might give our virtue a wider field for action. Suppose you are cut off from judicial office, and public speaking and elections are closed to you: consider all the extensive regions that lie open behind you, all the peoples — you will never find an area barred to you so large that an even larger one is not left open. But take care that this is not entirely your fault — for example, that you don't want to take public office except as consul or prytanis or herald or sufes. But suppose you didn't want to serve in the army except as general or tribune? Even if others hold the front line and your lot has put you in the third rank, you must play the soldier there with your voice, your encouragement, your example and your spirit. Even if a man's hands are cut off, he finds he can yet serve his side by standing firm and cheering them on. You should do something like that: if Fortune has removed you from a leading role in public life you should still stand firm and cheer others on, and if someone grips your throat, still stand firm and help though silent. The service of a good citizen is never useless: being heard and seen, he helps by his expression, a nod of his head, a stubborn silence, even his gait. Just as certain wholesome substances do us good by their odour even without tasting or touching them, so Virtue spreads her advantages even from a distant hiding place. Whether she walks abroad about her legitimate business, or appears on sufferance and is forced to furl her sails, whether she is confined, inactive and dumb, within a narrow space, or fully visible, in any condition at all she does good service. Why do you think that a man living in honourable retirement cannot offer a valuable example? Much the best course, therefore, is to combine leisure with some activity whenever a fully energetic life is impossible owing to the hindrances of chance or the state of the country; for you will never find absolutely every road blocked to some form of honourable activity.

Can you find a more wretched city than Athens when she was being torn apart by the Thirty Tyrants? Having killed thirteen hundred of the best citizens, they did not stop at that, but their very savagery spurred itself on. In a city which contained the Areopagus, a law court of the highest sanctity, and a senate and a popular assembly resembling a senate, there met daily a sinister group of executioners, and the unfortunate senate house was crowded with tyrants. Could that state be at peace where there were as many tyrants as attendants? There could not even be a hope of recovering their liberty nor any obvious chance of retaliation against such powerful villains: for where could the poor country find enough men like Harmodius? Yet Socrates was in the thick of it: he comforted the gloomy city fathers, encouraged those who were despairing of the state, reproached the rich who now feared their own wealth for a tardy repentance of their dangerous greed; and to those willing to imitate him he was a walking inspiration, as he moved about, a free spirit among thirty masters. Yet this was the man that Athens herself put to death in prison, and Freedom could not bear the freedom of the man who had openly scoffed at a whole troop of tyrants. So you can understand both that in a state suffering disaster the wise man has the opportunity to show an influential presence, and that in a successful and prosperous state money-grubbing, envy and a thousand other unmanly vices reign supreme. Therefore, according to the disposition of the state and the liberty Fortune allows us, we shall either extend or contract our activities; but at all events we shall stir ourselves and not be gripped and paralysed by fear. He indeed will prove a man who, threatened by dangers on all sides, with arms and chains clattering around him, will neither endanger nor conceal his courage: for self-preservation does not entail suppressing onself. Truly, I believe, Curius Dentatus used to say that he preferred real death to living death; for the ultimate horror is to leave the number of the living before you die. But if you happen to live at a time when public life is hard to cope with, you will just have to claim more time for leisure and literary work, seek a safe harbour from time to time as if you were on a dangerous voyage, and not wait for public life to dismiss you but voluntarily release yourself from it first.

However, we must take a careful look first at ourselves, then at the activities which we shall be attempting, and then at those for whose sake and with whom we are attempting them.

Above all it is essential to appraise oneself, because we usually overestimate our capabilities. One man comes to grief through trusting his eloquence; another makes more demands on his fortune than it can stand; another taxes his frail body with laborious work. Some men are too shy for politics, which require a bold appearance; some through brashness are not fitted for court life; some cannot restrain their anger and any feeling of annoyance drives them to reckless language; some cannot control their wit and refrain from smart but dangerous sallies. For all of these retirement is more expedient than public activity: a passionate and impatient nature must avoid provocations to outspokenness that will cause trouble.

Then we must appraise the actual things we are attempting and match our strength to what we are going to undertake. For the performer must always be stronger than his task: loads that are too heavy for the bearer are bound to overwhelm him. Moreover, certain tasks are not so much great as prolific in producing many other tasks: we must avoid those which give birth in turn to new and manifold activities, and not approach something from which we cannot easily withdraw. You must set your hands to tasks which you can finish or at least hope to finish, and avoid those which get bigger as you proceed and do not cease where you had intended.

We must be especially careful in choosing people, and deciding whether they are worth devoting a part of our lives to them, whether the sacrifice of our time makes a difference to them. For some people actually charge us for our services to them. Athenodorus says he would not even go to dinner with a man who did not thereby feel indebted to him. I suppose you realize how much less inclined he was to visit those who repay their friends' services with a meal, and count the courses as largesses, as if they were overdoing the honour paid to another. Take away their witnesses and spectators and there is no fun in private gormandizing.

You must consider whether your nature is more suited to practical activity or to quiet study and reflection, and incline in the direction your natural faculty and disposition take you. Isocrates forcibly pulled Ephorus away from the forum, thinking he would be better employed in writing history. Inborn dispositions do not respond well to compulsion, and we labour in vain against nature's opposition.

But nothing delights the mind so much as fond and loyal friendship. What a blessing it is to have hearts that are ready and willing to receive all your secrets in safety, with whom you are less afraid to share knowledge of something than keep it to yourself, whose conversation soothes your distress, whose advice helps you make up your mind, whose cheerfulness dissolves your sorrow, whose very appearance cheers you up! To be sure, we shall choose those who are as far as possible free from strong desires; for vices spread insidiously, and those nearest to hand are assailed and damaged by contact with them. It follows that, just as at a time of an epidemic disease we must take care not to sit beside people whose bodies are infected with feverish disease because we shall risk ourselves and suffer from their breathing upon us, so in choosing our friends for their characters we shall take care to find those who are the least corrupted: mixing the sound with the sick is how disease starts. But I am not enjoining upon you to follow and associate with none but a wise man. For where will you find him whom we have been seeking for ages? In place of the ideal we must put up with the least bad. You would scarcely have the opportunity of a happier choice if you were hunting for good men among the Platos and Xenophons and all that offspring of the Socratic breed; or if you had access to the age of Cato, which produced many men worthy to be born in Cato's time. (It also produced many who were worse than at any other time and who committed appalling crimes: for both groups were necessary for Cato to be appreciated — he needed the good to win their approval and the bad to prove his strength.) But in the current dearth of good men you must be less particular in your choice. Still, you must especially avoid those who are gloomy and always lamenting, and who grasp at every pretext for complaint. Though a man's loyalty and kindness may not be in doubt, a companion who is agitated and groaning about everything is an enemy to peace of mind.

Let us turn to private possessions, the greatest source of human misery. For if you compare all the other things from which we suffer, deaths, illnesses, fears, desires, endurance of pains and toils, with the evils which money brings us, the latter will far outweigh the others. So we must bear in mind how much lighter is the pain of not having money than of losing it; and we shall realize that the less poverty has to lose the less agony it can cause us. For you are mistaken if you think that rich people suffer with more fortitude: the pain of a wound is the same in the largest and the smallest bodies. Bion aptly remarks that plucking out hair hurts bald people just as much as those with hair. You can make the same point that rich and poor suffer equal distress: for both groups cling to their money and suffer if it is torn away from them. But, as I said, it is easier to bear and simpler not to acquire than to lose, so you will notice that those people are more cheerful whom Fortune has never favoured than those whom she has deserted. That great-souled man Diogenes realized this, and arranged that nothing could be taken from him. You can call this state poverty, deprivation, need, and give this freedom from care any shameful name you like: I shall not count this man happy if you can find me another who has nothing to lose. If I am not mistaken it is a royal position among all the misers, the cheats, the robbers, the kidnappers, to be the only one who cannot be harmed. If anyone has any doubts about Diogenes' felicity he can also have doubts about the condition of the immortal gods — whether they are living unhappily because they have no estates and parks and costly farms let out to foreign tenants and vast receipts of interest in the forum. Are you not ashamed of yourselves, all of you who are smitten by wealth? Come, look at the heavens: you will see the gods devoid of possessions, and giving everything though they have nothing. Do you think a man who has stripped himself of all the gifts of chance is poor, or that he resembles the immortal gods? Demetrius, Pompey's freedman, was not ashamed to be richer than Pompey: would you say he was thereby happier? He used to keep the tally of his slaves daily like a general reviewing his let us learn to rely on our limbs, and to adjust our style of dress and our way of living not to the newfangled patterns but to the customs of our ancestors. Let us learn to increase our self-restraint, to curb luxury, to moderate ambition, to soften anger, to regard poverty without prejudice, to practise frugality, even if many are ashamed of it, to apply to nature's needs the remedies that are cheaply available, to curb as if in fetters unbridled hopes and a mind obsessed with the future, and to aim to acquire our riches from ourselves rather than from Fortune. It is not possible that all the manifold and unfair disasters of life can be so repelled that many storm winds will not still assail those who spread their sails ambitiously. We must restrict our activities so that Fortune's weapons miss their mark; and for that reason exiles and calamities have proved to benefit us and greater disasters have been mended by lesser ones. When the mind is less amenable to instruction and cannot be cured by milder means, why should it not be helped by having a dose of poverty and disgrace and general ruin — dealing with evil by evil? So let us get used to dining without a mass of people, to being slave to fewer slaves, to acquiring clothes for their proper purpose, and to living in more restricted quarters. Not only in running and the contests of the Circus, but in this race course of our lives we must keep to the inner track.

Even in our studies, where expenditure is most worth while, its justification depends on its moderation. What is the point of having countless books and libraries whose titles the owner could scarcely read through in his whole lifetime? The mass of books burdens the student without instructing him, and it is far better to devote yourself to a few authors than to get lost among many. Forty thousand books were burned in the library at Alexandria. Someone else can praise it as a sumptuous monument to royal wealth, like Titus Livius, who calls it a notable achievement of the good taste and devotion of kings. That was not good taste or devotion but scholarly self-indulgence — in fact, not even scholarly, since they had collected the books not for scholarship but for display. In the same way you will find that many people who lack even elementary culture keep books not as tools of learning but as decoration for their dining-rooms. So we should buy enough books for use, and none just for embellishment. 'But this,' you say, 'is a more honourable expense than squandering money on Corinthian bronzes and on pictures.' But excess in any sphere is reprehensible. How can you excuse a man who collects bookcases of citron-wood and ivory, amasses the works of unknown or third-rate authors, and then sits yawning among all his thousands of books and gets most enjoyment out of the appearance of his volumes and their labels? Thus you will see that the idlest men possess sets of orations and histories, with crates piled up to the ceiling: for nowadays an elegant library too has joined hot and cold baths as an essential adornment for a house. I would certainly excuse people for erring through an excessive love of study; but these collections of works of inspired genius, along with their several portraits, are acquired only for pretentious wall decoration.

But perhaps you have become involved in some difficult situation in life in which either public or private circumstances have fastened a noose on you unawares, which you can neither loosen nor snap. You must reflect that fettered prisoners only at first feel the weight of the shackles on their legs: in time, when they have decided not to struggle against but to bear them, they learn from necessity to endure with fortitude, and from habit to endure with ease. In any situation in life you will find delights and relaxations and pleasures if you are prepared to make light of your troubles and not let them distress you. In no respect has nature put us more in her debt, since, knowing to what sorrows we were born, she contrived habit to soothe our disasters, and so quickly makes us grow used to the worst ills. No one could endure lasting adversity if it continued to have the same force as when it first hit us. We are all tied to Fortune, some by a loose and golden chain, and others by a tight one of baser metal: but what does it matter? We are all held in the same captivity, and those who have bound others are themselves in bonds — unless you think perhaps that the left-hand chain is lighter. One man is bound by high office, another by wealth; good birth weighs down some, and a humble origin others; some bow under the rule of other men and some under their own; some are restricted to one place by exile, others by priesthoods: all life is a servitude. So you have to get used to your circumstances, complain about them as little as possible, and grasp whatever advantage they have to offer: no condition is so bitter that a stable mind cannot find some consolation in it. Often small areas can be skilfully divided up to allow room for many uses and arrangement can make a narrow piece of ground inhabitable. Think your way through difficulties: harsh conditions can be softened, restricted ones can be widened, and heavy ones can weigh less on those who know how to bear them. Moreover, we must not send our desires on a distant hunt, but allow them to explore what is near to hand, since they do not submit to being totally confined. Abandoning those things which are impossible or difficult to attain, let us pursue what is readily available and entices our hopes, yet recognize that all are equally trivial, outwardly varied in appearance but uniformly futile within. And let us not envy those who stand higher than we do: what look like towering heights are precipices. On the other hand, those whom an unfair fate has put in a critical condition will be safer for lowering their pride in things that are in themselves proud and reducing their fortune as far as they can to a humble level. Indeed there are many who are forced to cling to their pinnacle because they cannot descend without falling; but they must bear witness that this in itself is their greatest burden, that they are forced to be a burden to others, and that they are not so much elevated as impaled. By justice, gentleness, kindness and lavish generosity let them prepare many defences against later disasters to give them hope of hanging on more safely. But nothing can rescue us from these mental vacillations so efficiently as always to set some limit to advancements, and not to allow Fortune the decision when they should cease but ourselves to stop far short of that. In this way we shall have some desires to stimulate the mind, but being limited they will not lead us to a state of uncontrolled uncertainty.

What I am saying applies to people who are imperfect, commonplace and unsound, not to the wise man. He does not have to walk nervously or cautiously, for he has such self-confidence that he does not hesitate to make a stand against Fortune and will never give ground to her. He has no reason to fear her, since he regards as held on sufferance not only his goods and possessions and status, but even his body, his eyes and hand, and all that makes life more dear, and his very self, and he lives as though he were lent to himself and bound to return the loan on demand without complaint. Nor is he thereby cheap in his own eyes because he knows he is not his own, but he will act in all things as carefully and meticulously as a devout and holy man guards anything entrusted to him. And whenever he is ordered to repay his debt he will not complain to Fortune, but he will say: 'I thank you for what I have possessed and held. I have looked after your property to my great benefit, but at your command I give and yield it with gratitude and good will. If you want me still to have anything of yours, I shall keep it safe; if you wish otherwise, I give back and restore to you my silver, both coined and plate, my house and my household.' Should Nature demand back what she previously entrusted to us we shall say to her too: 'Take back my spirit in better shape than when you gave it. I do not quibble or hang back: I am willing for you to have straightway what you gave me before I was conscious — take it.' What is the harm in returning to the point whence you came? He will live badly who does not know how to die well. So we must first strip off the value we set on this thing and reckon the breath of life as something cheap. To quote Cicero, we hate gladiators if they are keen to save their life by any means; we favour them if they openly show contempt for it. You must realize that the same thing applies to us: for often the cause of dying is the fear of it. Dame Fortune, who makes sport with us, says, 'Why should I preserve you, base and fearful creature? You will only receive more severe wounds and stabs, as you don't know how to offer your throat. But you will both live longer and die more easily, since you receive the blade bravely, without withdrawing your neck and putting your hands in the way. He who fears death will never do anything worthy of a living man. But he who knows that this was the condition laid down for him at the moment of his conception will live on those terms, and at the same time he will guarantee with a similar strength of mind that no events take him by surprise. For by foreseeing anything that can happen as though it will happen he will soften the onslaught of all his troubles, which present no surprises to those who are ready and waiting for them, but fall heavily on those who are careless in the expectation that all will be well. There is disease, imprisonment, disaster, fire: none of these is unexpected — I did know in what riotous company Nature had enclosed me. So many times have the dead been lamented in my neighbourhood; so many times have torch and taper conducted untimely funerals past my threshold. Often has the crash of a falling building echoed beside me. Many who were linked to me through the forum and the senate and everyday conversation have been carried off in a night, which has severed the hands once joined in friendship. Should it surprise me if the perils which have always roamed around me should some day reach me? A great number of people plan a sea voyage with no thought of a storm. I shall never be ashamed to go to a bad author for a good quotation. Whenever Publilius abandoned the absurdities of the mime and language aimed at the gallery, he showed more force of intellect than the writers of tragedy and comedy; and he produced many thoughts more striking than those of tragedy, let alone farce, including this one: 'What can happen to one can happen to all.' If you let this idea sink into your vitals, and regard all the ills of other people (of which every day shows an enormous supply) as having a clear path to you too, you will be armed long before you are attacked. It is too late for the mind to equip itself to endure dangers once they are already there. 'I didn't think it would happen' and 'Would you ever have believed it would turn out so?' Why ever not? Are there any riches which are not pursued by poverty and hunger and beggary? What rank is there whose purple robe and augur's staff and patrician shoe-straps are not attended by squalor and the brand of disgrace and a thousand marks of shame and utter contempt? What kingship does not face ruin and trampling down, the tyrant and the hangman? And these things are not separated by wide intervals: there is only a brief hour between sitting on a throne and kneeling to another. Know, then, that every condition can change, and whatever happens to anyone can happen to you too. You are rich: but are you richer than Pompey? Yet even he lacked bread and water when Gaius, his old relation and new host, had opened the house of Caesar to him so that he could close his own. Though he possessed so many rivers flowing from source to mouth in his own lands, he had to beg for drops of water. He died of hunger and thirst in a kinsman's palace, and while he starved his heir was organizing a state funeral for him. You have filled the highest offices: were they as high or unexpected or all-embracing as Sejanus had? Yet on the same day the senate escorted him to prison and the people tore him to pieces; and there was nothing left for the executioner to drag away of the man who had had everything heaped on him that gods and men could offer. You are a king: I shall not direct you to Croesus, who lived to see his own funeral pyre both lit and extinguished, thus surviving not only his kingdom but his own death; nor to Jugurtha, who was put on show to the Roman people within a year of causing them terror. We have seen Ptolemy, king of Africa, and Mithridates, king of Armenia, imprisoned by Gaius. One of them was sent into exile; the other hoped to be sent there in better faith. In all this topsy-turvy succession of events, unless you regard anything that can happen as bound to happen you give adversity a power over you which the man who sees it first can crush.

The next thing to ensure is that we do not waste our energies pointlessly or in pointless activities: that is, not to long either for what we cannot achieve, or for what, once gained, only makes us realize too late and after much exertion the futility of our desires. In other words, let our labour not be in vain and without result, nor the result unworthy of our labour; for usually bitterness follows if either we do not succeed or we are ashamed of succeeding. We must cut down on all this dashing about that a great many people indulge in, as they throng around houses and theatres and fora: they intrude into other people's affairs, always giving the impression of being busy. If you ask one of them as he comes out of a house, 'Where are you going? What do you have in mind?' he will reply, 'I really don't know; but I'll see some people, I'll do something.' They wander around aimlessly looking for employment, and they do not what they intended but what they happen to run across. Their roaming is idle and pointless, like ants crawling over bushes, which purposelessly make their way right up to the topmost branch and then all the way down again. Many people live a life like these creatures, and you could not unjustly call it busy idleness. You will feel sorry for some folk you see rushing along as if to a fire; so often do they bump headlong into those in their way and send themselves and others sprawling, when all the time they have been running to call on someone who will not return the call, or to attend the funeral of somebody they don't know, or the trial of somebody who is constantly involved in litigation, or the betrothal of a woman who is constantly getting married, and while attending a litter have on occasion even carried it. They then return home, worn out to no purpose and swearing they themselves don't know why they went out or where they have been — and the next day they will wander forth on the same old round. So let all your activity be directed to some object, let it have some end in view. It is not industry that makes men restless, but false impressions of things drive them mad. For even madmen need some hope to stir them: the outward show of some object excites them because their deluded mind cannot detect its worthlessness. In the same way every individual among those who wander forth to swell a crowd is led round the city by empty and trivial reasons. Dawn drives him forth with nothing to do, and after he has been jostled in vain on many men's doorsteps and only succeeds in greeting their slave-announcers, shut out by many he finds no one at home with more difficulty than himself. This evil leads in turn to that most disgraceful vice of eavesdropping and prying into public and secret things and learning about many matters which are safe neither to talk about nor to listen to.

I imagine that Democritus had this in mind when he began: 'Anyone who wishes to live a quiet life should not engage in many activities either privately or publicly' — meaning, of course, useless ones. For if they are essential, then not just many but countless things have to be done both privately and publicly. But when no binding duty summons us we must restrain our actions. For a man who is occupied with many things often puts himself into the power of Fortune, whereas the safest policy is rarely to tempt her, though to keep her always in mind and to trust her in nothing. Thus: 'I shall sail unless something happens'; and 'I shall become praetor unless something prevents me'; and 'My business will be successful unless something interferes.' That is why we say that nothing happens to the wise man against his expectation. We remove him not from the chances that befall mankind but from their mistakes, nor do all things turn out for him as he wished but as he reckoned — and above all he reckoned that something could block his plans. But inevitably the mind can cope more easily with the distress arising from disappointed longings if you have not promised it certain success.

We should also make ourselves flexible, so that we do not pin our hopes too much on our set plans, and can move over to those things to which chance has brought us, without dreading a change in either our purpose or our condition, provided that fickleness, that fault most inimical to tranquillity, does not get hold of us. For obstinacy, from which Fortune often extorts something, is bound to bring wretchedness and anxiety, and much more serious is the fickleness that nowhere restrains itself. Both are hostile to tranquillity, and find change impossible and endurance impossible. In any case the mind must be recalled from external objects into itself: it must trust in itself, rejoice in itself, admire its own things; it must withdraw as much as possible from the affairs of others and devote its attention to itself; it must not feel losses and should take a kindly view even of misfortunes. When a shipwreck was reported and he heard that all his possessions had sunk, our founder Zeno said, 'Fortune bids me be a less encumbered philosopher.' When a tyrant threatened to kill the philosopher Theodorus, and indeed to leave him unburied, he replied, 'You can please yourself, and my half-pint of blood is in your power; but as to burial, you are a fool if you think it matters to me whether I rot above or below ground.' Julius Canus, an outstandingly fine man, whom we can admire even though he was born in our age, had a long dispute with Gaius; and as he was going away that Phalaris said to him, 'In case you are deluding yourself with foolish hopes, I have ordered you to be led off to execution.' His reply was 'I thank you, noble emperor.' I am not certain what he meant, for many possibilities occur to me. Did he mean to be insulting by showing the extent of the cruelty which caused death to be a blessing? Was he taunting him with his daily bouts of madness (for people used to thank him whose children had been murdered and whose property had been confiscated)? Was he accepting his sentence as a welcome release? Whatever he meant, it was a spirited reply. Someone will say, 'After this Gaius could have ordered him to live.' Canus was not afraid of that: Gaius was known to keep his word in commands of that sort. Will you believe that Canus spent the ten days leading up to his execution without any anxiety at all? It is incredible what that man said, what he did, how calm he remained. He was playing draughts when the centurion who was dragging off a troop of condemned men ordered him to be summoned too. At the call he counted his pieces and said to his companion, 'See that you don't falsely claim after my death that you won.' Then, nodding to the centurion, he said, 'You will be witness that I am leading by one piece.' Do you think Canus was just enjoying his game at that board? He was enjoying his irony. His friends were sorrowful at the prospect of losing such a man, and he said to them, 'Why are you sad? You are wondering whether souls are immortal: I shall soon know.' He did not cease searching for the truth right up to the end and making his own death a topic for discussion. His philosophy teacher went with him, and when they were not far from the mound on which our god Caesar received his daily offering, he said, 'Canus, what are you thinking about now? What is your state of mind?' Canus replied, 'I have decided to take note whether in that most fleeting moment the spirit is aware of its departure from the body'; and he promised that if he discovered anything he would visit his friends in turn and reveal to them the state of the soul. Just look at that serenity in the midst of a hurricane, that spirit worthy of immortality, which invokes its own fate to establish the truth, and in that very last phase of life questions the departing soul and seeks to learn something not only up to the time of death but from the very experience of death itself. No one ever pursued philosophy longer. So great a man will not quickly be relinquished, and he should be referred to with respect: glorious spirit, who swelled the roll of Gaius' victims, we shall ensure your immortality.

But there is no point in banishing the causes of private sorrow, for sometimes we are gripped by a hatred of the human race. When you consider how rare is simplicity and how unknown is innocence, how you scarcely ever find loyalty except when it is expedient, what a host of successful crimes you come across, and all the things equally hateful that men gain and lose through lust, and how ambition is now so far from setting limits to itself that it acquires a lustre from viciousness — all this drives the mind into a darkness whose shadows overwhelm it, as though those virtues were overturned which it is not possible to hope for and not useful to possess. We must therefore school ourselves to regard all commonly held vices as not hateful but ridiculous, and we should imitate Democritus rather than Heraclitus. For whenever these went out in public, the latter used to weep and the former to laugh; the latter thought all our activities sorrows, the former, follies. So we should make light of all things and endure them with tolerance: it is more civilized to make fun of life than to bewail it. Bear in mind too that he deserves better of the human race as well who laughs at it than he who grieves over it; since the one allows it a fair prospect of hope, while the other stupidly laments over things he cannot hope will be put right. And, all things considered, it is the mark of a greater mind not to restrain laughter than not to restrain tears, since laughter expresses the gentlest of our feelings, and reckons that nothing is great or serious or even wretched in all the trappings of our existence. Let every man contemplate the individual occurrences which bring us joy or grief, and he will learn the truth of Bion's dictum, that all the activities of men are like their beginnings, and their life is not more high-souled or serious than their conception, and that being born from nothing they are reduced to nothing. Yet it is preferable to accept calmly public behaviour and human failings, and not to collapse into either laughter or tears. For to be tormented by other people's troubles means perpetual misery, while to take delight in them is an inhuman pleasure; just as it is an empty show of kindness to weep and assume a solemn look because somebody is burying a son. In your own troubles too, the appropriate conduct is to indulge as much grief as nature, not custom, demands: for many people weep in order to be seen weeping, though their eyes are dry as long as there is nobody looking, since they regard it as bad form not to weep when everyone is weeping. This evil of taking our cue from others has become so deeply ingrained that even that most basic feeling, grief, degenerates into imitation.

We must next look at a category of occurrences which with good reason cause us grief and anxiety. When good men come to a bad end, when Socrates is compelled to die in prison and Rutilius to live in exile, when Pompey and Cicero have to offer their necks to their clients, when Cato, that living pattern of the virtues, has to fall on his sword to show the world what is happening to himself and the state at the same time; then we have to feel anguish that Fortune hands out such unfair rewards. And what can each of us then hope for himself when he sees the best men suffering the worst fates? What follows then? Observe how each of those men bore his fate; and if they were brave, long with your spirit for a spirit like theirs; if they died with womanly cowardice, then nothing died with them. Either they are worthy of your admiration for their courage or unworthy of your longing for their cowardice. For what is more disgraceful than if supremely great men by dying bravely make others fearful? Let us repeatedly praise one who deserves praise and let us say: 'The braver one is, the happier he is! You have escaped all mischances, envy and disease; you have come forth from prison — not that you seemed to the gods worthy of ill fortune, but unworthy that Fortune should any longer have power over you.' But we have to lay hands on those who pull back and at the very point of death look back towards life. I shall weep for no one who is happy and for no one who is weeping: the one has himself wiped away my tears; the other by his own tears has proved himself unworthy of any. Should I weep for Hercules because he was burned alive, or Regulus because he was pierced by all those nails, or Cato because he wounded his own wounds? All of them by giving up a brief spell of time found the way to become eternal, and by dying achieved immortality.

There is also another not inconsiderable source of anxieties, if you are too concerned to assume a pose and do not reveal yourself openly to anyone, like many people whose lives are false and aimed only at outward show. For it is agonizing always to be watching yourself in fear of being caught when your usual mask has slipped. Nor can we ever be carefree when we think that whenever we are observed we are appraised; for many things happen to strip us of our pretensions against our will, and even if all this attention to oneself succeeds, yet the life of those who always live behind a mask is not pleasant or free from care. On the contrary, how full of pleasure is that honest and naturally unadorned simplicity that in no way hides its disposition! Yet this life too runs a risk of being scorned if everything is revealed to everybody; for with some people familiarity breeds contempt. But there is no danger of virtue being held cheap as a result of close observation, and it is better to be despised for simplicity than to suffer agonies from everlasting pretence. Still, let us use moderation here: there is a big difference between living simply and living carelessly.

We should also withdraw a lot into ourselves; for associating with people unlike ourselves upsets a calm disposition, stirs up passions again, and aggravates any mental weakness which has not been completely cured. However, the two things must be mingled and varied, solitude and joining a crowd: the one will make us long for people and the other for ourselves, and each will be a remedy for the other; solitude will cure our distaste for a crowd, and a crowd will cure our boredom with solitude.

The mind should not be kept continuously at the same pitch of concentration, but given amusing diversions. Socrates did not blush to play with small children; Cato soothed his mind with wine when it was tired from the cares of state; and Scipio used to disport that triumphal and military form in the dance, not shuffling about delicately in the present style, when even in walking men mince and wriggle with more than effeminate voluptuousness, but in the old-fashioned, manly style in which men danced at times of games and festivals, without loss of dignity even if their enemies were watching them. Our minds must relax: they will rise better and keener after a rest. Just as you must not force fertile farmland, as uninterrupted productivity will soon exhaust it, so constant effort will sap our mental vigour, while a short period of rest and relaxation will restore our powers. Unremitting effort leads to a kind of mental dullness and lethargy. Nor would men's wishes move so much in this direction if sport and play did not involve a sort of natural pleasure; though repeated indulgence in these will destroy all the gravity and force of our minds. After all, sleep too is essential as a restorative, but if you prolong it constantly day and night it will be death. There is a big difference between slackening your hold on something and severing the link. Law-givers established holidays to give people a public mandate to enjoy themselves, thinking it necessary to introduce a sort of balance into their labours; and, as I said, certain great men gave themselves monthly holidays on fixed days, while others divided every day into periods of leisure and work. I remember that this was the practice of the great orator Asinius Pollio, whom nothing kept at work after the tenth hour. After that time he would not even read his letters, in case something fresh cropped up to be dealt with; but in those two hours he would rid himself of the weariness of the whole day. Some take a break in the middle of the day and keep any less demanding task for the afternoon hours. Our ancestors also forbad any new motion to be introduced in the senate after the tenth hour. The army divides the watches, and those who are returning from an expedition are exempt from night duty. We must indulge the mind and from time to time allow it the leisure which is its food and strength. We must go for walks out of doors, so that the mind can be strengthened and invigorated by a clear sky and plenty of fresh air. At times it will acquire fresh energy from a journey by carriage and a change of scene, or from socializing and drinking freely. Occasionally we should even come to the point of intoxication, sinking into drink but not being totally flooded by it; for it does wash away cares, and stirs the mind to its depths, and heals sorrow just as it heals certain diseases. Liber was not named because he loosens the tongue, but because he liberates the mind from its slavery to cares, emancipates it, invigorates it, and emboldens it for all its undertakings. But there is a healthy moderation in wine, as in liberty. Solon and Arcesilas are thought to have liked their wine, and Cato has been accused of drunkenness; whoever accused him will more easily make the charge honourable than Cato disgraceful. But we must not do this often, in case the mind acquires a bad habit; yet at times it must be stimulated to rejoice without restraint and austere soberness must be banished for a while. For whether we agree with the Greek poet that 'Sometimes it is sweet to be mad,' or with Plato that 'A man sound in mind knocks in vain at the doors of poetry,' or with Aristotle that 'No great intellect has been without a touch of madness,' only a mind that is deeply stirred can utter something noble and beyond the power of others. When it has scorned everyday and commonplace thoughts and risen aloft on the wings of divine inspiration, only then does it sound a note nobler than mortal voice could utter. As long as it remains in its senses it cannot reach any lofty and difficult height: it must desert the usual track and race away, champing the bit and hurrying its driver in its course to a height it would have feared to scale by itself.

So here you have, my dear Serenus, the means of preserving your tranquillity, the means of restoring it, and the means of resisting the faults that creep up on you unawares. But be sure of this, that none of them is strong enough for those who want to preserve such a fragile thing, unless the wavering mind is surrounded by attentive and unceasing care.

注释

〔1〕 A friend of Seneca's.

导读

亚当·斯密（Adam Smith，1723—1790），苏格兰著名经济学家、哲学家与文学家。他最初进入格拉斯哥大学修习哲学，之后转入牛津大学（不过据说牛津大学的学习经历对他日后的事业并无太大帮助）。毕业后，他先是在爱丁堡大学教授文学与经济学，之后回到母校格拉斯哥大学教授逻辑学与道德哲学。他于1759年出版的第一部著作《道德情操论》便是总结格拉斯哥大学教学内容而成。自1763年底开始，亚当·斯密应邀担任私人教师，并辞去大学正式教职，也因此有机会同弟子一同游览欧洲大陆，并借机结识了许多精英知识分子。1766年，他返回故乡，开始潜心研究、专于创作；十年之后，他的鸿篇巨制《国民财富的性质和原因的研究》终于面世，也就是我们日后所熟知的《国富论》。

《国富论》是经济学领域里的不朽名著，被称为是现代经济学的开山之作，奠定了资本主义自由经济的理论基础，而作者亚当·斯密也因此被誉为是“古典经济学”的开山鼻祖，使经济学迈入了现代的维度。《国富论》集大成地将经济理论体系化，不仅第一次总结出“重商主义”这个概念，更深受“重农主义”的影响，重视劳动力与自由市场的作用，这在“凯恩斯主义”产生之前一直是世界的主流经济思想。

“重商主义”是16到18世纪流行于欧洲的经济政策，以商业为本位，强调以贸易顺差进行金银等贵金属的积累，所以通常会施行关税调节、垄断、殖民等措施。亚当·斯密创立“古典经济学”，写作《国富论》一书，并正式对前一个时代的“重商主义”进行理论总结，正是为了宣告“自由经济”时代将要脱胎而至。

《国富论》原作分上下两卷，共五篇，第一篇主要分析劳动分工及国民财富的分配，第二篇主要分析资本的性质、积累和用途，第三篇主要分析当时比较普遍的重视都市工商业却轻视农业的政策的原因，第四篇主要分析不同国家不同阶段的不同经济理论，第五篇主要分析国家收入的使用方式。

“看不见的手”的概念，是贯穿亚当·斯密一生学术思想的绝妙比喻，在其著作中共出现过三次，而在《国富论》中的文字则来自第四篇，也即本书的“对于商品进口实施的限制”一节：

“但是任何社会的年收入总是与其产业的年总产量的可交换价值绝对相等，也就是说，年收入与年总产量的可交换价值完全是同一回事。由此看来，既然所有个人都会尽可能地利用自己的资本支持国内产业，并竭尽全力使该产业产生最大价值，所有个人也必然会尽可能地利用劳动为社会创造最大收入。当然，他既不是在为公众谋福利，也全然不知自己为公众贡献了多少福利。他宁可支持国内产业也不愿支持对外贸易，因而我们说他只关心自己的安全。他全力引导产业，使其产量达到最大价值，我们说他只是为自己赚取利润，在种种情形下，他都是由一只看不见的手引导着，不由自主地去达到并非出于本意希望达到的目的。”

简而言之，个人在经济生活中只考虑自己的利益，受“看不见的手”的驱使，即通过分工和市场的作用，可以达到国家富裕的目的。在此之后，“看不见的手”逐渐成了资本主义自由竞争经济模式的代称，即在市场中采取自由放任的经济政策，任由看不见的市场机制自由调控一切经济活动。此概念自问世以来，便成为世界的共识，无论之后经济学如何演变，如何分帮立派，从未再有人质疑市场机制的作用。“伟大的思想”系列收录《国富论》一书，并以“看不见的手”为标题编选原作的相关章节，包括“劳动分工”“劳动分工的原理”“商业体系的原理”“商品进口的限制”“限制的不合理”“农业体系”等方面，涵盖原作的数个核心要素如“劳动分工”“反对重商主义”“借鉴重农主义”等，使读者也能够一窥原作的思想魅力。

由于历史原因，我国曾长期坚持计划经济体制，一切经济活动完全由国家计划支配，这在很长一段时间内限制了经济的活力与持续发展；直到八十年代的改革开放，“看不见的手”终于将我们引领入“中国特色社会主义市场经济”的大道，开启了持续至今的飞跃式发展，中国经济得以盛放出耀世光辉。

现如今，走在世界一体化轨道上的我们不会再执着于制度的论辩，而是专注于和平、发展与协作，无论“市场”还是“计划”，都是社会通往幸福终点的不同经济方法而已。亚当·斯密在三百年前创造的伟大思想，不仅为中国乃至世界敲响了现代经济的大门，更在门后埋藏了无限丰厚的财富，静待读者去发掘。

柴尔

论劳动分工

人类劳动生产力最显著的提高，以及人们在劳动、应用劳动时所体现出来的绝大部分技能、熟练性和决断力，似乎都是劳动分工的结果。

要了解劳动分工在社会一般事务中的作用，比较容易的方法是考察其在某些具体的制造业中是如何进行劳动分工的。人们普遍认为，在某些微不足道的制造业中，劳动分工是最细的；或许并不是这些微不足道的制造业真的比那些更重要的制造业分工细，而是在那些只需满足少数人少量需求的微型制造业中，工人的总数必然很少，整个工作过程中各个不同部门雇用的员工往往可以聚集在一个车间，我们一下子就可以看见他们。相反，在那些满足大多数人大量需求的大型制造业中，每一个不同的工作部门都会雇用很多人，所以不可能将他们集中在一个车间干活。除了在同一个部门干活的人，我们很少能一次看见很多人。因此，尽管和小制造业相比，大制造业中的工作划分要细致得多，但其分工并不是特别明显，因而不太会被人注意。

试举一个非常微型的制造业，在该制造业中人们往往能够注意到劳动的分工，比如别针制造行业。一个没有受过任何职业培训（劳动分工使之成为一种专门的职业），也不熟悉该职业所使用的机械如何应用（同样，这类机械的发明很可能是劳动分工的结果）的人或许无论怎样吃苦耐劳，勤勤恳恳，也不一定能一天做一枚别针，更不用说20枚了。但是别针制造业发展到今天，不仅整个工作已成为专门的职业，而且这种职业又分成了许多部门，其中大部分部门又逐渐成为专门的职业。一个人抽出铁丝，另一个人将其拉直，第三个人将其切断，第四个人将其一端削尖，第五个人将另一端打磨好以便装上圆头；制作圆头则另需要三步不同的操作；装圆头、把针涂白，以及把针装到纸盒里。这些都已经是专门的职业了。这样一来，重要的别针制造就被分成约18种不同的工序。在有些工厂，这18种不同的工序分别由18个人操作，而在其他工厂，有时会由一个人负责两三种不同操作。我见过一间这种类型的小工厂，只雇用了10个人，几个人负责两三种不同操作。尽管他们资金缺乏，不会购买必要的机械设备，但如果足够勤勉，每天仍能制造12磅重的别针。中等大小的别针，1磅最多可达4000枚。依此计算，10个人一天最多可生产48000枚别针，每个人的生产量为这一总数的1/10，可以大致推断出，每人每天能制造4800枚别针。但如果这些人分开独立工作，且其中没有人受过该行业的专门培训的话，则每人每天制造的别针数量不会达到20枚，甚至有可能1枚也制造不出来；这样一来，他们每天的工作量或许不及现今工作量的1/240，甚至1/4800也达不到，相比之下，如今的高效正是合理分工和不同工种协同合作的结果。

别针制造虽然是微不足道的行业，但就劳动分工的效果来说，与其他各种工艺和制造业没有什么差别，尽管许多行业中的劳动分工没有这么细，也不可能简化成如此简单的操作，然而一旦可以劳动分工，每一种工艺的劳动生产力则必然会提高。各个行业之所以各自分立，雇用不同员工，似乎也是因为劳动分工能够带来这样的裨益。那些工业水平和劳动生产力水平极高的国家，其行业分工的程度也很高。在较为原始的社会中由一个人完成的工作，在较为现代的国家则一般需要好几个人协作完成。每一个进步的社会中，农民一般只是单纯的农民，制造业者也只是单纯的制造业者。任何一件完整的制造业产品也几乎都需要许多人共同完成。以制麻业和毛织业为例，从亚麻和羊毛的生产到麻布的漂白、烫平，再到呢绒的染色、浆纱，各部门使用了许多不同的技艺。和制造业相比，农业的性质的确不容许有这么多精细的劳动分工，各种工作彼此也不像制造业那样完全独立分开。我们不可能将牧民和农民的工作截然分立，但是木匠和铁匠从事的工艺则完全不同。纺纱和织布几乎是完全不同的两个行当，而犁耕、耙掘、播种和收割经常可以由同一个人进行。不同农业劳动随季节时令而变化，因此不可能雇用一个人经常性地来从事其中某一种劳动。或许正因为不能雇用完全不同的人来从事不同类型的农业劳动，农业生产力的提高总是无法与工业同步。一般来说，最富有的国家在农业和制造业方面都要优于邻国，然而相较于农业，这些国家在制造业的优越性则更为明显和突出。在这些富有的国家，土地的耕种情况更好，投入的劳动力和资本也更多，在土地面积和肥沃程度相同的情况下，也能有更多的产出。但是，其农产品产量上的优越程度很少能与劳动力和资本投入上的优越程度成正比。在农业方面，富国和穷国劳动力的生产力水平差异并不一定很大，至少不会像制造业的生产力水平差异那么大。因此，如果质量相同的话，富国生产的谷物不一定总是比穷国便宜。在质量相同的情况下，波兰生产的谷物价格可能会和法国一样，尽管后者的富裕和社会进步程度要优于前者。尽管法国的富裕和社会进步程度要逊于英国，但在法国生产谷物的省份，其谷物的质量和英国谷物完全没有差别，大多数年份中价格也与英国谷物持平，然而就谷物田地的耕种水平来说，英国要高于法国，而法国又大大高于波兰。尽管在耕种水平较为低下的穷国，谷物的价格和质量可以在一定程度上与富国媲美，但在制造业方面则根本不能匹敌；至少在富国的土壤、气候和天然条件适合这些制造业的时候，情况是这样。法国的丝绸比英国的更物美价廉，因为在当前生丝进口关税如此之高的情况下，法国的气候至少比英国更适宜丝绸生产。然而英国的五金器具和生羊毛无论从哪一方面来说都远胜于法国，在质量相同的前提下，其价格也比法国便宜。据说波兰除了少数几种家庭用品制造业外几乎没有什么制造业，这少数几种还都是些较为原始的、任何国家都已拥有的制造业。

有了劳动分工，单位数量的人在单位时间内可以从事的工作比过去多得多，主要有三个原因：首先，每一个工人的劳动熟练程度提高了；其次，由一个工种转到另一个工种通常要损失很多时间，现在这些时间省下了；最后，大量提高劳动效率、精简劳动强度机器的发明，使得如今一个人可以做许多人做的工作。

先看第一个原因。工人劳动熟练程度的提高必然会增加他可以从事的劳动数量；劳动分工将每一个人的业务简化为某一种简单的操作，这又使这一操作成为此人一生所从事的唯一职业，由此必然会大大提高工人的劳动熟练程度。一个惯于使用铁锤却从不曾练习如何制作铆钉的铁匠，一旦遭遇某种特殊情况必须试着制作铆钉，我坚信他每天可能最多制作两三枚，且铆钉的质量还低劣不堪。即便是经常制作铆钉的铁匠，如果铆钉制作不是他唯一或主要的工作，即使他竭尽全力，也很难在一天之内制作出800或1000枚铆钉。我见过几个不到20岁的青年，他们除了制作铆钉外没有练习过其他技艺，这些人如果竭尽全力，则每人每天最多可以制作2300枚铆钉。然而制作铆钉绝不是最简单的操作。一个人要拉风箱，要在必要时调整火力，要将铁烧热，锤打铆钉的每一部分；在锻造钉头时他还不得不换工具。如果将制作一枚别针或一个金属钮扣的整个工序细分成不同的操作，所有的操作就要简单得多，如果一个人以其中的某一种操作作为一生的职业的话，其劳动的熟练程度就要高得多。制造业中某些工序的完成速度极其快，在那些从未亲眼见过的人看来，人类的双手根本不可能达到这样的速度。

第二，由一个工种转换到另一个工种通常要损失很多时间，而节省这段时间所带来的好处也绝不是我们一开始就能想到的。人们不可能从一个工种很快转到另一个地点不同且需要以完全不同的工具进行操作的工种。一个乡间的织工同时耕种一小片耕地，离开织机走到田间就需要一段时间，从田间回到织机还需要一段时间。诚然，如果能在同一个车间进行两种业务操作，花费的时间无疑会减少很多，但即使是这样，浪费仍然是巨大的。人们从一个工作转到另一个工作，一般都会休息或闲逛一会儿，很难在刚开始一项新工作时就精力集中、全情投入。这时他们难免心不在焉，在最初那段时间里，与其说他们在工作，不如说在虚度时间。每一个农村劳动者每半个小时就要更换工作和工具，一生中几乎每天都要做20种不同的工作，自然而然便会养成这种闲逛和懒散的习惯，因此农村劳动者总是懒惰散漫，即使时间紧迫，他们也不能全身心地投入工作。这样看来，先不论一个人是否技艺娴熟，单此一个原因，工作效率就大大降低。

第三，也是最后一个原因。人人都知道使用恰当的机械设备能够在某种程度上提高劳动效率、简化劳动工序，再举例论证难免多余。因此在这里只需讨论一下，所有提高效率、简化工序的机器之所以问世，起因也都是劳动分工。只有人们不再在各种工序和工具的转换中浪费时间，而是全身心地投入到一个目标上时，才更有可能发现更加简单和快速地达到该目标的方法。而分工的结果，正是每个人都自然而然地把全部注意力投注在某一种十分单一的目标上。因此只要工作的性质还有改良的余地，在每一个具体劳动部门从事具体劳动的人自然会很快发现新的方法，使其自身的工作更加简单，完成起来也更容易。在劳动分工最细的制造业中使用的大多数机器，最初都是由普通工人发明的，他们受雇从事某些很简单的操作，自然会考虑如何找到更加简单和快速的方法来执行这些操作。那些常去这类制造业参观的人一定会经常看到这类设计相当巧妙的机器，它们就是这类工人为了改进和提高各自特定工作的效率而发明的。在最早的蒸汽机中，本来需要雇用一个男孩根据活塞的升降不断转换开关，连接和断开锅炉和汽缸之间的通路。其中一个男孩因为贪玩，发现在开关该通路的阀门把手处系上一根绳子，阀门即可自行开关，这样他就能跑去和玩伴们游戏了。这是自蒸汽机发明以来人们对其作出的最大改进之一，而这一改进正是一个希望减少劳动的小男孩发现的。

然而，绝不是所有机械设备的改进都是由使用这些机器的人发明的。许多改进是得益于机械制造师的聪明才智，而所谓的机械制造师，正是在机械制造成为一个专门行业之后形成的；有些则是所谓的哲学家或思想者的智慧结晶，他们并非每日身体力行地做事，而是以观察万物为业。因此，这些人往往能够将一些完全不同且毫不相干的事物的力量结合起来加以利用。和其他各个行业一样，随着社会的进步，哲学或思考也成为某一类公民主要或唯一的职业。同样，和其他各个行业一样，哲学也被细分为大量不同的分支，每一个分支又为一群或一类哲学家提供专门职业；哲学行业的分工，也和所有其他行业的细致分工一样，提高了人们的技艺熟练程度，节约了时间。每个人更专精于自己从事的那份工作，这样一来，从总体而言，他们就能做更多的工作，从而大大提高了这门学问的整体质量。

在一个治理得很好的社会中，正是劳动分工使得所有不同行业的生产力水平大为提高，为整个社会带来了普遍财富，最底层的人也能够享受到这种普遍财富带来的利益。每个工人在自己的工作中所创造的产品大大超出了他自己的需求；所有其他人的情况也完全一样，能用大量自己的产品换得大量他人生产的产品或等价物品。他大量提供给他人所需要的产品，也同样大量满足他个人的需要，整个社会的所有阶层就普遍富裕起来。

观察一下文明和繁荣的国家中最普通的工匠或临时工的生活用品，你就会知道，为了使他们能享用到这些生活用品，那些行业中的人必须提供自己生产的一部分，但这样的人却多得难以计数。以临时工身上穿的羊毛外衣为例，无论看起来多么粗制滥造，也是许许多多工人共同劳动的成果。牧羊人、选毛人、梳毛人、染工、梳理工、纺工、织工、漂洗工、裁缝工等等，必须将这些人的工作结合起来，才能够完成一件如此简单朴素的产品。加之这些劳动者的所在地往往相隔很远，彼此之间运送材料，又需要多少商人和运输工人啊！染工所使用的染料往往来自世界各地，要将各种不同的染料汇集在一起，又需要多少商人和运输工啊，更不用说其中的船工、水手、帆布和绳索制造者了！还有，这些工人手中拿的哪怕是最简单的工具，又需要多少不同的劳动工种相互协作！水手的船只、漂洗工的作坊，甚至织工的织机这类复杂的机械姑且不论，单说那无比简单的器具，牧羊人修剪羊毛的剪刀，都需要许多种不同的劳动才能制成。为了生产这样一把简单的剪刀，就需要把采矿工、熔炉制造工、伐木工、熔矿炉所用焦炭的烧炭工、制砖工、泥瓦匠、锅炉工、作坊建造者、锻工、铁匠等所有人各自不同的技艺全部结合起来才行。如果我们以同样的方式再考察一下他身上穿的所有衣服或家里的所有家具：他贴身穿的粗麻衬衫、脚上穿的鞋子、家里睡的床，乃至这张床的不同部件、他在厨房做饭用的炉子、他做饭用的煤炭（那可是从地下深处挖掘出来，或许经过很远的水路和陆路运输才到达他这里），还有厨房里的其他各种用具、桌子上的所有用具、刀叉、盛放和分发食物用的陶瓷盘子和锡盘子，为他制作面包和啤酒要用到多少工种、雇用多少工人，他房间里保温、采光、遮风挡雨用的玻璃窗——那华美而便捷的发明中凝聚着多少知识和艺术，没有玻璃，整个北半球大概没有一处适宜人们舒适地居住——再想一想，为生产所有这些生活用品，所雇用的人手中又要拿着多少种不同的工具。总之，如果我们考察一下所有这些物品，想一想其中每一件物品要雇用多少劳动力才能制成，就能够理解，在文明社会中，如果没有成千上万人的协助和合作，普通工人就不可能得到他通常所能得到的那些按照我们的理解，平常而又简单的生活用品。诚然，和大人物豪华奢侈的生活相比，普通工人的生活用品算是极为简朴了；然而事实却是，欧洲某国王子的生活用品并非总是比一个勤劳节俭的农民的生活用品精致，而后者的生活用品却超过了许多非洲君主的生活用品，要知道这些大人物可是成千上万赤裸草民生命和自由的绝对主宰啊！

劳动分工的原理

尽管人类智慧地预见到劳动分工能够带来普遍富裕，并希望利用它来实现这一目的，但劳动分工及其产生的诸多裨益，却不是人类智慧的结晶。它是人性中某种倾向的必然结果——尽管产生这种结果需要经历一个缓慢而渐进的过程，而其本身也未曾期待有如此广泛的效用——那就是物物交换、以物易物和互相交易的倾向。

这种倾向到底是人性中最原始又无法进一步解释说明的原则之一，还是听起来更接近于事实，是人类理性和言语能力的必然结果，并不是我们当前探究的话题。这种倾向人人皆有，亦为人所特有，其他动物不会拥有，其他动物似乎不懂得订立任何形式的契约——包括这种交换在内。两只猎犬在追逐同一只野兔时，有时会出现某种意义上的协同行为，将猎物驱往对方的方向，或者在猎物被逐至己方时努力拦截。然而猎犬之间的彼此“配合”并非因为它们受到某种契约的约束，而是因为恰巧在那个特定时刻，它们对同一个目标产生了共同的渴望。我们从未见过两只狗公平谨慎地交换彼此的骨头，也从未见过有任何动物通过自己的肢体动作和叫声向同类示意这是我的，那是你的；我想用我的这根骨头来换你的那根。如果动物想从人或者其他动物那里得到什么，除了博取对方欢心之外，没有其他的说服手段。小狗若要吃奶，就得奉承讨好母狗；家犬若要得到食物，就得在主人就餐之时作出种种娇态引起注意。人类对其同伴有时也会采用同样的手段。当有求于他人又没有其他办法达到目的时，他会卑躬屈膝、阿谀奉承来博得他人的好感。然而一个人并不总是如此幸运。在文明社会，人们随时会需要他人的合作和帮助，但倾其一生也难以结交到几个知己好友。在其他动物中，每个个体一旦发育成熟便完全独立，在自然状态下，并不需要其他动物的帮助。但是人却时常需要同伴的帮助，而单单指望对方的善心是徒劳无益的。如果能够影响他们，利用其利己之心使其明白，此时提供帮助完全符合其自身的利益，那么达到目的可能性就要大一些。任何一个希望和他人进行交易的人都会这样提议。这种提议的要义在于：给我我想要的，你就能得到你想要的。正是通过这种方式，彼此得到了自己所需要的绝大部分服务。我们的一日三餐并非来自屠夫、酿酒师或面包烘焙师的恩惠，而是来源于他们对自身利益的考虑。我们不是向他们乞求仁慈，而是诉诸他们的利己之心；我们不谈论自身的需求，而只谈对他们的好处。除了乞丐，不会有人选择把大部分希望寄托于他人的恩惠，即使乞丐也并不完全依赖于此。乐善好施之人的施舍的确为乞丐提供了全部的生存必需品。由此，尽管乞丐通过这种方法最终获得了全部生活所需，但他没有，也不可能在每当有需要的时候得到自己想要的东西。和其他人一样，他也要通过协定、交换和购买来满足自己平时绝大多数的需求。他用某人施舍的钱买来了食物；用另一个人赠予的旧衣物换来自己尺寸的旧衣物，或栖身之所，或一餐食物，或者他卖掉旧衣，用得来的钱随时购买自己需要的食物、衣服或住所。

人们通过协定、交换和买卖等方式彼此获得自己需要的绝大部分服务，正是这种相互交易的倾向最初引发了劳动分工。例如在以狩猎或游牧为生的部落，有人擅于打造弓弩，其技艺之娴熟超过其他族人。他便经常用自己制作的弓弩和族人交易，换得家禽和兽肉。并且他后来发现，通过交换得来的家禽和兽肉要比自己亲自去狩猎得到的更多。因此，出于个人利益考虑，弓弩制作逐渐成为他的主要营生，由此他就成了最初意义上的弓弩制作师。另有人擅于制作棚屋或活动房的屋架和屋顶，他们已习惯用自己的这门手艺，给族人制作屋架和屋顶来交换家禽和兽肉，直到后来他发现全力以赴于这门手艺符合自身的利益，因此他也就成为了最初的木匠。就这样，有人以同样的方式成为铁匠或铜匠，还有人成为毛皮或皮革（原始人类主要的衣料）硝皮人或鞣革人。因此，当人们确定能够用自己的劳动产品中自己消费不掉的所有剩余部分去交换自己需要的他人劳动产品的剩余部分时，便得到了鼓励，开始从事各自擅长的某一专门职业，并不断改进和完善自己从事这些专门职业的资质或才能。

事实上，不同的人在天赋才能上的差异比我们想象的要小得多，而且，促使人们最终从事不同职业的天赋差异，在其发展成熟之时，多半并非劳动分工的原因，而是分工的结果。两个特性全然不同的人，比如一个哲学家和一个普通的街头搬运工，与其说是天分有差异，倒不如说是后天的习惯、风俗和教育起到了很大的作用。在他们刚来到这个世界的前六年或者八年，两者几乎没有什么不同，无论是各自的父母还是玩伴都察觉不到两者之间有任何明显差异。也就在那个年纪，或者紧接着的几年里，他们开始了截然不同的活动。此后他们才能的差异才得以凸显并逐渐扩大，直到最后，哲学家的虚荣心使他不愿承认自己与搬运工之间存在任何相同之处。但是如果没有物物交换、以物易物和互相交易的倾向，每一个人都必须自己设法获得需要的生活必要品和便利品。所有的人都必须行使同样的职责，干同样的工作，那么，就没有什么职业上的差别，产生巨大才能差异的唯一根源也就不复存在了。

交换的倾向造就了才能的不同——不同职业者在才能上的差异极其显著——也正是这种倾向使得这种差异能够为人所用。要知道许多被认为属于同一族的动物在自然界中生存所产生的天资差异，要远远大于人类在未受习俗熏陶和教育影响时的天赋差异。就其本性而言，一个哲学家与一个街头搬运工在天资和性情上的差异，一点也不会比大獒犬与灰毛犬，或者灰毛犬与长毛犬，或者长毛犬与牧羊犬之间的差别更大。不过那些不同种类的动物，尽管都属于同一族，却很少能够对彼此有用。大獒犬以力大取胜，绝不会从灰毛犬的敏捷、长毛犬的聪明或牧羊犬的温顺中得到帮助和激励。动物的这些天资与才能的差异，因为缺少易物或交换的能力和倾向，无法在同一个平台上发挥作用，因而也就无法改进生存条件，增加生存实利。动物依然必须依靠个体的力量单枪匹马地存活和防卫，丝毫没有受益于自然界赋予它们的个体差异。而人类则相反，即使是天分差别最大的人也会对彼此有用，可以说，人类利用各自才能生产的不同产品，通过交易、易物和交换这种普遍倾向，呈现在同一个平台上。每个人在这里，可以根据自己的需要购买到他人凭借聪明才智生产的任何产品。

商业体系的原理

通常认为，政治经济学是经济学的一个分支，是政治家或立法者的经济学，它提出了两个明确的目标：其一，为该国征缴足量的税收或维持国民生存的钱款，更确切地讲，国民要能够为该国缴纳足量的税收或维持自身生存的钱款。其二，要为整个国家或全体国民提供足够的收入，使公共服务得以维系。简单地说，政治经济学的目标就是国富民强。

谈到国民的富足，各国在不同时期所经历的迈向富强之路各不相同，由此产生了两种迥异的政治经济体系：其一为商业体系，其二则是农业体系。

……

一个普遍的概念是，财富的多少是用货币或金银这两种贵金属的数量来衡量的，这源于货币的双重职能——既是交易工具又是价值尺度。鉴于货币的第一重性质，我们无需借助其他商品便可随时以货币换得自己需要的物品。人们总是觉得挣钱是大事，只要有钱，想买什么都轻而易举。而鉴于货币的第二重性质，我们一般会根据交换所用的货币数量估量商品的价值。正因如此，我们称富人价值千金，穷人不名一文。我们说节俭吝啬或迫切渴望变富的人喜爱钱财，认为那些大大咧咧、出手大方或生活富足的人不那么贪恋钱财。富有即是钱多，简单来讲，财富和货币在一般人的语言中没有丝毫差别。

正如富人腰缠万贯，富足之国理应储备大量的货币；无论哪个国家，走向富强最便捷的途径莫过于积累大量金银。在发现美洲之后的一段时间里，西班牙人每登陆一个陌生的海岸，首先要做的，就是搜寻附近的金银，根据搜集得来的相关信息再判断该地是否值得定居，抑或该国是否值得征服。修道士普拉诺·卡尔比诺受法国教廷派遣前去拜见一代天骄成吉思汗的后人，他说，鞑靼人经常会问他法兰西王国是否牛羊遍野。鞑靼人的询问和西班牙人的实地调查有着同样的目的——了解该国富裕的程度，从而判断是否值得征服。和任何其他游牧国家的人民一样，鞑靼人通常说不清货币有何功用，取而代之成为交换媒介和价值尺度的是牛羊。因此，正如西班牙人认为金银的数量决定财富的多少，鞑靼人认为牛群的数量是衡量财富的决定因素。就这两种不同的观念而言，或许鞑靼人的想法更加接近事实。

洛克[1]先生曾评论过货币与其他动产的不同之处。他说，所有其他动产在本质上都容易消耗，因此其内含价值并不十分可靠。一个国家可能在某一年对某种动产的拥有量十分充足，但即使没有任何出口，这种动产也很有可能仅仅因为国人的浪费或消耗而在下一年成为紧缺物品。与之相反，货币则十分稳定。在流通过程中，货币可能流经多方，但只要不流失到国外，它便不大可能被浪费或消耗。因此，按照洛克先生的说法，一个国家可流通的财富中最为可靠和真实的莫过于金银，根据这一点，增加国家对这两种金属的储备在他看来便是一国政治经济学的重要目标。

也有人认为，如果一个国家可以独立于全世界，那么该国国内流通的货币有多少也就无关紧要了。使用该货币进行流通只不过是用一种消费品换得数量或多或少的另一种消费品，在这种说法的提出者看来，这个国家是真正富有还是贫穷全然取决于可消费物品的多寡。但是另一方面，他们认为，如果一国要与他国建立联系、被迫与他国作战，或者必须维持远在他乡的军舰和军队开销，情况就完全不同了。这时只能向国外大量运送货币，而前提就是该国国内拥有足量的货币储备。因此，所有这类国家都应该在和平年代努力积累黄金白银，只有这样才能在战争爆发时拥有强大的财力后盾。

由于深受这些通俗观念的影响，欧洲各国都曾仔细研究如何在本国最大数量地储备金银，尽管这类研究几乎没有什么实际的收获。欧洲绝大部分金银矿藏位于西班牙和葡萄牙，向全欧洲输送金银的也主要是这两个国家。但两国要么明令禁止金银输出，严惩违者，要么课以高额关税。欧洲其他各国自古以来也都将类似禁令视为国策的一部分，甚至最出乎我们意料的，是古代苏格兰的某些议会法案也明令禁止携带黄金白银出境，违者重罚。古时英法两国也都颁发过类似的法令。

然而，那些国家一旦成为商业国，此禁令就会在许多情况下给商人带来不便。无论是买进别国商品还是将本国商品出口到其他国家，金银在交易中都要比其他商品占据更大的优势。于是商人以不利于本国贸易为由，抵制这项禁令。

首先，他们声称以购买外国商品为目的输出金银不一定会减少本国的金银储量，恰恰相反，此举倒有可能增加金银储量。因为如果本国进口了商品，销量却没有增加，则可以通过将其转售给其他国家获得更多利润，由此所得的金银收益或许要远远高于起初购买这些进口商品的支出。托马斯·孟[2]先生将国际贸易的这一运作方式比作农业中的播种和收割。他说：“如果我们只看到播种时农夫大把大把地将好玉米扔到地里，我们会认为他是个疯子。但是考虑到在他一年忙碌结束后的丰收，我们就会发现他当初的劳作不但值回成本，还能够产生更多的价值。”

商人们抵制该禁令的理由之二，是该禁令根本无法限制金银的输出，与其代表的巨大价值相比，金银的体积并不大，偷运到他国实为易事。用这些商人的话说，要想防止偷运走私成风，唯一的做法是适度地关注商人们所谓的“贸易差额”。如果一国的出口额大于进口额，则其他国家需要向其支付一部分贸易差额，这部分差额必然以金银的形式支付，因而该国的金银储量就会相应增加。而当该国贸易进口大于出口时，它就需要向其他国家支付贸易差额，因为同样需用金银支付，该国的金银储备就会相应减少。在这种情况下，禁止金银输出不仅不能达到预期效果，反而会因运输风险的增加而导致金银的价格高涨。商人们还认为，这样一来，整个贸易对于那些应支付贸易差额的国家更加不利。商人在他国交易需要从发行货币的银行那里购买汇票，不但要承担往那里运送货币本身的风险、麻烦和费用，还要承担该禁令带来的额外风险。而贸易越是对一国不利，这部分贸易差额对于应收取该差额的国家而言价值就越小。以英国和荷兰两国的贸易为例，如果英国的进口比出口多了5%，就需要用英国的105盎司白银在荷兰购买相当于100盎司白银的汇票：因而英国的这105盎司白银在荷兰将贬值到100盎司，只能购买价值100盎司的荷兰商品；而荷兰的100盎司白银在英国却升值到105盎司，且能购买价值105盎司的英国商品。英国商品在荷兰出售的价格相对便宜，荷兰商品在英国出售的价格相对昂贵，二者与正常价格的差距正是两国的贸易差额。相应的，英国货物所换回的荷兰货币量相对减少，荷兰货物所换回的英国货币相对增多，其减少和增多的幅度也相当于两国的贸易差额。因此，这种贸易差额必然会对英国造成相应程度的不利，必须将更多的金银运往荷兰，以弥补差额。

以上争论在某种程度上不无道理，在某种程度上也多少有些强词夺理。说其不无道理，是因为他们断言贸易中金银的输出往往对国家裨益颇多。同时也是因为，当国民发现输出金银能为他们带来好处时，任何禁令都将是一纸空文。谓之强词夺理是因为他们认为，保有或增加金银的数量，相对于保有或增加任何其他有用商品的数量而言，更需要政府关注。因为自由贸易完全能够确保其他商品的适量供应无需政府过多的关心。谓之强词夺理还在于他们断言，汇兑的高额差异必然会扩大所谓的贸易逆差，造成更多的金银流出。汇兑差额对用本国货币在他国支付的商人来说实为不利，商人们为购买本国银行在那些国家发行的汇票所支付的价格更高，高出的部分正是兑换差额。但是尽管禁令引发的风险可能会使银行收取额外费用，却未必会输出更多的货币。一般而言，这笔费用是走私货币时在国内支付的，除了所汇出的实际金额外，不会多输出一文钱。高汇率差也自然会使商人努力平衡其出口和进口，以便尽可能缩小支付额。此外汇兑的高额差异必定会起到类似课税的作用，因为它提高了进口商品的价格，减少了这些商品的消费。因此，汇兑差不但不会增加这些商人所谓的贸易逆差，反而会使之缩小，并最终减少了金银的输出。

尽管如此，此番言论却使听者深信不疑。深谙商道的商人提出这些言论说服国家议会、亲王参事和贵族乡绅，暗喜后者对此一无所知。和商人们一样，乡绅贵族仅凭经验即可得知对外贸易可以富国，却对其如何富国的具体原理所知甚少。商人非常清楚对外贸易让他们自身致富的原理，这是他们的本分，至于如何富国却并非其分内之事。除了他们要求国家对有关外贸的法律进行一些调整，如何富国从来不在他们的考虑范围之内。只有在那时，他们才有必要谈及外贸的裨益，以及现行法律如何对这些裨益构成了障碍。在就此事作出决策的法官们听来这可真是再恰当不过的陈述：如外贸如何能够源源不断地为本国带来收入，而当前讨论的法律形成了障碍。如果没有该法律，对外贸易带来的收入将会更高，等等。论证最终达到了预期效果。在法国和英国，本国的金银严禁输出，仅允许本国铸币流出。他国铸币和金条银块则可以自由出口。在荷兰和其他的一些地方，甚至本国的铸币也可以自由输出。政府关注的焦点不再是防范金银输出，而是转而关注贸易差额，以此作为可能引发国内金银增加或减少的唯一原因。对于前者的关注本是徒劳，而新的关注焦点看似更为错综复杂，却同样无济于事。《英国得自对外贸易的财富》，托马斯·孟先生这部著作的标题不仅成为英国政治经济学遵循的基本准则，也适用于任何其他商业国家。最重要的是，内陆贸易或国内贸易——在这种贸易中，同样数量的资本可以产生最大的收入，同时也为本国人民创造了最多的就业机会——却沦为国际贸易的附属品。人们认为，国内贸易既不能把货币带入国内，也不能把货币带到国外，国家也不可能因为国内贸易而变得更加富强或贫穷，除非国内贸易的兴旺与否会间接影响到国际贸易的形势。

好比没有葡萄园的人若要饮酒就只能与人交易，没有金银矿藏的国家无疑只能和他国交易获得金银。然而，对于国内和国际贸易，政府也似乎没有必要偏重两者之中的任何一种。一个人只要有购买葡萄酒的钱就能够随时买到葡萄酒，一个国家只要有购买金银的货币也就永远不会金银匮乏。金银和其他商品一样，也有自己的价格；既然金银可以用来购买任何商品，任何商品也都可以用来购买金银。我们可以确信，即使没有政府的关注，贸易的自由总能在我们急需好酒时及时供应好酒；同样我们也要深信，贸易的自由总能为我们提供用于商品流通或其他用途中用于购买或使用的全部金银。

在任何国家，人类劳动所能购买或生产的每一种商品的数量，都可以根据实际需求自我调节，这种需求也可以理解为那些愿意支付生产和出售该商品所需支付的全部地租、劳动力和利润的人的需求。但是没有哪一种商品能像金银这样根据实际需求轻松作出准确的自我调节，这是因为金银这两种贵金属有限的体积代表着巨大的价值，比其他任何商品都更容易地周转于异地之间——从价格较低的地方周转至价格较高的地方，从金银供给充盈的地方周转至金银不足的地方。例如，如果英国需要一批额外数量的黄金，一艘邮船即可从里斯本或任何供应黄金的地方运来50吨黄金，可铸成500多万几尼[3]。但是如果需要同样价值的谷物，按1吨谷物价值5几尼计算，总共需要运送100万吨，假设每艘邮船的承载量为1000吨，则需要1000艘邮船。如此这般，英国海军全部用来运输都是不够的。

当一国进口金银的数量超出实际需求时，无论政府如何警惕小心，金银的出口都无法避免。西班牙和葡萄牙所有严苛残暴的法律都未能保住其国内的金银储量。西葡两国陆续从秘鲁和巴西进口的金银超出了两国的实际需求，导致两国金银价格低于周边国家。相反，如果任何国家的金银储量不能满足实际需求，从而使其价格高于邻国，政府就无需费心进口金银。即使政府想要费心去禁止进口金银，亦绝不会奏效。当斯巴达人有足够的能力购买金银时，无论莱克格斯[4]制定怎样的法典限制人们都无济于事，自有大量黄金白银源源不断地流入拉塞德蒙[5]。再严苛的关税法都挡不住从荷兰和戈登堡东印度公司进口茶叶，因为这些公司的茶叶比英国公司的便宜。不过另一方面，1磅茶叶的市价通常以白银计算，即使按最高价格，即16先令，这1磅茶叶的体积也相当于这16先令白银体积的100倍；如果用黄金，则相当于等价值的黄金体积的2000倍。走私茶叶的难度相对于走私金银，自然也须按此比例增加。

在某种程度上，正是由于金银比较容易从充足的市场转运到短缺的市场，这两种贵金属的价格不像其他大部分商品的价格那样不断上下波动，许多商品因为体积太大，很难在市场存货过多或过少时作出灵活反应。固然，金银的价格也并非完全稳定，但其可能发生的变动一般来说都是缓慢、渐进、统一的。举例来说，欧洲有些人认为——或许这样想并没有太多根据——在本世纪和上世纪，由于人们不断从西属西印度群岛进口金银，这两种贵金属不断贬值，尽管贬值的过程是渐进的。然而要想使金银的价格发生突然变化，从而使得所有其他商品的货币价格立即发生巨大的涨落，则需要像发现美洲所带来的那样的商业革命。

尽管如此，一个有财力购买金银的国家如果在什么时候短缺金银，补足这两种贵金属的供应几乎要比补足其他任何商品都更加方便。如果制造业的原料不足，工业必陷于停顿；如果食物供给不足，人们就要为饥饿所苦；但如果货币不足，就可以代之以物物交换，只不过可能会有诸多不便。另一种方法是赊账买卖，交易各方每月或每年结算一次，互相补偿赊欠，这种方法就比物物交换方便一些。如果能够利用某种调控得当的纸币，则不但没有任何不便，在某些情况下还能带来一些裨益。所以无论从哪个方面来说，任何国家的政府都绝对没有必要花费心思去关注货币数量的保有或增加问题。

然而，“货币稀缺”始终是我们最常听到的抱怨。货币和葡萄酒一样，对那些既无财力购买又没有信用赊购的人，永远是紧缺之物，而只要拥有财力或信用这二者之一，就很少会在需要的时候感到匮乏。不过对货币稀缺的抱怨并不仅限于没有远虑的挥霍之人，有时整个商业城市及附近地区会普遍感到货币短缺，过度贸易是造成这一现象的常见原因。即使足够稳重冷静的人，如果不按照当前的资金情况制定营运计划，也可能会像入不敷出的挥霍之人一样，既没有购买货币的资力，也缺乏借贷的信用，在计划完成之前，他们的财力就已经耗光，信用也跟着没有了。这时他们只好四处借贷，而人人都会说没钱借给他们。即使我们到处听到人们说货币短缺，也并不一定就证明国内流动的金银数量比通常减少了，而只能表明许多人想要得到金银却无力支付罢了。贸易利润偶然高于通常情况时，无论大小商人都会犯过度贸易的通病。此时他们输往国外的货币不一定比平常多，而是在国内外赊账购买数量庞大的商品，并将其运往遥远的市场，期望在付款期限之内收到货款。一旦不能在付款期限之内收到货款，他们将没有财力购买货币，也没有可靠的借贷担保。如此看来，对货币稀缺的普遍抱怨，根本不是由于金银的稀缺，而是在于债务人难于借贷，债权人又难于收回借款所致。

如果我们在此一针见血地论证财富并不在于货币或金银的多少，而取决于可以用手中的金钱购买多少商品——也就是说，金钱只有在购买时才有价值，未免过于简单。货币无疑是国家资本的一个组成部分，但我们已经证明，它只是国家资本的一小部分，甚至始终是最无利可图的那一小部分。

商人之所以觉得用货币购买商品要比用商品购买货币更加容易，不是因为货币相对于商品而言是财富更为重要的组成部分，而是因为众所周知，货币是已知并确立的交易工具，方便与一切货物交换，而用货币交换货物却未必那么容易。此外，大多数商品要比货币更容易损坏，因此保存这些商品可能经常需要承担更大的损失。当商人有商品在手上时，他更有可能需要钱进行周转，毕竟什么都不如把已经获得的回报锁在自己的保险箱里来得安全，而最重要的是，卖比买利润来得更直接。因为所有这些原因，商人一般总是更急于出售商品换得货币，而不是用货币来交换商品。不过尽管一个商人在仓库中存有大量存货时，会因为无法及时出售这些存货而最终破产，但是一个国家却不大可能有这样的遭遇。商人的全部资本中有易破损的商品和预计用于换取货币的商品，而国家的土地和劳动产品的年产量却只有很少一部分用于和邻国交换获取金银，绝大部分都是在国内流通和消费的；即使在运往国外的剩余产品中，绝大多数通常也是用于交换和购买外国的其他商品。因此，国家即使不能用预计购买金银的商品换得足够的金银，也不至于濒临破产。诚然，国家的确会面临一些损失和不便，且可能不得不采取一些必要的权宜之计来替代货币供应，然而其土地和劳动产品的年产量与往常相比没有变化，或者几乎没有变化，因为可以花费同样多或几乎同样多的消费资本来维系这一产量。尽管用商品交换货币没有用货币交换商品那样容易，但从长远来看，前者却比后者更加必要。商品除了用于交换货币之外还有许多其他用途，而货币除用于购买商品外别无他用。因此，货币必然要追求商品，而商品却并不一定要追求货币或者根本没有这个必要，购买的人并不一定要转手出售，而常常是为了使用或消费，而出售的人却永远都是为了换取货币再次买入。前者在买入之后往往就完成了整个过程，而后者在卖出货物之后，最多只完成了整个过程的一半。人们渴望货币并不是为了它本身，而是为了可以用货币买来的一切。

有人说可消费品很快会被损坏，而金银的耐久性更强一些，因此如果不是要持续出口，金银可以积累很长时间，这样一来，国家的真正财富就会有极大的增加。所以，一般人就会认为，对一个国家最不利的，就是其主要贸易行为是用耐久性较强的商品去换取比较容易损毁的商品。然而，我们不能想当然地认为，用英国的五金器具去换取法国的葡萄酒就是对英国贸易不利；尽管五金器具是耐久性很强的商品，若没有持续出口，而是在国内积累很长时间，到时整个英国的铁锅就会多得惊人了。不过一般来说，无论在哪个国家，这类五金器具的数量必然受到其需求的限制；如果一个国家所拥有的铁锅数量大于其烹制食物所需，未免有点超乎情理了；如果食物的总量增加了，则铁锅的数量也很容易随之增加，只要用一部分增加的食物量购买铁锅，或者换取更多生产铁锅的劳动力就行了。同样我们也很容易理解，任何国家的金银数量也应受其需要所限；这些贵金属的用途包括铸成硬币当作流通的货物，以及制成器皿当作家具；每个国家的铸币数量应受到国内流动的商品价值的调节，一旦该价值增加，就立即会有一部分被输往国外有金银铸币的国家，换得国内流通所需的更多铸币：而金银器皿的数量则要受到国内喜好奢华的家庭数目和财富的支配，这类家庭的财富增加了，其中一部分很有可能要用于向有剩余金银器皿的国家购买。任何国家，为了增加财富从国外输入或在国内保留超过需求量的金银都是荒谬的，就像家庭也不能依靠购入不必要的厨具来增添愉悦，这是因为出资购买不必要的厨具不但不会增添愉悦，反而会减少家庭必需品的数量和质量；同样，任何国家出资购买不必要的金银，也必定会减少维持国民衣食住行所需的财富。切要牢记：金银，无论其形状是铸币还是盘盏，无非只是用具而已，在这一点上，它们和厨房用具没有区别。如果增加金银的用途，增加靠金银来流通、支配和制造的消费品，自然可以增加金银的数量；但是如果希望通过非常方法增加金银数量，必将减少金银的用途，甚至会减少金银的数量，因为这两种贵金属的数量必然会受到其用途的限制。一旦金银的积累超出了需求，就很容易被转运，而由于闲置会造成极大损失，任何法律也无法阻止它们被立即输往境外。

一个国家要进行对外战争，维持远在海外的海军和陆军所需，并不一定要积累金银。维持海军和陆军依靠的不是金银，而是可消费商品。因此，只要一国的国内工业年产量，即土地、劳动和消费品存量所产生的年收入使它有能力在远离边境的国外购买足够的消费品，它就能够维持那里的战争。

一个国家可以通过三种不同的方式向远在国外的军队运送粮饷和物资：一是若干其所积累的不同的金银；二是若干其制造业年产物；三是若干其农产品年产物。

我们可以合理地认为，任何国家积累或存储的金银都可以分成三部分：一是用于流通的货币；二是家用的金银器皿；最后则是经过多年节俭积累，存在国库中的货币。

国内用于流通的货币很少能够节省下来，因为这方面不可能有太多的盈余。在任何国家，一年之内买卖的商品的价值需要一定数量的货币进行流通并将其分配给不同的消费者，因此货币的使用不能过量。流通渠道必定会吸引来充足的货币量，但不能容纳更多的货币。然而在国家进行对外战争时，一般会从该渠道抽取一定数量的货币。由于大量人口远在境外，在国内维持生计的人口数量相对减少；在国内流通的商品数量减少了，也就不需要那么多货币流通了。这时国家通常会大量发行各种纸币，诸如英国的财政部证券、海军债券和银行票据，以此替代流通的金银，以便将更大数量的金银输往境外。不过，对外战争花费浩大，且旷日持久，以上这些财政来源是远不够维持的。

无论在何种情况下，熔化私家金银器皿都于事无补，法国在上一次战争开始使用过这种办法，不过收获并不大，还不够补偿铸造带来的损失，结果得不偿失。

过去，王室积累的财宝曾提供更多且持续更久的资源；而在今时，除了普鲁士国王之外，积累财宝似乎不再是欧洲王室的政策了。

本世纪各国用于维持对外战争的资金——或许已经创造了人类有史以来战争花费的最高记录——几乎已经很少再依赖流通货币或输出家用金银器皿，抑或国库积累的财物了。在上一次对法战争中，英国的花费超过了9000万英镑，其中不仅包括7500万英镑新募的国债，还包括为每英镑土地税征收的两个先令的附加税，以及每年从还债基金中借用的款项。这笔巨额费用中有2/3花费在遥远的境外：德国、葡萄牙、美国、地中海各港口、东印度和西印度群岛。英国的各任国王没有积累财宝，我们未曾听说有超量金银器皿被熔化铸币这样的事情，当时人们认为，国内流通的金银不会超过1800万英镑，然而自最后一次金币改革以来，人们开始觉得他们低估了国内的金银流通量。所以，姑且根据我亲眼所见抑或听说过的最夸大的算法，假设当时国内流通的金银共值3000万英镑，假如战争全部用的是英国自己的货币，那么即使根据这样夸张的算法，在六七年的时间内，英国的全部货币必然会全部运出并运回至少两次。如果这种假设成立的话，那么它所能证明的最具决定性意义的观点就是，政府根本没有必要监管货币的保存，因为根据这个假定，国内的所有货币必然要在这么短的时间内在国境内外往返两回，且整个过程无人察觉，可见对任何人都没有什么影响。然而事实是，在这段时期内，流通渠道似乎根本没有显得比平时更空虚，那些有财力换取货币的人几乎没有感到货币匮乏。在整个战争期间，尤其是在战争将要结束时，对外贸易的利润比以往更大了，这种情况必然导致了全英国各个地区普遍的过度贸易；而过度扩张营运的结果，和惯常一样，是人们又开始抱怨货币短缺。许多需要货币的人既没有办法购买货币又没有信用借贷；而一旦借贷者感觉到很难借贷，对于放贷者来说，收回欠款也变得困难了。不过拥有能换取金银价值的人，基本上都能够按金银的价值换取金银。

所以，用来支付上一场战争巨额支出的，一定不是国内输出的金银，而是英国出口的这样那样的商品。当政府或代表政府行事的人士与某一个商人签约汇款到国外时，该商人会向与其来往的国外联系人寄送一张期票，而他也一定会尽力以商品而不是金银来支付该期票。如果英国的商品不是该国所需，他将设法将其运往其他国家，购买一张期票，来支付所欠国家的款项。只要是市场所需，商品的运输总是能够产生可观的利润，而金银的运输就很难产生什么利润了。为了购买国外商品而将金银运往国外，商人获取的利润并非来自购买商品，而是来自销售运回国后的商品；但是如果仅仅为了支付债务而将其运往国外，就不会有任何商品运回，商人自然也就得不到任何利润，因此，他会绞尽脑汁，用出口商品而非出口金银的办法偿还国外债务。于是《英国现状》一书的作者指出，在上一次战争期间，英国出口了大量商品，却没有任何商品运回国内。

除了上述三种金银之外，所有商业大国中还有大量金条银块交替地输入输出，为对外贸易提供方便。这些金条银块在不同商业国家之间的流通与每一个国家内部的硬币流通方式一样，因而可以被看作是一个由不同国家组成的大商业共和国的货币。国内硬币的流通及其方向受到每个国家境内流通商品的支配，该商业共和国的货币则要受到不同国家之间流通商品的支配。无论在单独一个国家还是这个大型商业共和国，使用货币都是为了促进交换，前者是一个国家内部不同个人之间的交换，后者是不同国家之间的交换。该大型商业共和国的一部分货币可能已经用于上一次战争的支出了。在全面发生战争时期，人们自然会认为，货币的流通及其流通方向因为受到战争的影响而与和平时期不同；认为在战事发生地点附近的流通量应该更大，交战国军队所需的饷给和物资都需要在那里及邻近国家购买。但是就这一大商业共和国的货币来说，无论英国每年需要以这种方式使用多少，它每年都必须用英国商品或其他可用于交换该货币的东西购得；所以归根结底，进行战争所需要的资源仍然是商品，是国内每年的土地和劳动产品。的确，人们很容易联想到，这样巨大的年支出一定需要极大的年产量才能够支付。例如，1761年的支出高达1900多万，任何金银的积累都无法支持每年这样巨大的费用，即便是金银本身，年产量也达不到这样的程度。根据最可靠的统计，每年输往西班牙和葡萄牙的金银总量一般不超过600万英镑，在上一次战争的某些年份，这个数目都不够支付四个月的费用。

最适合运往遥远的境外，在当地购买军队所需的粮饷和物资，或用于购买大商业共和国的一部分货币，进而购买这些粮饷和物资的商品，似乎应该是制造得更加精巧的工业品，如体积小价值高，能以最小的费用输出到千里之外的制造品。因此，如果一个国家每年生产的此类工业品有大量剩余，并将其出口到国外，它就能够将非常昂贵的对外战争持续多年，此时它不需要输出任何可观数量的金银，甚至也没有这样大量的金银可以输出。诚然，每年剩余的制造品中有很大一部分必须在这种情况下输出，而它虽给商人带回利润，却不会给国家带来任何回报，因为政府向商人购买外国期票，以便在外国购买军队所需的饷给和物资。不过，总有一部分剩余制造品的输出是可以产生利润的。在战争期间，国家对制造业有双重需求：首先，国家需要生产足够的商品运往境外，支付其为供应军队饷给和物资而向国外购买的期票；其二，国内通常所需的普通外国商品，也必须由国内生产足够的商品来购买。如此说来，在最具破坏性的对外战争期间，大部分制造业可能会大大繁荣，相反，在和平时期其利润可能会下降。制造业可能在国家走向毁灭的过程中繁荣一时，而一旦国家重新繁荣，制造业就可能衰败下去。英国制造业的许多不同部门在上一次战争期间，乃至战争结束后一段时间的不同景况，正是我们刚刚所得结论的一个例证。

对任何国家来说，出口土地原产品显然无法很好地支撑费用浩大而旷日持久的对外战争，将一部分土地原产品输往国外，用它来购买军队所需的饷给和物资，费用太过昂贵。很少有国家生产的原产品远远超过可以维持国民生计所需的量，因此，将大量此类原产品运往国外，无异于夺取国民生活所需的必要生活资料，而工业制造品的出口就是另一回事了。制造业工人的生活资料仍然保留在国内，所输出的仅仅是他们劳动所产生的剩余部分。休谟先生屡次提到，古代英国的国王们无法不间断地为任何旷日持久的对外战争提供资助。那个年代的英国人没有能力在外国购买其军队所需的饷给和物资，农业原产品没有办法从国内消费中大量节省下来，少量最粗糙的制造品又和农产品一样，运输费用过于昂贵。这种情况并非源于货币短缺，而是因为那时缺乏更加精细的工业制造品。那时的英国和现在一样，买卖都是通过货币进行交易的，当时的货币流通量与买卖的数量和价值之间的比例必然与现在相同，或者比现在更大，因为那时没有纸币，而现在纸币已经在很大程度上替代了金银。在那些对商业和制造业所知甚少的国家，一旦遇到非常事件，君主很少能够从国民那里获得大的帮助，具体原因我将在下文中说明。因此，正是在这类国家，君主通常会竭力积聚财富，因为那是应对紧急事件的唯一资金来源，即使没有这种必要，在当时那种条件下，君主也会自然地倾向于为累积财富而躬行节俭。在那样一种简朴的状态下，即便君主的花费也不受喜好宫廷豪华生活的虚荣心支配，而是用于赏赐佃户、款待家臣；虽然虚荣心几乎总是导致浪费，但赏赐和款待却很少如此。因此，每一个鞑靼酋长都有财宝。据说，查理十二世著名的同盟——乌克兰哥萨克酋长马捷帕就拥有大量财宝，梅罗文加王朝的法兰西国王也个个都有财宝，如果他们将王国分封给不同的子嗣，也会分给他们相应的财宝。撒克逊君王以及征服之后的最初几个国王，似乎也一样聚集过财宝。每一个新王朝所做的第一件事，通常都是夺取前一个国王的财宝，那是保有王位最有效的手段。先进的商业国家君主却不再有必要积累财宝，因为他们一般都可以在非常时期从臣民那里获得很大帮助，也不再倾向于这样做。他们自然地、或许也是必然地追随所处时代的流行趋势，在花费方面，君主和领土内所有其他大业主一样，受到追求奢华的虚荣心的支配。宫廷中精致到极细微处的华丽奢靡与日倶增，其巨额花费不仅让财富的积累不再可行，甚至往往会侵及原本用于更为必要之用途的资金。德西利达斯对波斯宫廷的评价或许同样适合好几个欧洲君主的宫廷，他说他在那里感受到的更多是奢华而不是力量，看到的更多是奴仆而不是战士。

金银的输入绝不是国家从对外贸易中获取的主要利益，更不是对外贸易的唯一利益。无论对外贸易在哪两个地区间进行，国家都可以从中获得两种不同的利益：一是，它将其土地和劳动力所生产产品的剩余部分，即国内不再需要的部分输出，作为交换，带回国内需要的其他东西。对外贸易使得剩余产品获得了价值，可以用来换取其他东西，从而满足国内的一部分需求，增加享受。二是，有了对外贸易，国内市场的有限性就难以阻碍任何工艺或制造业部门的劳动分工趋于完善的发展。这样就为劳动产品中超出国内消费的那一部分拓展了新的市场，从而鼓励劳动者提高生产力，最大限度地增加年产量，也进而增加了全社会的实际收入和财富。对于彼此间进行对外贸易的所有不同国家，对外贸易都在持续不断地起到极其显著而重要的作用。所有国家都从对外贸易中大大受益，不过商人所在的国家获得的利益最大，因为一般来说，商人总是更加关注供应他人之所需，并将他所在国家的剩余产品运出境外。将金银输入那些因为没有矿藏而缺乏这些贵金属的国家无疑是对外贸易业务的一个组成部分，但它只是最微不足道的一部分。如果一个国家只因为这样一个原因而开展对外贸易，恐怕一个世纪内也很难有机会装满一船金银。

美洲的发现之所以让欧洲走向富裕，也并非源于金银的进口。因为美洲富藏金银矿，这两种贵金属的价格反而降低了，与15世纪相比，如今购买金银器皿所需的谷物或者劳动，大概只有那时的1/3，也就是说，以同样的劳动和商品支出，欧洲每年可以购买的金银器皿的数量是那时的3倍。但是如果某一商品的售价仅相当于通常售价的1/3，那么，不但原先的买主现在购买的数量可以达到先前的3倍，而且由于价格下降，可以出价购买的买主数量也较先前多出许多，或许买主数量增加至先前的10倍多，甚至高达20倍以上。因此，欧洲现有的金银器皿数量，不仅要比美洲金银矿没有发现之时——即使在其现有的进步状态下——多出3倍，或许更是前者的20至30多倍，直到目前为止，欧洲无疑得到了真正的便利，尽管那的确只是非常微不足道的便利。金银价格的下降导致这两种金属不如先前那样适合用作货币了：为了进行同样的购买活动，我们必须携带更大量的金银，对于以往4便士就能购得的物品，如今得在口袋里装1个先令。要说这种不便可以忽略不计，上述与之相对的便利怕也不比它重要多少，两者都不会对欧洲目前的状况造成任何重大的影响。然而，美洲的发现的确对欧洲产生了极为重大的影响。它为欧洲所有商品开辟了一个全新而永不枯竭的市场，它为新的劳动分工和工艺改进创造了机会，而在古代商业的狭窄范围内，由于大部分产品缺乏市场，这是绝对不可能发生的。劳动者的生产力提高了，欧洲所有国家的劳动产品增加了，各国国民的真实收入和财富也就随之增加了。欧洲的商品对于美洲来说几乎是前所未有的，同样，美洲的许多商品对于欧洲来说也是新鲜事物。因此，一系列之前从未有人预见过的交换开始了。事实证明，这既然一定会对旧大陆有利，也自然会对新大陆同样有利。当然，欧洲人颇为野蛮的不公行径使得一桩本来对所有方都有利的事件，变成了几个不幸国家的灭顶之灾。

大约同时，欧洲人发现了经由好望角前往东印度的道路，尽管其距离比美洲更加遥远，却或许为欧洲人打开了比美洲更为广阔的对外贸易市场。整个美洲只有两个国家在各个方面比蛮荒之地稍强一些，这两个国家在美洲发现不久就被消灭了，其他的都不过是蛮荒之地。而中国、印度、日本等帝国以及东印度的其他几个国家即使金银矿藏不如美洲富足，却在其他所有方面都要比墨西哥或秘鲁更加富裕，农业耕种水平更高，所有工艺和制造业也都更加先进。就算这样说无异于相信了西班牙作家们关于那些帝国往昔状况的夸大记载，我们也必须承认这些事实，而那些记载显然是不足置信的。不过，富裕文明的国家彼此之间进行交易，其价值要远远大于与未开化的野蛮人作交易。但是，截止到此时，欧洲与东印度各个帝国商业往来获得的利益却大大低于与美洲经商获得的利益。葡萄牙垄断东印度贸易约一个世纪之久，其他欧洲国家从东印度购入任何商品，或将任何商品输入该国，都只能间接通过葡萄牙人之手。上世纪初荷兰人开始侵入这片商业领地，将整个东印度公司的业务全部交由一家公司独家经营。英国人、法国人、瑞典人和丹麦人都纷纷效法，此时，没有一个欧洲大国能够享受到对东印度进行自由商业贸易的利益。仅此一个原因就能够解释，为什么对东印度的贸易根本没有对美洲贸易那样有利，美洲贸易，即几乎每一个欧洲国家与其殖民地之间的贸易，对其所有臣民都是自由开放的。而那些东印度公司的专营特权和巨大财富，以及从各自的政府那里获取的惠益和保护，招来了不少嫉妒。这种嫉妒心理往往使人们觉得其贸易是完全有害的，因为进行这种贸易的国家每年都输出大量白银。有关方面回答说，这种持续的白银输出的确有可能使整个欧洲陷于贫困，但从事贸易的具体国家却不受此影响。它们通过将一部分用白银购回的商品输出到欧洲的其他国家，实际获得的白银数量远比输出的多。反对者和辩驳者所持观点的依据都是我刚刚讨论过的普遍观点，因此我也没有必要就此多作论述。因为每年向东印度输出白银，欧洲的金银器皿价格很可能比以往更贵一些；而银币所能购买的劳动力和商品或许也比以往更多。在这两种影响中，前者不是什么大损失，后者也并非巨大收益，二者都微不足道，因而没有引发公众的广泛关注。与东印度的贸易为欧洲商品打开了一个新的市场，或者换一种说法，为那些商品所能购买的金银开辟了一个新市场，因而必然增加欧洲商品的年产量，从而增加欧洲的实际财富和收入总额。至于到目前为止所增加的数量甚少，则或许要归咎于那种贸易处处受到限制。

在这里，我觉得有必要详细考察一下这一通行概念，即关于财富的多少主要取决于金钱或者金银数量的大小，尽管这未免显得冗长繁琐。如我在上文所述，在一般人的概念中，金钱总是财富的象征，这种表达上的模棱两可使得此概念深入人心，以至于那些已经确信其荒谬无稽的人也常常会忘记自己的原则，在推理的过程中想当然将其作为一条确定无疑、不可否认的真理。英国商业界有几个数一数二的作家往往会在他们的文章开头论述道，一个国家的财富多少不仅在于所拥有的金银的数量，也在于拥有土地、房屋、可消费商品以及其他各种不同物品的数量。然而在推理过程中，他们似乎将土地、房屋和可消费商品统统抛到脑后，论证的核心往往变成了所有财富在于金银，增加这两种贵金属的数量乃是国家工商业最重要的目标。

但如果这两个原则都成立，即财富的多少取决于金银的数量，且缺乏这两种贵金属的国家只能通过贸易差额，或者说使出口大大超过进口来收入金银，那么政治经济学的目的必然变成了尽可能减少进口外国商品用于本国消费，并尽可能增加本土工业品的出口，因而国家致富的两大手段就变成了限制进口和鼓励出口。

对进口的限制包括两种。

首先，凡能够由本土生产的国内消费品，无论从什么国家进口，都一律加以限制。

其次，如果本国与某些国家的贸易差额对本国不利，则对那些国家几乎所有商品的进口加以限制。

限制的方式也各有不同，有时采用高关税，有时则采用绝对禁止的办法。

而鼓励出口的办法，有时是退税，有时是政府奖励，有时是与外国签订有利的通商条约，有时是在遥远的境外建立殖民地。

退税的情形一般有两种。对于已缴纳关税或国产税的国产商品，在出口时往往会返还全部或部分税款；而对于已征收进口税的外国商品，如果进口目的是为了加工后出口，有时会在出口时返还全部或部分进口税。

政府奖励要么是为了鼓励某些新兴制造业，要么是为了奖励政府认为应给予特殊照顾的某些工业。

通过建立有利的通商条约，本国的货物和商人可以在某一境外国家获得别国货物和商人所没有的特权。

而通过在遥远的境外建立殖民地，宗主国的货物和商人不仅可以获得特权，而且还可以获得垄断地位。

上述两种对进口的限制，连同四种鼓励出口的做法，乃是商业主义所倡导的六种主要手段，使各国扭转贸易逆差，情势对己有利，从而增加金银数量。我将在以下各章分别对其进行论述，关于这六种手段能够给国内带来金钱的说法，我就不再关注了，而重点考察它们各自可能对国内工业年产量产生何种影响。如果这些手段能够提高或降低国内工业年产量的话，也必然能够增加或降低国家的实际财富和收入。

对于商品进口实施的限制

通过征收高关税或绝对禁止的方式，限制可以由本国生产的商品从国外进口，在一定程度上保证了生产这些商品的国内工业对于国内市场的垄断。因此，禁止从国外进口活牲畜和腌制食品，确保了英国畜牧业者对国内肉类市场的垄断；对谷物进口课以高关税，也让英国的谷物种植者得到了相同的利益，因为在谷物丰收的年份里高额关税相当于禁止进口。禁止进口外国羊毛制品，同样对国内羊毛制品生产商有利；英国的丝绸制造商曾经完全依靠外国原材料，但最近它们也开始得到同样的好处；麻织品制造商尚未得到什么好处，不过他们正在大踏步地朝着这一方向迈进，很快就会得到。英国的许多其他产业制造商也以同样的方式获得了针对国人的全部或几乎全部垄断权。英国绝对禁止或在某种条件下禁止进口的商品，种类极其多，对于不十分熟悉关税法律的人来说，已经大大超出了他们的想象。

这种对国内市场的垄断总是能够给予享受垄断的行业很大的鼓励，因此往往能够使更大份额的劳动力和社会资源转向该行业，这是毋庸置疑的。但它是否能够增加整个社会的财富，或者使之朝着最有利的方向发展，或许就算不得什么不证自明的真理了。

社会全部产业的总和绝不会超过社会总资本所能维持的限度。正如任何个人所能雇用的工人数量必须与他所拥有的资本保持一定比例，整个社会所有成员持续雇用的工人数量也必须与该社会的资本总量保持一定比例，并绝不能超过该比例。任何商业调控都不可违反这一常识，增加社会产业的总量，使之超出其资本所能维持的限度。商业调控只能改变其中部分产业的导向，至于这种人为的方向调整是否就要比产业根据自身条件自然发展更为有利，则纯属不确定因素。

每个人都会持续不断地竭力为自己所支配的资本找到最合适的用途。诚然，这样做的时候，他考虑的是自己的利益而不是整个社会的利益，但他在仔细考察自己的利益之后，自然，或者说必然会倾向于选择那些最有利于社会的用途。

首先，只要资本获利的程度与一般水平持平，或者至少不太低于一般水平，所有个体都尽力在距离自己最近的地方使用自己的资本，这样的结果是，他会尽其所能支持国内产业。

因此，在利润相等或接近相等的情况下，每一个批发商自然宁愿经营消费品国内贸易也不愿经营对外贸易，宁愿经营消费品对外贸易也不愿意经营转口贸易。与对外贸易相比，经营国内贸易时，资本总是在他的可控范围之内。他能够更好地了解信托之人的品行和境况，万一不小心被骗，他也更熟悉国内的法律，知道如何从中获得补偿。在转口贸易中，商人的资本可以说是被分割在两个境外国家，而这两部分资本都不一定会回到国内，也就是回到他可以监管和支配的范围之内。譬如，一个阿姆斯特丹商人将俄国哥尼斯堡的玉米运往葡萄牙里斯本，将里斯本的水果和葡萄酒运往哥尼斯堡。一般来说，他必须有一半的资本投在哥尼斯堡，另一半投在里斯本，两部分资本似乎都没有必要回到阿姆斯特丹。这样一个商人自然应该住在哥尼斯堡或里斯本，只有在非常特殊的情况下，他才会选择居住在阿姆斯特丹。不过，因为距离自己的资本太远使商人深感不安，他一般都会从原定运往里斯本市场的哥尼斯堡货物和原定运往哥尼斯堡的里斯本货物中，分出一部分运往阿姆斯特丹。尽管这必然会带来装载和卸载的双重费用，还需要支付一些税金和关税，但为了让一部分资本始终处于自己的监控和管理之下，他愿意支付这部分额外费用。正因为如此，每个从事大量转口贸易的国家最后都会成为一个大型综合市场，那里交易着来自转口贸易相关各国的货物。为了避免二次装载和卸载，商人总是想方设法尽可能多地在本国市场上出售来自所有国家的货物，也就是尽其所能地将转口贸易转化为消费品的对外贸易。同样，从事消费品对外贸易的商人，在收集货物运往国外市场时，在利润相等或接近相等的情况下，也总是更愿意尽可能地将大部分货物放在国内出售。为了规避出口的风险和麻烦，他总是尽其所能地将消费品的对外贸易转化为国内贸易。于是，如果可以这样说的话：本国总是成为每个国家的居民不断流通其资本的中心，各国居民总是更愿意让资本流向国内，只是由于特殊原因资本才会远离该中心，在较远处付诸使用。不过事实不断证明，相对于消费品对外贸易中使用的同等数量的资本，国内贸易中使用的资本总是能够启动更多的国内产业，增加国内更多居民的收入和就业机会。而用于消费品对外贸易的资本，与用于转口贸易的等量资本相比，也有同样的效果。因此，在利润相等或接近相等的前提下，个人都自然会尽力正确使用资本，给予国内产业最大的支持，并使自己国家的绝大多数人在收入和就业方面获利。

其次，任何人只要利用自己的资本支持国内产业，就必然会竭尽全力，力求使该产业的产量达到最大值。

产业的产量是指它为产业主体或劳动中所使用的原材料增加的价值。随着产业产量价值的增加或减少，雇主所得的利润也会按比例增减。然而，任何人利用自己的资本支持产业都只是为了赚取利润；因此，他必然会竭尽全力利用自己的资本支持那些能够产生最大价值的产业，或者用它换取最大数量的货币或其他商品。

但是任何社会的年收入总是与其产业的年总产量的可交换价值绝对相等，也就是说，年收入与年总产量的可交换价值完全是同一回事。由此看来，既然所有个人都会尽可能地利用自己的资本支持国内产业，并竭尽全力使该产业产生最大价值，所有个人也必然会尽可能地利用劳动为社会创造最大收入。当然，他既不是在为公众谋福利，也全然不知自己为公众贡献了多少福利。他宁可支持国内产业也不愿支持对外贸易，因而我们说他只关心自己的安全。他全力引导产业，使其产量达到最大价值，我们说他只是为自己赚取利润，在种种情形下，他都是由一只看不见的手引导着，不由自主地去达到并非出于本意希望达到的目的。当然，并非出于本意而达到目的，对社会来说不一定就有害。在为自己谋福利的过程中，他往往能够比出于本意更有效地提升整个社会的福利。我没有听说过有哪些假装为公众谋福利的生意人真正为社会作出过什么大的贡献。当然，这种刻意作秀的做法在商人中并不常见，也用不着多费唇舌去劝阻他们。

至于应该将自己的资本用在国内哪些产业中，以及哪些产业有可能获得最大价值，显然，任何个体都能够根据其自身的具体条件作出判断，且比任何政治家或立法者所能提供的建议都更显合理。如果有哪一个政治家希望知道个人应该如何使用自己的资本，那不但是在自寻烦恼，而且是在攫取一种权力，社会在任何时候都不会放心地给予任何个人、任何形式的委员会或参议会这种权力。让一个虚伪荒唐、自以为能够担此大任的人拥有这种权力，是再危险不过的了。

让国内产业中任何特定的工艺或制造业产品垄断国内市场，在某种程度上无异于指导个体国民应该如何使用他们的资本，在几乎任何情况下，这都是一种毫无用处甚至颇为有害的调控。如果国内产品的价格能够像外国产品一样便宜，这样的调控显然没有用处；如果不能一样低廉，那么一般来说，这种调控必然是有害的。任何一个明智的一家之主，都应该坚持这样一个原则，即如果自行制作的成本高于从别处购买，就绝不选择前者。裁缝不会尝试自己做鞋，而是从鞋匠那里买鞋；同样，鞋匠也不会尝试自己做衣服，而是请裁缝帮着做；农夫既不做鞋也不做衣服，就花钱请手艺人来做。从以上种种例子可以看出，所有人都知道，将所有精力投注在自己比他人更有优势的领域，并用其部分产品去购买，或者换句话说，用其产品的部分价格去购买他们偶尔需要的东西，这种做法符合个人的最大利益。

如果某种行为对于一个家庭来讲是审慎明智的，那么对于一个大国来说，它也错不到哪里去。如果某一外国可以提供我们某一种商品，其价格要比我们自己生产更加便宜，那么更明智的做法显然是用我们自己的部分产品来购买，因为我们在生产后一种产品的产业中具有某种优势。国家的劳动总量既然一定和维持它所用的资本成正比，就不会因此而减少，正如上文提到的各类手工制造业者的劳动不会减少一样，人们只会因此而找到能够产生更大价值的使用资本的方法。因而我们说，使用资本来生产一种物品，生产的成本却高于购买的价格，则资本必然不能够产生最大价值。如果劳动力去生产那些显然不能产生更多价值的商品，则一定会或多或少地减损一个国家年产物的总价值。根据这一假设，从外国购买商品要比在本国制造更加便宜。这样，如果按照其自然发展方向的话，使用以同样的资本在本国产业中所生产商品的一部分，或者换句话说，用这些在本国产业中所生产商品价格的一部分，即可以购买到外国商品。所以，上述调控的结果是，将国家的劳动从较为有利的用途转为较为不利的用途，其年产量的可交换价值不但没能像立法者原先设想的那样有所增加，反而因为有了国内产业垄断而有所减少。

诚然，有了此类调控，某一特定的制造业可能要比没有调控时更快地确立起来，且经过一段时间之后，特定商品在国内的生产成本也将不再高于国外的生产成本。然而，尽管社会中某一产业可以因为获利而更加快速地进入某一特定轨道，但无论是劳动还是收入总额，都绝不会因为有了此类调控而增加。社会中劳动的增加必须与资本的增加成正比，而其资本的增加必须取决于社会收入中逐渐节省出来的那一部分。但是每一个此类调控的直接后果都是减少社会收入，而凡是减少收入的措施，自然不会迅速增加社会的资本，无论是社会的资本还是劳动，它们都只能在自然状态下才能够很快增加。

虽然某种特定的制造业因为缺少这样的调控无法在社会上确立起来，但社会在其发展的任何一段时间内并不会因这一原因变得贫穷。在其发展的每一个时期，社会的总资本和劳动的使用或许仍然是当时最有利的，只是在不同的时期，社会发展的目标不尽相同。在每一个特定时期，社会收入可能都是其资本所能支持的最大收入，资本和收入的增长速度也是该社会当时所能够达到的最大速度。

有时，一个国家在生产特定商品方面相对于其他国家的自然优势非常突出，全世界都承认无法与之竞争。诚然，通过嵌玻璃、设温床、建温壁，苏格兰也能栽种极好的葡萄，并用来生产上等的葡萄酒，只是与从其他国家购买的品质不逊的葡萄酒相比，其制作费用差不多是前者的30倍。如此说来，如果单单为了鼓励苏格兰制造波尔多和勃艮第葡萄酒而发布禁令，禁止进口一切外国葡萄酒，这种做法难道合理吗？如果人人都能看出，在需要特定数量的某种商品时，使用比从外国进口高出30倍的本国资本和劳动来生产的做法无比荒谬，那么即使所使用的资本和劳动只不过高出了1/30，甚或3%，也是一样的不合情理，只不过没有那么荒唐可笑就是了。一个国家在这方面的优势究竟是天然的还是后来拥有的，这无关紧要，只要它有那些优势，而另一个国家又缺乏优势，那么就后一个国家来说，从前者购买就要比自己生产更具优势。一个手工业制造者对于从事另一个行业的人而言，其优势只能是后天获得的。然而他们两人都会发现，从彼此那里购买要比制造不属于自己行业的产品更为有利。

商人和制造业者是这种国内市场垄断中最大的获利者。禁止从外国进口牲畜或腌制品，加之对外国谷物征收较高关税——在一般的丰年这就相当于禁止——为英国畜牧业者和农场主带来的利益，远远低于英国商人和制造业者因其他此类禁令所得的利益。制造业者，特别是较精细产品的制造业者，其产品在各国之间的运输要比谷物或牛羊更加容易。因此，对外贸易的主要业务是制造品贸易。在制造业，很小的利益就能够让外国人倾销自己工人的产品，即使在其国内市场上也是如此。而对于土地的原产品来说，这样做的成本就很高，需要有很大利益才有人肯做。如果允许外国制造品自由输入，就会有好些国内制造业者受到重创，甚至或许还有一些会倒闭，而这时，该制造业使用的很大一部分资本和劳动就不得不重新寻找新的用途。但是即使国家允许土地原产品完全自由输入，也不会对国内的农业产生这样巨大的影响。

举例来说，即使对外国牲畜的进口完全开放，进口的数目也非常少，英国的畜牧业不会受到多大影响。活牲畜或许是唯一一种海运比陆地运输更加昂贵的商品了。牲畜能够行走，使用陆运的话，它们自己就能走向目标市场；而海运不但要运送它们自身，还要运送它们需要的粮食和水，费用昂贵，且无比麻烦。爱尔兰和英国之间的海程距离很短，这的确使爱尔兰牲畜的运输容易一些。最近只在一段时间内对牲畜进口实施了开放政策，然而即使永久放开进口牲畜，对于英国畜牧业者的利益也不会产生太大影响。英国靠近爱尔兰海的部分全都是畜牧养殖的乡村。进口的爱尔兰牲畜绝不会为那里的人们所用，必然是要经过那里转运到很远的地方，要经过很大一番周折才能到达适当的市场，费用不低，且麻烦不小。肥牲畜无法走这么远的路途，因而就只能进口痩牲畜，这不会损害到那些从事牲畜养殖或育肥的乡村的利益，而只能损害到从事牲畜繁殖的地方的利益，因为对于前者而言，痩牲畜的价格下降，事实上对他们是有利的。自从允许进口爱尔兰牲畜以来，从爱尔兰进口牲畜数量不大，痩牲畜的价格一直卖得不错，这样看起来，似乎连英国那些繁殖牲畜的地方也不会因为放开进口而受到太大影响。据说爱尔兰的普通民众经常诉诸暴力反对出口牲畜，然而如果出口商看到继续该贸易有任何大的好处，而法律又在他们那一边的话，他们完全可以轻易战胜这种民众的反对。

除此之外，从事牲畜养殖和育肥的地方必定都是土地经过大大改良的地方，而繁殖牲畜的地方一般都是未经开垦的荒地。痩牲畜价格高，增加了未经开垦荒地的价值，这无异于一项重奖，鼓励人们不要开荒改良。因为在任何整个土地经过高度改良的地方，进口痩牲畜都要比自己繁殖更加有利。据说现在荷兰就信奉此理。的确，苏格兰、威尔士和诺森伯兰郡的山区都是无法进行土地高度改良的地方，似乎自然条件注定了这些地方只能是英国繁殖牲畜的地方。完全开放进口外国牲畜的唯一结果就是，使那些繁殖牲畜的地方无法从牲畜数量增加和国内其他地方的土地改良中获益，无法无休止地提高繁殖牲畜的价格，要知道如果可以随意提高繁殖牲畜的价格，实际上就相当于给国内致力于开垦和改良的地方加收了一道税。

同样，如果说进口活牲畜对于英国畜牧业者的影响尚且有限，那么完全放开进口腌制品对于英国畜牧业者利益的影响更是微乎其微。腌制品也是体积很大的商品，这种商品不但品质不如新鲜畜肉，而且其中所含的劳动较多、成本较高、价格也更高，因此根本无法与新鲜畜肉竞争，不过倒是可以和本国的腌制品竞争。腌制品可以为远航的船只供应食物，等等，不过绝不可能成为人们食物供应中举足轻重的一部分。自从准许腌制品自由进口以来，从爱尔兰进口的腌制品数量很少，这证实了畜牧业者丝毫不用担心此类产品的进口。屠夫出售的生肉价格似乎根本不会因为腌制品的进口而受到任何显著的影响。

即使是完全自由进口外国谷物对于英国农场主利益的影响也可以忽略不计。谷物的体积可要比屠夫卖的生肉大多了，用一个便士购买的一磅小麦在重量上相当于用四个便士购买的一磅生肉。即使在国内谷物最匮乏的年景，从外国进口的谷物数量仍然很少，这完全可以消除我国农场主对于自由进口的恐惧感。根据见闻广博的谷物贸易研究者的论文，每年从国外进口谷物的平均数量不过只有23728夸脱，不到我国年消费总量的1/571。不过由于谷物出口奖励使得丰年的出口量超过了实际耕种所允许的数量，必然导致在谷物歉收之年的进口量也超过实际耕种所需要的数量。这样一来，某一年的丰收不能够补偿另一年的歉收，而出口的平均数量必然会因为国家奖励而增加，因而进口的平均数量也必然会相应增加，超过实际耕种所需的进口量。如果不对谷物出口进行奖励，谷物的出口量会随之减少，那么按年份平均，谷物的进口量也会少于当前的水平了。谷物商人，那些在英国和境外各国之间贩运谷物的人因此业务量大大减少，可能会遭受很大损失，但是国内的乡绅和农场主却不会受到什么影响。所以，据我观察，最希望奖励制度更新并持续下去的人不是乡绅和农场主，而是谷物商人。

乡绅和农场主算得上是最没有卑劣的独占心理的人，这是他们无上的光荣。一个大型制造厂的经营者有时会因为附近20英里内新建了一所同样类型的工厂而警觉起来。在阿比维尔经营羊毛制造业的荷兰人规定，该城市周围方圆30里格内[6]不得兴建另一家同类制造厂。农场主和乡绅则相反，他们一般都倾向于鼓励而不是阻挠邻人开垦和改良农场和土地。他们没有大多数制造业者拥有的所谓商业秘密，一般都更愿意与邻人交流心得体会，希望自己刚刚发现的、能够带来裨益的最新做法传播得越远越好。老伽图就说过：“这是最受人尊敬的职业。从事这种职业的人，生活最为稳定，最不为人嫉恨，他们也最没有怨气。”乡绅和农场主们零星分布在国内各地，不像商人和制造业者那样容易合并，后者因为聚集在城镇中，习惯了那种普遍的排他性企业思维，自然都会在获得各自城镇居民所没有的专营权之后，竭力设法获得所有国人中唯一的专营权。这样看来，他们似乎是禁止外国商品进口的始作俑者，为的就是确保自身对国内市场的垄断。或许是为了模仿这些人，或许因为发现这些人企图压迫自己，要获得和这些人平起平坐的权利，英国的乡绅和农场主们忘记了自己原本拥有的宽大之心，反而要求获得向国民供应谷物和生肉的独有特权。他们或许根本没有花时间认真思考一下，与商人和制造业者相比，自由贸易对他们的影响实在是微乎其微。

要颁布一项永久的法律禁止进口外国谷物和牲畜，事实上就相当于规定：国内的人口和工业在任何时候都不能超过其土地原产品所能供养的限度。

然而，在以下两种情况下，通过对国外产业征收税负来鼓励国内产业看来是有利的。

首先，某些特定产业是为国防所需。例如，英国的国防在很大程度上取决于海员和船只的多少。因此，英国的航海法案试图确保英国的海员和船只在国内航海业的垄断地位是非常正确的。具体做法有时是绝对禁止，而有时是对外国的船只征收很高的税负。以下是该法案的几条主要的规定：

一、凡与英国居留地和殖民地通商或在英国沿海经商的船只，其船主及3/4船员必须为英国籍臣民，违者没收船舶及其所载货物。

二、各种体积庞大的进口商品，只能由上述船只或所购商品出产国的船只（其船主、船长及3/4船员为该国籍公民）运入英国，但由后一类船只运入的商品，必须加倍征收关税。若由其他国家的船只运入，则处以没收船只及其所载货物的惩罚。此法案颁布之时，荷兰人是欧洲海运业的巨头，到现在仍是欧洲海运业的巨头；但该法案颁布之后，他们再也不能以海运输送者的身份，将本国货物或欧洲其他各国的货物运入英国了。

三、各种体积极大的进口商品，只许由出产国的船只运入，即使英国船只也在被禁止之列，违者没收船只及其所载货物。这项规定很可能也是专门针对荷兰人制定的。那时的荷兰和现在一样，是所有欧洲商品进行交易的大市场，有了这个条例，英国船只就不能在荷兰国内起运欧洲其他各国的货物了。

四、各种腌制咸鱼、鲸须、鲸鳍、鲸油和鲸脂，不是由英国船只捕获并加工处理的，在运入英国时，须加倍征收关税。那时在欧洲，以捕鱼为业并供给他国的只有荷兰人，即使现在也仍主要是荷兰人。该法案颁布后，荷兰人向英国供给这类海产品就须缴纳极重的关税了。

航海法案制定之时，英、荷两国虽然实际上没有交战，然而两国之间的仇恨却已达到极点。这种仇恨在制定该法律的长期议会统治时期已经开始，不久以后，终于在护国公（即克伦威尔王朝）和查理二世王朝期间的荷兰战争中来了一次大爆发。所以，说这个著名法案中的几项条例是从民族仇恨出发的，也不是完全不可能。不过这些条例本身非常明智，很像是深思熟虑的结果。当时存在于两国间的民族仇恨，其目标与经过最明智的决策之后制定的目标别无二致，那就是削弱荷兰的海军力量，那是唯一可能危害英国安全的海上力量。

航海法案不利于对外贸易，或者说遏制了对外贸易带来的财富增长。一国在对外国的通商关系中所获得的利益，与个体商人在与他人做生意时一样，都力求最大程度地贱买贵卖。完全自由的贸易鼓励一切国家购买和输入所需要的商品，在这种情况下，国家最有可能贱买；也是出于同一原因，由于大量买者麇集于该国市场，商品的售价可以尽量提高，因而也最有可能贵卖。诚然，航海法案对于前来输出英国产品的外国船只并没有课税；甚至之前原本需要对所有出口和进口商品征收关税，而航海法案之后颁布的好几个法案，则规定对大部分出口商品减免这部分关税。但是如果外国人因禁令或高关税的原因而不能来我国售卖，他们也不能来我国购买。因为如果空船来我国装货，单是从其本国来到我国的船费就是一笔损失。所以减少售卖者人数，必然也会减少购买者人数。这样，与贸易完全自由之时相比，我们可能在购买外国货物时付价更高，而在售卖本国货物时出价更低。但是，由于国防比国富重要得多，所以在英国所有通商条例中，航海法案或许是最明智的一项法案。

除上述情况外，还有一种情况，可以通过对外国产业征收若干税负来鼓励国内产业，总体而言又能对国内有利，那就是在国内对该产业的产品课税。在这种情况下，对外国的同类产品课以同额的赋税，似乎也合情合理。这种方法不会造成国内该产业对于国内市场的垄断，也不会出现流入某一特殊用途的资本与劳动大于其自然流入的情况。课税的唯一结果，不过是阻止本应流入该用途的任何一部分资本与劳动流入非自然的用途，而在课税之后，本国产业与外国产业仍然能在与课税前大致相同的条件下互相竞争。在英国，国内产业的产品被课以此等税负时，通常会同时对同类外国商品的进口课以高得多的关税，免得国内商人和制造业者吵吵嚷嚷地埋怨说，这些商品要在国内贱卖了。

有人认为，对于自由贸易的这第二种限制，在某些情况下，不应仅限于输入本国而与本国课税商品相竞争的那些外国商品，应该扩大并适用于许多外国商品。他们声称，如果在国内对生活必需品课税，那么不仅对从外国输入的同类生活必需品课税是正当的，对输入国内、与国内任何产业的产品竞争的各种外国商品课税也都是正当的。他们认为，这样课税必然会抬高生活必需品的价格。而随着劳动者生活品价格的提高，劳动价格也必定跟着提高。所以，本国产业所生产的各种商品虽然没有被直接课税，但其价格都将因此种课税而提高，因为生产这些商品的劳动价格上升了。所以他们说，这样虽然表面看来只对生活必需品课税，实际上却相当于对国内一切产业的一切商品课税。因此他们认为，为使国内产业与国外产业处于同等地位，有必要对输入本国而与本国任何商品竞争的所有外国商品加收税负，其额度应该相当于本国商品价格提高的额度。

生活必需品税，如英国的肥皂税、盐税、皮革税、蜡烛税等，是否必然提高劳动价格，从而提高一切其他商品的价格，我将在后面考察赋税时详细阐述。但是另一方面，假设这种赋税有此后果（它的确有此后果），则一切商品价格由于劳动价格上涨而普遍上涨的情况，在以下两个方面与特定商品由于直接课有特种税负而涨价的情况有所不同。

第一，关于特种税负能够使该特定商品的价格提高到什么程度，总可以作出准确的判断；但劳动价格的普遍提高将在何种程度上影响每一种不同商品的价格，却不可能准确判断。因此，要按各种国内商品价格上涨的比例，对各种外国商品课以相当的税负，就不可能将额度确定得相当准确。

第二，生活必需品税对人民生活的影响，无异于土壤贫瘠和气候恶劣对人民生活的影响。粮食价格因此比从前昂贵，正如在贫瘠的土壤和恶劣的气候之下，生产粮食需要付出额外的劳动和费用。在土壤和气候等条件导致自然资源贫乏的情况下，指导人民如何使用其资本和劳动无疑非常荒谬；同理，在生活必需品赋税人为导致资源匮乏时，这么做也显得滑稽可笑。很明显，在上述两种情况下对人民最有利的做法，便是让他们尽可能地适应当前的环境，为自己的劳动寻找合适的用途，使之即使在不利的情况下，也能在国内或国外市场上占有稍稍优越的地位。人民的捐税负担已经太重了，且已经为生活必需品支付了极为高昂的价格，如果再课以新税，要他们再为其他大部分商品也支付过高的价格，无疑是雪上加霜，此乃最为荒谬的补救办法。

这类赋税高到一定程度，所造成的祸害绝不低于土壤贫瘠和天时险恶所造成的祸害。然而最普遍征收这类赋税的地方，却正是那些人民最富裕、最勤勉的国家，其他国家经不起这么大的失调。只有最强健的身体，才能在饮食不卫生时也存活得下去并拥有健康；国家也是一样，只有当一个国家的各种产业都具有最大的先天和后天优势时，才能在这么重的税负下继续存在并繁荣发展。在欧洲，这一类赋税最多的国家要算荷兰，而荷兰之所以继续繁荣，并不是像人们无端想象的那样，得益于这类税负，而是因为荷兰本国的特殊情形，这类税负无法阻止其继续繁荣。

对外国产业课以关税负担，以此来鼓励本国产业的做法，总体而言在上述两种情况下是有利的，而在下述两种情况下，则需要斟酌考虑两个问题：一，应在何种程度上继续允许自由进口某些外国商品；二，应在何种程度上，或以何种方式，在自由进口中断一段时间之后再次恢复。

有时需要考虑应在何种程度上继续允许自由进口某些外国商品的情况是：某个境外国家通过高关税或禁令，抑制我国某些制造业产品进口到该国。在这种情况下，复仇之心自然会诱使我们实施报复，我们应该对该国的某些或全部制造业产品同样征收高关税或完全禁止进口。事实上，各国通常都是如此实施报复的。法国人为了庇护本国的制造业，特别喜欢用限制进口的办法，对付一切能和他们竞争的外国商品。这似乎是科尔贝尔先生政策的重要组成部分，科尔贝尔先生尽管才智超群，但在这一点上却似乎被商人和制造业者的诡辩蒙骗了，他们总是要求获得针对其同胞的垄断权。如今，就连法国最有才智的人都认为，科尔贝尔先生的这种做法对国家毫无裨益。这位财政大臣于1667年颁布关税法，对大多数外国制造业产品课以极高的关税。荷兰人请求降低关税而不得，便于1671年颁布法令，禁止进口法国的葡萄酒、白兰地及制造业商品。两国之所以于1672年开战，部分原因就是这一商业纠纷。1678年的奈梅亨和约结束了战争，应荷兰人之请，降低了部分关税，荷兰人也撤销了进口法国商品的禁令。英法两国大约是在同一个时候开始使用同样的关税和禁令来抑制对方国家的产业的，不过首先采取行动的似乎是法国。从那以来一直存在于两国之间的敌忾之心，使得双方都不肯降低关税。1697年，英国禁止进口佛兰德斯制造的梭结花边。佛兰德斯那时是西班牙领地，其政府立即宣布禁止进口英国毛织品，以示报复。1700年，英国撤回了禁止进口佛兰德斯梭结花边的禁令，条件是佛兰德斯必须撤销禁止进口英国毛织品的禁令。

为了要撤销广受抱怨的高关税或禁令而纷纷采用的报复政策，如果能够达到目的，则不啻一记良策。一般来说，能够恢复较大的外国市场，不但可以完全抵消由于某些商品价格暂时高昂而经历的暂时困难，还能带来额外补偿。要判断这种报复能否产生效果，与其说需要立法者的知识，不如说需要所谓的政治家或政客的技巧，前者的深思熟虑应该受到普遍的一般原理的指导，而那些狡猾的“动物”，即被俗称为政治家或政客的那些人，在考虑问题时一般都得随机应变、见风使舵。在没有可能撤销这种禁令的时候，为了补偿我国某些阶层人民所受的伤害伤及我们自身的利益，则除了本来受伤害的那些阶层，几乎所有阶层都会受到伤害，这似乎不是一个好办法。当邻国禁止进口我国某种制造品时，我们通常不但禁止进口该国的同种制造品，而且禁止进口其生产的其他几种制造品，因为仅仅禁止那一种制造品很少能够对他们造成显著的影响。这样做无疑可能会给我国某些生产部门的工人以鼓励，替他们排除一些竞争者，使他们在国内市场上抬高自己的劳动价格。不过，我们那些因邻国禁令而蒙受损失的工人是决不会从这类禁令中获益的。反之，他们以及我国几乎所有其他阶层的人民，在购买某些商品时，都不得不支付比从前更为昂贵的费用。所以，每一项此类法律的实施，事实上都给整个国家的民众增加了税负，不仅不利于那些因邻国禁令而遭受损失的我国工人，也不利于我国其他各阶层的民众。

在外国商品的自由进口中断一段时间之后，应该在何种程度上，或以何种方式恢复自由进口，这是一个值得深思的问题，由于一切能与其竞争的外国商品都被课以高关税或禁止进口，我国的某些制造业大大扩充，雇用了大量工人。在这种情况下，出于人道主义的考虑，也许应该一步一步、小心翼翼地恢复自由贸易。如果骤然撤销高关税与禁令，价格低廉的外国同类货物将迅速涌入国内市场，导致我国千千万万的人口失业，连日常的生活资料也无从获取。由此引发的混乱无疑非常可怕。不过由于以下两个原因，由此引发的混乱或许要比一般人想象的小得多。

第一，所有在无奖励金的情况下通常也可以出口到欧洲其他各国的制造品，都很少会受到外国商品自由进口的影响。这类制造品在输往外国时，其售价必须与同品质的同类其他外国商品同样低廉，因而在国内的售价必然更低。这样一来，它们仍然能够占有国内市场。有一些爱赶时髦的人有时只因为是外国货便趋之若鹜，而本国制造的同类商品虽价廉物美，亦为他们所不取，然而根据自然规律，这种愚行总不会那么普及，所以对人们的就业不会产生显著的影响。在我国的毛织品制造业、鞣革业、五金业中，就有很大一部分制造品每年不依赖奖励金而输往欧洲其他各国，而雇用职工人数最多的制造业，也恰恰就是这几种制造业。从自由贸易中受到最大损害的或许是丝绸制造业，其次是麻布制造业，不过后者所受的损失比前者少得多。

第二，这样恢复贸易自由，虽然会令许多人突然失业并丧失基本生活资料，但他们不会因此而彻底失业或了无生计。上次战争结束时，海陆军人数裁减超过10万，相当于国内最大制造业所雇用的人数；他们顿时失去了平素的职业，无疑会感到种种不便，但他们并没有因此被剥夺所有的职业和生计。较大部分水兵或许会有机会逐渐转移到商船上提供服务。与此同时，他们和被遣散的陆军士兵一起被吸收到广大民众中，受雇于各种职业。10万多人惯于使用武器，而且其中有许多人惯于劫掠，他们的生活状况发生了那么大的变化，却不曾出现大的骚动，也不曾引起显著的混乱。在我国的任何地方，流浪汉的数目并未因此而显著增加，而且据我所知，除了水兵转为商船海员外，任何一种职业的劳动工资也未曾减少。但是要是我们将士兵的习惯和任何一种制造业工人的习惯放在一起作比较，即可发现：与前者相比，后者总是有可能且有资格转而从事新的行业。这是因为士兵一向以依赖粮饷为生，而制造业工人则只能靠自己的劳动为生；前者倾向于怠惰与闲荡，而后者倾向于勤勉与刻苦。由一种辛勤劳动转而从事另一种辛勤劳动，当然要比由怠惰闲荡变为勤勉刻苦容易得多。此外我们在前面已经论及，大部分制造业都有与其性质相似的旁系制造业，所以工人很容易从这些制造业的一种转到另一种。而且这类工人中的大部分，偶尔还被雇用从事农业劳动。以前在特定制造业中雇用他们的资本仍将留在国内，以其他方式雇用同样数目的人。国家的资本和从前相同，对劳动的需求也和从前相同或大致相同，不过是用在不同地方和不同职业中罢了。诚然，海陆军士兵被遣散后即拥有了自由，可以在英国或爱尔兰的任何城镇或任何地方从事任何职业。让我们恢复国王陛下的一切臣民所享有的选择任何职业的天赋自由，像海陆军士兵所享有的那样，换言之，摧毁同业组合的专营特权、废除学徒法令（此二者实际上都是对天赋自由的侵犯），再废除居住法，使贫穷工人在此地此业中失业之后，能够在彼地彼业中就业，无须担心被人检举，也无须担心被迫迁移，这样，公众与个人由于某特定制造业工人的偶然遣散而蒙受的损害，就不会大于士兵遣散所遭受的损害。我国的制造业工人无疑对国家有很大的功绩，但和以血肉保卫国家的士兵相比，他们的功绩就显得小些，因而也不奢望得到什么更好的待遇。

我们不能指望自由贸易在英国完全恢复，正如不能指望理想国或乌托邦在英国实现一样。不仅是公众的偏见，还有更难克服的许多个体对私利的欲望，这些都是完全恢复自由贸易所面对的不可抗拒的阻力。如果军队的将领都像大制造业者反对每一个有关在国内市场增加其竞争者人数的法律一样，激烈地一致反对裁减兵力，都像制造业者鼓动工人以暴力攻击和伤害此类法律的提议者那样，激烈地一致鼓动他们的士兵以暴力攻击缩减兵力政策的提议者，那么要想缩编军队就会非常危险，正如我们现在想在任何方面减缩我国制造业者既得的有害于同胞的垄断权一样危险。这种垄断权已经在很大程度上增加了某些制造业的人数，他们像一个过于庞大的常备军一样，不但可以胁迫政府，而且往往可以胁迫立法机关。支持加强此种垄断权提案的议会成员不仅可以获得理解贸易的佳誉，而且可以在那种因为人数众多、财富庞大而占据重要地位的阶层中备受欢迎与拥护。反之，要是此人胆敢反对这类提案，或者甚而有权阻止这类提案，那么，即使他被公认为是最正直、有最高的地位、有最大的社会功绩的人，恐怕仍不免遭受最不名誉的侮辱与诽谤，不免受到人身攻击，而且有时会面临实际的危险，因为愤怒和失望的垄断者有时会以无理的暴行加害于他。

大制造业经营者，如果由于在国内市场上突然遇到了外国竞争对手而不得不放弃原来的行业，其损失无疑是巨大的。通常用来购买原材料和支付工资的那一部分资本，要另觅用途或许不会十分困难；但固定用在工厂及职业工具上的那一部分资本，处置起来却难免会造成相当大的损失。因此出于对这类人利益的公平考虑，就要求这种变革不要操之过急，而要徐缓、逐渐地在发出警告很久以后实行。要是立法机构能够深思熟虑，不为出于片面利益的嘈杂抱怨声所左右，而是为大众普遍利益的卓识远见所引导，它就要特别小心，既要防止形成任何新的此类垄断，又不能让已经形成的垄断继续扩大。这样的法规会在一定程度上给国家的体制带来实际的混乱，而后来的补救措施也难免引发新的混乱。

至于在何种程度上可以适当地对进口外国商品课以关税，不是为了阻止进口，而是为政府筹集收入，我将在以后考察税负时详细探讨。但为了减少甚至阻止进口而强加关税，显然是在破坏自由贸易，对国家关税收入也是有百害而无一利。

限制的不合理性

第一节　即使根据商业体系的原则，这种限制也不合理

商业体系所提倡的增加金银储量的第二个方法，是对通常认为其贸易差额不利于我国的那些国家的近乎所有商品的进口施加额外限制。正因如此，西里西亚的上等细布只需缴纳一定的关税即可输入英国，供英国本土消费；但法国的细麻布和上等细布却禁止进口，只能被运往伦敦港，在那里的仓库中等待转运输出。相对于葡萄牙或任何其他国家生产的葡萄酒，我国对法国葡萄酒进口征收的关税也格外苛重。依照所谓的“1692年关税”的相关规定，一切法国商品都必须缴纳相当于其价格或价值25%的关税；但来自其他各国的大部分货物所缴纳的关税却要轻得多，很少超过5%。诚然，法国的葡萄酒、白兰地、食盐和醋均不在此限，但这些商品须依照其他法律或相同法律的特定条款而加重税务负担。1696年，有关方面认为25%的税负尚不足以阻止法国商品进口，于是又对白兰地以外的法国货物新增25%的税负，同时对法国葡萄酒每吨课以25英镑的新税，对法国醋每吨课以15英镑的新税。我国税则上所列举的各种商品或大多数商品所必须缴纳的那些一般补助税或“百分之五税”，法国商品无一能够省免。如果把1/3补助税和2/3补助税也计算在内的话，单单一般补助税就多达五种；因此，在这次战争开始之前，法国大部分农副产品或制造品至少需要负担75%的进口税。而大部分商品根本负担不起这样重的税负，因此那些税负无异于一纸禁令。我相信，法国一定也针锋相对地对英国的商品和制造品征收同样苛重的税负，不过我并不清楚那些税负具体苛重到什么地步。这种相互施加的限制几乎断绝了两国间一切公平的贸易往来，如此一来，如今无论是法国商品运至英国，还是英国商品运至法国，主要都靠走私。我在前一章所考察的所有原则均起源于私人利害关系和垄断精神；而本章所要考察的各项原则就要归咎于民族偏见与敌意了。于是我们不难推断，这里提到的这些原则更加缺乏合理性，即使根据商业体系的诸项原则，也是极不合理的。

首先，即使英法之间自由通商，使得贸易差额确实对法国有利，我们也不能因此而断言该贸易就对英国不利；也不能因此而断言，英国全部贸易的总差额会因此而对英国更加不利。如果法国产的葡萄酒比葡萄牙产的葡萄酒价廉物美，法国产的亚麻布比德国产的亚麻布价廉物美，那么英国需要的葡萄酒与外国亚麻布，当然是从法国购买更加有利，而从葡萄牙和德国购买更为不利。尽管这样一来，每年从法国进口的商品价值将大大增加，但因同品质的法国商品价格要比葡萄牙和德国的商品更为低廉，全部进口商品的总价值应该有所减少，而减少的数量恰与其低廉程度相称。即便从法国进口的商品将完全用于在英国本国消费，情况也是如此。

其次，我们进口的法国商品中大部分可能会转而出口到其他国家去赚取利润，这种转出口带来的回报也许会等同于我们从法国进口的全部商品的原始费用。人们经常挂在嘴边的关于东印度贸易的种种理论，或许对法国贸易也同样适用，那就是，尽管东印度的商品中大部分都是用金银购买的，但将其中一部分商品再出口之后所能够带回到本国的金银，就比所有货物的初始费用还要多。现在，荷兰最重要的贸易部门之一，就是负责将法国商品运到欧洲其他各国。英国人饮用的法国葡萄酒，也有一部分是秘密经由荷兰及西兰岛[7]输入的。如果英法之间实施自由贸易，或者法国商品在进口时缴纳的税负水平与欧洲其他各国相同，并在出口时退回，那么在如今对荷兰如此有利的对法贸易中，英国就有机会分得一杯羹了。

第三点也是最后一点，我们没有一个明确的标准，可以判定任何两国之间的贸易差额究竟对哪国有利，或哪一个国家输出的价值最大。关于这一类问题，我们判断的依据往往是为个别贸易者的私利所左右的国民偏见与敌意。然而在这种情况下，人们往往会使用两种标准，即海关手册和汇兑行情表。在我看来，这也是如今大多数人所认可的，海关手册这种标准是非常靠不住的，因为根据该标准对大多数商品的估值都极不准确。至于汇兑行情表，恐怕也同样不可靠。

据说，如果两地，如伦敦和巴黎，以等值票面进行汇兑，那表明伦敦欠巴黎的债务，恰被巴黎欠伦敦的债务抵消了。反之，如果在巴黎购买汇票时需要在伦敦给付贴水，据说那就表明，伦敦欠巴黎的债务尚未与巴黎欠伦敦的债务完全抵消，还需从伦敦汇出一定的差额；鉴于此输出有风险、麻烦及出口费用，代汇者要求给付贴水，汇兑人也必须给付贴水。然而据说，两个城市之间债务与债权的一般状况必然会受到彼此间通常的商务往来的支配。如果两个城市之间，甲从乙那里进口的数额不大于它向乙出口的数额，乙从甲那里进口的数额也不大于它向甲出口的数额，则两个城市的债务和债权可以相互抵消。但如果有任何一方从另一方进口的数额大于其向另一方出口的数额，则前者所承担的债务必然大于其对后者拥有的债权，那么二者间的债务和债权就无法互相抵消，前者必须向后者汇出一部分货币，其金额即相当于债务和债权之间的差额。因此，既然两地间商业往来的通常情况可以表明其债务和债权的一般状况，它也必然能表明两地间进出口的一般状况，因为这些都是债务和债权状况的支配因素。不过虽然我们可以从两地间商业往来的通常情况看出二者债务和债权的一般状况，但我们不能就此推断出，债务和债权情况有利于哪一方，贸易差额也就一定对其有利。任何两地之间债务和债权的一般状况并不一定完全取决于彼此通常的商务往来，通常它还受到任何一方与其他许多地方的交易情况的影响。例如，英国商人通常会用荷兰汇票从汉堡、丹泽和里加等地购买货物，这样一来，英国和荷兰之间债务和债权的一般状况就不完全取决于两国彼此交易的通常情况，它还将受到英国和那些地方进行交易情况的影响。在这种情形下，即使英国对荷兰的出口可能大大超出它从荷兰进口的价值，即使所谓的贸易差额可能大大有利于英国，它仍然必须每年向荷兰汇出一笔货币。

此外，按照一向计算汇兑平价的方法，同样不能充分表明，如果汇兑的一般情况被认为有利于一个国家，那么债务与债权的一般情况也必然对它有利。换言之，真实的汇兑情况与计算所得的汇兑情况可能极不相同，而且事实上往往极不相同，所以，在许多情况下，关于债务和债权的一般情况，我们决不能根据汇兑的一般情况得到确实的结论。

当我们为了在英国支付一笔货币，收到一张可以在法国兑现一笔货币的汇票时，如果前一笔货币根据英国铸币的标准所含的纯银，与后一笔货币根据法国铸币标准所含的纯银的盎司数目相同，我们就说，英国和法国之间以平价汇兑。如果你所支付的多于兑付所得，人们就认为你支付了贴水，并说汇兑对英国不利，对法国有利。如果你支付的少于兑付所得，人们就认为你得到了贴水，并说汇兑对法国不利，对英国有利。

但是，第一，我们不能总是按照各国造币厂的标准来判断各国通货的价值。各国通货的磨损程度，或者因为其他原因而低于其所制定标准的程度，有多有少。一国通用铸币与他国通用铸币的相对价值，并不取决于各自应该包含的纯银量，而是取决于各自实际所含的纯银量。在威廉王时代的银币改革之前，根据通常的算法，英国和荷兰之间的货币兑换按照其各自铸币的一般标准计算，需要英国支付25%的贴水。然而朗兹先生的调查研究表明，当时英国现行货币的价值比其标准价值低了不止25%。因此，尽管按照通常算法当时的汇兑非常不利于英国，真正的汇兑却有利于英国；事实上，在英国支付较少量纯银所购得的汇票可以在荷兰兑换较大量的纯银，原本被认为在英国支付贴水的人最终却得到了贴水。在上一次英国金币改革之前，法国铸币的磨损程度要远远小于英国，法国铸币接近其标准的程度要比英国铸币高出两到三个百分点。因此，如果按照通常算法，英国与法国铸币之间的兑换对英国不利的程度不超过2%到3%的话，实际兑换就很可能对英国有利。自金币改革以来，兑换一直都对英国有利，对法国不利。

第二，在某些国家，铸币的费用是由政府支付的；而在另一些国家，它是由个人支付的，此时个人不但要持银块前往造币厂，政府甚至还有可能从铸币过程中获得一些税收。在英国，铸币的费用是由政府支出的，如果你持有1磅重的标准纯银前往造币厂，可以得到62先令，其所含的同类标准纯银的重量正好是1磅。在法国，政府对铸币收取8%的税，不但支付了铸币的费用，还能够为政府带来少量收入。由于英国的铸币不收费，流通银币的价值绝不可能大大超过其实际包含的银块的价值。而在法国，由于铸币是收费的，劳动增加了铸币的价值，正如劳动使得精致的金银器皿的价值提高一样。如此说来，包含一定重量纯银的一笔法国货币要比包含同样重量纯银的英国货币的价值更高，购买时也必然需要花费更多的银块或其他商品。因此，虽说两国流通铸币与各自标准的贴近程度没有什么差别，然而一笔英国货币无法买到含有同样重量纯银的一笔法国货币，因而也就无法买到价值相当于这笔货币的法国汇票。如果说我们为这样一笔货币支付的款项足以补偿法国铸币的费用，那么两国间的实际兑换为汇兑平价，其债务和债权或许事实上能够相互抵消，而根据计算所得的汇兑则对法国大大有利。如果所支付的款项低于这一数目，则两国间的汇兑事实上可能有利于英国，但根据算法则有利于法国。

第三点，也是最后一点，在某些地方，如阿姆斯特丹、汉堡、威尼斯等，外国汇票是以其所谓的银行货币兑换的；而在另外一些地方，如伦敦、里斯本、安特卫普、莱戈恩等，外国汇票则是以本国的通用货币支付的。所谓银行货币的价值始终大于同等面值的通用货币。举例来说，阿姆斯特丹银行的1000荷兰盾的价值大于阿姆斯特丹通行的1000荷兰盾的价值。二者间的差额被称为银行的贴水，在阿姆斯特丹，银行的贴水一般为5%。假设两国当前使用的货币同样接近其各自铸币标准的程度，且其中一国使用通用货币来支付外国汇票，而另一国使用银行货币来支付外国汇票，那么显然，根据通行算法所得的汇兑有利于用银行货币支付的一国，而实际汇兑应该有利于以通用货币支付的一国；其道理和根据算法所得汇兑有利于用磨损较小的货币，或更接近于其各自标准的货币支付汇票的一方，而实际汇兑则有利于用磨损程度较大的货币支付的一方的道理是一样的。在上一次金币改革之前，在伦敦与阿姆斯特丹、汉堡和威尼斯等地交易时，计算所得的汇兑不利于伦敦，并且我认为，在与所有其他用所谓银行货币支付的地方交易时的情况也都是如此。不过那并不表明实际汇兑也同样不利于伦敦。自金币改革以来，即使在与那些地方交易时，实际汇兑也一直是有利于伦敦的。在伦敦与里斯本、安特卫普、莱戈恩等地交易时，或者，我认为在伦敦和除法国外的大多数欧洲国家的交易中，当以通用货币支付时，根据计算所得的汇兑一般都是有利于伦敦的，且实际汇兑很可能也是有利于伦敦的。

……

第二节　根据其他原则，那些额外的限制也不合理

在上一节中我试图论证了即使根据商业体系的诸项原则，对于来自贸易差额被认为不利于我国的国家的进口商品进行额外限制也是完全不必要的。

然而，事实上整个贸易差额原则根本经不起推敲，但是另一方面，不仅是这些限制，而且几乎所有其他商业监管规则全都是建立在这一原则之上。当两个地方彼此进行贸易时，贸易差额原则认为，如果差额平衡，则双方均没有损失或利润产生；但是如果贸易差额在任何程度上倾向于其中一方，则必有一方遭受损失，另一方获益，其损失和获益的程度与平衡倾斜程度一致。但是这些推想本身就是错误的。通过补贴或垄断等方式强迫进行的贸易，可能并且通常都不利于原本旨在获益的那一方，在接下来的文字中我会竭力证明这一点。而在没有外力强迫或限制的情况下自然、经常地在任何两地之间进行的贸易对双方都是有利的，不过对双方有利的程度不尽相同。

这里所谓的有利或获益并不是指金银数量的增加，而是指该国土地或劳动年产量的可交换价值的增加，或者其居民年收入的增加。

如果贸易差额平衡，且两地间的贸易完全是用各自本国生产的产品进行交换的话，则在大多数情况下，两地不但都会获益，且获益的程度也完全相同或基本相同；在这种情况下，两国各自会为对方的一部分剩余产品开辟出一块市场；甲方为生产和制造这一部分剩余产品而投入的资本，即在一定数目居民之间分配并为他们提供收入和生计的资本，会由乙方偿还；乙方投入的这部分资本则由甲方偿还。如此说来，两地各有一部分居民的收入或生计是间接从另一方获得的。同样，由于互相交换的商品被认为具有同等价值，在贸易中所使用的两种资本在大多数情况下也就一样多，或几乎一样多；在两国用于生产本国商品的资本，两国居民由此种分配而得的收入与生计，也必然相等或几乎相等。彼此互相提供的收入和生计，根据商务往来的程度，有多有少。举例来说，如果按一年计，两方居民各自所获得的收入或生计高达10万英镑，或者100万英镑，那么两方各自就需要为另一方的居民提供10万英镑或100万英镑的年收入。

如果两边的贸易是这样一种情况，即甲方向乙方出口的全部都是本国生产的商品，而乙方输入甲方的回程货物全都是外国商品，那么贸易差额被认为是平衡的，即双方都在以物易物。在这种情况下，双方也都会获益，但获益的程度不尽相同；纯粹出口本国商品的那个国家的居民，显然从该贸易中获得的收入最多。例如，如果英国从法国进口的商品只包括法国本国生产的商品，而英国本国的商品并不为法国人所需，因而每年向法国输入大量外国商品，例如烟草，或其他东印度商品作为补偿的话，这样的贸易尽管同样能为两国居民带来一定的收入，但为法国居民带来的收入显然要高于英国居民所得的收入。法国每年用于该贸易的全部资本都将在法国民众之间进行分配。而就英国资本而言，只有一部分，即用于生产英国商品（英国用来购买外国商品）的那部分资本，每年是在英国民众之间分配的，大部分英国资本都被用于补偿在弗吉尼亚、印度和中国使用的资本了，并将为那些遥远国度的居民提供收入和生计。在资本数目相同或几乎相同的情况下，法国用于该贸易的资本为法国民众所增加的收入就要大大高于英国用贸易资本为英国民众增加的收入。在这种情况下，法国与英国进行的是直接的消费品对外贸易，而英国与法国进行的是一种迂回的消费品对外贸易。在直接消费品对外贸易和迂回消费品对外贸易中所使用的资本的不同效果，我在前文中已经详细论述过了。

事实上，任何两个国家之间的贸易既不可能是双方都用本国生产的商品进行交换，也不大可能是一方完全用本国商品，而另一方完全用外国商品进行交换。几乎所有的国家都是用一部分本国商品和一部分外国商品进行交换的。然而，在贸易货物中包含最大比例的本国商品和最小比例的外国商品的国家，必然是主要的获益者。

如果英国不是用烟草和东印度商品，而是用金银来支付每年从法国进口的商品的话，则通常认为在这种情况下贸易差额是不平衡的，因为一国的商品不是用商品，而是用金银支付的。然而在这种情况下，正如前一种情况一样，贸易仍然会带给两国居民一些收入，只不过带给法国居民的收入稍高于英国；英国居民还是会从中获得一些收入。用于生产为购买金银所需的英国商品而投入的资本，即在一定数目居民之间分配并为其产生收入的资本，也因此而被收回，从而继续用于生产英国商品。输出这部分金银并不会减少英国的资本总量，正如输入同等价值的其他商品不会减少其资本总量一样。相反，在大多数情况下，英国的资本总量还会有所增加。商品之所以出口，就是因为国外对该商品的需求要大于国内，因此一般认为，出口所换回的商品在国内的价值要大于出口商品的价值。如果在英国价值仅10万英镑的烟草被出口到法国之后，购回的葡萄酒的价值可以在英国达到11万英镑，那么这次交易就使得英国的资本总量增加了1万英镑。同理，如果用价值10万英镑的英国黄金所购回的法国葡萄酒在英国的价值高达11万英镑，那么这次交易也同样使得英国的资本总量增加了1万英镑。如果说酒窖中存有价值11万英镑葡萄酒的商人要比仓库中存有价值10万英镑烟草的人富裕的话，那么葡萄酒商人也一定比保险箱里藏有价值10万英镑黄金的商人更加富裕。葡萄酒商人所能够启动的产业数目，并因此而能够为其提供收入、生计和就业者的数目，显然要大于其他二人中的任何一个。然而国家的资本总量等同于其各行各业居民的资本总量，国家一年中所能够维持的产业数目也等同于各行各业的资本所能维持的产业数目。因此一般而言，国家的资本和国家在一年内所能维持的产业数目，将通过这次交换而增加。诚然，如果英国能够用自己生产的五金制品和绒面呢，而不是用弗吉尼亚烟草或巴西和秘鲁的金银来购买法国葡萄酒的话，这次贸易对英国将更加有利；直接的消费品对外贸易永远比迂回贸易更为有利。然而用金银进行交换的迂回的消费品对外贸易，却似乎并不会比其他同类迂回贸易更为不利。一个没有金银矿藏的国家不会因为每年出口这两种金属而造成金银严重短缺，正如一个不生产烟草的国家也不会因为烟草出口而造成烟草资源枯竭。一个有财力购买烟草的国家不会长期短缺烟草；同样，只要有财力购买到金银，任何一个国家也不会长期缺乏金银。

据说，工匠若与麦酒馆进行交易，必对工匠不利；自然，一个制造业国家与生产葡萄酒的国家进行的贸易也同属亏本贸易。我的答案是，与麦酒馆进行的交易不一定是亏本交易。从其本质上来看，它和任何其他交易的获利程度是一样的，只不过这种交易比较容易被滥用。一个酿酒师的职业，或者即使是小酒贩的职业，都必然与其他职业一样，同属必要的劳动分工。在需要时，一个工匠从酿酒师那里购买麦酒通常要比他自己酿造同样数量的麦酒更为划算，如果他是一个穷工匠，则对他来说，从小酒贩那里一点一点买，要比从酿酒师那里大量购买更加划算。如果此人贪吃好饮，则无疑会从酿酒师和酒贩那里购买大量麦酒，也会从附近其他的商人那里购买其他商品，比如会从屠夫那里购买更多的畜肉，如果此人贪慕时尚，则必然会从附近的布匹商人那里购买大量呢绒布匹。贸易自由有时的确会被滥用，就某些贸易来说尤其如此，但无论如何，就工匠这一整体而言，这些贸易能够自由进行，显然是利大于弊。此外，个人有时会因为过量饮酒而倾家荡产，但对于一个国家而言，似乎没有这等风险。虽说每个国家都有很多人因为饮酒而入不敷出，为此量入而出或根本分文不花的人总是占更大多数。此外还应该指出，根据经验，葡萄酒如此便宜，并没有导致满街酒鬼烂醉如泥，倒反而使人们更有节制。大致说来，生产葡萄酒的国家的居民是全欧洲最有节制的人，例如西班牙人、意大利人以及法国南部各省的居民，人们很少会不加节制地饮食，像温和的啤酒那样廉价的饮料，就算再怎么大肆挥霍，也无法表现出一个人出手阔绰、慷慨好客。相反，在那些因为气候过热或过冷而不生产葡萄，因而葡萄酒变得稀贵的国家，酗酒倒成了一种普遍的恶行，诸如北方诸国，以及所有居住在热带附近的国家，像几内亚海岸的黑人，就是如此。当来自法国北部各省的兵团驻扎在南部某省，即从葡萄酒比较昂贵的省份来到葡萄酒非常便宜的省份时，我经常听人说，那些士兵起初会因为稀罕优质葡萄酒如此便宜而纵饮，但几个月之后，大多数人就会像当地居民一样节制了。如果我们立刻废除对外国葡萄酒征收的关税，并取消对麦芽酒、啤酒和发酵麦芽酒加收的税负，英国的中下阶层民众或许也会出现普遍而短暂的酗酒现象，但很可能过不了多久，几乎所有人都会节制起来，且这种节制将一直延续下去。如今，在上流社会，即有能力消费最昂贵的酒精饮料的人士中，酗酒已经不再是普遍的恶行，因为饮用麦芽酒而烂醉如泥的绅士，实不多见。此外，在英国对葡萄酒贸易所进行的限制，与其说阻止了人们前往酒馆，不如说阻止了人们买到最物美价廉的酒精饮料。此种限制对葡萄牙的葡萄酒贸易更有利，而对法国的葡萄酒贸易不利。据说与法国人相比，葡萄牙人是英国制造业商品更好的顾客，因而与他们进行的贸易应该得到鼓励。政客们说，既然葡萄牙人照顾了我们，我们理应照顾他们。小商人的卑鄙策略，居然就这样成为一个伟大帝国的政治原则。的确如此，只有小商人，才会把这种策略看作是对待顾客的金科玉律。大商人不会过问这些小节，他们只关心能否在最物美价廉的地方购买到自己需要的商品。

然而，实施通过这类原则，各国最终得出的结论是，他们的利益在于让周围所有的邻国都变成穷国。每个国家最终都以嫉妒之心看待所有与之进行贸易的国家的繁荣，并认为那些国家一旦得利，就必然意味着自己遭受了损失。各国之间的商业，如同个人之间的商业交易一样，原本应该是团结和友爱的纽带，最终却变成了滋生冲突和仇恨的沃土。在本世纪和上世纪，因为王公大臣们的任性和野心而对欧洲和平造成的伤害，远没有商人和制造业者那种无端的嫉妒之心来得更为严重。人类统治者施行的暴力和不公，自古以来就是祸害，在我看来，根据人类行事的规律法则，这种祸害是无法根除的。商人和制造业者既不是也不应该是人类的统治者，他们的贪婪和独占欲也许不能彻底改正，但要其不妨碍其他人的安宁，还是能够轻易做到的。

毫无疑问，最初发明并宣传这种原则的，正是商人们独占和垄断的精神；而最先倡导这种原则的人，却并不像后来笃信这种原则的人那般愚蠢。在任何国家，能够从卖得最便宜的人那里买到自己需要的商品都是也必然是符合最大多数人利益的。这个道理不言自明，所以花费精力论证会显得有些滑稽；商人和制造业者出于自私、精明而故意混淆了这一基本常识，如果不是这样，我们甚至根本无须质疑这一道理。在这方面，他们的利益与大多数民众的利益截然相反。就像行会内自由人的利益在于阻止国内居民雇用其他人而只雇用他们自己一样，这些商人和制造业者的利益，也在于自己保有国内市场的垄断权。因此，英国和几乎所有其他欧洲国家均对所有由外国商人输入的商品课以额外的税负。于是就有了我们如今看到的，对所有可能与我们的制造品进行竞争的外国制造品征收高关税或干脆明令禁止的现象。因此也正如我们所看到的，对于贸易差额被认为不利于我国的国家，是那些与我国的国民仇视最为激烈的国家，几乎所有商品的进口都施加了额外限制。

然而，尽管在战争或政治中邻国的富裕意味着我国的危险，在贸易中却显然是对我们有利的。在敌对状态下，富裕有可能使敌人保有比我们更为精良的船舰和军队；而在和平的商业状态下，它必然会使邻国与我们进行价值更大的交易，为我们提供更好的市场，使我们得以出售那些自己生产的产品或用那些产品购买任何商品。对于勤劳生产的人来说，有富裕的邻人作为顾客自然要比贫穷的邻人更好，有一个富裕的邻国也是同样的道理。的确，如果富人本身又是一个制造业者，对所有同业的邻人来说不啻一种严重威胁。不过其他邻人，从目前看来也是最大多数邻人却能够从中得益，因为富人的花费为大多数邻人提供了很好的市场。甚至，他的产品比那些贫穷的工匠们生产的同类商品更加低廉，也能使大多数邻人受益。同样，一个富国的制造业者对邻国制造业者而言无疑是非常危险的竞争对手，然而竞争本身对大多数民众是有利的，此外，这样一个富裕的国家在其他方面的巨额花费，也必然为人们提供良好的市场，使之从中得益。希望发财的人绝不会退居穷乡僻壤，而必然居住在首都或者大的商业城镇附近。他们很清楚，如果财富的流通量很小，他们便很难从中受益，而如果财富的流通量极大，他们或许能够从中分得一杯羹。这种原则能够引导一两个，乃至一二十个普通人的常识，也应该能够影响一二百万，乃至一二千万人的判断，应该能够使整个国家认识到，邻国的富裕可以看作是其本身获得财富的可能来源和潜在机遇。一个国家要想通过对外贸易富强起来，那么如果邻国都是富裕而勤勉的商业国家，它自然最容易达到目的。如果一个大国四周都是些游牧的未开化之人或贫穷的野蛮人，那么它无疑只能通过开垦本国的土地或发展国内商业来获取财富，想靠对外贸易则基本无望。古代埃及人和近代[8]中国人似乎正是通过这种方式获得财富的。据说，古埃及人极不重视对外贸易；众所周知，近代中国人极其轻视对外贸易，根本不给对外贸易以正当的法律保护。由于对外商业贸易的现代原则旨在使所有的邻国陷入贫困，就算能够达到目的，产生其所企望的效果，也必然使得对外商业陷入极其微不足道、受人鄙视的处境。

正是这些原则，导致法国和英国之间的商业往来在两国受到了很多阻碍和限制。然而，如果两个国家考虑一下自己真正的利益，而不要顾及商业上的妒忌或民族仇恨，法国商业为英国带来的利益可能远非任何其他国家可比；出于同样的原因，英国之于法国也是如此。法国是距英国最近的邻国。英国南部沿海各地与法国北部及西北部沿海各地间的贸易，好像国内贸易一样，可以每年往返四次、五次乃至六次。两国投入到这种贸易中的资本，比起投入到对外贸易的大部分其他分支中的等量资本而言，可以启动四倍、五倍乃至六倍的产业活动，为四倍、五倍乃至六倍的人口提供就业和生计。就算是英国和法国距离最远的那些地区之间，其贸易往来至少也能达到每年一次，迄今为止英国从这一贸易中所获得的利益也至少和与大部分其他欧洲国家进行对外贸易的获利一样多。如果与被我们鼓吹夸大的英国和北美殖民地之间的贸易相比——那种贸易至少每三年，甚至常常是每四到五年才能往返一次——则对法贸易的获利至少要高出三倍。此外，据估计法国居民多达2400万，而我们的北美殖民地人口绝不会超过300万；法国要比北美富饶得多；由于更为严重的财富不平等分配的现象，法国的穷人和乞丐人数也要比北美多得多。因此，法国所能提供的市场至少要比北美市场大八倍，且由于贸易往来的频率极高，英国从对法贸易中所得的利益要比对北美殖民地贸易所得的利益高出24倍之多。与英国的贸易对法国也同样有利，且根据两个国家的财富、人口、邻近程度，法国与英国的贸易也同样比法国与其殖民地之间的贸易优越得多。以上就是两种贸易之间的巨大差别：一种是两国的所谓“智者”认为应该阻止的贸易，而另一种是最受他们偏爱的贸易。

然而本该促进两国之间的开放自由贸易，使双方都从中收获甚丰的现实环境，却最终变成了对这种商业贸易的主要阻碍力量。由于彼此相邻，两国必然成为竞争对手，因此，一方的富强必然会使另一方感到恐惧；本来可以增进民族友谊的有利因素，最终却助长了激烈的民族仇恨。两国都是富饶而勤勉的国家；两国的商人和制造业者都害怕由另一方的高超技能和勤勉劳动所带来的激烈竞争。商业上的嫉妒由强烈的民族仇恨所激起，而强烈的民族仇恨又助长了商业上的嫉妒，两者相互助长；两国的贸易者，都无比笃信其自私自利的谬说，宣称不受限制的国外贸易，必然会生出不利的贸易差额，而不利的贸易差额，又一定会导致国家的毁灭。

在欧洲各商业国家内，秉持这种学说的自命不凡的学者常常预言说：贸易差额的不利必将导致国家濒于灭亡。但在这一切令他们激奋不已的焦虑论调背后，几乎所有贸易国家都试图改变贸易差额，使其有利于本国而不利于邻国，不过，这些努力似乎都是徒劳，无论从哪个方面来说，似乎没有一个欧洲国家曾因上述原因而陷入贫困。相反，每一个城镇和国家都因为对所有国家开放港口而致富，它们并没有像商业体系原则所预期的那样，因为自由贸易而走向毁灭。今日的欧洲，从某些方面来说，虽有几个城镇能够配得上自由贸易港口之称，但真正开放自由贸易的国家却没有一个。荷兰或许要算是最接近这一特征的国家了，却仍然离此目标甚远；众所周知，不仅荷兰的国家财富全部来自对外贸易，其国民必要生计的大部分也来自于对外贸易。

我在上文中已经解释过，还有一种差额全然不同于贸易差额，而这种差额的有利或不利，将必然决定一个国家的兴衰，这就是年产量和年消费量的差额。前文已经指出，如果年产量的可交换价值超过年消费量的可交换价值，则社会在这一年内的资本必然增加，增加的部分正好是前者超出后者的部分。在这种情况下，整个社会就其收入来说是量入而出的局面，整整一年中节省下来的收入自然增加了其资本总量，社会可继而使用这些盈余资本进一步增加年产量。相反，如果年产量的可交换价值低于年消费量的可交换价值，则整个社会的资本必然减少，减少的部分也正好是前者低于后者的部分。在这种情况下，整个社会就其收入来说，陷入了入不敷出的局面，消费必然会侵蚀资本。因而，社会的资本总量必然减少，随之而减少的，还有工业年产量的可交换价值。

产量和消费量的差额与所谓的贸易差额截然不同。即使是完全没有对外贸易、与世隔绝的国家，也可能存在这种差额。无论整个地球上的财富、人口和土地改良社会进步情况如何逐渐增加或逐渐减退，这种差额始终存在。

即使在所谓的贸易差额从整体而言不利于某一个国家时，产量和消费量之间的差额仍然可能始终有利于该国。也许半个世纪以来，一个国家的进口价值始终超出其出口价值；即使这整个时期流入的金银可能立即流出；即使其流通的铸币逐渐磨损，只能用各种纸币替代铸币；甚至即使该国对与之交易的主要国家的债务逐渐增加，在同一时期内，这个国家真正的财富，它的土地和劳动年产量的可交换价值仍然可能以大大超过这些负面因素的比例与日倶增。

……

农业体系

我认为有必要对政治经济学的贸易或商业体系作出详尽的解释，而对农业体系就不必长篇大论了。

据我所知，没有任何一个国家的农业体系将土地农产品作为该国政府收入和社会财富的唯一来源，这种观点目前仅仅是几个学识渊博且独辟蹊径的法国人的构想。显然，如果一种学说根本没有，甚至可能永远不会对世界上的任何国家造成任何危害，实在没有必要费心去详尽罗列该学说的弊端。不过在此，我还是要尽可能地解释清楚这个天才学说的大致轮廓。

法王路易十四当政期间，鼎鼎有名的财政大臣科尔贝尔先生为人正直、工作勤勉、所学甚详，对审查政府账目有着丰富的经验和敏锐的洞察，简言之，他具备足够的能力，完全可以用新方案来管理政府税收的收支，并处理得井井有条。遗憾的是，这位杰出的财政大臣已经习惯了管理诸多政府部门的方法，习惯了建立必要的核查和监督机制，使这些部门各归其所。商业体系本质上的诸多束缚和严格管制，恰恰迎合了这位兢兢业业的财政大臣的口味，他的头脑中充斥着商业体系带来的所有偏见。他试图将政府部门的管理模式运用到法国的工商业中，不但不允许个体商人在平等、自由、公正、开明的原则下以各自的方式追求利益，还赋予某些工商业部门额外的特权，对另一些部门又特别限制。在城镇工商业和农业两者之间，他不仅和欧洲其他各国的财政大臣一样倾向于鼓励前者的发展，甚至不惜以抑制和阻止后者的发展为代价来辅助前者。为了给城镇居民提供价格低廉的生活必需品，以此来鼓励法国制造业和对外贸易，科尔贝尔先生全线禁止玉米出口，致使该国迄今最重要的工业原料无法进入国外市场。法国有着肥沃的农田和宜人的气候，自然条件十分优厚，但上述禁令连同各省自古就有的禁止玉米省际运输法案，再加上各省土地耕种者担负的名目繁多的苛捐杂税，导致法国的农业发展严重滞后。政府抑制农业发展的情况在法国各地多少都有所体现，对其原因也展开过各种调查，原因之一似乎是科尔贝尔政府在城镇的工商业和农业之间选择优先发展前者。

常言道，为使一端弯曲的棍棒伸直，必得掰弯另一端。曾提出将农业作为每一个国家政府税收和社会财富的唯一来源的法国哲学家们，似乎恰恰就是以此为座右铭的。如果说在科尔贝尔的方案中，城镇工商业发展被给予过高重视，那么这些哲学家设想的体系无疑又对它太不重视了。在任何方面可能有助于增加一国土地和劳动年产值的各阶层人民主要分为三类。第一类是土地所有者。第二类是土地耕种者、农场主和农村劳动者，这类人被尊称为生产阶级。第三类是饱受歧视并被冠以“非生产阶级或纯消费阶级”这一侮辱性称号的工匠、制造业者和商人。土地所有者对土地年产值的贡献在于，他们不定期投入资本以改良土地、修葺农舍、疏通排水设施、修补篱笆并改善其他设施。有了这些，耕种者就能够在同等资本投入的基础上获得更好的收成，从而缴付更高的地租。增加的这部分地租可以看作土地所有者支出费用或投入资本以改良土地所应得的利息或利润。在农业学说中，这种费用被称为土地费用。

土地耕种者或农场主对土地年产值的贡献在于，他们支出费用耕种土地，在农业学说中，这部分费用被称为原始费用和年度费用。原始费用包括购买农具、牲畜、种子，以及农场主在第一年租种土地期间至少大半年时间或在土地有若干收成之前，维持其家人、雇工和牲畜的费用。年度费用包括购买种子、农具磨损和维修的费用，以及农场主在一年内维持其雇工和牲畜而支出的费用，如果农场主的家人也参与劳动，被视为耕种的雇工，则也包括这部分家人的基本生活费用。对于农场主而言，土地的收成除去上缴的地租应充足有余。首先要在合理的时间内，至少在他租种期间，能够收回他所有的原始费用及其资本产生的一般利润；其次要能够每年补偿他的所有年度费用及其资本产生的一般利润。这两种费用是农场主在耕种期间投入的资本，如果资本不能定期收回并带来一定的利润，农场主付出的劳动和其他职业就不在同一水平上，那么从自身利益出发，他就必须尽快放弃这种劳动，寻求其他能够带来利润的工作。土地产值中用于使农场主再生产的部分应该留给耕种者专用。如果土地所有者将其挪作他用，其土地的产量必然下降，几年之后农场主将不但难以缴付上调的地租，甚至连原来的合理地租也难以承受。应该归属土地所有者的地租，不过是把先前用于提高土地总产值而支付的所有必要费用完全扣除之后所剩余的部分。正是由于土地耕种者的劳动，在扣除了所有必要费用之后还能产生这样一部分净产值，他们在农业学说里才被冠以“生产阶级”的美称，也正是因此，其原始费用和年度费用才在该学说中被称为“生产性费用”，因为除了能够收回其本身的价值，这些费用每年还能产生一部分净产值。

所谓的土地费用，即土地所有者为改良其土地所花费的成本，在农业学说中也被冠以“生产性费用”的美称。在上调的那部分地租偿还了所支出的所有费用以及所投入资本的一般利润之前，这部分上调的地租应该是神圣而不可侵犯的，教会和国王都不得觊觎：教会不能对其征收什一税，国王不能对其征税。否则，这笔资金的缺失将不利于土地所有者改良土地，从而降低日后教会征缴什一税和国王征税的金额。因此，在一个井然有序的社会里，那些土地费用除了完全再生其本身的价值外，也会在一段时间之后产生净产值，所以在该学说中也被称为“生产性费用”。

不过，土地所有者的土地费用，以及农场主的原始费用和年度费用，是农业学说中仅有的三种生产性费用。其他任何形式的费用和其他任何阶层的人，即使在常人看来是最具有生产能力的，根据这样的标准，也都被视为完全不生产。

工匠和制造业者尤为典型。根据常人的理解，他们的劳动大大增加了土地原产物的价值，可是在农业学说中，他们被认为是完全不生产的阶层。这种学说一般认为，他们的劳动不过是收回了雇用他们的资本，且为这部分资本创造了一般性利润。雇用资本包括由雇主事先垫付的原材料、工具和工资，是专门用于支付其劳动和维持其生活的资金，其所产生的利润则是专门用于维持雇主生活的资金。雇主既垫付了工匠和制造业者劳动所需的原材料、工具和工资，也垫付了维持他自身生活所必需的那部分资金，一般来说，他垫付的这部分资金和他所希冀的劳动价格带来的利润呈正比。如果劳动价格还不能够偿还他维持自身生活的全部费用和投入到雇工劳动中的原材料、工具和工资费用，那么显然，它未能偿还雇主所投资的全部费用。因此，制造业资本的利润不同于地租的利润，不是在偿还了雇主为获得利润所投下的全部费用之后所剩余的净利润。和大制造业者一样，农场主投入的资本也能够创造利润，但它还为他人创造了地租，这是大制造业者的投资所无法做到的。因此——这么说吧——用于雇用和维持工匠和制造业者生活的那部分资本不过只是让它本身的价值继续存在，而没有创造任何新价值。这就是为什么农业学称之为完全不生产的费用。相反，用于雇用农场主或农村劳动力的费用则不仅能够继续维系其自身的价值，还能够产生新价值，即土地所有者的地租，因此它是生产性费用。

商业资本同制造业资本一样，都是不能生产的，都只能维持自身的价值，没有产生任何新价值。商业利润仅仅偿还了其雇主在投资期间、收回资本回报之前垫付给自身维持生活的费用，充其量只补偿了投资所必须支付的一部分费用。

工匠和制造业者的劳动的确从未增加过土地原产品年产量一分一毫的价值，可又的确大大增加了某些特定原产品的价值，不过其所消费的其他部分的价值及其所增加的那部分价值正好相等。因此，在整个过程中，农产品年产总量的价值并未有丝毫增加。举例来讲，一个将褶边加工成蕾丝的手艺人，有时会将价值仅为几便士的亚麻原料的价值增加到30英镑。乍看之下，他似乎把原材料价值增加了7200多倍，但事实上他一丁点儿都没有增加土地原产品年产总量的价值。加工蕾丝或许要耗去他两年的劳动。完工后所得到的30英磅，不过只是偿还了他在这两年劳动期间的生活花费而已。他日复一日的劳动为那对褶边所增加的价值，不过只是补偿了他那日复一日的劳动过程中的生活花费。因此在整个过程中，他丝毫没有增加土地原产品年产总量的价值：他在此期间所持续消费的农产品部分，总是与他所持续创造的价值相抵。在这个费用高却又不重要的制造业中，受雇的大多数人都很贫穷，这一点恰恰证明，他们的劳动价格一般不超过他们所消耗的生活必需品的价值。而农场主和农村劳动力的情况则不同，一般来说，土地所有者的地租就是其不断产生的价值，而地租又是在扣除了完全补偿劳动者及其雇主的雇用和维持生活所需的全部费用之后剩余的部分。

工匠、制造业者和商人若要增加国家税收和社会财富，唯一的途径就是节俭，或者按照农业学说中的说法，只能靠克己，即自行剥夺原本用于维持自身生活所用的那部分资金。年复一年，他们再生产的只是那部分资金。因此，如果他们每年不节省下一部分资金或限制自己使用一部分资金，他们的劳动就根本不能增加整个社会的税收和财富。农场主和农村劳动力则相反，他们可以充分享有维持自身生活的那部分资金，同时还能增加政府的税收和社会财富。除去维持他们自身生活的花费外，他们年复一年的劳动还创造了净产值，产值的增加必然将增加税收和社会财富。因而诸如法国和英国这样在很大程度上由土地所有者和耕种者组成的国家，劳动之余还能享乐，国家也因此走向富裕。与之相反，荷兰和汉堡这类主要由商人、工匠和制造业者组成的国家，就只能通过节俭和克己来累积财富。由于各国所处的境况截然不同，国家的利害关系也大不相同，国民的性格也各有特点：前一类国家的国民自然而然地形成了善良慷慨，诚实直率，热情友爱的性格；后一类国民则难免狭隘、卑鄙、自私自利，拒绝任何俗世的享乐。

非生产阶层，即商人、工匠和制造业者完全要靠其他两个阶层，即土地所有者和耕种者来维持和雇用。后两者既为前者提供了生产原料和维持其生活所需的费用，又提供了他们在从事该劳动期间所消费的粮食和牲畜。土地所有者和耕种者最终不但要支付非生产阶层所有劳动者的工资，还要支付其雇主的所有利润。那些劳动者及其雇主在某种程度上都受制于生产阶层，只不过他们是在外做工的奴仆，而不是在主人家中做事，不过无论哪一种奴仆，都要靠同一类主人养活。因而两者的劳动都是非生产的，对于土地原产品总价值的增加没有什么影响——不仅没有增加，反倒还需从总价值中抽出一部分来支付自身费用。

尽管如此，非生产阶层不仅不能算作无用，而且对其他两个阶层颇有助益。通过商人、工匠和制造业者的辛勤劳动，土地所有者和耕种者就可以用其自身一小部分的劳动产品，来购买他们所需的他国产品及本国加工的产品；否则，无论是购买别国商品还是本国制造品，因其操作的笨拙和生疏，他们就得付出更多的劳动。因为有了商人、工匠和制造业者的辛勤劳动，土地耕种者才得以心无旁骛地致力于土地的耕种，也正由于这种全力以赴的劳动，他们才能够收获足量的农产品，来支付土地所有者和他们自身为了维持和雇用非生产阶层所支付的全部费用。因此，尽管商人、工匠和制造业者本质上是不生产的，但他们的劳动以这种方式间接增加了土地产量。通过给予生产阶层充分的时间和自由来专注于自己的劳动，即土地耕种，非生产阶层的劳动提高了生产性劳动的生产力；可以这样说，往往由于与耕种毫不相干的人的劳动，耕种的效率得到大大的提高。

对土地所有者和耕种者而言，以任何方式抑制商人、工匠和制造业者的发展，向来都不符合他们的利益。非生产阶层享受的自由度越大，诸多行业间的竞争就越激烈，他们提供给土地所有者和耕种者的商品——无论是别国商品还是本国制造品——就越低廉。

对非生产阶层而言，抑制另外两个阶层的发展也不符合其自身利益。用于维持其生活和雇用其劳动的，正是扣除了土地耕种者和土地所有者维持生活所必需的投资之后剩余的那部分土地农产品。同理，这部分盈余越多，维持和雇用该阶层的费用就越高。建立完全的公正、完全的自由和完全的平等，是这三个阶层最大限度地同臻繁荣的最简单、最有效的秘诀。

在荷兰和汉堡等以商业为主的国家或地区，非生产阶层主要由商人、工匠和制造业者构成，维持和雇用他们的资本也同样要由土地所有者和耕种者承担。唯一的区别是，为这些非生产阶层提供生产和生活资料的大多是其他国家的土地所有者和耕种者，是别国臣民，与荷兰等国的工商业阶级相隔千里，极不便利。

然而这些商业国对于其他国家的居民，不仅有用，而且用处颇大。其他国家居民本应拥有其各自的工商业阶层，但因各国政策的某些缺陷，工商业阶层未能形成。这些以非生产阶层为主的国家在某种程度上填补了这个极其重要的空缺，代替了这些国家的商人、工匠和制造业者。

那些农业国家——我姑且这样称呼它们——也决不会对荷兰等国的贸易或输出的商品课以高额关税，来束缚和限制这些商业国家的发展，这不符合它们自身的利益。高额关税会提高这些商品的价格，由于这些商品是用输入国的土地原产物的盈余，换言之，是以这些剩余产物的价格购买的，如此只会导致本国土地原产物实际价值的贬抑。高额关税只会打击生产阶层的积极性，使之不再乐于增加土地产物的盈余，并进而导致本国土地的改良与耕种受到影响。与之相反，如若想提高剩余部分产物的价值、扩大生产、激励改良和耕种土地，最为有效的策略莫过于允许所有商业国家进行绝对的自由贸易。

这种绝对的自由贸易，从以下这一点来说也是最有效的方案：它能够及时提供那些农业国所需要的工匠、制造业者和商人，以最恰当、最便利的方式填补这个对他们极为重要的空缺。

土地剩余产物持续增加，在适当的时候，会创造出多于用于耕种和改良土地的利润值的资金，而这部分利润中剩余的部分自然又被投资，用于雇用国内的工匠和制造业者。然而，一旦那些工匠和制造业者发现本国既提供生产原料又提供维持其生活的费用，那么即便他们缺乏精湛的技艺，也极有可能立即生产出与商业国的工匠和制造业者同等低廉的产品，毕竟后者的生产和生活资料要从遥远的地方运来。由于技艺不精，在一段时间内，这些手工业者的制作成本可能不会和他国技艺娴熟的同行一样低廉；可一旦放眼国内市场，他们的产品和那些来自千里之外的异国他乡的产品相比，由于减免运费，价格相差无几，并且随着他们技艺的改善与精进，其产品的价格很快就会更大幅度地降低。这样，那些商业国的工匠和制造业者在这些农业国的市场上就会立刻面临来自对手的竞争，随后其产品销量大减，他们最终被完全挤出该国市场。由于不断改进技艺，农业国的制造业产品价格低廉，假以时日便会走出国门、进军他国市场，且最终会以同样的方式，逐渐将那些商业国家的制造业者挤出市场。

农业国土地原产物和加工产品均保持持续增长，到一定时候会创造一笔较大的资本，其金额会高于用于农业或制造业的费用所产生的一般利润。这部分盈余自然会转向对外贸易，用于将本国土地原产物和制造业产品超出本国消费需求的那一部分输出到其他国家。在向他国输出本国农产品时，和那些商业国家的商人相比，农业国的商人也具有一定的优势，道理和农业国的工匠和制造业者一样，即农业国的商人可在国内得到货物、原料及供给，而商业国家的商人若要得到这些，就得不远万里地去寻找。因此，如果农业国的商人缺乏先进的航海技术，他们和商业国商人输入到外国市场的货物价格基本持平；一旦农业国商人的航海技术发展成熟，他们的产品价格将更加低廉。如此说来，不久他们就可以在这一部分对外贸易中与商业国家平起平坐，并最终将后者完全挤出市场。

因此，按照这个自由宽宏的制度，一个农业国若要促进本国工匠、制造业者和商人的发展，最有利的办法就是给予其他国家的工匠、制造业者和商人以最大限度的贸易自由。这样可以提高本国土地剩余产物的价值，逐渐积累一笔资金，经一段时间的积累，这笔资金必然能够培养起本国所需的工匠、制造业者和商人。

相反，如果农业国对外贸课以高额关税或设置重重障碍，必然会从两方面危害到自身利益。其一，抬高所有外国商品和其他制造品的价格，必然会降低本国土地剩余产物的实际价值，因为该国是用这些盈余，或换言之，是用这些剩余产物的价格购买那些外国商品和制造品的；其二，通过给予本国商人、工匠和制造业者在国内市场上的某种垄断，提高商业和制造业相对于农业的利润，就会使先前应用于农业的一部分资本流入商业和制造业，或者阻碍了本应用于农业的资本流入农业。因此我们说，这项政策从两个方面挫伤了农业的发展。首先，它降低了农产品的实际价值，因而降低了农业的利润；其次，它提高了所有其他行业的利润。由此，农业相对处于劣势，贸易和制造业则拥有了原本不该有的优势。受到一己私利的驱使，每个人都会尽可能地将自己的资本和劳动从前者转投到后者。

农业国通过实施这项抑制性政策，可藉相对自由贸易以较快的速度培养出自己的工匠、制造业者和商人——这一点非常可疑——然而我们可以说，这是在其还未发展成熟之前，过早地将他们培养起来。过速地培育起某一个行业，就必然会抑制另一个更有价值的行业。被过速培育的这个行业只能回收起初投入的资本并产生一般利润，而被抑制的那个行业在回收该资本并产生一般利润之后还能够产生净值，即支付给地主的地租。这必然会压制生产性劳动，而过早地鼓励非生产性劳动。

……

前面已经谈到，任何国家内规模最大和最重要的商业活动是在城乡居民之间展开的。一方面通过交换，城镇居民获得了土地原产物，从而获得了生产材料和维持生活所需的花费；另一方面，他们在交换中支付加工过的能够立即付诸使用的那部分原产物。在截然不同的两类群体之间开展交易，其实最终是一定数量的原产物与一定数量的加工品之间的交换，因此后者越贵，前者就会越便宜；任何国家无论以任何方式提高加工品价格，都会导致土地原产物价格下跌，从而不利于该国农业的发展。用一定数量的土地原产物，或用一定数量的土地原产物的价格所能购买的加工品的数量越少，这部分土地原产物的可交换价值就越低，就越会打击土地所有者改良土地或农场主耕种土地的积极性。此外，任何国家无论以何种方式减少工匠和制造业者的从业人数，都会导致国内市场萎缩，而国内市场是土地原产物的诸多市场中最为重要的市场，因而该国的农业发展就会进一步受到抑制。由此，那些认为农业胜过任何其他行业的学说，为促进农业的发展，总是对制造业和对外贸易设置障碍，最终却事与愿违，原本旨在促进农业发展，却间接地起到了抑制作用。就这一点来说，其自相矛盾的程度或许要比商业体系的原则更为严重。商业体系对制造业和对外贸易的重视超过对农业的重视，因而从社会资本中抽取部分资本，使社会资本不再用于支持较有优势的行业，转而用于支持不大具备优势的行业。但事实上它最终却能够实现初衷，鼓励其意欲支持的行业的发展。与之相反，重农学说最终只会抑制其所要保护的行业。由此看来，无论是额外鼓励某个行业的发展，增加投入，使之远远超过本应投入的社会资本的制度，还是限制某个行业的发展，减少投入，使之远远低于本应投入的社会资本的制度，事实上都会和原来的目标背道而驰，不仅没有加速富国强民的进程，还降低了土地年产物和劳动力的实际价值。所有学说，无论是优先发展还是抑制发展的学说，一旦完全废除，最明白、最简单的自由制度就会自然而然地建立起来。只要不违背公正原则，任何人都可以完全自由地按照自己的方式谋求私利，并用他自己的劳动和资本与任何其他个人或阶层展开竞争。

6
The Agricultural Systems

The agricultural systems of political economy will not require so long an explanation as that which I have thought it necessary to bestow upon the mercantile or commercial system.

That system which represents the produce of land as the sole source of the revenue and wealth of every country has, so far as I know, never been adopted by any nation, and it at present exists only in the speculations of a few men of great learning and ingenuity in France. It would not, surely, be worth while to examine at great length the errors of a system which never has done, and probably never will do, any harm in any part of the world. I shall endeavour to explain, however, as distinctly as I can, the great outlines of this very ingenious system.

Mr Colbert, the famous minister of Louis XIV, was a man of probity, of great industry and knowledge of detail, of great experience and acuteness in the examination of public accounts, and of abilities, in short, every way fitted for introducing method and good order into the collection and expenditure of the public revenue. That minister had unfortunately embraced all the prejudices of the mercantile system, in its nature and essence a system of restraint and regulation, and such as could scarce fail to be agreeable to a laborious and plodding man of business, who had been accustomed to regulate the different departments of public offices, and to establish the necessary checks and controls for confining each to its proper sphere. The industry and commerce of a great country he endeavoured to regulate upon the same model as the departments of a public office; and instead of allowing every man to pursue his own interest in his own way, upon the liberal plan of equality, liberty, and justice, he bestowed upon certain branches of industry extraordinary privileges, while he laid others under as extraordinary restraints. He was not only disposed, like other European ministers, to encourage more the industry of the towns than that of the country; but, in order to support the industry of the towns, he was willing even to depress and keep down that of the country. In order to render provisions cheap to the inhabitants of the towns, and thereby to encourage manufactures and foreign commerce, he prohibited altogether the exportation of corn, and thus excluded the inhabitants of the country from every foreign market for by far the most important part of the produce of their industry. This prohibition, joined to the restraints imposed by the ancient provincial laws of France upon the transportation of corn from one province to another, and to the arbitrary and degrading taxes which are levied upon the cultivators in almost all the provinces, discouraged and kept down the agriculture of that country very much below the state to which it would naturally have risen in so very fertile a soil and so very happy a climate. This state of discouragement and depression was felt more or less in every different part of the country, and many different inquiries were set on foot concerning the causes of it. One of those causes appeared to be the preference given, by the institutions of Mr Colbert, to the industry of the towns above that of the country.

If the rod be bent too much one way, says the proverb, in order to make it straight you must bend it as much the other. The French philosophers, who have proposed the system which represents agriculture as the sole source of the revenue and wealth of every country, seem to have adopted this proverbial maxim; and as in the plan of Mr Colbert the industry of the towns was certainly over-valued in comparison with that of the country; so in their system it seems to be as certainly undervalued.

The different orders of people who have ever been supposed to contribute in any respect towards the annual produce of the land and labour of the country, they divide into three classes. The first is the class of the proprietors of land. The second is the class of the cultivators, of farmers and country labourers, whom they honour with the peculiar appellation of the productive class. The third is the class of artificers, manufacturers, and merchants, whom they endeavour to degrade by the humiliating appellation of the barren or unproductive class.

The class of proprietors contributes to the annual produce by the expense which they may occasionally lay out upon the improvement of the land, upon the buildings, drains, enclosures, and other ameliorations, which they may either make or maintain upon it, and by means of which the cultivators are enabled, with the same capital, to raise a greater produce, and consequently to pay a greater rent. This advanced rent may be considered as the interest or profit due to the proprietor upon the expense or capital which he thus employs in the improvement of his land. Such expenses are in this system called ground expenses (dépenses foncières).

The cultivators or farmers contribute to the annual produce by what are in this system called the original and annual expenses (dépenses primitives et dépenses annuelles) which they lay out upon the cultivation of the land. The original expenses consist in the instruments of husbandry, in the stock of cattle, in the seed, and in the maintenance of the farmer's family, servants, and cattle during at least a great part of the first year of his occupancy, or till he can receive some return from the land. The annual expenses consist in the seed, in the wear and tear of the instruments of husbandry, and in the annual maintenance of the farmer's servants and cattle, and of his family too, so far as any part of them can be considered as servants employed in cultivation. That part of the produce of the land which remains to him after paying the rent ought to be sufficient, first, to replace to him within a reasonable time, at least during the term of his occupancy, the whole of his original expenses, together with the ordinary profits of stock; and, secondly, to replace to him annually the whole of his annual expenses, together likewise with the ordinary profits of stock. Those two sorts of expenses are two capitals which the farmer employs in cultivation; and unless they are regularly restored to him together with a reasonable profit, he cannot carry on his employment upon a level with other employments; but, from a regard to his own interest, must desert it as soon as possible and seek some other. That part of the produce of the land which is thus necessary for enabling the farmer to continue his business ought to be considered as a fund sacred to cultivation, which, if the landlord violates, he necessarily reduces the produce of his own land, and in a few years not only disables the farmer from paying this racked rent, but from paying the reasonable rent which he might otherwise have got for his land. The rent which properly belongs to the landlord is no more than the net produce which remains after paying in the completest manner all the necessary expenses which must be previously laid out in order to raise the gross or the whole produce. It is because the labour of the cultivators, over and above paying completely all those necessary expenses, affords a net produce of this kind that this class of people are in this system peculiarly distinguished by the honourable appellation of the productive class. Their original and annual expenses are for the same reason called, in this system, productive expenses, because, over and above replacing their own value, they occasion the annual reproduction of this net produce.

The ground expenses, as they are called, or what the landlord lays out upon the improvement of his land, are in this system, too, honoured with the appellation of productive expenses. Till the whole of those expenses, together with the ordinary profits of stock, have been completely repaid to him by the advanced rent which he gets from his land, that advanced rent ought to be regarded as sacred and inviolable, both by the church and by the king; ought to be subject neither to tithe nor to taxation. If it is otherwise, by discouraging the improvement of land the church discourages the future increase of her own tithes, and the king the future increase of his own taxes. As in a well-ordered state of things, therefore, those ground expenses, over and above reproducing in the completest manner their own value, occasion likewise after a certain time a reproduction of a net produce, they are in this system considered as productive expenses.

The ground expenses of the landlord, however, together with the original and the annual expenses of the farmer, are the only three sorts of expenses which in this system are considered as productive. All other expenses and all other orders of people, even those who in the common apprehensions of men are regarded as the most productive, are in this account of things represented as altogether barren and unproductive.

Artificers and manufacturers in particular, whose industry, in the common apprehensions of men, increases so much the value of the rude produce of land, are in this system represented as a class of people altogether barren and unproductive. Their labour, it is said, replaces only the stock which employs them, together with its ordinary profits. That stock consists in the materials, tools, and wages advanced to them by their employer; and is the fund destined for their employment and maintenance. Its profits are the fund destined for the maintenance of their employer. Their employer, as he advances to them the stock of materials, tools, and wages necessary for their employment, so he advances to himself what is necessary for his own maintenance, and this maintenance he generally proportions to the profit which he expects to make by the price of their work. Unless its price repays to him the maintenance which he advances to himself, as well as the materials, tools, and wages which he advances to his workmen, it evidently does not repay to him the whole expense which he lays out upon it. The profits of manufacturing stock therefore are not, like the rent of land, a net produce which remains after completely repaying the whole expense which must be laid out in order to obtain them. The stock of the farmer yields him a profit as well as that of the master manufacturer; and it yields a rent likewise to another person, which that of the master manufacturer does not. The expense, therefore, laid out in employing and maintaining artificers and manufacturers does no more than continue, if one may say so, the existence of its own value, and does not produce any new value. It is therefore altogether a barren and unproductive expense. The expense, on the contrary, laid out in employing farmers and country labourers, over and above continuing the existence of its own value, produces a new value, the rent of the landlord. It is therefore a productive expense.

Mercantile stock is equally barren and unproductive with manufacturing stock. It only continues the existence of its own value, without producing any new value. Its profits are only the repayment of the maintenance which its employer advances to himself during the time that he employs it, or till he receives the returns of it. They are only the repayment of a part of the expense which must be laid out in employing it.

The labour of artificers and manufacturers never adds anything to the value of the whole annual amount of the rude produce of the land. It adds, indeed, greatly to the value of some particular parts of it. But the consumption which in the meantime it occasions of other parts is precisely equal to the value which it adds to those parts; so that the value of the whole amount is not, at any one moment of time, in the least augmented by it. The person who works the lace of a pair of fine ruffles, for example, will sometimes raise the value of perhaps a pennyworth of flax to thirty pounds sterling. But though at first sight he appears thereby to multiply the value of a part of the rude produce about seven thousand and two hundred times, he in reality adds nothing to the value of the whole annual amount of the rude produce. The working of that lace costs him perhaps two years' labour. The thirty pounds which he gets for it when it is finished is no more than the repayment of the subsistence which he advances to himself during the two years that he is employed about it. The value which, by every day's, month's, or year's labour, he adds to the flax does no more than replace the value of his own consumption during that day, month, or year. At no moment of time, therefore, does he add anything to the value of the whole annual amount of the rude produce of the land: the portion of that produce which he is continually consuming being always equal to the value which he is continually producing. The extreme poverty of the greater part of the persons employed in this expensive though trifling manufacture may satisfy us that the price of their work does not in ordinary cases exceed the value of their subsistence. It is otherwise with the work of farmers and country labourers. The rent of the landlord is a value which, in ordinary cases, it is continually producing, over and above replacing, in the most complete manner, the whole consumption, the whole expense laid out upon the employment and maintenance both of the workmen and of their employer.

Artificers, manufacturers, and merchants can augment the revenue and wealth of their society by parsimony only; or, as it is expressed in this system, by privation, that is, by depriving themselves of a part of the funds destined for their own subsistence. They annually reproduce nothing but those funds. Unless, therefore, they annually save some part of them, unless they annually deprive themselves of the enjoyment of some part of them, the revenue and wealth of their society can never be in the smallest degree augmented by means of their industry. Farmers and country labourers, on the contrary, may enjoy completely the whole funds destined for their own subsistence, and yet augment at the same time the revenue and wealth of their society. Over and above what is destined for their own subsistence, their industry annually affords a net produce, of which the augmentation necessarily augments the revenue and wealth of their society. Nations therefore which, like France or England, consist in a great measure of proprietors and cultivators can be enriched by industry and enjoyment. Nations on the contrary, which, like Holland and Hamburg, are composed chiefly of merchants, artificers, and manufacturers can grow rich only through parsimony and privation. As the interest of nations so differently circumstanced is very different, so is likewise the common character of the people: in those of the former kind, liberality, frankness, and good fellowship naturally make a part of that common character: in the latter, narrowness, meanness, and a selfish disposition, averse to all social pleasure and enjoyment.

The unproductive class, that of merchants, artificers, and manufacturers, is maintained and employed altogether at the expense of the two other classes, of that of proprietors, and of that of cultivators. They furnish it both with the materials of its work and with the fund of its subsistence, with the corn and cattle which it consumes while it is employed about that work. The proprietors and cultivators finally pay both the wages of all the workmen of the unproductive class, and of the profits of all their employers. Those workmen and their employers are properly the servants of the proprietors and cultivators. They are only servants who work without doors, as menial servants work within. Both the one and the other, however, are equally maintained at the expense of the same masters. The labour of both is equally unproductive. It adds nothing to the value of the sum total of the rude produce of the land. Instead of increasing the value of that sum total, it is a charge and expense which must be paid out of it.

The unproductive class, however, is not only useful, but greatly useful to the other two classes. By means of the industry of merchants, artificers, and manufacturers, the proprietors and cultivators can purchase both the foreign goods and the manufactured produce of their own country which they have occasion for with the produce of a much smaller quantity of their own labour than what they would be obliged to employ if they were to attempt, in an awkward and unskilful manner, either to import the one or to make the other for their own use. By means of the unproductive class, the cultivators are delivered from many cares which would otherwise distract their attention from the cultivation of land. The superiority of produce, which, in consequence of this undivided attention, they are enabled to raise, is fully sufficient to pay the whole expense which the maintenance and employment of the unproductive class costs either the proprietors or themselves. The industry of merchants, artificers, and manufacturers, though in its own nature altogether unproductive, yet contributes in this manner indirectly to increase the produce of the land. It increases the productive powers of productive labour by leaving it at liberty to confine itself to its proper employment, the cultivation of land; and the plough goes frequently the easier and the better by means of the labour of the man whose business is most remote from the plough.

It can never be the interest of the proprietors and cultivators to restrain or to discourage in any respect the industry of merchants, artificers, and manufacturers. The greater the liberty which this unproductive class enjoys, the greater will be the competition in all the different trades which compose it, and the cheaper will the other two classes be supplied, both with foreign goods and with the manufactured produce of their own country.

It can never be the interest of the unproductive class to oppress the other two classes. It is the surplus produce of the land, or what remains after deducting the maintenance, first, of the cultivators, and afterwards of the proprietors, that maintains and employs the unproductive class. The greater this surplus the greater must likewise be the maintenance and employment of that class. The establishment of perfect justice, of perfect liberty, and of perfect equality is the very simple secret which most effectually secures the highest degree of prosperity to all the three classes.

The merchants, artificers, and manufacturers of those mercantile states which, like Holland and Hamburg, consist chiefly of this unproductive class, are in the same manner maintained and employed altogether at the expense of the proprietors and cultivators of land. The only difference is, that those proprietors and cultivators are, the greater part of them, placed at a most inconvenient distance from the merchants, artificers, and manufacturers whom they supply with the materials of their work and the fund of their subsistence, are the inhabitants of other countries and the subjects of other governments.

Such mercantile states, however, are not only useful, but greatly useful to the inhabitants of those other countries. They fill up, in some measure, a very important void, and supply the place of the merchants, artificers, and manufacturers whom the inhabitants of those countries ought to find at home, but whom, from some defect in their policy, they do not find at home.

It can never be the interest of those landed nations, if I may call them so, to discourage or distress the industry of such mercantile states by imposing high duties upon their trade or upon the commodities which they furnish. Such duties, by rendering those commodities dearer, could serve only to sink the real value of the surplus produce of their own land, with which, or, what comes to the same thing, with the price of which those commodities are purchased. Such duties could serve only to discourage the increase of that surplus produce, and consequently the improvement and cultivation of their own land. The most effectual expedient, on the contrary, for raising the value of that surplus produce, for encouraging its increase, and consequently the improvement and cultivation of their own land, would be to allow the most perfect freedom to the trade of all such mercantile nations.

This perfect freedom of trade would even be the most effectual expedient for supplying them, in due time, with all the artificers, manufacturers, and merchants whom they wanted at home, and for filling up in the properest and most advantageous manner that very important void which they felt there.

The continual increase of the surplus produce of their land would, in due time, create a greater capital than what could be employed with the ordinary rate of profit in the improvement and cultivation of land; and the surplus part of it would naturally turn itself to the employment of artificers and manufacturers at home. But those artificers and manufacturers, finding at home both the materials of their work and the fund of their subsistence, might immediately even with much less art and skill be able to work as cheap as the like artificers and manufacturers of such mercantile states who had both to bring from a great distance. Even though, from want of art and skill, they might not for some time be able to work as cheap, yet, finding a market at home, they might be able to sell their work there as cheap as that of the artificers and manufacturers of such mercantile states, which could not be brought to that market but from so great a distance; and as their art and skill improved, they would soon be able to sell it cheaper. The artificers and manufacturers of such mercantile states, therefore, would immediately be rivalled in the market of those landed nations, and soon after undersold and jostled out of it altogether. The cheapness of the manufactures of those landed nations, in consequence of the gradual improvements of art and skill, would, in due time, extend their sale beyond the home market, and carry them to many foreign markets, from which they would in the same manner gradually jostle out many of the manufactures of such mercantile nations.

This continual increase both of the rude and manufactured produce of those landed nations would in due time create a greater capital than could, with the ordinary rate of profit, be employed either in agriculture or in manufactures. The surplus of this capital would naturally turn itself to foreign trade, and be employed in exporting to foreign countries such parts of the rude and manufactured produce of its own country as exceeded the demand of the home market. In the exportation of the produce of their own country, the merchants of a landed nation would have an advantage of the same kind over those of mercantile nations which its artificers and manufacturers had over the artificers and manufacturers of such nations; the advantage of finding at home that cargo and those stores and provisions which the others were obliged to seek for at a distance. With inferior art and skill in navigation, therefore, they would be able to sell that cargo as cheap in foreign markets as the merchants of such mercantile nations; and with equal art and skill they would be able to sell it cheaper. They would soon, therefore, rival those mercantile nations in this branch of foreign trade, and in due time would jostle them out of it altogether.

According to this liberal and generous system, therefore, the most advantageous method in which a landed nation can raise up artificers, manufacturers, and merchants of its own is to grant the most perfect freedom of trade to the artificers, manufacturers, and merchants of all other nations. It thereby raises the value of the surplus produce of its own land, of which the continual increase gradually establishes a fund, which in due time necessarily raises up all the artificers, manufacturers, and merchants whom it has occasion for.

When a landed nation, on the contrary, oppresses either by high duties or by prohibitions the trade of foreign nations, it necessarily hurts its own interest in two different ways. First, by raising the price of all foreign goods and of all sorts of manufactures, it necessarily sinks the real value of the surplus produce of its own land, with which, or, what comes to the same thing, with the price of which it purchases those foreign goods and manufactures. Secondly, by giving a sort of monopoly of the home market to its own merchants, artificers, and manufacturers, it raises the rate of mercantile and manufacturing profit in proportion to that of agricultural profit, and consequently either draws from agriculture a part of the capital which had before been employed in it, or hinders from going to it a part of what would otherwise have gone to it. This policy, therefore, discourages agriculture in two different ways; first, by sinking the real value of its produce, and thereby lowering the rate of its profit; and, secondly, by raising the rate of profit in all other employments. Agriculture is rendered less advantageous, and trade and manufactures more advantageous than they otherwise would be; and every man is tempted by his own interest to turn, as much as he can, both his capital and his industry from the former to the latter employments.

Though, by this oppressive policy, a landed nation should be able to raise up artificers, manufacturers, and merchants of its own somewhat sooner than it could do by the freedom of trade — a matter, however, which is not a little doubtful — yet it would raise them up, if one may say so, prematurely, and before it was perfectly ripe for them. By raising up too hastily one species of industry, it would depress another more valuable species of industry. By raising up too hastily a species of industry which only replaces the stock which employs it, together with the ordinary profit, it would depress a species of industry which, over and above replacing that stock with its profit, affords likewise a net produce, a free rent to the landlord. It would depress productive labour, by encouraging too hastily that labour which is altogether barren and unproductive.

[...]

The greatest and most important branch of the commerce of every nation, it has already been observed, is that which is carried on between the inhabitants of the town and those of the country. The inhabitants of the town draw from the country the rude produce which constitutes both the materials of their work and the fund of their subsistence; and they pay for this rude produce by sending back to the country a certain portion of it manufactured and prepared for immediate use. The trade which is carried on between these two different sets of people consists ultimately in a certain quantity of rude produce exchanged for a certain quantity of manufactured produce. The dearer the latter, therefore, the cheaper the former; and whatever tends in any country to raise the price of manufactured produce tends to lower that of the rude produce of the land, and thereby to discourage agriculture. The smaller the quantity of manufactured produce which any given quantity of rude produce, or, what comes to the same thing, which the price of any given quantity of rude produce is capable of purchasing, the smaller the exchangeable value of that given quantity of rude produce, the smaller the encouragement which either the landlord has to increase its quantity by improving or the farmer by cultivating the land. Whatever, besides, tends to diminish in any country the number of artificers and manufacturers, tends to diminish the home market, the most important of all markets for the rude produce of the land, and thereby still further to discourage agriculture.

Those systems, therefore, which, preferring agriculture to all other employments, in order to promote it, impose restraints upon manufactures and foreign trade, act contrary to the very end which they propose, and indirectly discourage that very species of industry which they mean to promote. They are so far, perhaps, more inconsistent than even the mercantile system. That system, by encouraging manufactures and foreign trade more than agriculture, turns a certain portion of the capital of the society from supporting a more advantageous, to support a less advantageous species of industry. But still it really and in the end encourages that species of industry which it means to promote. Those agricultural systems, on the contrary, really and in the end discourage their own favourite species of industry.

It is thus that every system which endeavours, either by extraordinary encouragements to draw towards a particular species of industry a greater share of the capital of the society than what would naturally go to it, or, by extraordinary restraints, force from a particular species of industry some share of the capital which would otherwise be employed in it, is in reality subversive of the great purpose which it means to promote. It retards, instead of accelerating, the progress of the society towards real wealth and greatness; and diminishes, instead of increasing, the real value of the annual produce of its land and labour.

All systems either of preference or of restraint, therefore, being thus completely taken away, the obvious and simple system of natural liberty establishes itself of its own accord. Every man, as long as he does not violate the laws of justice, is left perfectly free to pursue his own interest his own way, and to bring both his industry and capital into competition with those of any other man, or order of men.

导读

查尔斯·达尔文（Charles Darwin，1809—1882），生于英国的一个医学世家，不过年少时的达尔文却对动植物学、地质学、自然历史、化学等学科表现出浓厚兴趣，经常“游手好闲”地做些与父亲的意愿相违背的事情。终于，忍无可忍的父亲将达尔文送去爱丁堡大学修读医学，之后又转去剑桥大学修读神学。但是，这依然不能阻挡达尔文内心对自然科学的热情与实践，他课余时间依然不断地游山览水、进行狩猎、逛博物馆、撰写动植物观察报告、结交同好、参与社交活动，也算初有所成，颇积累了些名气。1831年底，在朋友的推荐下，当然也源于他在学界的口碑，达尔文才能以博物学家的身份登上“小猎犬号”，开启了一段满是艰辛却又无比充实的环球航程。

小猎犬号在英国普利茅斯起航，先是跨越赤道抵达南美洲，之后驶过太平洋落脚大洋洲，然后横穿印度洋在南非中转，接着又一次越过大西洋抵达南美洲的巴西，最后才沿着佛得角线路返航英国。航程共历时五年，不过达尔文却将途中的绝大多数时间都留在陆地进行探索，他详尽记录了大量的地理现象、动植物化石标本、当地的风土人情，并持续不断地将这些珍贵的材料寄回英国保存、研究。回国之后的达尔文总结一路心得，并出版游记《小猎犬号之旅》一书，也是引起一时轰动，名声大噪。达尔文基于这些第一手的素材进行潜心研究，对生物学、地质学等学科都产生了新的理解，终于逐渐归纳形成了一套系统的生物进化论思想，并于1859年出版巨作《物种起源》。

达尔文的进化论认为自然界中的所有物种都并非是一成不变的，而是由低级向高级不断进化发展的。“变异”为自然界提供了多样物种的可能，物种之间存在天然的“生存竞争”，再经“自然选择”筛选出其中适应自然的形态，逐渐演变为今日的世界。由此可见，“自然选择”是达尔文进化论的核心概念。本书章节包括“生存竞争”“自然选择”“理论上的难点”与“结论”，分别对应着《物种起源》原作的第3、4、6、15章。本书以“自然选择”为核心，介绍了达尔文进化论中关于“自然选择”的种种内容要素，希望使读者们借此可以一窥原作思想的伟大。

其实在达尔文之前，学界早已经有了一些类似进化论的概念，这甚至可以追溯到古希腊时期。但直到达尔文的《物种起源》，才最终形成了较为成熟系统的进化论学说，并在众多学者的修改与补充之下成为生物界的主流理论。虽然如今有越来越多的专家学者开始对达尔文进化论这一假说进行证伪，不过这依然无法改变其在大众心中的崇高地位。

达尔文进化论自诞生之日起便超越了生物学的范畴，在科学、社会学、哲学等诸多领域中皆产生了重大影响，可谓是继哥白尼的“日心说”之后第二次影响世界的思想巨变。在达尔文之前，西方社会由于宗教思维根深蒂固，普遍坚信人类是由上帝创造；而达尔文的假说则首次以科学的理念撼动了上帝造人说，进一步改造了西方自中世纪以来形成的宗教型世界观。

“自然选择”概念，由翻译家严复先生于19世纪末的《天演论》中首次引入中国，更被阐发为“物竞天择，适者生存”的社会口号，在那个旧时代掀起了一场波澜。自此，礼让谦逊的中国人开始突破传统，重视竞争，社会被装上了强有力的引擎而不断飞跃发展，直至今日这仍是现代中国社会普遍认可的生存法则与评价规范。

今日重读《论自然选择》一书，我们虽然会发现其中的某些生物学观点已被更完善的科学理论所淘汰，但这也恰恰是“自然选择”概念的必然；世界也早已不是两百年前的样子，而这一切的原因皆在本书之中，等待读者觅寻。

柴尔

生存竞争

1.没有什么事情比口头承认普遍生存竞争的真理更为容易，或者说，没有什么事情比将此结论时刻牢记在心更加困难——至少我是这样想的。但除非这一结论在心中已经根深蒂固，否则，我相信，人们将会对整个自然法则以及有关分布、珍稀、繁盛、灭绝与变异等一切事实认识模糊，或者在相当程度上产生误解。我们见到自然界欢欢喜喜光明的一面，我们时常看到食物极大丰富；我们没有看到，或者忘记了那些在我们周围悠闲鸣叫的鸟儿主要以昆虫或种子为生，它们因此不断摧毁生命；或者我们忘记这些鸣禽或其蛋或雏鸟，是如何被食肉鸟类或兽类大量消灭；我们并不总是记得，尽管食物现在可能极大丰富，但年复一年的每一季节并不都是如此。

2.我应该预先说明：我是在广义与比喻的意义上使用“生存竞争”这个术语的，其中包括一种生物对另一种的依存，而且，不仅包括（这一点更加重要）个体的生命，也包括在留下后代方面的成功。也许可以确切地说，两只犬科动物在饥馑时刻彼此争斗，以决定谁将得到食物并且活下去。但是长在沙漠边缘的植物，与其说是与干旱斗争以求存活，不如说是依赖水分。我们也许可以更确切地说：每年结成一千颗种子，平均只有一颗种子能够长成的植物，是与已经长在地面上的同类或异类植物进行竞争。槲寄生依赖苹果树和少数其他树种而生存，但我们只能在牵强意义上说它与这些树木竞争，因为如果同一棵树上生长了太多的这些寄生生物，这棵树就将枯萎而死。但是好几株槲寄生幼苗在同一根树枝上挤在一起生长，更确切的说法或许是它们彼此竞争。槲寄生是靠鸟类传播种子的，所以它的生存依赖于鸟类；为了引诱鸟类吞食来传播它的而不是其他植物的种子，也许我们可以比喻说，槲寄生与其他结果实的植物竞争。在这好几种彼此相通的意义上，为方便起见，我使用了“生存竞争”这个通用术语。

3.一切有机生物皆有高速繁殖的倾向，其后就必定继之以生存竞争。每一种生物在其自然生命期间都生产好几个卵或种子，在其生命中的某一时刻、某一季节或偶然的一年，必定遭到摧毁，否则，根据几何增加的原理，这种生物的数目就可能异常得多，以至于无地可容。因此，由于产生出来的个体比可能存活下来的个体要多，在任何情况下都必定有生存竞争，生物个体不是与同种的另一个体竞争，就是与异种的个体竞争，或是与生存的物质条件竞争。将繁殖力应用于整个动物与植物王国的正是马尔萨斯[1]的学说；因为在这种情况下，既不能人为地增加食物，也不能谨慎地限制结合。某些物种当前可能或多或少地迅速增加数量，但是并非所有生物都能如此，因为这个世界可能就容不下它们了。

4.各种生物都以如此高的速度自然增加，如果不遭毁灭，地球就可能很快为一对生物的后代所覆盖，这条规则是毫无例外的。即使是繁殖缓慢的人类也会在25年之内增加1倍，按照这样的速度，几千年后，人类的后代可能实际上就没有立足之地了。林奈[2]曾经计算过：如果某种一年生植物只结两粒种子——没有任何植物的生产力会这样低下——而且第二年这两棵幼苗各结两粒种子，以此类推，则20年后可能有100万株这样的植物。在所有已知的动物中，大象被视为繁殖最慢的，但我曾经尽力估计大象自然增长很可能的最低速率；假设大象在30岁时繁殖，一直繁殖到90岁，其间生出3对小象；如果情况果然如此，那么，500年后就可能有1500万只大象存活，它们都是第一对大象的后代。

5.但是在这个问题上我们有比单纯理论计算更好的证据，那就是，在自然状态下，如果在两三个连续季节里环境对各种动物都一直有利，则动物会以令人吃惊的速度增长，这样的无数例子都是可以查证的。更加令人惊讶的证据来自许多种类的家畜，这些家畜在世界上好几个地方无人管束：在南美洲以及近年来在澳洲繁殖缓慢的牛和马增殖率的报告，如果不是确有实据，简直令人难以置信。植物也是一样：可以给出这样的事例，即不到10年，引进的植物便遍及全岛。如今在拉普拉塔[3]的广阔平原上，数量极多的好几种植物覆盖了好几平方里格[4]地面，几乎排除了所有其他植物，它们却是从欧洲引进的；我从福尔克纳[5]博士处听说，在发现美洲以后便传入印度的植物，现在已经分布在从科摩林角[6]到喜马拉雅一带地方了。在这样的例子，以及可能给出的无数例子中，没有人会假设这些动植物的繁殖力突然、暂时地以任何觉察得到的程度提高了。显而易见的解释是生存条件一直非常有利，因此无论老幼都很少遭到毁灭，几乎所有年轻个体都能繁衍后代。在这类例子中，几何比率的增加速度——其结果永远惊人——就简单地解释了驯化生物为什么在新家异常快速增加并且广泛散布的现象。

6.在自然状况下，几乎每种植物都结籽，而在动物之中很少有每年不交配的。因此我们也许可以大胆断言：所有植物与动物往往以几何速率增加，所有生物都可能最快速地在它们无论以何种方式生存下来的每一生境进行储备，而且这种以几何速率增加的倾向一定在生命的某一时期因毁灭而受到制约。我认为，我们对于大型家畜的熟悉程度往往误导我们：我们没有看到任何大规模毁灭降临到它们头上，而且我们忘记了每年有成千上万头家畜被屠宰作为食物；另外，在自然状况下，同样数目的动物可能已经以某种方式被处理掉了。

7.每年产卵或结籽数以千计的生物与那些产卵或结籽极少的生物之间唯一的区别是：假定某区域非常大，那么在有利条件下，后者可能需要多几年的时间才能布满整个区域。秃鹫产两枚卵，而鸵鸟产20枚，但在同一地区，秃鹫可能是两者之中数量较多的：管鼻鹱（Fulmar petrel）只产一枚卵，但据信它是世界上数量最多的鸟。一只苍蝇产卵数百，而另外的蝇，如虱蝇，只产一枚；但这种区别并不决定在某区域之中这两种蝇各有多少个体能够生存。对于依赖食物数量急剧波动的那些物种来说，大量的卵具有相当的重要性，因为食物可以让该物种的数量迅速增多。但是大量产卵或结籽的真正重要性在于为生命某个时期的大量毁灭提供补充；在绝大多数情况下，这样的时期是在生命的早期。如果某种动物能够以任何方式保护自己的卵或幼仔，那就可能产出少量的卵或幼仔，但平均储备量依然能够得到充分保持；但是如果许多卵或幼仔遭到毁灭，那就必须大量生产，否则物种就会灭绝。某种树平均存活一千年，如果每千年结一粒种子，假设这粒种子永远不遭毁灭，并保证它在适宜的地方发芽，那么这就足以保持这种树的全部数量了。所以在任何例子中，所有动物或植物的平均数量只间接取决于它们的卵或种子的数量。

8.在观察自然的时候，最必要的就是始终记住上述各种考虑因素——永远不要忘记，可以说我们周围每一种生物都在尽最大努力增加数量；每一种生物在其生命的某一时期都要竞争求存；在每一代或重复间隔期间，无论老幼都不可避免要遭到严重的毁灭。减轻任何制约或毁灭稍许缓和，物种的数量将几乎立即增加到任何数量。可以将自然界的面貌与曲面相比：一万个尖锐的楔子紧紧地挤在一起，被不断向内打击着，有时某个楔子被击中了，然后另外一个却受到更大的打击。

9.制约每一物种增加数量的自然倾向的因素极不明晰。看看最有生命力的物种，纵使它们的个体大量密集，其扩大繁殖的倾向依然愈发强烈。哪怕是在单一的例子里，我们也并不能确切知道制约因素究竟是什么。想到我们在这方面太无知了，这对于任何人来说都不足为奇，哪怕是在人类方面，我们对人类的了解远比对任何其他动物的了解要更加深刻。好几位作者已经高明地涉及过这个主题，我将在日后的著作中以相当长的篇幅论述若干种类的制约，特别是对南美野生动物的制约。我在本文中只略作评论，只是为了让读者注意一些要点。一般说来，卵和幼兽似乎受害最多，但也并非一概如此。就植物来说，种子会遭到大规模的毁灭，但是，根据我的若干观察，在已经密集生长着其他植物的土地上，我认为受害最多的是萌芽的幼苗。幼苗还因各种敌人而大量毁灭；例如，在一片松过土并除过草的3英尺长2英尺宽的土地上，不会再受到其他植物的抑制，在本地的野草长出以后，我对所有幼苗做了记号，在357棵幼苗中至少有295棵被毁，主要毁于蛞蝓和各种昆虫。如果草地早就刈割过，并让植物任意生长，生命力比较旺盛的植物就会逐渐消灭掉那些生命力较弱的植物，尽管后者已经完全长成，情况可能与被四足动物仔细啃过的草地一样：这样，在一小片草地（3英尺宽4英尺长）上生长着的20个物种中，就有9种因其他物种能够自由生长而灭亡。

10.每一物种能够得到的食物数量自然给出了每一物种能够增加的极限；但决定某个物种平均数量的因素往往不是获得食物，而是被其他动物猎食。因此，似乎很少有疑问的是，在任何大片土地上的山鹑、松鸡和野兔，其数量主要取决于害兽的毁灭。如果今后20年内在英格兰不射杀一头猎物，而且与此同时，如果不毁灭任何害虫，那么，尽管现在每年射杀成千上万头猎物，很可能猎物比现在还少。另一方面，在某些情况下，如同大象与犀牛那样，这两种动物都不是死于食肉兽：即使是印度的老虎也很少胆敢攻击受到母象保护的小象。

11.在决定某一物种的平均数量上，气候起着重要的作用，我认为间歇出现的极端寒冷与干旱是所有制约条件中最有效的。我估计，在1854至1855年冬季，在我自己的家园有五分之四的鸟类被杀死；这是一次重大的毁灭，我们知道，人类传染病的死亡率达到百分之十便是异常惨重了。气候的作用乍看之下似乎完全与生存竞争无关；但是要考虑到气候主要作用是减少食物，造成个体之间最严酷的竞争，不论是同种还是异种之间的竞争，只要是依赖同样的食物生存者都一样。甚至气候例如严寒直接起作用的时候，生命力最不旺盛或者在整个冬季获得食物最少的个体将受害最多。当我们自南向北旅行，或者从潮湿地区走向干燥地区，我们必将看到某些物种渐渐稀少，直至最后消失；而且气候的变化是显著的，我们不由得要将全部效果归因于气候的直接作用。但是这是相当错误的观点：我们忘记了每个物种即使是在它极其兴旺的地方，也在其生命的某一阶段遭受巨大的破坏，这种破坏来自敌人或者来自争夺同一区域或食物的竞争者；如果这些敌人或竞争者受到任何微小的气候变化的有利影响，其数量就会增加，随着每个地区完全被有些生物占据，其他物种的数量就会减少。如果我们向南旅行并且见到某个物种数量减少，我们可能确定地感到，在相当程度上其原因在于其他物种受益，而此种物种受害。所以，如果我们向北而行，情况也是这样，但在程度上多少有些减轻，因为所有种类的物种及其竞争者的数量，都是向北逐渐减少的；因此在向北而行或者登山的时候，我们遇到形态矮小的植物，这是气候所起的直接伤害作用，这种情况要比我们向南而行或下山时更加常见。如果我们抵达北极地区、积雪的山顶或者纯粹的沙漠，为生存所作的斗争几乎完全是与自然环境的斗争。

12.我们可以在花园里清楚地看到大量植物完全能够忍受我们的气候，却永远不能归化，因为它们不能与本地植物竞争，也不能抵抗本地动物的摧毁，这说明气候主要以间接方式作用以有利于其他物种。

13.如果某一物种由于高度有利的环境而在一小块土地上数量异常增加，那就会出现传染病——至少，我们的猎物似乎一般会发生这样的情况：在这里我们看到与生存竞争无关的限制性制约。但是即使某些所谓的传染病似乎也是由于寄生虫引起的，这类寄生虫出于某种原因，很可能部分地因便于在密集动物中传播而格外获益：于是在寄生虫与其牺牲品之间就发生了某种程度的竞争。

14.另一方面，在许多情况下，与其敌害的数量相比，同一物种的保存绝对需要有大量的个体。因此我们很容易在田间种出许多玉米和油菜籽等，因为这些种子的数量大大超出了以此为食的鸟类数量；而鸟类虽然在这一季有极其丰富的食物，却并不能按照种子供应的数量成比例地增加其数量，因为这些鸟类的数量在冬季是要受到制约的：但是曾经试做过的人都知道，要从花园里的少量小麦或其他这类植物获得种子是多么困难；我曾在这种情况下失去了每一粒种子。我认为，同一物种为了保存而需要大量个体这一观点解释了自然界中某些异常的事实，诸如相当珍稀的植物在它们的确出现的少数地方有时数量极多；而某些群生植物即使在其群生范围的边缘还能群生。因为在这种情况下，我们可以相信：某种植物也许只在其生存条件有利、能够允许许多这种植物一起生长的地方才能存活，从而免于全部毁灭。我应该加上一句，在这些例子中，有些很可能是由于频繁杂交产生了良好结果，有些则由于近亲交配而产生了不良结果；但是在这一复杂的主题上我不打算在此赘述。

15.许多记录在案的例子表明，在同一地区势必彼此竞争的生物之间，其制约作用和关系是多么复杂和出人意料。我只举一个例子，这例子虽然简单，却令我感兴趣。在斯塔福德郡[7]一位亲戚的地产上，我做过大量的调查研究，那是一片广大而极其荒芜的地块，从来没有人工的痕迹；但是25年以前性质完全相同的一块几百英亩的土地被围起来，并且种上了欧洲赤松。这块荒地上种上的本地植物的变化极其明显，这种变化比在两块相当不同的土地上一般见到的要大：不但荒地植物的比例完全改变，而且有12种植物（禾本科与苔属植物没有计算在内）在种植区域内长势茂盛，这些植物在荒地上本来是见不到的。对于昆虫的影响甚至更大，因为有6种荒地原本看不见的食虫鸟在种植场上却很常见；而这块荒地时常有两三种不同的食虫鸟光顾。在这里我们看到引进一个树种所产生的影响是多么强大，除了围起这块地，防止牛群进入外，其他什么事情也没有做过。但是我在萨里的法纳姆镇[8]附近清楚地看到了，围地这一因素的重要性。那里有广阔的荒地，在远处的小山顶上有几处古老的欧洲赤松：最近10年之内，大片地块围了起来，如今天然播种的冷杉已大批生长，但长得过密，因而未能全部成活。当我确定这些冷杉幼树是并非人力播种或种植的时候，不由对这些冷杉的数量大为惊讶，因此我去了几处观察点，我可以调查上百英亩未被围住的荒地，除了早年间种植的那些老树以外我确实看不到一棵欧洲赤松。但是仔细观看荒地上树干之间的地方，我发现了许多树苗和幼树，它们总是被牛群吃掉而长不起来。在距离一片老树大约几百码的地方，我在1平方码的地方数出32棵小树；从年轮判断，有一棵小树在26年期间试图长得高出荒地上的茎干，却没有成功。怪不得一旦荒地被围起来，就会密布着生气勃勃的小冷杉了。但这片荒地太荒芜广阔，决没有人会想到牛群可能在那里仔细有效地搜索食物。

我们在这里看到牛群绝对控制着欧洲赤松的生存；但是在世界上好几个地方，昆虫决定了牛群的生存。也许巴拉圭提供了这方面最奇怪的例子；因为这里的牛、马、狗都没有变成野生的，而往南或往北而去，它们都以野生状态群集着；阿萨拉[9]和伦格尔[10]都曾证明这是由于巴拉圭的某种蝇增多的缘故，这种蝇在这些刚出生动物的脐部产卵。这些蝇虽然很多，但其数量的增加必定经常受到某种制约，很可能是鸟类的制约。因此，如果巴拉圭的某种食虫鸟（其数量很可能受到鹰类或食肉兽的制约）数量增加，这种蝇就可能减少——然后牛群和马群就可能变成野生的，而这种现象肯定会大大改变植被（我在南美某些地方的确观察到这种情况）：这种改变又会大大影响到昆虫；而且，如我们在斯塔福德郡曾经看到的那样，这又可能影响到食虫鸟，如此等等，这种复杂关系的圈子不断扩大。我们是从食虫鸟开始这一系列观察的，我们也以食虫鸟作为其结束。自然界中的关系并不总是这样简单。战争之中的战争必定屡屡重现且胜败无常；但是长期说来各种力量平衡得很好，使得自然界的面貌长期保持一致，尽管最微小的事件往往可能使某种生物胜过另外一种。纵然如此，我们的无知程度太深，我们的假定又太之多，致使我们听到某种生物的灭绝就惊叹不已；由于我们看不到其原因，我们就乞灵于灾难来破坏世界，或者造出有关生命形式持续时期的法则！

17.我忍不住要再给出一个例子，以说明在自然界的等级中相距极远的植物和动物是如何被复杂的关系网束缚在一起的。我以后应该有机会表明，在英格兰的这一地区，外来植物毛半边莲（Lobelia fulgens）是从来没有昆虫访问过的，因此，由于特殊的结构，它从来不结籽。我们的许多兰科植物绝对需要飞蛾的光顾以便带走它们的花粉块，从而使它们受精。我也有理由相信，土蜂是三色堇（Viola tricolor）受精所必不可少的，因为其他蜂类不来访问这种花。根据我所做过的实验，我发现蜂类的来访，如果不是必不可少的话，至少对三叶草的受精是极为有益的；但是土蜂只访问红三叶草（Trifolium-pratense），因为其他蜂类接触不到它的花蜜。因此我几乎毫不怀疑，如果英格兰的整个土蜂属都灭绝了或者变得罕见，那么三色堇和红三叶草就可能变得相当稀少或者完全消失。任何地区的土蜂数目在很大程度上取决于田鼠的数目，因为田鼠破坏土蜂的蜂房与蜂巢；长期注意土蜂习性的H.纽曼[11]先生认为“在英格兰，三分之二以上的土蜂就这样遭到毁灭。”正如大家所知，现在田鼠的数目大体上取决于猫的数目；纽曼先生说：“在村庄和小镇附近，我发现土蜂的蜂巢比别的地方都多，我把这归因于毁灭田鼠的猫的数量。”因此相当可信的是，如果某地区有大量猫科动物，它们也许就会先通过田鼠再通过土蜂决定该地区某种花的增减次数！

18.以每一个物种而论，在其生命的不同时期、在不同的季节或年份，可能有许多不同的制约因素在起作用；某一种或少数几种制约因素一般来说最有威力，但是所有制约因素在决定物种的平均数量甚或其生存方面是共同起作用的。在某些情况下，可以看到极不相同的制约因素在不同地区对同一物种起作用。我们看到混杂的浅滩上长着植物和矮树丛，这时我们不由得将它们的比例数和种类归因于所谓的可能性。但是这种观点是多么错误啊！大家都听说过：美洲的森林遭到砍伐以后，就有截然不同的植被在那里生长起来；但人们已经观察到：美国南部昔日的印第安土丘上现在生长着的树木，展现了与周围原始森林同样美丽的多样性与物种比例。这里几个树种之间必定已经进行了好几个漫长世纪的竞争，每一种树每年都散播数以千计的种子；昆虫与昆虫之间的竞争——昆虫、蜗牛，还有其他动物与食肉鸟兽之间——所有生物都竞争着增加数量，而且所有生物都彼此以对方为食，或者以树木或树木的种子与幼苗为食，或者以首先在这片土地上生长因而抑制了树木生长的其他植物为食！向天空撒一把羽毛，羽毛就会按照明确的法则落到地上，但是这个问题与无数动植物的作用与反作用相比，与它们在数百年时间里决定了如今长在这片昔日的印第安废墟上的树木之数量和种类相比，又是何等简单！

19.一种生物依赖另一种生物而生存，如寄生虫之于其猎物，这种现象一般发生在自然界等级上相距遥远的生物之间。严格地说，在彼此斗争以求生存的生物之间，如蝗虫与食草的四足动物，是时常发生这种现象的。但是，同物种个体之间的竞争几乎不可避免地是最严酷的，因为它们常去同一地区、需要同样的食物并且暴露于同样的危险之中。在同一物种的各品种间，这种竞争一般来说几乎是同样严酷的，而且我们有时看到争夺很快就决出胜负：例如，如果将好几个小麦品种一起撒播，再将这些混合的种子再次撒播下去，那么最适应土壤与气候、或者天生最能繁殖的若干品种就将打败其他品种，从而结出更多的种子，因此在几年之后便在相当程度上取代其他品种。要想保持即使像各种颜色的香豌豆这样极其接近品种的混合品系，就必须每年分别收割，然后将种子按适当比例混合，要不然比较弱的种类就会在数量上稳步下降并且消失。说到羊的品种也是一样：人们曾经断言，某些山区品种会使其他的山区品种饿死，所以不能把它们放在一起饲养。将不同品种的医用水蛭养在一起也会得到同样的结果。如果让人类家养的植物或动物像在自然状态下那样进行竞争，而且每年不去拣选种子或幼仔，则它们的任何品种是否还能具有如此完全同等的力量、习性与构造，使得某个混合品系原先的比例可以保持6代之久，这甚至是值得怀的。

20.同属的物种通常在习性和构造方面也有若干类似之处——尽管决不总是这样——而且在结构方面永远如此；同属的物种如果彼此竞争，一般来说会比截然不同的属内各物种之间的竞争更加剧烈。我们看到，最近某种燕子在美国一些地方扩大了生存范围，致使另外一种燕子数量减少。近来，在苏格兰某些地方槲鸫增多，致使歌鸫数量减少。我们有多少次听说，在极其不同的气候条件下，一种老鼠取代了另外一种老鼠！在俄罗斯，小型亚洲蟑螂到处驱逐同属的大型蟑螂。野芥子的一个物种取代了另一物种，在其他例子中也是如此。我们隐约知道，在自然结构中占据着几乎相同位置的近似物种之间，为什么竞争是最剧烈的；但可能是，我们永远都不能确切说明，为什么在伟大的生存竞争中一个物种战胜了另外一个物种。

21.从以上的叙述可以得出具有极其重要意义的推论，那就是，每一种生物的结构是以最本质、却又时常是隐藏方式与所有其他生物的结构有关联的，一种生物与其他生物为了食物或栖息地进行竞争，或者从其身旁逃脱，或者以其为食物。这种情况在老虎的爪与牙的结构上是显而易见的，在附着于虎毛的寄生虫的腿与钩爪上也是明显的。但是，在蒲公英美丽的羽状种子和龙虱扁平而生有排毛的腿上，这种关系似乎第一眼看上去只与空气和水有关。然而羽状种子的优势无疑在于它与已经密布着其他植物的土地最密切地相关；因而蒲公英的种子可以广泛散落到空地上。龙虱的腿很适合潜水，得以与其他水生昆虫竞争，获取猎物并能逃脱其他动物的追捕。

22.许多植物在种子里贮藏营养物质，一眼看来与其他植物没有任何关系。但是如果这些种子（例如豌豆和蚕豆）撒播到深草之中，出土幼株茁壮成长，我推测，种子里这些营养物质的主要用途是有利于幼苗的成长，同时与周围生长茂盛的植物进行竞争。

23.看看生长在分布范围中央的植物吧，它的数量为什么没有翻一番或者两番呢？我们知道它完全能经得住稍热或稍冷、稍湿或稍干的环境，因为它的分布范围能延伸到其他略为热一点或冷一点、潮湿一点或干燥一点的地方。在这种情况下，我们能够清楚地看到，如果我们在想象中希望赋予这种植物增加数量的能力，我们就必须给以超过其竞争者的若干优势，或者超过以其为食的动物的若干优势。在其地理分布范围内，与气候有关的构造变化对于我们的植物显然是一种优势；但是我们有理由相信，只有很少几种动植物延伸到相当遥远的地方，但仅仅是严酷的气候就能使之归于毁灭。不到生命的极端疆界，如北极地区或纯粹沙漠的边缘，竞争是不会停止的。土地也许极其寒冷或者干燥，但少数物种之间，或者同一物种的个体之间，为了争夺最温暖或最湿润的地点而进行竞争。

24.所以我们也可以看到，如果某种植物或动物被安置在新的地方、处于新的竞争者之中，尽管气候也许与其以前所在的地方完全一样，但它的生活条件一般来说将发生本质的变化。如果我们希望它在新的生息地增加数量，那我们就必须以不同于我们在其本土应该做到的方式来改变它；因为我们应该赋予它以某种优势，以胜过一批不同的竞争者或敌人。

25.因此，试图在我们的想象之中赋予某种形式以胜过另一种形式的一些优势，这样的意愿是良好的。我们很可能无法举出哪怕一个例子，以便于我们知道该做什么才能获得成功。这就使我们确信，我们对所有生物的相互关系一无所知；这是一种必要的信念，因为要获得这种信念似乎是困难的。我们所能做到的是，时刻记住：每一种生物都在努力以几何比率增加；每种生物在其生命的某一时期、一年中的某一季节、每一世代或间隔期间，都必须进行生存竞争，还要遭受巨大的毁灭。当想到这种竞争的时候，我们或许可以用充分的信念来安慰自己，即自然界的战争不是无休无止的，任何恐惧都是感觉不到的，一般说来死亡是迅速的，而强壮、健康和幸运的生物则可生存下去并繁衍后代。

理论上的难点

1.想必读者早在读到本书的这一部分之前，已为许多无法解释的难点困扰许久了。其中有些的确是非常严肃的难题，我到现在想起来仍不免踌躇；不过根据我的判断，其中大部分不过是表面上的难题，而且我认为，即使那些真正的难点也不足以判定我的理论就是错误的。

2.这些难点和异议可以分为以下几类：首先，如果物种是经由无法察觉的渐变从其他物种延伸下来的，为什么我们并没有随处见到无数的过渡类型呢？为什么整个自然界并非一片混乱，而是如我们看到的这般界限分明？

3.其次，举例来说，如果某种动物具有蝙蝠的结构与习性，是否可能是由习性完全不同的某种动物经过变异形成的呢？我们是否可以认定，自然选择一方面可以产生一些基本无用的器官，像长颈鹿的尾巴不过是用来赶走苍蝇等昆虫的困扰；而另一方面，却又能够发展出如眼睛这样构造奇妙的器官，我们至今仍然难以完全理解那种无法仿效的完善性？

4.第三，本能可以通过自然选择获得并改进吗？引导蜜蜂建造蜂巢的神奇本能，事实上出现在深奥的数学发现之前，对此我们该作何置评？

5.第四，物种杂交时不育或产生不育的后代，而品种杂交时生殖能力不受损害，又该如何解释？

6.本章将讨论前两个问题——本能与杂交将在单独的章节中加以论述。[21]

7.关于过渡品种的缺失或罕见。由于自然选择的结果仅仅体现在保留有利变异中，在一个物种丰富的大陆，每一种新类型往往会取代并最终灭绝那些发展不够完善的亲种，或者在竞争中处于不利地位的其他类型。因此正如我们所看到的，自然选择的发生始终伴随着灭绝过程。如此说来，如果我们将每一个物种看作是由某种其他未知形式发展延续而来的，那么一般来说，其亲种和所有过渡品种都必然会在新类型的形成和发展完善过程中逐渐灭绝。

8.但是，既然根据这一理论，自然界必定曾有无数的过渡类型存在过，那么，我们为什么没有发现有大量过渡物种包埋在地壳里呢？【……】对此我只能说，我认为问题的答案主要在于地质学记录要比一般想象的贫乏得多；记录的缺陷主要是由于有机生物并非生活在海洋深处，还因为只有当它们被包埋在足够深厚广泛的大量沉积物中，才能长期抵御未来的大量剥蚀，其残骸才能够嵌在地下保存至未来的某一年代；这类含有化石的团块状物质，只有在堆积着大量沉积物、缓慢下沉的浅海底才能够累积起来。这些偶然事件同时发生的情况极其少见，其每次发生的间隔时间也极为漫长。在海底静止或上升时期，或者几乎没有什么沉积物储存下来时，我们的地质史上就是一片空白。地壳是个巨大的博物馆；然而自然界藏品的收集是非常缓慢的，其间跨过漫长的岁月，相隔久远。

9.但是仍有人极力主张，好几个彼此近似的物种栖息在同一地域时，即使在现在，我们也的确应该看到许多过渡类型。举一个简单的例子：如果从北到南穿越一块大陆，我们一般会在连续的各段旅程看到彼此近似或者有代表性的物种，显然，这些物种在这片大陆的自然结构中几乎占据着相同的地位。这些代表物种往往会相遇或发生关联；随着其中一个物种越来越稀有，另一个物种就越来越常见，直到彻底取代前一个物种。但是，如果我们比较一下这些混合的物种，一般来说，它们的构造完全不同，就像从两个物种的核心栖息地选取的两个标本一样。根据我的理论，这些相似物种是从同一个亲种衍生来的；在其变异的过程中，每一个物种都会逐渐适应所在地区的生存条件，并取代和灭绝最初的亲种，以及将其自身的过去和现在连接起来的所有过渡品种。因此我们不应该指望如今能够在每个地区看到许多过渡品种，尽管它们的确曾经存在于斯，且可能以化石的形式嵌进那里的地壳。然而如果是这样的话，为什么在具有过渡生存条件的中间地带，我们如今也无法找到关联紧密的中间型品种呢？这个难题也困扰了我很久，不过我觉得它大体上是能够解释的。

10.首先，我们在推论时一定要极为小心，不能因为一个地区现在是连续的，就想当然地认为它在过去很长一段时期以来就一直是连续的。地质学或许会引导我们相信，即使是在距离我们最近的第三纪晚期，几乎每个大陆也都曾经被分裂为多个岛屿；而在这些岛屿中，彼此全然不同的物种或许根本就是各自形成的，不可能有过渡品种存在于中间地带。由于陆地形状和气候的变迁，现在看来连续的海域，即使距离我们最近的地质时期，也多半远远不是现在这样连续和齐整的状态。不过我还是不要采取这样一条避开难题的取巧做法；因为我相信，许多界定鲜明的物种都是在完全连续的地区形成的；尽管我毫不怀疑，某些以前是断裂的、而现在看上去是连续的陆地，在新物种的形成过程中起到了非常重要的作用，对于那些自由杂交和漫游的动物来说尤其如此。

11.观察一下现在分布于某一广大区域的物种，我们一般会看到，它们在大片地带存在的数量繁多，而到了边界地带就会突然变得越来越少，直到最后彻底消失。因此，相对于其各自本身存在的地带来说，两个代表物种之间的中间地带往往较为狭小。在登山时会看到同样的情况，正如阿方斯·德·堪多的观察结果所示，有时一个普通的高山物种会突然消失，这是相当引人注目的。福布斯[22]在用捞网探测海洋深度时，也曾注意到同样的事实。对于那些认为气候或生存的物质条件是物种分布的首要因素的人来说，这些事实无疑会令他们感到吃惊，因为气候也罢，高度或深度也罢，都是不知不觉地逐渐改变的。然而如果我们还记得这样一个事实：每一个物种，即使是在其本身栖居的核心地带，如果不是因为其他竞争物种的存在，其数量都会大大增加，直至难以计数；几乎所有的物种要么捕食其他物种，要么被其他物种所捕食；简言之，每种生物都会直接或间接地与其他生物有着极为重要的联系，那么我们就必定会明白，任何地方的栖居生物的范围大小绝不仅仅取决于逐渐发生微小变化的物质条件，而是在很大程度上取决于其他物种的存在，它依赖于该物种，或者为该物种所毁灭，或者与之竞争；且由于这些物种已经界限分明地存在（不管这是如何发生的），并没有通过无法察觉的渐变而混淆在一起，任何一个物种的栖居范围，由于它需要取决于其他物种的栖居范围，都会倾向于有明确的界线。此外，在栖居范围的边界上生活的每一个物种，由于在该处数量较少，随着天敌或捕食物的数量上下浮动，或随着季节的变化，极易完全消失，因此它的地理范围也就更容易界限分明。

12.相似物种或代表物种居住在一片相连地区时，一般来说，其分布情况都是各自栖居在一片较大的范围，中间的中立地带相对比较狭窄，在这片中立地带，它们的数量会突然越来越少；如果我的这种看法正确，那么，由于各品种与这些物种本身没有本质区别，同样的规则大概也适用于各品种；也就是说，如果我们在想象中将一个逐渐变异的物种分布在一个很大的地区，我们应该将其中两个品种分布于两个较大的地带，而将第三个品种分布在一个较为狭窄的中间地带。这样一来，该中间型品种因为生活在一个狭小的地带，其数量也相对较少；事实上据我了解，这一规则完全适用于自然状态下的各品种。我遇到过明显的例子可以证明这一规则，在界定分明的藤壶属物种的各个品种之间的中间型品种就是一例。沃森[23]先生、阿萨·格雷博士和沃拉斯顿[24]先生向我提供的材料表明，一般来说，两个物种类型中出现中间型品种时，该中间型品种的数目要比与其所关联的那两个物种类型少得多。因此，如果我们确信这些事实和推断，并就此得出结论，即与其他两个品种相关联的品种，其数目一般都少于它所关联的物种，于是我们就可以理解为什么中间型品种不应持续存在很长时间——为什么一般说来，它们应该比其最初关联的物种更快地灭绝和消失。

13.如前所述，任何数目较少的物种类型被灭绝的风险都要大于现有数目较多的类型；而在目前这种特殊情况下，中间类型显然极易受到两边紧密相连的物种类型的侵害。然而在我看来，一个远为重要的考虑因素是，根据我的理论，两个品种可能会通过进一步变异，转变并完善为两个截然不同的物种，在此过程中，两个因为栖居于较大区域而数目较多的物种必然要比中间型品种有更大的优势，后者存在于较为狭小的中间地带，数目也相对较少。这是因为在任何特定时，存在数目较多的物种类型总要比数目较少的较稀有物种类型更有机会产生更多有利的变异来适应自然选择。因此，在生存竞争中，物种类型越普遍，就越能够打败并取代较不普遍的类型，因为后者的变异和改善过程更加缓慢。据我所信，正是这条原则能够解释，为什么在每一个地区，普遍的物种【……】平均来说，都要比相对稀有的物种能够出现更多具有显著特征的品种。我可以举例说明我的意思，假设需要保持3个绵羊品种，第一种生活在广袤的山区；第二种生活在相对狭小的丘陵地带；第三种以山底广阔的平原作为其栖居地。假设这3个地区的居民都有同样的决心和技巧，希望通过选种来改良羊群品种；在这种情况下，拥有大量羊群的山区或平原的居民的机会更多，因为他们要比生长在中间的狭小丘陵地带的少量羊群饲养者更快地改善其品种。因此改良后的山区或平原品种不久就会取代改良较慢的丘陵品种。这样一来，起初数目较多的那两个品种就逐渐密切接触，因为已经被取代的中间型丘陵品种不会再夹在两者中间了。

14.总之，我认为，各个物种逐渐发展成为界限较为分明的生物，而不会在任何一个时期因为不断变异的中间环节而呈现出无法解决的混乱状态：首先，因为新品种的形成非常缓慢，变异是一个非常缓慢的过程，只有等到更有利的变异个体碰巧产生，且只有等到该地区的自然结构中的某个空位可以被某一个或多个栖居生物的某些变异后代所占据，自然选择才能发挥作用。这样一个空位置的产生取决于气候的缓慢变化，或者某种新的栖居生物偶然迁徙至此，或者更重要的是，很可能取决于某些原有栖居生物正在慢慢变异，变异过程产生的新类型和原有类型正在互相发生作用和反作用。因此，在任何一个地区或任何一个时期，我们只能看到少数几个物种呈现出微小的结构变异，且这些变异在某种程度上是稳定而持久的；这的确是我们看到的情形。

15.其次，现在相连的地区，在距离我们不远的地质时期往往必定存在相互隔离的部分，其中许多物种类型，特别是每次生育都需要结合和漫游甚广的那些类型，或许已具备不同于其他物种的特点，足以成为代表物种。在这种情况下，好几种代表物种与其亲种之间的中间型品种，过去一定在这片大陆的各个分离的区域中存在过，不过这些环节后来在自然选择的过程中被取代和灭绝，因此它们不会再继续存活。

16.第三，如果两个或两个以上的品种是在全然相连地区的不同区域形成的，那么这些中间型品种很可能首先在中间地带形成，不过一般来说，它们存在的时间都比较短。这是因为，由于我们已经指出的原因（也就是根据我们所知道的密切联系的物种或代表物种的实际分布情况，以及公认品种的实际分布情况），这些中间型品种在中间地带存在的数量要少于与它们有联系的那些品种的数量。仅仅这一个原因就有可能导致中间型品种濒临灭绝；在通过自然选择进一步发展变异的过程中，这些品种几乎必定要被与其相关联的物种类型所打败和取代；因为总的来说，这些数目较多的物种类型的品种更多，因此可以通过自然选择进一步变异，从而获得更多的优势。

17.最后，如果我的理论是正确的，那么展望整个历史时期、而不是通过任何一个单独的时期，可以确信一定有与同一种群的所有物种联系最密切的无数中间型品种曾经存在过；但是正如我们在上文中反复提到的，自然选择的过程本身往往会不断地灭绝那些亲种类型或中间环节。因此，其过去曾经存在过的证据只能在化石残骸中找到，这些残骸的记录【……】极不完善且极不连贯。

18.论具有特殊习性和构造的生物的起源和过渡。对我所持有的学说提出异议的人总是会问这样的问题，例如，一种陆栖食肉动物怎么可能是由一种具有亲水习性的动物转变而来的？因为这样一来，处于二者之间的过渡状态的动物如何生存？这很容易证明，因为同一种群的食肉动物中存在有各种中间级别，从真正的水栖习性到严格的陆栖习性，不一而足；由于每一种中间动物都必须为生存而竞争，显然，每种动物所呈现出的习性都已经适应了其所生存的自然地域。北美的美洲水貂（Mustela Vison）就是一例，这是一种蹼足动物，软毛、短腿和尾巴的形状都很像水獭；夏季，这种动物潜入水中捕食鱼类，而在漫长的冬季，它会离开冰冷的水域，像其他鼬鼠科动物一样捕食老鼠和陆栖动物。如果举另外一个例子，询问一只食虫的四足动物怎么能转而变为能飞的蝙蝠，问题就要复杂得多，我目前也无法给出确切答案，不过我觉得解决这样的难题意义不大。

19.面对这类问题以及其他一些理由，自然会让我处于严重不利的局面，因为在我所收集到的许多明显个例中，我只能举出一两个例子证明同一属中密切相关的物种的过渡性习性和构造；以及同一个物种的多样化习性，无论是永久性的还是偶然生成的。要让我解释任何特殊的个例，诸如解决以上关于蝙蝠的难题，我似乎一定要收集一长串关于过渡状态的实例才行，否则就不足以减少其中的困难。

20.看一看松鼠科的动物吧；它们的渐变种类繁多而精细，有些松鼠的尾巴仅仅是稍呈扁平状，而另一些则正如J.理查森[25]爵士所说，身体后部相当宽阔，两肋的皮肤开张得相当充分，这样渐变下去，一直到所谓的飞鼠；飞鼠的四肢乃至尾巴的根部由一片广阔的皮肤连在一起，其作用就像降落伞一样，足以让飞鼠们从这棵树滑翔到那棵树上，两棵树之间的距离让我们人类望而惊叹。我们确信，每一种构造对于生活在其所在地域的每一种松鼠而言都是有用的，它们使得松鼠可以逃离禽类或兽类的捕食，或者更快地收集食物，或者——我们有理由相信——降低其偶尔从树上跌落的危险。不过这样的事实并不导出以下结论，即每一种松鼠的构造都是其在所有自然条件下所能够发展的最佳构造。如果气候和植被条件发生变化，如果与之竞争的其他啮齿动物或新的食肉动物迁徙到此，或者原有的此类物种发生变异，所有这类情况的发生都可能使我们相信，至少会有一些松鼠的数量会减少甚至灭绝，除非它们也已经相应地进行了变异或在构造上有一定的改善。因此我觉得这个问题不难理解——在生存条件不断发生变化时尤其如此——那些两肋皮膜越来越张大的个体将继续保留下来，每一次变异都是有用的，都会传衍下去，直到这一自然选择过程的累积结果最终产生了构造完美的所谓飞鼠。

21.接下来再看看鼯猴属或者飞狐猴，以前人们把它们错误地归为蝙蝠类。它有极为宽阔的胸膜，从下颚的两角一直延展到尾巴，把生着长趾的四肢也包含在内，这种胸膜还生有伸肌。尽管目前找不到什么适合在空中滑翔的渐变结构的环节将鼯猴属动物与其他狐猴科动物联系起来，但我觉得不难推断出这类环节是曾经存在过的，每一种构造的发展过程都和不够完美的飞鼠的发展变异过程无异；每一级构造对于其主体来说都是有用的。我也找不出有什么无法超越的障碍阻止我们进而认为，鼯猴属动物那以膜连接起来的趾甲和前臂之所以那么长，大概多半也是自然选择的作用；而就飞行器官来说，也正是自然选择将这种动物变异成蝙蝠的。蝙蝠的翼膜从肩头一直延伸至尾巴，将后肢也包含在内，我们或许能够从中看出一些痕迹，这个器官最初构造的目的不是为了飞行，而是为了滑翔。

22.如果大约一打鸟类都灭绝了或者再也不为人所知，又有谁敢冒险推断像大头鸭（Micropterus of Eyton）一样将翅膀仅用来击水的鸟儿；或者像企鹅那样在水中将翅膀用作鳍、在陆地将翅膀用作前腿的鸟儿；像鸵鸟那样把翅膀用作风蓬的鸟儿；以及像几维鸟那样，翅膀根本没有什么功能的鸟儿或许真实地存在过呢？然而在其栖息的各种生存条件下，上述每一类鸟儿的构造对其本身都是有益的，因为每一种鸟都需要依靠竞争来生存；不过该构造并不一定是所有可能的生存条件下所能具有的最佳构造。我们决不能根据这些话贸然推断说，这里所讲的各个级别的翅膀构造（它们可能都是弃用的结果）表明了鸟类获得完善的飞行能力所经历的每一个自然步骤；不过它们至少能够表明，多种多样的过渡方式是完全可能的。

23.看到像甲壳动物和软体动物这些在水中呼吸的物种中有少数成员可以适应陆地生活；看到飞鸟、飞兽和各种类型的飞虫，以及先前曾经存在过的飞爬虫，可以想象，如今那些在空中滑翔很远、依靠鳍的拍击而稍稍上升和旋转的飞鱼，大概也可以变成有着构造完善的翅膀的动物。如果真是这样的话，谁又能想象，在先前的某一个过渡时期，它们曾经是栖居在大洋中的物种，而且据我们所知，那时它们那原始的飞行器官的唯一作用是为了逃脱其他鱼类的吞噬？

24.当我们看到那些为了任何特殊的习性而高度完善的构造，例如鸟类为飞行目的而发展完善的翅膀时，必须铭记，显示出这些构造的早期过渡级别的动物很少能够存活到现在，因为它们已经在通过自然选择进行的发展过程中被取代了。此外，我们可能会得出这样的结论，即为适应截然不同的生命习性而产生的这类构造，其中间过渡级别很少能够在早期还存在有许多从属类型时大量发展完善。那么让我们回到飞鱼那个假想的例子，真正会飞翔的鱼能够以多种方式在陆地和水中捕食猎物，直到它们的飞行器官达到很高的完善程度，使得它们能够在与其他动物进行生存竞争时具备决定性优势，这样的动物似乎多半不会是从许多从属的类型中发展出来的。因此发现有着过渡性构造的物种，即使是发现这些物种的化石状态，也并非易事，因为相对于那些有着发展完善的构造的物种来说，它们生存的数目较少。

25.接下来我要举两三个例子说明同一物种的不同个体具有不同习性或习性发生改变的情况。上述两种情况之任何一种发生时，自然选择很容易通过其构造的某种变异让个体动物适应其发生变化的习性，或专门适应好几种不同习性中的一种。不过我们很难说——这个问题也不重要——一般来说是习性先发生改变，构造后发生变化呢，还是构造的轻微变异引发习性的改变；二者往往很有可能几乎同时发生改变。关于习性改变的情况，我们只需举出一个例子就足以说明问题，许多英国昆虫现在靠外来植物，或只靠人造食物存活。而关于多种不同习性的情况，我们可以举出无数的例子：我在南美洲常常观察一种霸鹬（Saurophagus sulphuratus），它像红隼那样在一个地方的上空盘旋，随后又飞往另一个地方，有时则静静地立在水边，然后像翠鸟一样冲入水中捕食鱼类。在英国，有时可以看到大山雀（Parus major）几乎像旋木雀一样攀行枝上；有时又像伯劳鸟一样啄击小鸟的头部，将其杀死；我曾多次看到和听到它在树枝上击打紫杉的种子，像五子雀一样把它们敲碎。赫恩[26]曾经在北美看到黑熊在水中游泳好几个小时，大张着口，像鲸鱼一样捕捉水中的昆虫。即使在像这样的极端情况下，如果不断有昆虫供应，且如果该地区尚没有适应性更好的竞争者的话，我倒觉得通过自然选择，熊类的构造和习性很有可能越来越亲水，它们的嘴越来越大，最终变成一种像鲸鱼那样的庞然大物。

26.我们有时会看到同一物种中不同个体的习性与其本身物种以及同一属的其他物种的习性截然不同，根据我的理论，此时我们或许会认为，这类个体有时会产生新的物种，它们有着类似的习性，相对于其本身所属的物种类型，它们的构造要么呈现出些许改变，要么呈现出很大变异。在自然界中，这样的例子的确屡见不鲜。我们能否给出一个更具说服力的适应自然的例子，而不仅仅是攀爬树木并从树皮的裂缝里捉捕昆虫的啄木鸟呢？然而在北美洲的确存在着大部分时间都依靠水果存活的啄木鸟还，有一些有着很长的翅膀，便于追逐有翅膀的昆虫；在拉普拉塔的平原地带没有一棵树，那里却生长着这样一种啄木鸟，它身体组织的每一个主要部分，甚至它的颜色、它刺耳的鸣叫、高低起伏的飞行，都显示出与我们常见的啄木鸟有着密切的血亲关系；然而那确实是一种从不攀爬树木的啄木鸟！

27.海燕是最擅飞行的海洋鸟类，然而在火地群岛[27]的恬静海峡间生长着一种水雉鸟（Puffinuria berardi），它的一般习性、惊人的潜水能力、游泳的样子以及被迫起飞时的飞翔姿态，都会让人误以为那是海雀或朧鷉；然而它在本质上的确是海燕，只不过组织构造的许多部分都已经发生了显著的变异。另一方面，最敏锐的观察者也无法通过仔细检验河乌的尸体而发现它有半水栖的习性；然而这种与严格陆栖性鸫科近似的鸟儿却完全以潜水为生——它在水中使用翅膀，用两爪抓握石子。

28.认为每一种生物在创造出来时就是我们今天看到的样子的人，他一定有时会感到奇怪，因为他经常会遇到一种动物的习性与其构造完全不一致。鸭子和鹅的蹼脚的构造是为了便于游泳，没有什么比这更显而易见的了；然而有一种产于高地的鹅也生有蹼脚，它们却很少或者根本不去水边；除了奥杜邦[28]一人之外，没有人看见四趾都有蹼的军舰鸟停留在海面上。另一方面，朧鷉和海番鸭显然是水栖的，它们的脚趾却只是四周包裹着一层膜而已。涉水禽类长趾的形成就是为了在沼泽地和浮水植物上行走，似乎也没有什么比这更明显的了，然而水鸡几乎和海番鸭一样是水栖性的；而秧鸡则几乎和鹌鹑或山鹑一样是陆地生物。在这类例子中——我们还可以举出很多这样的例子——动物的习性发生了改变，而构造却没有相应发生变化。有人或许会说，高地鹅的蹼脚在功能上已经退化成未成熟的状态，而其构造却并非如此。军舰鸟趾间深凹的膜表明，这种构造已经开始发生变化。

29.认为创造行为是独立和不计其数进行的人会说，这些例子只能说明造物主喜欢创造一种生物来取代另一种生物；不过在我看来，这不过是用庄严的语言重述事实罢了。笃信为生存而竞争以及自然选择原则的人会承认，每一种生物都在不断努力地增加数量；同时也认为，任何一种生物只需在习性或构造上作出一点点改变，就能够获得所在区域的某些其他栖居生物所没有的优势，这样它就能够占有该生物的领地，不管那个领地和它自己所占有的地域有着多大的不同。这样，此人就不会在看到以下现象时感到奇怪：世界上竟有生有蹼脚的鹅或军舰鸟生活在干燥的陆地上或几乎很少在水面上停留；世界上竟有长脚趾的长脚秧鸡生活在草地上而不是沼泽中；有些啄木鸟生长在没有树木的地方；还有会潜水的鸫，以及具有海雀习性的海燕。

30.极度完善和复杂的器官。如果说眼睛这种能够调整不同的焦距、能够接受不同数量的光、能够校正球面和色彩像差、完美得无可比拟的构造是由自然选择形成的，我坦白承认，连我自己都觉得这样的说法非常荒诞。然而理性告诉我，如果我们能够证明，在从非常完美和复杂到非常不完美和简单的眼睛之间，的确曾经存在过无数过渡类型，而每一种过渡类型对其拥有者来说都是有用的；进而如果眼睛的变异非常微小，并且这些变异是能够遗传的（事实的确如此）；如果该器官的任何变异或改进曾经为某种生存条件正在发生变化的动物带来了有益的结果，那么我们很难再否定眼睛这样一个完善而复杂的器官是由自然选择形成的说法，尽管这无论如何都超出了我们的想象。一种神经如何能够感受到光，这个问题和生命最初的起源一样，不属于我们的研究范围；但是我可以说，若干事实让我怀疑，是否任何敏感的神经都会感受到光；同样，是否任何敏感的神经也都会感受到产生声音的空气的粗糙振动。

31.寻找任何物种的某种器官在发展完善的过程中经历的分级过渡时，我们应该单独观察其直系祖先；然而这几乎是不可能的，因此我们不得不在探讨每一个此类器官时都去观察同一种群的不同物种，也就是观察有着共同的原始亲本的多个旁系，以便观察在发展完善的过程中可能存在哪些分级，这样也有机会看到，某些分级是从变异阶段的初期遗传下来的，没有发生变化或者只发生了微小的变化。在现存的脊椎动物中，我们发现该物种眼睛的构造只经历了少量分级，而从化石状态的物种中我们对此一无所得。就这一大纲的动物来说，我们大概应该在已知的最底化石层以下很深处去发现其早期的发展阶段，此时，眼睛这种器官多半已经发展完善了。

32.在关节海百合亚纲的动物中，我们可以去观察一系列仅仅包裹着色素层、却不带有任何其他机能的视神经；从此低级阶段开始，我们可以发现该构造无数的中间级别通过两条迥然不同的方向不断发展完善，直至达到一种还算高的完善程度。例如，某些甲壳类动物就具有双层角膜，内层角膜分裂成多个小眼面，每个小眼面内都有一个透镜状的鼓胀部位。其他甲壳类动物则只有色素层包裹的透明锥形细胞，这些锥形细胞只能通过阻止两侧的光束才能发生作用，其上端凸起，必须通过聚光方能行使眼睛的功能；其下端似乎存在着不完全的玻璃样物质。目前这些事实的数量极其有限，我们的观察结论也不够完善，然而它们的确表明现存甲壳类动物的眼睛存在着渐变的多样性，此外还须铭记，和已经绝种的动物数量相比，现存动物在数量上可谓微不足道，我实在看不出人们为什么就是不能够相信：是自然选择把仅仅包裹着色素层和透明膜的视神经这样一种简单机能，转变成任何关节海百合亚纲的动物都拥有的高度完善的视觉器官（许多其他构造的情况也别无二致）。

33.如果相信这一点的人在读完本书后发现，大量以前无法解释的事实都能够通过遗传理论进行解释，那么此人就应该毫不犹豫地进一步承认，即使像鹰眼这样一种高度完善的构造也可能是由自然选择形成的，尽管就鹰眼这种具体情形来说，人们对任何过渡级别都一无所知。理性无论如何应该战胜想象，只是我痛感这一定非常困难，所以看到有人对于将自然选择原理进行如此深远的延伸有任何程度的踌躇，我一点儿也不觉得奇怪。

34.人们很难不把眼睛比作一架望远镜。我们知道，这种仪器的完善是人类最高智力不断努力开拓的结果；因此我们也就很自然地推断出，眼睛的形成也经历了一个差不多相同的过程。但是这样的推论不是太武断了吗？我们有什么权利想当然地认为，造物主也是以人类那样的智力来创造万物的呢？如果我们必须将眼睛比作某种光学仪器的话，我们不妨想象这样一块厚厚的透明组织，其下有一个感光神经，继而假设这层透明组织每一部分的密度是不断缓慢变化的，从而分离成密度和厚度截然不同的地方，彼此之间的距离有长有短，每一层表面的形状也呈现出缓慢变化。进而我们必须假设，有一种力量始终密切注视着这些透明层的每一个微小的偶然变化；并且细心挑选每一种变化，这种精心挑选的变化在不断发生改变的情形下可能以任何方式或在任何程度上产生比较明显的图像。我们必须假设，这种器官的每一种新的状态都以成百万倍的速度增长着；每一种都被保留下来，直到一种更好的状态产生，之后原有的状态就彻底消失了。在生物体内，变异可能导致微小的变化，生殖繁衍会使这些变化几乎无限地倍增，自然选择将通过无比精准的技巧筛选出每一次改进。这种过程持续几百万年，其中每一年都有许多种类的成百万生物个体经历这种过程；难道这还不足以使我们相信，一种生物体的视觉器官的形成要比玻璃光学仪器的制造过程更为复杂和精密，就像造物主的成就要比人类更为高妙？

35.如果能够证明，任何曾经存在的复杂器官是不可能通过无数延续的微小变异形成的，我的理论自然绝对不能成立，不过我实在找不出这样的例子。毫无疑问，对于现存的许多器官而言，我们并不知道其过渡的中间级别，那些十分孤立的物种更是如此，根据我的理论，这些物种周围的物种类型有许多都灭绝了。或者当我们注意观察某个大纲内所有成员共有的一种器官时也是如此，因为在这种情况下，该器官最初一定是在极为久远的年代形成的，自那以后，该物种类别的许多成员都经历了发展变化；为了发现这种器官经历过的早期过渡级别，我们必须观察极古的师祖类型，可是这些类型早已灭绝。

36.我们必须十分谨慎，决不能轻易断言某种器官不可能是经由某些过渡类别发展形成的。可以有无数低等动物的例子来说明同样的器官能够同时行使全然不同的机能；如蜻蜓的幼虫和泥鳅，它们的消化管兼具呼吸、消化和排泄等机能。又如水螅，这种动物可以把身体内部翻到外面来，使外表面行使消化功能，而胃行使呼吸功能。在这类情形下，如果能够从中得到任何好处的话，自然选择也许就会很轻易地将某一个行使两种机能的部位或器官变得只行使一种机能，这样一来，经过不知不觉的步骤，就彻底改变了这种部位或器官的性质。在同一个体中，有时会有两个完全不同的器官同时行使同一种机能；举例来说，有些鱼类能够用鳃呼吸溶解在水中的空气，同时用鳔呼吸游离的空气，鳔有一个气管向它供给空气，又被血管密集的隔膜分成不同部分。在这种情况下，两个器官中的一个受到另一器官的辅助而很容易地发生变异并发展完善，从而独立行使所有相关机能；继而另一器官大概也会因为某个其他的特殊目的而发生变异，或者就此消失。

37.鱼类的鳔是一个很好的例子，因为它清楚地向我们展示出这样一个极为重要的事实，即一种原本为某种目的（即浮游）而生成的器官完全可能转变成为了另一个全然不同的目的（即呼吸）而存在的器官。某些鱼类的鳔所行使的机能又是作为听觉器官的附件，或者听觉器官的一部分所行使的机能是辅助鳔，我不清楚如今哪一种观点更被普遍接受。所有的生理学家都承认，鳔这个器官的位置和构造都与更为高级的脊椎动物的肺同源，或“理论上相似”。因此在我看来，认定事实上是自然选择将鳔转变为肺或者专门行使呼吸功能的器官，实在不是什么难事。

38.的确，我很难怀疑一切有真肺的脊椎动物都是从同一种具有浮游器官或鳔的古代原始型代代相传而来的，我们对这种原始物种类型一无所知。因此，正如我根据欧文[29]教授对这些器官的有趣描述中所推断出来的结论，我们能够理解咽下去的每一点食物和饮料都必须经过气管开口这一奇怪事实，虽然那里有一种美妙的装置可以使声门紧闭，但食物还是有落入肺部的危险。在较高级的脊椎动物中，腮已经完全消失了——然而在这类动物的胚胎中，颈部两旁的狭长开口和动脉的环状曲线仍然向我们显示出这正是腮先前所在的位置。但可以想象，现在已经完全消失的腮也许被自然选择逐渐利用于某个极为不同的目的：某些博物学家认为，环节动物的气管和背壳与昆虫的翅膀和翅鞘是同源的，在很早以前一度用作呼吸的器官实际上很可能已转变成飞翔器官了。

39.在考虑器官过渡的问题时，我们必须铭记机能转变的概率，我试举一例来突出这一点的重要性。有柄蔓足类动物（pedunculated ciipedes）有两个很小的皮褶，我把它叫作“保卵系带”，它用分泌粘液的方法把卵保持在一起，直至卵在袋中孵化。这些蔓足类动物没有腮，它们使用整个身体表面和卵袋（包括那个很小的系带）来行使呼吸功能。另一方面，藤壶科即无柄蔓足类动物（cirripedes）却没有保卵系带，卵松散地置于袋的底部，外面包裹着密封的壳；但它们却生有大而褶皱的腮。我想现在不会有人再质疑这一科动物的保卵系带和那一科动物的腮是严格同源的，事实上它们是相互逐渐转化生成的。因此我毫不怀疑那些起初作为保卵系带但同时又起到轻微的辅助呼吸作用的小皮褶，是通过自然选择逐渐转变为腮的，转变的过程也很简单，不过是形状逐渐增大、粘液腺最终消失。如果所有有柄蔓足类动物都灭绝了——相对于无柄蔓足类动物，它们的灭绝情况的确要严重得多——谁又能想象到，后一科动物的腮最初的功能是为了防止卵被冲出袋外呢？

40.尽管我们必须极为谨慎，不可贸然断定没有哪一种器官可能通过连续的过渡分级过程产生，毫无疑问，我们面对的一些实例的确很难解释，我将在以后的著作中讨论其中的某些实例。

41.最难解释的实例之一是无性昆虫，它们的构造往往与雄虫和能育的雌虫截然不同【……】。鱼类的发电器官则是另一个非常难以解释的例子；我们无法想象，这些奇异的器官究竟是经过哪些步骤生成的，然而正如欧文等人所说，它们的内部结构与常见的肌肉的结构非常相似；最近的研究显示，鳐鱼有一个器官和发电器官非常类似，但是正如马泰乌奇[30]所断言，鳐鱼的这种器官并不发电，我们必须承认目前人类还太过无知，无法断言其间不可能存在任何一种过渡类型的器官。

42.这些发电器官还向我们提出了另一个更为严肃的难点；因为它们只出现在大约十多种鱼类的体内，其中几种在亲缘关系上相距甚远。一般来说，如果同一种器官出现在同一科的好几种动物身上，特别是这些动物的生活习性截然不同时，我们可以认为，其存在的原因是它们拥有一个共同的祖先；而同一科的其他动物没有这种器官则可以归因于弃用或自然选择的结果。然而如果发电器官是从某一古代祖先那里继承而来的，我们大概会认为，所有能够发电的鱼类彼此之间都有着特殊的亲缘关系。地质学也根本不会导出这样的结论，认为以前大多数鱼类都有发电器官，而许多经过变异的后代却丧失了该器官。少数分属于不同科目的昆虫体内会有发光器官，这一事实也同样成为本理论中的难点。还可以举出其他例子；例如在植物中，红门兰属和马利筋属植物都有一个相同的奇怪装置，在末端有一种粘液腺的花梗上生有花粉块——在开花植物中，这两个属的植物可谓亲缘关系相去甚远。在所有两个全然不同的物种显然生有同一种类似器官的例子中，我们应该看到，尽管该器官大致的外形和功能或许相同，但一般来说，我们还是能够发现一些根本的不同之处。我倾向于认为，就像有时两个人各自独立作出了完全相同的发明一样，自然选择为了每种生物各自的好处，并且利用相似的变异，有时也会使两种生物各自的部位发生非常相似的变异，而这两种生物在结构上几乎没有什么是遗传自同一祖先的共同之处。

43.尽管在许多情况下我们很难推测出一种器官经过了什么样的过渡才达到现有的状态；然而考虑到现存和已知的物种类型只占已经灭绝和未知类型的很少一部分，让我感到诧异的倒是我们很难说出有哪个已知器官不是经过多个过渡级别发展而来的。博物学中的那句经典格言——“自然界里从无飞跃”，就能够证明我这句话并非妄言。几乎每一个经验丰富的博物学家的著作中都会承认这一点；或者，米尔恩·爱德华兹说得好：自然界种类繁多却创新不足。那么，根据创世说，为什么会这样呢？如果说许多独立生物的所有部位和器官都是为了其本身在自然中的特定位置而单独创造出来的，又为什么所有这些部位和器官普遍被分阶段的诸多步骤连接在一起？为什么自然界不采取从一种器官到另一种器官的飞跃？根据自然选择理论，我们显然能够理解自然界为什么不采取这样的飞跃；因为自然选择只能通过微小的延续性变异起作用；它根本不可能飞跃，而只能通过极为微小而缓慢的步骤前行。

44.缺乏明显重要性的器官。由于自然选择是通过生命和死亡起作用的——发生任何有利变异的个体被保留下来，发生任何不利的构造变异的个体被无情地毁灭——有时我会觉得，我们很难理解简单部位的起源，其重要性似乎不足以导致有着延续性变异的个体被保存下来。而有时像眼睛这样一个完善又复杂的器官也会让我觉得难以理解，尽管在这方面，这个例子和上述情况全然不同。

45.首先，我们对于任何一种生物的全部结构的知识都太过缺乏，因而无法说出什么样的微小变异可能是重要的或是不重要的。在上一章，我曾举出过一些微小性状的例子，例如果实上的绒毛和果肉的颜色，由于这些性状能够决定昆虫是否会来攻击，或与构造性差异相关，它们也许确实能受到自然选择的作用。长颈鹿的尾巴看上去就像人造的苍蝇拍；说它适于现在的用途是经过连续、微小的变异，每次越来越好的变异都更适合于像赶掉苍蝇那样的琐事，乍看起来似乎令人难以置信；然而即使在讨论这样的实例时，我们也要多加考虑，因为我们知道，在南美洲，牛和其他动物的分布和生存完全取决于其抗拒昆虫攻击的力量：因为任何个体只要可以任何方式防避这些体积微小的敌人，它就能漫游到新牧场，从而获得巨大优势。这并不是说这些庞大的四足动物实际上会被苍蝇消灭（除了一些很少的特例），而是它们的体力因不断受到骚扰而降低，因而较易得病，或在饥荒到来的时候不能有效地找寻食物或逃避食肉兽的攻击。

46.如今看来没有什么重要性的器官，在某些情形下，大概对于早期的始祖类型十分重要，这些器官在以前一个时期的缓慢完善之后，虽然现在已经极少有用了，仍以几乎相同的状态传递给现存的物种；任何事实上有害的构造变异都将不可避免地被自然选择所抑制。看到尾巴在大多数水栖动物身上是何等重要的运动器官，大概就可以解释为什么这种器官普遍存在于众多陆栖动物（从肺或变异了的鳔可以证明它们的水栖起源），以及它的多种用途了。某一种水栖动物有了一个发展完善的尾巴，它后来或许会被用于所有不同的目的，用来拂蝇，用作抓握的器官，或者像狗尾一样作为转弯的辅助器官，尽管其辅助作用一定很小，因为野兔虽然几乎没有什么尾巴，却仍然能够加倍迅速地急转弯。

47.第二，我们有时会认为某些独立于自然选择之外的性状具有重要意义，而实际上这些性状都起源于相当次要的原因，也并不重要。我们应当记得，气候、食物等很可能会对生物的构造产生某些直接的小影响；性状再次出现是由于回复突变的法则；生长的相关作用对于各种结构的变异过程可能有极其重要的影响；最后，性选择时常会在很大程度上改变那些有性意愿的动物的外部性状，给予雄性个体与其他雄性争夺或吸引雌性的优势。此外，由于上述或其他未明原因导致的结构变异，虽然在起初对于一个物种并没有什么优势，此后却会被其经过变异的后代在新的生存条件下和新获得的习性中加以利用。

48.下面我试举几个例子来证明以上结论。如果现存的啄木鸟只有绿色的，而且我们不知道还有许多黑色和杂色的啄木鸟，我敢说，我们应该会以为它之所以呈现绿色，是为了完美地适应自然界，这样一来，这些频繁往来于树木之间的鸟就能够在敌害面前隐蔽自己；因此我们就会认为这是一种重要的性状，也许是通过自然选择获得的；事实上，我毫不怀疑，这颜色是由于某些极为不同的原因而获得的，很可能应该归因于性选择。马来群岛上生长着一种矮竹，它借助丛生在枝端、构造精致的钩，攀缘高高耸立的树木，这种钩型构造对于该植物无疑极为有用；但是我们在许多非攀缘性树木上也看到了极相似的钩型构造，因而这种矮竹上的钩可能起因于某些未知的生长法则，后来就被正在经历进一步变异并发展攀缘性的植物加以利用了。秃鹫裸露的头皮一般被认为是为了直接适应其大量吞食腐败物质的习性而生成的；也许是这样，或者可能应归因于腐败物质的直接作用；但是当我们看到食用清洁饲料的雄火鸡的头皮也这样裸出时，就应该慎重一些，不该再妄下此类推论了。幼小哺乳动物的头骨上的缝曾被认为是为了很好地适应其辅助分娩的作用而生成，毫无疑问这一构造的确能够方便分娩，或者也许它还是分娩所必需的；但是，幼小的鸟和爬虫不过是从破裂蛋壳里爬出来的，而它们的头骨也有缝，所以我们可以推想这种构造的发生应归因于某些生长法则，只不过高等动物是在分娩时利用了这一构造。

49.对于产生轻微变异和次要变异的原因，我们真是极度无知；只要考虑一下不同地区家畜品种间的差异——特别是在文明程度较低的国家，还极少施用人工选择——就会立刻意识到我们对这一问题的无知。仔细观察者会认定，潮湿的气候会影响毛发的生长，而角又与毛发有关。高山品种与低地品种之间总是有这样那样的差异；多山的地方很可能对生物的后腿有影响，因为那样的地形迫使生物对后腿的使用较多，甚至骨盆的形状也可能因此受到影响；于是，根据同源变异的法则，该生物的前肢乃至头部也很可能受到影响。此外，骨盆的形状还可能会通过压力而影响到子宫中幼仔的头部的形状。我们有某些理由相信，在海拔较高处必须费力呼吸以增大胸腔；也会导致一系列的相关反应。各个国家的野蛮人所饲养的动物往往不得不为自己的生存而竞争，而且可能会在某种程度上受到自然选择的作用；构造稍有不同的个体在不同的气候条件下可能最易获得成功；我们还有理由相信，构造和生物的颜色是彼此相关的。同样，据一个细心的观察者陈述，牛对于蝇的攻击的敏感性，犹如对于某些植物的毒性的敏感性，也与其体色相关；所以生物的颜色也可能是自然选择作用的结果。但是我们实在所知甚浅，无法推测若干已知和未知的变异法则的相对重要性；我这样说只是要表明，虽说我们一般都认为家养品种的性状差异一般是遗传下来的，但是既然我们连这些性状差异的具体原因都无法解释，也就不必斤斤计较于人类为什么不能了解物种之间类似的微小差异究竟是什么原因所造成。为了同样的目的，我可以接引人种之间非常明显的差异；我还可以对这些差异的起源略加说明，我认为它们主要是通过某一特定的性选择而产生的，但如果不引用大量细节，我的推理就显得毫无意义了。

50.以上论证使我就一些博物学家最近提出的异议多说几句，这些博物学家反对功利说，即生物构造的每一细节都是为了其所有者的利益而产生的论点；他们认为，许多构造都是为了人类眼中的美感，或者只是为了多样性的存在而产生的。如果这种学说是正确的，绝对会对我的学说造成致命的影响。不过，我完全承认许多生物构造对其拥有者的确没有什么直接用途。物质条件很可能会对生物构造产生一些微小的影响，这与生物因此而获得的任何好处全然无关。生长相关性无疑也会起到非常重要的作用，某个部位的一个有用的变异常会引发其他部位多种变化，而这些变化往往没有什么直接的用途。因此同样，某些以前有用、或曾经起因于生长相关作用或其他未明原因的性状，可能就由于回复突变的法则而重新出现，不过现在它们已经没有什么直接用途了。性选择的作用体现为吸引雌性的美感时，可以勉强称之为有用。但是重要得多的考虑是，每一种生物的构造的主要部分都只是遗传而来的；因此，虽然每一种生物的确能够很好地适应在自然界中的位置，当前有许多构造与各个物种的生活习性并没有任何直接的关系。这样一来，我们很难认定高地鹅或军舰鸟的蹼脚对它们有什么特别和用处；也不能认为生长在猴子的臂、马的前腿、蝙蝠的翅膀以及海豹的鳍脚中的同样骨骼对于这些动物有什么特别的用处；倒是可以很稳妥地把这些构造都归因于遗传。但是蹼脚对于高地鹅和军舰鸟的祖先和如今大多数现存水栖鸟类无疑一样是有用的。因此我们可以认为，海豹的祖先并不生有鳍脚，却生有五个趾的脚，适于行走或抓握；我们还可以进一步大胆地认为：猴子、马和蝙蝠的四肢内的几根骨头遗传自这些生物的共同祖先，这几根骨头对于这个祖先或祖先的祖先曾经有特殊的用途，而对于这些现存的习性截然不同的动物而言，其用途自然就不那么明显了。所以我们可以推论：这几根骨头可能是通过自然选择而获得的，其过程需要遵从遗传、回复变异、生长相关作用等法则，这一点直到如今也是一样。因此，现存的每一种生物的每一个结构上的细节（物质条件的直接作用除外）都可以看作是对于某些始祖类型具有特殊用处，或者如今直接或间接地通过各种复杂的生长法则而对该类型的某些后代具有特殊的用途。

51.自然选择不可能使任何一个物种产生全然有利于另一个物种的任何变异；虽然在整个自然界中，任何一个物种都不断利用并得益于利用其他物种的构造。但是自然选择能够而且的确时常产生出直接有害于别种动物的构造，如我们所看到的蝰蛇的毒牙，以及姬蜂的产卵管——依靠它就能够把卵产在其他活昆虫的身体里。如果能够证明任何一个物种的构造的任何部位全然是为了有利于另一个物种而形成的，那就可以彻底击溃我的理论，因为这样的构造不可能是通过自然选择产生的。虽然在博物学的著作里可以找到许多大意如此的叙述，但我找不到哪怕一个在我看来有任何分量的说法。人们承认，响尾蛇的毒牙是用来自卫和杀死猎物的；但某些作者假定它同时拥有对自己不利的响器，这种响器会发出警告，使猎物逃跑。如果是这样的话，我几乎马上就要认定，猫每每准备纵跳时卷动尾端，竟是为了警告它注定要捕食的老鼠。限于篇幅，我在这里不再就此类实例逐一赘述。

52.自然选择从来不会使一种生物产生对自己有害的任何构造，因为自然选择是完全根据并且为了各种生物的利益而起作用的。正如佩利[31]曾经说过的，没有一种器官的形成是为了给予其拥有者苦痛或损害。如果公平地权衡由各个部位所引发的利与害，我们就可以看到，从整体来说，每一个部位都是有利的。随着时间的推移，在不断变化的生存条件下，如果任何部位变得对生物个体有害，那么它就必须要变异；不然这种生物就会灭绝，无数已经灭绝了的生物就是这种情况。

53.自然选择只会使每一种生物与栖息于同一地方、与之展开生存竞争的其他生物一样完善，或稍微更加完善一些。我们还看到，这就是在自然状态下所能达到的完善程度。例如，新西兰的各种本土生物与彼此相比都是同样完善的；但是在人们从欧洲引进大量先进的植物和动物之后，这些生物显然立即表现出落后和不足。自然选择不会产生绝对的完善，就我们的判断来说，我们也不曾在自然界里遇见过这样高的标准。据高级权威称，就算对于人眼这样近乎完美的器官来说，对光线像差的校正也是不完善的。如果说理性引导我们热烈地赞美自然界里许多天衣无缝的生物构造，那么理性也同样告诉我们（尽管我们在这两方面都很容易犯错误），某些其他构造并没有那么完美无缺。我们能够认为黄蜂或蜜蜂的刺针是完善的吗？刺针刺完敌害以后，因为有倒生的锯齿而无法抽回，蜂的内脏就会被拉出，必然导致死亡。

如果我们认为蜜蜂的刺针在遥远的始祖类型中已经存在，和这个大目里的许多成员的情形一样，原本是穿孔用的锯齿状构造，后来为了现在的目的而变异但却没有发展完善，它的毒素原本用于产生树瘿，后来才变得强烈起来——我们大概就能理解为什么刺针会如此经常地引发这种昆虫自身的死亡：因为如果从整体来看，针刺的力量对于整个蜂群是有用的，它就可以满足自然选择的一切需求，尽管它可能会导致少数成员的死亡。如果我们赞叹许多雄性昆虫依靠绝对奇异的嗅觉能力去寻找雌性昆虫的本领，那么，只为了生殖目的而产生的成千上万的雄蜂，对于蜂群没有任何其他用处，因而最终被它们勤劳而不育的姊妹们弄死，对此我们也要赞叹吗？也许很难说这是自然界的完美杰作，不过我们还是应当赞叹蜂后那野蛮而本能的仇恨，这种仇恨促使它在幼小的蜂后——它的女儿们刚出生的时候就把它们弄死，或者自己在这场战斗中死亡；因为这对蜂群无疑是有好处的；母爱抑或母恨（幸而后者非常罕见），在自然选择的无情法则面前没有区别。我们赞叹红门兰属植物和许多其他植物的若干巧妙构造，植物们依靠那些构造通过昆虫的力量来受精，那么看到杉树所产生的密云般的花粉只有少数几粒能够碰巧吹送到胚珠上去，我们也要认定它们同样完美无缺、巧夺天工吗？

结论

1.【……】我们之所以自然地不愿意承认一个物种产生了其他截然不同的物种，主要是因为当我们看不到中间步骤的时候，总是迟迟不愿承认任何巨大变化的发生。莱尔最初坚称，狭长的陆地岩壁和巨大河谷的形成都是由于海洋波浪的缓慢作用时，那么多地质学家对此说法难以接受，其感受想必也是一样的。人类的智力可能理解不了亿万年期间的全部意义，也不能将许多微小的变异相加并且察觉其全部效果，要知道这些微小变异可是在几乎无限的世代间积累起来的。

2.虽然我深信本书以摘要形式提出的观点都是真实的，但我决不指望能够说服诸位经验丰富的博物学家，因为他们的脑子里早已装满了大量事实，而长期以来，他们对这些事实所持的固有观点则与我的理论截然相反。人们总是很容易用诸如“创造计划”“设计一致性”之类的词语来掩盖自己的无知，只是换一种说法重述事实就想象自己作出了解释。任何人，只要他的性情使他更重视未经解释的难点，而不关心我已就某些事实提出的解释，就必定会反驳我的理论。少数几位博物学家脑袋比较灵活，而且已经开始对物种的不变性产生怀疑，他们可能会受到本书的影响；然而我对未来以及正在崛起的新一代博物学家充满信心，相信他们一定能够公正地看待问题的两面。无论是谁，只要他受到引导，相信物种是可变的，并负责任地表达出自己深信的观点，就是为人类作出了贡献；因为只有这样，人们才能够逐渐抛弃对本书主题所持有的如许偏见。

3.有几位杰出的博物学家最近出版著作，认为每个属里都有许多公认的物种其实不是真正的物种；不过其他物种是真正的物种，也就是说，是被独立创造出来的物种。在我看来这是一种奇怪的结论。他们承认，有许多物种类型——直到最近他们自己才改变观点，此前一直都认为这些是造物主的特殊作品，且绝大多数博物学家至今也仍是这样看待它们的，现在他们认为这些物种类型具有真正的物种所具备的所有外部性状特征——这些博物学家承认这些类型是由变异产生的，但是他们拒绝将同样的观点延伸到只有相当微小差异的其他物种类型上去。纵然如此，他们并不谎称自己能够定义甚或推测哪些物种类型是造物主的创造，哪些又是次级法则产生的。他们承认变异在某一情形下是真实原因，在另一种情形下却武断地驳斥这个观点，又不指明这两种情况有何区别。总有一天，这些会被人们当作古怪的例子来表明先入为主的想法是多么盲目。这些作者对奇迹般的创造似乎司空见惯，看到普通的生育倒倍感震惊。但是他们真的相信，在地球历史无限漫长的时期，会有某些元素的原子因为得到命令而突然变成活的组织吗？他们真的相信人类假想的每一个创造行为都会产生一个或许多个体吗？所有的动植物究竟是以卵或种子的形式，还是作为完全长成的个体被创造出来的？而且以哺乳动物而论，难道它们是带着虚假的营养标志从子宫里被创造出来的？博物学家们严格要求我们这些相信物种易变性的人对每一个难点作出充分解释，这一点虽然无可厚非，但在他们自己这一方阵地，这些人却总是以一种在其看来高高在上的沉默，全然无视物种第一次出现的情形这一课题。

4.有人可能会问，我究竟要把物种变异的学说扩展到多远。这个问题很难回答，因为我们可能考虑的类型越是孤立独特，这些论据的说服力就越弱。但是某些分量最重的论据可以扩展得很远。整个纲的所有成员都可以通过亲缘关系链联系在一起，而且所有成员都可以根据同样的原则进行分类，所有类群层层分级。化石遗迹有时可填补现存纲目之间很大的空白。某些生物生有未发展完善的器官，这明白无误地表明，其早期祖先拥有充分发展的器官；在某些情形下这必定暗示其后代发生过极其大量的变异。整个纲里各种生物的构造以同样的方式形成，不同物种在胚胎时期竟极为相似。这些使我毫不怀疑后代变异的学说必定囊括了同纲的所有成员。我认为动物最多是从4个或5个始祖繁衍而来的，而植物的始祖数目也差不多，或者更少。

5.以此类推，我还可以更进一步，即认为所有动植物都是从某一个原始祖先繁衍下来的。但是类推法很可能误导。纵然如此，所有生物都有共同之处，要么是它们的化学构成，要么是它们的胚胞，要么是它们的细胞结构，要么是它们生长与繁殖所遵循的法则。我们甚至在一个极为无足轻重的情况中也能看到这一点，那就是同一种毒质时常会对动植物有类似的影响；或者五倍子虫分泌的毒质会导致野玫瑰或橡树畸形生长。因此我应该根据类推作出如下推断：很可能在地球上生存过的所有生物都是从某一个原始类型传下来的，正是从那一刻开始了生命的第一次呼吸。

6.我们能够隐约地预见到，一旦本书所持的关于物种起源的观点或者类似观点得到广泛承认，博物学就会发生一场深刻的革命。分类学者将如现在这样继续孜孜不倦地分类；但是他们再也不会经常被怀疑的阴影所笼罩，怀疑这种或那种类型本质上到底是不是物种。根据经验，我可以肯定，这可不是微不足道的安慰。人们终于可以停止那无休止的争论，探讨大约50种英国悬钩子到底是不是真正的物种。分类学家将只需决定（这也不容易）任何类型是否足够持续并截然不同于其他类型；以及它们的存在是否界定分明，与其他类型的差异是否足够重要，值得称之为物种。后一个问题将比现在远为重要；因为任何两个类型之间的差异不论多么微小，如果没有与中间等级相混合，则大多数博物学家仍会认为这足够将其分列为不同的物种。此后我们将被迫承认：物种与明显品种之间的唯一区别是，人们知道或者认为明显品种目前是由中间等级联结起来的，而物种则是以前就这样联结起来的。因此，在不排斥任何两个类型之间目前存在中间等级这个概念的前提下，我们倾向于更加仔细掂量它们之间实际上到底有多大差异，并予以更多重视。很有可能现在一般仅被承认为是品种的类型此后认为应该冠以科学名称，如樱草花和黄花九轮草；这样，科学语言与通俗语言将趋于一致。总之，我们将不得不以与博物学家对待属的方式来看待物种，博物学家认为，属只是为方便起见而产生的人为合并方式。这可能不是令人高兴的前景；但是我们至少将从此摆脱无用的学术桎梏，不再徒劳地探求物种这个术语未经发现和不可发现的本质。

7.博物学其他更具普遍性的分支的趣味性将大大增加。博物学家所用的术语如亲缘、关系、类群、父系、形态学、适应性状、退化和发育不全的器官等等，将不再是比喻用法，而将具有明白无误的含义。如果我们不再像野蛮人看轮船一样看待生物，认为它们完全超出了我们所能理解的范围，如果我们认为自然界的每一种生物都有自己的历史；如果我们认为每一种复杂构造与本能都是各自对于拥有者有用的许多构造和机能的集大成，几乎就像我们把任何伟大的机械发明都看作劳动、经验、理性乃至许多工人所犯错误的集成一样；如果我们这样看待每一种生物，那么，我凭经验说，博物学研究将远比现在有趣得多！

8.一个极重要的、几乎未经前人涉足的探索领域将被开拓出来，研究变异的原因与法则、生长的相关性、使用与不使用的效果、外部条件的直接作用，等等。对家养生物进行研究的重要性将大大增加。人类培育的新品种将成为一个研究课题，远比在已有记载的无数物种中新增一个物种重要和有趣得多。我们的分类将尽可能逐渐成为系谱；到那时就能够提出真正的所谓“创造计划”。如果我们有明确的目标，分类的规则无疑将变得更加简单。我们没有任何家谱或纹章，因而不得不凭借久已遗传下来的任何性状去发现并追踪自然系谱中许多不断分歧的世系线。未经完全发展的器官将绝对无误地显示出久已灭失的生物构造的本质。称为异常、又可夸张地称为活化石的物种与物种群将帮助我们对古代生物类型形成一个大致的概念。胚胎学将向我们揭示出每一个大纲内原始类型中多少已被弃用的构造。

9.如果我们能够确定：同一物种的所有个体，以及多数属内所有关系密切的亲种，都是在并非相当遥远的过去某个时期从同一个祖先遗传下来的，并且是从某个诞生地移徙到这里的；如果我们根据地质学现有且还将不断更新的有关气候与地层变化的知识，更好地了解移徙的多种方式，那我们肯定就能以绝妙的方式追踪栖居于世界各地的生物以前的移徙情况。即使在目前，通过对某个大陆两边的海洋生物之间的差异进行比较，对在该大陆栖居的各种生物的性质与其迁入手段进行相关研究，我们就能够获得一些古代地质学的知识。

10.地质学这门高尚学科因其记录极其不完善而失去了光辉。一定不要把地壳及嵌在地壳里的遗迹看作内容充实的博物馆，它们只不过是随便、偶然积累起来的贫乏收藏。每一块含化石的遗迹的积累应被看作是诸多情况非同寻常的巧合，各个连续阶段之间的空白间隔也是极其漫长的。但是我们应该能够通过对先前和之后的生物类型进行比较，较为稳妥地衡量这些间隔的持续时间。我们必须十分谨慎，不能随意试图根据生物类型的一般演替，就将两个包括少数相同物种的地层归为严格意义上的同时期地层。物种是由于至今仍然存在的原因缓慢产生和灭绝的，不是奇迹般的创造行为或巨大灾难的结果；生物变化的所有原因中最重要的原因几乎完全独立于物质条件（这些物质条件已经变更而且也许是突然变更的），乃是生物与生物之间的相互作用——某种生物的改进引发其他生物的改进或消灭；由此得出结论：连续地层内化石中的生物变化量很可能是实际时间流逝的一种公平的量度标准。然而，作为一个整体群居生活的若干物种也许长时期不变，而与此同时，这些物种中的几种因为迁入新地区并与不相关的本地生物展开竞争，也许就会发生变异；所以我们一定不要过高评价生物变异在衡量时间方面的准确性。在地球历史的早期，生物类型很可能较少且较为简单，变异的速率很可能也比较缓慢；在地球生命曙光初现的时刻，只有少数几种构造极为简单的生物类型，变化的速率很可能极其低下。如我们目前所知，整个世界的全部历史虽然有很长一段时间是我们很难理解的，今后却会被看作仅仅是一个时间段，毕竟相对于自从第一个生物，即无数已经灭绝和仍然存活着的后代的那个祖先来到世间之后的漫长岁月，那的确只是一段短暂的时期。

我看到在遥远的将来，必定会有远为重要的、开放的研究领域。心理学将以全新的基础为依据，即每一种智力与能力都是按顺序分阶段获得的。关于人类起源与人类历史，也将不断有全新的发现和观点。

12.最出色的作者似乎能够在每个物种都是单独创造出来的这个观点中得到最充分的满足感。在我看来，世界上过去和现在的生物的产生与消失应该是由于一些次要原因，诸如决定个体的出生与死亡的那些原因，这样的观点更符合我们所知道的“造物主”在物质上留下印记的法则。当我不再把所有生物看作特殊的创造物，而看作在志留纪第一层沉积下来以前很久就生活在地球上的少数几种生物的直系后代时，在我看来，它们只会变得更加高贵。以过去来判断，我们可以放心地推论：没有一个现存的物种会把它未经改变的外表传递到遥远的未来。而在现存的生物之中，很少会有哪一种生物会把任何一种后代传到极其遥远的未来；因为所有生物聚合成群的方式表明，每个属内的大多数物种，以及许多属内的所有物种，都没有留下后代，而是已经完全灭绝。迄今我们能够展望未来而预言，最终胜出并且繁衍出新的优势品种的，将是那些隶属于较大的优势种群中常见且分布广泛的物种。既然所有现存生物都是志留纪以前很久就生活在地球上的生物的直系后代，我们就有把握认为，普通的世代演替从来没有中断过，而且任何灾难也不会使世界变成一片荒芜。因此我们可以怀着一定的信心展望未来，我们有把握的未来在漫长历史时期中也同样微不足道。既然自然选择是完全根据每一种生物的利益并且为了它们的利益而起作用的，所有生物在物质与精神方面的天赋都将不断发展，趋于完善。

凝视一片错综复杂的河岸，河岸上覆盖着许多种类的许多树木，鸟类在灌木中啁啾，各种昆虫飞来飞去，蚯蚓在湿润的泥土中蠕动；细想一下，这些结构精巧的类型彼此如此相异，以如此复杂的方式彼此依赖，又都是由在我们周围起作用的法则所产生的，这实在非常有趣。这些法则就其最广泛的意义来说，就是伴随繁殖的生长；繁殖几乎总是意味着遗传；变异的起源既是外界生活条件的间接和直接作用，也是使用和弃用；繁殖比率如此之高，必将导致生存竞争，而作为自然选择的一个结果，必将引发性状分歧和改进不大的类型的灭绝。如此看来，自然战争、饥馑与死亡的直接结果，就是我们能够想到的最高尚的目的，即高等动物的产生。这样一种对于生命的看法是庄严的：生命及其好几种能力最初是被注入少数几种甚或一种生物类型中的；就在这个行星根据固有的重力法则始终不断地运行的同时，生命竟从如此简单的开始而不断发展，且至今仍在继续繁衍出无数最美丽、最奇妙的类型。

译者导读

约翰·斯图亚特·密尔（1806—1873）是英国哲学家、政治经济学家、政府文官，最富影响的19世纪思想家之一。他的父亲，英国历史学家、经济学家、功利主义哲学家詹姆斯·密尔按照约翰·洛克的认识理论，从密尔童年时期就对他进行了严格的教养。密尔是个早慧的天才。据其自传，他3岁开始学习古希腊语；8岁时已经熟读了大量古希腊和古罗马典籍，学习了代数、物理学和天文学等自然科学知识；12岁时即通晓经院和亚里士多德的逻辑学；13岁时接触到政治经济学，与父亲共同研究了经济学家亚当·斯密和大卫·李嘉图的经济学，协助父亲创建了古典经济学中的生产要素论。密尔在成长过程中，与李嘉图、功利主义哲学家杰里米·边沁、法国政治经济学家让·巴蒂斯特·萨伊、法国空想社会主义者圣西门、法国社会学家奥古斯特·孔德等当世英杰过从甚密，在思想的频繁交流中获益良多。作为不信奉英国国教的新教徒，密尔没有资格进入牛津大学与剑桥大学读书，于是随父亲到东印度公司任职，并在非宗教高校伦敦大学学院接受了教育。在大学期间，他受到了英国法学家约翰·奥斯丁的思想影响。1851年，他与哈莉特·泰勒结束21年的恋爱长跑，步入了婚姻殿堂。聪慧无双的泰勒对密尔影响很大，她包括妇女权利在内的许多思想都在密尔的著作中得以体现。

密尔著述颇丰，覆盖哲学、政治、经济等多个领域，重要著作有《逻辑体系》（1843年）、《政治经济学原理》（1848年）、《论自由》（1859年）、《论代议制政府》（1861年）、《功利主义》（1861年）、《女性的服从》（1869年）等。其中，《论自由》是其哲学代表作。

《论自由》讨论了个人在宗教信仰、思想、言论、个性等方面的自由，研究了社会对个人可行使权力的性质和界限，明确提出了“多数人的暴政”这一振聋发聩的名言，和“人类无论作为个人或集体，只有出于自卫这唯一目的时，才能干预任何人或人群的行动自由”这一鲜明论点。全文篇幅不长，但思想深刻、视域辽阔，引人入胜；且旁征博引、前后相贯、逻辑严谨、条理清楚、论说明晰。例如，他信手征引了苏格拉底、耶稣、奥勒留大帝、路德等宗教改革家，洪堡、卢梭、斯坦利勋爵、摩门教等古今人物与教派的事迹，列举了食物禁忌、禁酒令、婚姻契约、妇女权益、社会和政府干涉等现实问题，涉及英、法、德、美、俄、中、印度等多个欧洲、美洲、亚洲国家，使本文既具历史的深刻，又具有现实之锋芒。密尔剖析问题时，十分注重多方辩证，使全文读来底气丰沛而思路细密，兼备学者的严谨学风、文学家的生动文采与演说家的敏捷辩才。因此，该书问世以来，影响广播，深受历代读者推崇，跻身经典名著之列。

自清末严复《群己权界论》问世以来，《论自由》已有多种汉译本。按照恩师辜正坤先生“筛选积淀重译论”的内在要求，笔者本应尽数搜罗更逐一研读，多方借鉴而去粗取精，以图继承创新、递进提高，创造出最佳近似原作的译作。惜因多种缘故，未能充分实现。近些年来，在不同译论视角的解构风潮下，百多年前的严复译文数遭诟病。然而，严复翻译此书距密尔原著出版隔不过40年，称得上去古未远，其中西学养亦未必输于今人后学，故此，其译文中虽不免杂有清末的时代噪音，但对密尔之论点与文风的把握，是足以信赖的。笔者在翻译过程中，每遇疑词难句，除多方查阅当世资料之外，亦将拙见考校于严复译文，以求义理精审，兼向先贤筚路蓝缕之功致敬。

此外，笔者曾将书中部分章节的汉译作为课程作业，在河北大学2012级和2013级翻译硕士专业学位研究生“人文社科文献翻译”课堂上进行研讨推究。研究生们各具千秋的理解和译文也对笔者有所启发，在此一并致以谢忱。

最后，密尔原著中个别地方用词过简，或句法过于繁复，逻辑关系缴绕，笔者虽尽力剖解、前后引衬，仍恐译文中有表意不清甚或理解谬误之处。叩请方家不吝赐教。

谨将此书献给我挚爱的、悲痛追忆中的她——我的贤妻益友。是她启发并与我共同创作了我作品中的所有精彩华章。她崇高的真理心与正义感给予我最强劲的激励，她的嘉许是对我最宝贵的奖赏。本书同我多年写出的所有其他作品一样，是我们二人的共同心血。但是，书稿中只有很少部分极其幸运地经她亲手润正，某些最重要的部分本准备请她细加审阅，而今已永无可能了。无数伟大的思想与高贵的情感已随她而长眠地下，倘若我能向世人传述其中的半数，必将令他们受益良多；她的睿智旷世无匹，失去了她的激励与帮助，我的所思所作何足同等裨益世人？！

“这些书页上展现的每句论述都辐辏于一条伟大的主导原则：让人类任意地多样化发展，这一点绝对至关重要。”

——威廉·冯·洪堡

《政府的权限与责任》

一　序言

本文所论并非所谓的“意志自由”——那个不幸与误称为“哲学必然性”的学说相对立的东西，而是“公民或社会自由”，即：社会以何种性质、在何种限度内对个人实施权力才算正当。关于这一问题，尚无人概述及或浮泛而论，但其隐性存在却深深影响着当前的种种现实论争，并将很可能迅速成为未来的关键问题。这一问题绝非新生事物，在某种意义上，人类几乎自诞生之初就被它分裂为不同群体。然而，人类中相对文明的群体如今已进入了新的发展阶段，在新阶段、新形势下，公民自由问题浮现而出，需要人类提出更具实质性的新对策。

自由与威权的斗争是我们熟悉的某些历史阶段的最显著特征，在古希腊、古罗马和英国历史上尤其如此。不过，古代的斗争是臣民或臣民中某些阶层与政府之间的斗争。自由意味着受到保护，免遭政治统治者的暴政之害。统治者们（古希腊某些平民政府中的统治者除外）被认为与其治下的民众必然相互对立。他们或是居于统治地位的个人，或是一个部族或阶级；其威权或由继承而得，或借征服获取。他们的权柄绝非民众可任意予夺，只要有可防范其强权镇压的法子，民众便不会冒险或许也并不愿去争夺他们的尊位。统治者的权力被视为不可或缺但也极其危险之物，是一种既可用以对抗外敌亦可毫不犹豫地对抗臣民的武器。若要防止鹫群中的弱小成员惨遭众秃鹫捕杀，则需委派一只最为强悍的秃鹫做首领，以制伏其他秃鹫。然而，秃鹫王之嗜好劫掠鹫群，绝不亚于那些劲量略小的凶鹫，所以必须永远警惕其尖喙与利爪。故此，那时爱国志士的目标就是为统治者设定权限，防止其对民众滥施权力；这种设限行为就是他们意谓的自由。设限方式有两种：第一，获得统治者对某些名为政治自由或政治权利的承认。统治者若侵犯这些自由或权利就是渎职，他若果真悍然侵犯，那么民众进行某种抵制甚或全民造反就属合理合法。第二，确立宪法作为制约手段。总体而言，这一方式发生较晚。据此，统治者若想采取某些较为重要的行动，必须先征得民众或被认为代表着民众利益的某个组织的同意。大多数欧洲国家的统治者都或多或少地被迫服从于第一种设限方式，但并未服从第二种方式。使第二种方式奏效，或者在其已部分奏效的情况下使其完全奏效，就成为各国自由爱好者的主要目标。只要人类满足于靠一个敌人对抗另一个敌人，满足于接受某个主人的统治——前提是他多少可以有效地保证不对他们实施暴政，他们便别无祈望。

但是，在人类事务的发展进程中，出现了这样一刻：人们意识到，由与自己利益对立的他者充当统治者，并非天然法则。他们感到，更好的办法是，应该让国家的各种官员充当他们的租户或代表，他们可以随意解约，遣散这些官员。似乎唯有如此，才能绝对确保政府权力不被滥用，他们的利益才不会受损。渐渐地，不论何处，只要存在平民政党，这种靠选举产生临时统治者就会提出新的需求，这在很大程度上取代了以前限定统治者权力的做法，成为该政党的主要奋斗目标；他们力图使统治者产生于被统治者的周期性选举。发展到后来，一些人开始认为，以前太看重限定权力本身这件事了。当统治者利益与民众利益对立时，限定其权力（似乎）只是一种权宜之计。现在所需要的是，让统治者认同民众，让统治者的利益和意志与全体国民的利益和意志合一。国家不必防范自己的意志，不必担忧其会对自己实行暴政。让统治者完全向全体国民负责，国民可以随时罢免他们，因为国民可自主决定权力的用途，所以可放心将权力托付给他们。统治者的权力正是全体国民自身的权力，这种权力高度集中，便于行使。这种想法或感觉，曾普遍出现于上一代欧洲自由主义者之中，并在今天的欧陆自由主义者中仍占主流地位。那些同意给政府——他们认为非法的政府除外——设立权限的人，在欧陆的政治思想家中显得卓尔不群。我国的形势也一度鼓舞了与这些自由主义者想法类似的论调，倘若后来情势未改，这种论调如今可能已甚嚣尘上。

然而，与人生经历一样，在政治和哲学学说中，失败可能会掩藏各种缺陷与弱点，而成功则会暴露它们。当平民政体仅存于梦想或远古历史的传闻之中时，人们无须限定自己对自己行使的权力，这种观念似乎不争自明。法国大革命之类的暂时性社会骚乱也全然没有动摇这一观念。在此观念中，那些最糟糕的骚乱乃是少数篡夺者造成的；它与大众机构的常规运作方式毫无关系，而是反对国王独裁和贵族专制的突发事件。但是，后来一个民主共和国占据了巨幅的国土，且竟然跻身世界强国之列；这一重大事实使人们开始关注和评论选举制、责任制政体。此时，世人方才意识到，“自治”、“人民对自我行使的权力”等词语并未表达事情的实相。行使权力的“人民”与作为权力行使对象的人民并不总是同一群体；所谓“自治”并非每个人自我管治，而是一切别人对他进行管治。而且，“人民的意志”实际上意味着人民当中人数最多或最活跃的群体——即多数派，或那些成功将自己打造为多数派的人——的意志。于是，人民可能会有压迫自己当中部分群体的意愿。这种情况同其他形式的权力滥用一样，都需严加防范。因此，即便掌权者要定期对全民——即其中的最强大派——负责，限定政府对个人的权力仍然至关紧要。上述主张不仅受到思想家们的支持，也获得了欧洲社会中重要阶层的青睐——因为民主政体会损害其实际利益或假定利益，顺利成为了主流观点。现在，各种政治理论已普遍将“多数人的暴政”列为社会需警惕的罪恶之一。

如同其他暴政一样，多数人的暴政主要是通过公权机构的行为实施的，从其诞生至今，令人恐惧不已。但富有思想的人们意识到，倘若社会这一集体本身即是凌驾于其每一单个成员之上的暴君，那么其暴虐手段之丰富，将绝不限于它通过其官吏所实施的那些行为。社会有能力也确实执行着它自己的种种命令：如果发出的命令并非正确，或者竟对无权插手的事情滥发号令，那么它就是在实行比许多其他政治压迫更可怕的社会暴政。这是因为，它虽然通常不以极刑威慑单个成员，却能更深刻地渗透到个人生活的方方面面，束缚住个体的灵魂，令其无可逃遁。因此，保护人们免遭官员的暴政并不足够，还需保护他们免遭主流意见和大众感觉的暴政，免遭社会的暴政：社会倾向于用民事处罚之外的手段，将自己的主张和做法当作行为规范强加于那些持异议者身上；它倾向于束缚任何与己相左个性的发展、尽可能防止这种个性的形成，并迫使所有的性格特点以社会自身为模型进行自我塑造。所以，集体意见对个人独立性的合法干预是有界限的。发现这一界限，并保护它免遭侵越，同保护人们免遭政治独裁之害一样，对维护人类事务的健康状态而言不可或缺。

然而，一般说来，虽然上述主张通常不太可能遭到反对，但把这一界限设在哪里——如何在个人自主与社会管控之间进行恰当调整，却几乎是个毫无头绪的全新问题。所有人们珍视的生存价值，都有赖于对他人行动的切实约束。因此，必须要强制实行某些行为规范；其手段首先是法律，在许多法律不适用的事项上则要借助舆论。这些行为规范应该是什么呢？这一点就成为人类事务中的重大问题。而倘若我们排除少数最显著的例子，就会发现，它乃是人类最难以解决的问题之一。没有哪个时代、哪个国家对其解决方案与其他时代、其他国家雷同；一个时代、一个国家对它的判定会令另一个时代、另一个国家大为震惊。然而，任何时代、任何国家的人们全浑然不觉其解决之难，似乎人类历来对其看法并无二致。在他们心目中，自己所建立的规程是不言而喻更自证自明的。这种几乎普遍存在的错觉便是一个例证，足以证明习俗之神奇影响。习俗不仅是谚语所说的第二天性，还屡屡被错当成了第一天性。在防止人类对彼此强加的种种行为准则产生疑虑方面，习俗的效果格外彻底。那是因为，人们普遍认为，在这一问题上，无论人与人之间，还是个人，都不需讲什么理由。人们已习惯于相信，也因为受那些向往哲学家风范的人鼓动而相信，在这类问题上，他们的感觉比推理更重要，所以推理毫无用处。指导他们形成人类行为规则的实用原则就是每个人心中的感觉：所有人都必须像他或他赞成的人所希望的那样行动。事实上，谁都不肯承认，他的判断标准只是个人偏好；一个毫无理据的、衡量某个行为的主张，只能算是个人偏好；就算他亮明了理由，倘若这些理由仅仅是唤起其他人感觉中的类似偏好，那也仍然只是许多人的个人偏好罢了。不过，对普通人而言，他获得别人支持的个人偏好不仅仅是一个完美无瑕的理由，而且是他用以判断自己所有的道义观、趣味观或得体观的唯一依据，甚至也是理解自己宗教信条的总指南，尽管他的道德观、趣味观或得体观都并未明确写入其宗教信条当中。相应地，人们对什么值得赞美、什么值得谴责的看法，是受到一切五花八门动机影响的。那些动机繁多，会潜移默化地影响人们对他人行为的期望；而他们关于任何其他事物的愿望，同样受到数不胜数的诱因的影响。这些动机有时是他们的理智，有时又是某些偏见或迷信，经常是对社群的喜爱之情，也经常是对社群的厌恶之情——羡慕或嫉妒、傲慢或轻蔑，但最通常是他们自己的各种欲求或畏惧——即他们那合法或非法的一己私利。无论哪国，只要存在某个占据支配地位的阶级，该国的道德观就会源于此阶级的阶级利益以及阶级优越感。斯巴达人与其奴隶之间、种植园主与黑奴之间、王侯与臣民之间、贵族与平民之间、男人与女人之间的道德准则，多半就是阶级利益和阶级优越感的产物。由此产生的种种是非观念又作用于该权势阶级内部成员的道德观，影响着他们彼此的关系。反观之，无论哪国，只要存在一个丧失了支配地位或其支配地位已不得人心的权势阶级，该国盛行的道德观念便往往带有对优越感不耐烦甚至厌恶的痕迹。对于已被法律或舆论强加的各种将行和缓行的行为规范，还有一大决定性原则：人类会想象其俗世主人或天上神灵之好恶，并屈己以从。人类这种奴性虽然本质上是自利的，但并不虚伪；它产生的是十足真诚的憎恶之情，驱使人们烧死了巫师和异教徒。许多恶劣因素都会影响道德观念的走势，社会那些普遍且显著的利益无疑是其中之一，而且是一大因素。然而，与其说这些社会利益本身是道德观念的产生原因，不如说它们是道德观念派生的喜恶之情所造就的结果。原本与社会利益无关的人类喜恶之情，在道德观念的建立过程中赫然突显，威力惊人。

这样，社会之好恶，或其中某强势群体之好恶，乃是实际决定道德规范的主要事物。全体成员都要遵循那些规则，否则便会遭到法律或舆论的惩罚。总体而言，那些思想和情感超前于社会的人原则上都会对此情形听之任之，但在某些枝节问题上可能与之发生抵牾。他们忙于探寻社会应对哪些事物产生好恶，而不是质疑社会之好恶应否成为个人必须遵守的法律。他们更乐意努力改变人类对他们持有异见的具体事项的看法，而不愿与其他异端分子一起，共同致力于捍卫自由。只在一件事上，他们不再单打独斗，而是依理占据了制高点且坚守始终；这件事就是宗教信仰。做此事有很多益处，尤其是它极为醒目地表明，所谓道德感是多么不可靠：一个顽固者心中“神学家之间的憎恨”是道德感表现最直白的事例之一。第一批打破自诩为“普世教会”组织之枷锁的人，通常与该教会一样，不愿容忍异己的宗教主张。而一旦冲突结束，哪一方都没有获得完胜，每个教派都会被弱化，各教派都会把期望值降低到能够维持既有的地盘就行；少数派发现没有机会变成多数派，只得恳求那些他们无法改变其信仰的人，允许他们持有不同宗教主张。这样，几乎仅仅在宗教信仰的战场上，才存在个人有权利反对社会原则的理据，才能公开驳斥社会有权管辖异见分子的说法。那些给世界带来了宗教自由的伟大作者大都坚称：良心自由是一项不可废除的权利，并彻底否定了“个人有义务向他者解释自己宗教信仰”的观点。然而，人类天生对自己真正关心的一切不容异议；除了个别宗教观念淡漠的地方，人们因厌烦神学争论而赞成宗教自由之外，宗教自由在任何国度都没有真正实现过。几乎所有宗教信仰者心中，对信仰自由义务的承认都是暗自有所保留的；即便在那些最宽容的国家，情况也是如此。有人会做到容忍教政问题上的异见，但不会容忍教义问题上的异见；有人能宽容任何人，却不能宽容天主教徒或唯一神论者；有人则能宽容任何人，却不能宽容天启教信徒；有些人宽容的程度更进一步，但是在关于上帝和来世的信仰上却又止步不前。无论何处，只要大多数人的宗教情感仍然真诚而热烈，要求全员遵从宗教的呼声就高涨不退。

相比其他欧洲国家，英国政治历史情形特殊，所以其法律的枷锁较轻，而舆论的枷锁较重。英国人对立法或执法当局明目张胆干预私人行为的事情十分戒备。他们这样做并非出于维护个人独立的公正考虑，而是出于将政府视为公众利益对立面的思维习惯。大部分英国人都尚未感觉到政府的权力就是他们自己的权力，或政府的主张就是他们自己的主张。他们若果真感觉如此，个人自由就很可能像遭到舆论侵犯那样，面临政府侵犯的威胁。然而，直至今日，他们仍有一股强烈的情感，可以随时唤起：抵制法律在它以前未曾管辖过的事情上对个人进行管制的任何企图；可他们在这种情感升腾时，却毫不分辨所涉事项是否属于法律管制的范畴。因此，此种情感虽然总体而言十分有益，但很可能在具体事例的处理上对错参半。事实上，并不存在一种公认的原则可常规衡量种种政府干预是否正当；人们的判断依据就是其个人好恶罢了。有些人不管发现有善事需实行，抑或有恶事需矫正，都很乐意鼓动政府采取行动；而其他人则宁愿承受几乎所有的社会弊病，却不肯增加一项允许政府管控的新事物，使人类受益。在任一具体事例中，人们是属于前一群体或后一群体，要看他们大体怀有哪种感觉；倘若那件事被提议由政府作为，就要看他们对此事的兴趣度如何，或者看他们是否相信政府会按他们的意愿作为。判断他们属于哪一类群体，不要看他们对政府适合做什么是否持有始终如一的意见。在我看来，缺乏公认衡量原则或规则的后果是，这一派与那一派同样常常出错，他们错误调用和错误谴责政府干预的频率大体相当。

本文旨在宣明一条十分简单的原则，以完全监管社会强迫以及控制个人的方式施行，无论是法律刑罚的肉体暴力或公共舆论的精神威压。该原则就是，人类无论作为个人或集体，只有出于自卫这唯一目的时，才能干预任何人或人群的行动自由。违反其意志，对一位文明社会的成员正当行使权力的唯一目的是：防止伤害他人。个人的物质或精神利益不足以作为对其行使权力的正当借口。“那样做是为了他好”、“那样做会使他更幸福”、“在别人看来那样做很明智甚或非常正确”，这些都不是强迫接受或忍受管制的正当理由。我们可以提出许多充足的理由抗议、与之理论、说服或恳求，但没有充足理由逼迫或告知他如若不然必将自吞恶果。要证明这一做法的正当性，必须估算出，要阻止其从事的那一行为会对他人产生何种恶果。任何人需要对社会负责的那些行为都必须是关联他人的；对那些只与个人有关的行为，他都拥有绝对的自主权。个人是自己身体和精神的君主。

也许，我无须指出，这一原则仅仅适用于心智成熟的人。本书所论无关儿童或未及法定成年期的青少年。那些尚需他人照顾的人，应当受到保护，以免他们受到自身造成或外来的伤害。同理，本文所论也并不包括落后的社会，因为处于该社会状态的种族可能被认为尚未成熟。在社会自然演进的早期阶段，存在种种巨大而几乎无法克服的困难；富于进取精神的统治者为了达成某个目标，可以使用任何便宜的手段，否则他就可能无法成功。对待未开化民族时，只要是为了他们自身的进步，只要所用手段确实能产生预期的效果，实施专制统治就是合法的。在人类尚未达到通过自由平等的讨论而进步的阶段时，自由原则是不适用的。处于这一阶段的人群只能绝对服从于某个阿克巴大帝[1]或查理大帝[2]，倘若他们有幸遇到这样的人物。而一旦人类有能力通过接受劝说而实现进步（本文所论及的诸国早已达到这一阶段），威压就不容许了，无论直接的方式还是迫使其服从的痛苦和刑罚等手段。即便使用，目的也只是为了保护他人的安全。

应该说，我并未引用绝对正确这一无关功用的概念以支撑我的论点。我认为，对一切伦理问题而言，功用都是最终的理论诉求；然而，它必须是最大意义上的功用，其基础必须是人作为一种不断进步的存在者的长远利益。我主张，以人的长远利益作为个人自发行为必须服从于外部管控的条件，其适用范围仅限于个人行为关系到他人利益的情况。如果某人作出伤害到他人的事情，就需要用法律制裁他；如果不能确定可否用法律惩罚，就用大众谴责惩罚他。有许多为别人利益而应采取的积极行为，强迫其实施这些行为乃是正当的。例如，出庭作证、参加集体安全保卫战或其他捍卫社会利益的联合行动，因为自身的利益也受到了保护。其还要实施某些个人慈善行为，如挽救他人的生命、见义勇为，以及诸多任何显然属于人类天职范畴的事情。在这类事上，若袖手旁观，就应受到社会的正当谴责。个人的行动可能危害社会，不作为也可能如此。不管哪种情况，他都应当为此造成的伤害负责。比起前者，后一种情况社会在对他施加强力时必须更为慎重。任何人都要为自己的恶行负责，这是铁律；相对而言，让他为未能阻止恶行负责，则是例外。然而，有许多事实清楚、后果严重的事件足以证明，所谓的例外实为正当要求。在所有个体与他人关联的事情中，他对那些利益攸关者都负有法律责任，并按需充当社会的保护人。不让个人承担责任的理由经常很充足，但这些理由必须源于对所涉事项的特殊考量：原因要么是这样一种情况，倘若他并非受制于社会的全权控制，而是由其自行决定，那么在整件事上他极有可能做得更好；要么是，控制可能会导致另外的、比要防范之恶更严重的恶果。如果这类原因使个人免于承担责任，那么当事人本身的良心应当走上审判席，保护那些无人保护的人们的利益；他尤其要严格地审判自我，因为该事项的特殊情况不容许他接受其他人的审判。

但是，有一个行为领域，社会即便与之利益关联，也只是一种间接的关联，而个人却与之有着千丝万缕的利益关系。这个领域包括生活和行为中所有仅仅影响到个人的活动；倘若这些活动也对他人有所影响的话，则前提必须是他们自由、自愿、理智地同意并参与了这些活动。我所谓“仅仅影响到个人”的意思是，那些活动直接、最先作用于他。因为那作用于他的一切，可能通过他而作用于别人。以此为据反对我的异议将在后文加以讨论，此处不赘。这就是人类自由的恰当范围。首先，它涵盖意识这一内心领域，要求最广泛意义上的良心自由、思想和情感自由，以及在所有话题上绝对的观念及意见自由，不论是现实性话题或思辨性话题；不论是科学话题、道德话题，或神学话题。言论和公开发表意见的自由似乎应受另外原则的支配，因为它关涉到他者的个人行为。但出于同样的原因，与思想自由几乎同等重要，实际上与后者无法分割。第二，本原则要求趣味和爱好自由、按照个人性格特征设计自己生活的自由，以及虽可能遇到下述情况也要随意行动的自由：只要我们的行为对我们的同类无害，我们的行为就不能受到他们的妨害；即便他们可能以为我们的行为很愚蠢、很荒诞，甚至完全错误。第三，从这项个人自由导出：不同个人在上述行为范围内进行联合的自由，即为任何不损及他者的目的进行结社的自由。其前提是：结社的成员必须已达法定成年年龄，且没有受到逼迫或欺骗。

任何在总体上不尊重上述自由的社会，不论其政府形式如何，都是不自由的；上述自由未能完全地、绝对地存在的社会，其自由是不完整的。名副其实的自由仅指我们以自己的方式追求自己福祉的自由，只要我们不试图剥夺别人的这一自由或阻止别人努力获得这一自由。每个人都是自己身体、心理和精神健康的正当守护者。比起迫使所有人为看似利他的目的而生存，容忍彼此为看似利己的目的而生存，会使人类获益更多。

本书此论并非新说，而且在一些人看来，或许有种老生常谈的腔调。但是，由于现有观念和社会实践的大势所趋，没有哪种学说的针对性比此论更为直接。社会竭尽全力，企图（按照它自己的标准）迫使人们像服从其关于优秀社会的观念那样，服从关于优秀个人的主张。古代共和制国家认为，自己有资格用公权力管控公民的所有个人行为，理由是：对每个公民的身体和精神规训都与国家利益深切相关。古代哲学家们赞同这一观念。那些强敌环伺的小共和国或许向来奉行此种理念，因为它们长期以来深恐外患内忧导致国覆家灭，而不敢稍有精神懈怠和自制简疏。它们哪里等得及自由的长远善果？当代世界，由于政治社群规模更大，最主要是由于精神威权与世俗威权的分离（对人们道德良心的管理和对其世俗事务的管理由此分属不同权力部门负责），法律无法再大肆干涉个人生活的各种细节。然而，对于个人异于主流意见的自我关注主张，社会机器一向都悍然发动精神压制的引擎，频次甚至超过对其于社会事务之另类主张的压制。宗教是塑造道德感诸因素中最有力者，但支配宗教的力量，几乎始终是试图全方位管制人类行为的某个僧侣统治集团的勃勃野心，或是清教精神。一些站在与往昔宗教全然对立角度上的现代宗教改革者，所提出的人类精神主宰权要求，毫不逊于任何宗教派别。孔德先生[3]即是一个显例。如其《实证政治体系》中揭示的社会组织所示，他完全超越了古代哲学家当中最刻板铁律信奉者的一切政治理念，打算（主要通过道德手段而非法律手段）建立起社会对个人的专制统治。

除个别思想家提出的特殊原则，世人也越来越倾向于借助舆论甚或立法手段，大肆扩张社会权力并凌驾于个人权力之上。尽管世上一切变化的大势所趋乃是强化社会、削减个人的权力，但这种权力侵蚀不像其他恶行那样会自然而然地趋于消失，却会越来越变本加厉。不论是统治者或一般公民，人类都倾向于将自己的主张和偏好当作一种行为准则强加给他人。这种倾向受到人性中某些最善和最恶情感的大力鼓舞，除了让他们手无寸权之外，简直无法抑制。然而，权力并非日渐减少而是日渐增长；在当前的世界环境下，若不能建起一道强大的道德信念屏障阻止其祸害，我们就只能看着它增长。

为论证展开之便，我们不会立即开始讨论主论点，而要首先探讨一个分论点，因为本章阐明的该分论点的指导原则，即便并非全部，也已在一定程度上受到了当下舆论的认可。该分论点就是：思想自由。它与言论和创作自由同根而生、不可分割。虽然在所有公开承认宗教信仰自由和结社自由的国家，上述自由都是其政治道德中的可观组成成分，但这些自由的哲学和现实基础，大众或许并不熟悉，甚或许多意见领袖也未如想象中的那般通晓。一旦人们正确理解了这些哲学和现实基础，就会发现：其适用范围远远超过本文主题的某一方面；对本分论点的透彻考察乃是解析其他分论点的最佳路径。因此，我希望，那些熟知下文所论内容的读者能够有所谅解，对于这个三百年来的热点论题，我斗胆再论一番。

三　论个性作为幸福的因素之一

上一章所述若干原因使人类势必能够自由形成各种意见，且能毫无保留地自由表达其意见。如果不准许意见自由和意见表达自由，或禁止它们使其无法继续得到主张，就会对人的心智、并通过心智对人的道德特质带来灾难性后果。接下来，我们将探讨的是，上述的这些原因是否要求人类按照其观点自由行动——即：只要他们自负责任、自担风险，就可将其观点付诸生活实践，而不应受到其同类物质或精神上的阻挠。毫无疑问，自负责任、自担风险这一附加条件必不可少。谁都不会妄言，行动应该同观点一样无拘无束。反过来看，一旦意见的表达环境本身构成了实实在在的刺激因素，表达意见就会变成煽动因素，引发骚乱行为，这时就连意见自由也不再安全。说“粮商就是饿死他人的人”，或者“私有制就是掠夺”，这类言论若仅仅是印在报刊上流传，应该可以不受干预；可这类言论若是在粮商门前，面对群情激奋的暴徒进行口头发表，或印成海报散发给那群暴徒，就应当依法惩处。不论何种行为，只要在没有正当理由的情况下伤害到他人，就应当——在更重大的情况下则绝对必须——受到反对观点的管控，并在必要时受到人类的积极干预。个人的自由必须受到这种限制，绝对不能为害他人。但若他足以自制，不会在与他人有关的事情上妨害他人，而在仅仅关乎自身的事情上根据自己的偏好和判断采取行动，那么前文中证明言论自由的所有理由也适用于他，使他应当能够不受干扰、自负代价地将自己的主张付诸实践。人类并非永远正确；人类发现的绝大多数真理都只是片面真理；不经最充分、最自由的比较，就把相互对立的论点协调统一，是不可取的；观点多元并存并非坏事，而是好事，除非将来人类比现在更睿智，能够认知真理的所有方面。这些原则不仅适用于人类的言论，也同样适用于其行为方式。当人类心智尚不完善时，应当允许不同观点的存在。同理，也应当允许不同生活试验的存在；应当在互不妨害的前提下给予各种个性特征的人以自由的活动空间；只要任何人认为某种生活方式适合自己，就应当允许他们通过实践证明各种生活方式的价值。简而言之，在那些绝少涉及他人的事物上，个人应当坚持自己的选择。无论何处，只要当地不以个人的个性特征，而以他人的传统或习惯为行为规范，就会缺少人类福祉的一大要素——它也是个人发展和社会进步的核心要素。

坚持本条原则可能遭遇的最大困难，并非如何评价为达到某一公认目标而采用的种种手段，而是常人对该公认目标本身的漠不关心。人类个性的自由发展是其福祉的主导性要素之一，它不仅与名为“文明”“教导”“教育”“文化”的一切事物同等重要，而且其自身就是它们必不可少的组成部分和前提条件。倘若人们懂得这些，自由就不会被低估，自由与社会约束之间的界限调整就不会产生特别的困难。而现存的祸患是，普通思维方式几乎认识不到，个人自发行为竟然有其内在价值，竟然值得众人尊重。绝大部分人都满意于人类生活的现状（因为造成这种现状的恰恰就是他们），而无法理解为什么这些生活方式难以适用于所有人；更重要的是，个人自发行为并不从属于大多数道德和社会改革者们的理想目标，而被他们充满戒备地看作棘手甚或反叛性的行为，会阻碍大众接受他们断定为最有益于人类的改革方案。在德国之外，几乎无人懂得威廉·冯·洪堡[37]学说的含义。这位卓越的天才学者和政治家在其专著中写道：“人类的目的就是使他的各种才能获得最高度、最和谐的发展，成为圆满、一贯的完人。这是理智的永恒规定对人类下达的命令，而不是含混、短暂的俗世欲望对人类的启示。”因此，“每个人都必须不懈地竭力达成的、特别是那些想影响同类的人必须永远关注的目标，就是个人能力与发展的独特性”。为达到此目标，有“自由和情况多元”两大要件；从这两大要件的结合中，将产生“个人的活力和千差万别”；后二者又结合于“独创性”之中。

然而，虽然冯·洪堡的学说令人们感到十分陌生，他赋予个性如此崇高的价值也让他们大吃一惊，但是有人肯定认为，这不过是个程度问题。没有人会认为，人们毫不越轨地完全相互照搬生活模式，才是行为美德。没有人会宣称，人们决不应在自己的生活方式，在涉及自己的行动上，打下任何自己观念或个性的烙印。另一方面，极其荒诞的做法是：诡称人们的生活方式必须完全新奇，仿佛在他们出生之前世人对一切都浑然无知一般，仿佛人类经验毫无作用，不能展现某种生存或行为方式为何优于其他生活或行为方式。无人否认，人们在年轻时应接受良好的教育和训练，懂得已经人类经验确证的成果，并从中获益。然而，只有当人的个性成熟之后，方有特权、有合适条件以其独特方式使用和诠释人类经验。他必须澄清，现存人类经验中哪个部分真正适用于所身处的境况及其个性特征。在某种程度上，他人的传统与惯例只能表明他们的经验教授了他们什么；此类推定性依据有资格要求他遵从。但是，首先，别人的经验也许范围太小，或者他们也许未能对前人经验做出正确的解释。其次，他们的诠释或许正确，但对他而言并不适用。惯例是为惯常的情境和惯常的性格准备的，他所处的情境或他的个性或许非比寻常。第三，即便那些惯例非常良好，也适用于他，但仅仅把惯例作为惯例遵从，他就不会培养或发展出任何体现人类独特天赋的特质。人类的洞察力、判断力、辨别力、心智活动，甚至道德偏好等各种才赋，只有在作出抉择时才可获得锻炼。那些凡事都按照惯例来办的人，并没有做出抉择。他们失去了练习辨别或期望何为最优事物的机会。人的心智与道德能力同肌肉的能力一样，都只能通过使用得以提升。一人若仅仅因为他人做某事就随之也做此事，就与仅仅因为他人相信某事物就跟着也相信此事物一样，根本无从锻炼其才赋。如果在此人的理性看来，某意见的依据并不确凿可靠，而他竟然采信了此意见，那么他的理智就无法增强，反而极可能减弱。如若使他采取某行动的诱因与其本身的感受和性格并不一致（该行动无关别人的情感或权利），那么采取此行动多半会导致他的感受和个性变得迟钝而麻木，而不是敏捷而活跃。

那类让世人或身边人代他们选择人生计划的人，除了类人猿般的模仿能力之外，根本不需要任何其他才赋。那类自择人生方案的人方能运用其所有才赋：必须运用观察力进行观看，运用推理和判断力进行预见，运用行动力收集数据以供决策，运用辨别力进行决断，并在做出决断后运用毅力和自制力将自己的慎重决策贯彻到底。如果根据自己的判断和感受决定实施的行为能够产生巨大作用，那么其上述才能必然得到相应的全面调动和充分训练。倘若没有这些能力，或也有可能被人引上某条正确路径远离危险。但那样一来，作为一个人的比较价值是什么？不仅懂得人们做了什么很重要，而且懂得做此事人们的行为特征也的确非常重要。在人类正确地消耗其生命以不断完善和美化的诸种功业之中，无上重要的必定是人本身。假定机器——人形的机械——能够建房造屋、种收粮食、攻城打仗、听讼断案，甚或创宗立派、祈祝颂祷，那么把目前居住在世上较为文明国度的男男女女——他们无疑只是自然能够且将要制造的饿殍标本罢了——替换为这些人形机器，也将是一大损失。人性不是一架可以按照模型制造、根据严格指令做工的机器，而是一棵树，有着使其成为一个生物的内在力量，并需要依循这股内力的走势全面成长和自由伸展。

有人可能会勉强承认：好吧，可以让人们训练自己的理解力；机灵地遵从惯例、甚或机灵地背离惯例的做法，要强于只是盲目、机械地坚持惯例。有人在一定程度上承认，我们确实应有属于自己的理解力；但他们并不乐意承认，我们也应同样有属于自己的欲望和冲动，或曰这些属于自己的、任何强度的冲动绝非危险和罗网。不过，欲望和冲动与信条和限制一样，都是完人的组分。强烈的冲动仅仅在得不到适当制衡时才是危险的：一组目标和意愿发展强大起来，而应当与之并存的目标和意愿却仍然微弱呆滞。人类之所以做出坏事，并非因其欲望太强，而是因其良心太弱。强烈的冲动和微弱的良心之间不存在天然关联。天然关联的是相反的情形。说某人的欲望和感受比别人更强烈、更杂多，仅仅说明他有更多的人性原料，所以也许比别人更坏，但肯定比别人更好。强烈的冲动只是活力的别名。活力或许会被用来做坏事，但比起怠惰冷漠的性格，活力蓬勃的性格往往能成就更多的好事。那些天性最容易冲动的人，也总是那些可能情操陶冶得最高雅的人。一些炽盛的灵敏感受，既可造成劲猛剧烈的个人冲动，又可涵育生发出最激昂的热爱美德之情和最严格的自制力。社会得以履行自己的职责、保卫自身的利益，正是通过对这些灵敏感受的培育，而不是拒斥这造就英雄的原料，因为它不懂得该如何创造英雄。据说，如果一人的欲望和冲动都发自本心，是本人天性的表露，且展现了其后天教养对天性的发展和改良，那么此人就有个性。若一人的欲望和冲动并非发自本心，他就毫无个性，如同一台蒸汽机一样毫无个性。如果他的冲动不仅是自发的，而且很强烈，并受到强大意志的监管，那么他就有着精力充沛的性格特征。无论是谁，只要认为不该鼓励人类个性之欲望和冲动的自发流露，都必然会坚称：社会不需要那些强烈的性格特征——它并未因包括许多个性鲜明的人而有所改良；社会活力的总平均数那么高也没有什么好处。

在一些尚处于早期发展阶段的社会中，个人欲望和冲动的力量有可能——实际上也确实——远远超过社会能够用于规训和驾驭它们的力量。个性自发行动曾一度泛滥，令社会道德准则疲于应付。当时的困难是，如何让那些体魄强健或心理刚强的人服从于所有要求他们控制其冲动的社会规则。为克服这一困难，法律和道德规范就像对抗各国君主的历任教皇一样，坚称自己有权管辖人的整体，要管制人的全部生活，最终管制其个性——因为社会当时未能找到其他任何有效方法约束他的个性。可如今，社会已经完全战胜了人的个性，人性面临的危机不是个人的冲动和嗜好太多，而是太少了。事情发生了剧变。从前那些因其社会地位或个人天赋而势强力大者的激情，一贯喜欢反抗法律和习俗，所以要把它们牢牢锁住，让处在它们阴影笼罩下的人的安全能够有所保障。在我们这个时代，全社会从顶层到底层，人人都仿佛生活在审查制度那敌对、可怕的目光之下。不单在关乎他人的事物上，在仅仅关乎自己的事物上，个人或家庭都不会自问：我喜欢什么？什么会适合我的性格脾气？什么能让我最优秀、最高超的才赋得到公正对待并可以长足充分发展？他们自问的是：什么事物才适合我的社会地位？与我地位、财产状况相当的人通常要做什么？（更糟的是）比我地位高、家境好的人通常要做什么？我并不是说，他们抛弃了适合自己偏好的事物，而选择了惯常的事物；实际上，他们根本就没有想到自己会有什么偏好，只知道惯常的事物。这样，人的精神自动低头钻进了枷锁：就连在娱乐这件事上，人们首先想到的也是“随大流”。他们喜欢待在群体之中，仅仅在平凡的事情上运用选择权。在他们心目中，奇特趣味、古怪行为同犯罪一样，避之唯恐不及。他们决不遵循自己的天性，结果天性泯灭，无从遵循；他们作为人的才能凋零、枯死，无法再产生任何强烈的愿望或纯真的快乐，完全没有自发的主张或感受——更准确地说，是完全没有自己的主张。这难道就是——或曰不是——人类天性的理想状态吗？

是的，加尔文派教义如是说，这就是人类天性的理想状态。按照该派教义看，人类最大的罪行就是任性而为；人类能够实现的全部美德都蕴含在驯顺之中；你无可选择，因此你必须且唯有顺从：“任何职分之外的事都是罪。”人性根本上是堕落的，所以任何人若想得救，就必须先把他心中的人性彻底消灭。对信仰该教义的人而言，扑灭人的任何才赋、能力、敏感，均不是恶行，因为人除了把自己交给上帝的意志之外，不需要任何能力；如果他敢把任何才能另作他用，而非更有效地实践上述假定的意愿，那么对他而言，没有这些才能会更好。这就是加尔文派的主张。现在有许多并不自认为是加尔文信徒的人都在信仰它，只是形式较为温和罢了。他们对所谓上帝意志的解释禁欲色彩略淡，宣称上帝的意志允许人类满足自己的某些意愿；当然，满足这些意愿时，他们决不能用自己喜好的方式，而要使用温顺的方式；也就是说，其方式要由权威所规定，从而由具体事例的必要条件而定——无论是谁，都得用同一方式。

眼下就有一种强烈的趋势，用上述阴险形式，把人们引向这种狭隘的人生论及那类压扁的、收紧的人性特征。毫无疑问，许多人真诚地相信，如此钳梏、挤压而成的人才符合造物者设计的人类型范；就像许多人相信，树木被修剪成截头树或各种动物造型，而不是保持其天然形态，才会更漂亮。可是，宗教若果真相信人是某个至善存在者创造的产物，那么更前后一贯的信仰应该是：该存在者赋予了人类一切才能，为的是让他们能够接受教化、打开心胸，而不是让这些才能被铲除、被摧残；该存在者乐于看到他的创造物运用各种更为便捷的方法，实现他预置于他们心中的完美蓝图；乐于看到他们的理解力、行动力或欣赏力等诸种能力的节节提升。有一种与加尔文派理想完全不同的人类美德，它认为，人的天性之所以赋予人类，绝不是要人类戒除它。“不信神者的自以为是”同“基督徒的自我否定”一样，都是人类价值的组成元素。古希腊人有个理想是自我发展，柏拉图和基督教的自治理想中混合了这一古希腊观念，但并未取而代之。成为约翰·诺克斯[38]式的人物或许优于成为亚西比德[39]式的人物，但比起这二者，更优的选择是成为伯里克利[40]式的人物。如果现在真有伯里克利式的人物，他身上也必然会有约翰·诺克斯的某些优秀品质。

人类之所以能成为高贵、美丽的思考对象，并非因为他们把自己的个性磨蚀净尽，变得万夫一面，而是因为他们不断培养自己的个性，让它粲然展露。正如任何作品都会带有其制作者的特征，人生也同样借此而变得丰富多彩、生机蓬勃，为高远的思想和高昂的情感提供丰富滋养，让人这种生物永远越来越值得归属，巩固那将每一个人与其种属紧密相连的纽带。随着其个性不断发展，每个人对自己而言都变得更为宝贵，因此也对他人而言变得更为宝贵；每个人因其存在而使生命更加充实。如果基本单元更加富有活力，那么它们所组成的整体将更加富有活力。为防人性中强悍者侵犯他人的权利，必须要有足够的弹压手段，故而禁制不可或缺。但是，甚至从人类发展的立场看，对此也有充分的补偿办法。个人天性中伤害他人的倾向被压制而得不到满足，他在该发展手段方面受到了损失，而获得了他人发展的重大代价补偿。即便对个人而言，正因约束了自己天性中的利己部分，才获得了其中利群部分的更大发展，这也是等价补偿。为了他人利益而强制个人遵守严格的正义法则，会使个人生发出多种以他人利益为目标的感觉和能力。而仅仅因为别人不悦就禁止他从事无碍他们利益的事情，不会使他发展出什么有价值的知觉和能力，只能逐渐形成一种能够对抗管束的人格力量。如果他顺从了这种管制，他的全部天性就会变得黯淡而麻木。为了让每一个体的天性合理发挥，最关键的做法是允许不同的人过不同的生活。一个时代在多大程度上行使了这一自由，对后人而言，它便相应地具有关注价值。只要允许人类的个性存在，那么即便是独裁统治也不会产生最糟糕的结果；反之，凡是毁碎了人类个性的，必然是独裁统治，无论其名义如何，无论它宣称自己执行的是上帝意志或人类的训令。

上文讨论过，人类的个性与发展同一不二，只有通过培养个性才能产生健康的人类。至此，我应该结束讨论了：人类事务的任何状况，除了使人类自身更加接近他们能够成为的最优秀人物之外，还有什么更值得赞扬呢？任何妨碍人类利益的事物，除了阻碍人类自身更加接近他们能够成为的最优秀人物之外，还有什么更值得批判呢？可毋庸置疑的是，这些因素并不足以说服那些最需要说服的人；我必须进一步证明，对那些不够健康的人而言，这些健康的人还是有用的——必须向那些不渴望自由、不肯接受自由的人指出，如果他们允许别人畅通无阻地运用自由，就可能得到显著的回报。

首先，我认为，那些不渴望自由、不肯接受自由的人有可能从这些健康人那里习得一些东西。谁都不会否认，独创性在人类事务中是一个宝贵因素。永远要有一些人发现新的真理，指出曾经的真理已经不再正确，并创造新的惯例，开创更为文明的行为、更高的人生趣味和人生意义。无论是谁，只要不相信这世界在一切方面、一切事上都已臻完美，便都不会反驳这一点。确实，不是每个人都能够带来这样的益处。与全人类相比，只有极少数人的尝试值得效仿，且如果被他人所效仿，极有可能会改进惯例。而这少数人是社会的栋梁，没有他们，人类生活将是死水一潭。正是这些栋梁之材不仅将前所未有的优秀事物带给了人类，而且为既有事物赋予了生机。倘若再也没有需要创造的新鲜事物，人类智力是否会变得多余？那些重复旧事物的人是否因此应该遗忘做这些事情的初衷，要像牲畜而不是像人类那样继续下去？所有的最佳观念和最好惯例都有一种退化为机械行为的强烈趋势。若非总有一批人前仆后继地运用其不断涌现的创造力，阻止它们蜕变为陈陈相因的腐套，这些呆板的观念和惯例就无法抗拒任何来自真正鲜活事物的最微小打击，人类文明就会消亡——拜占庭帝国就是个显例。没错，天才人物很可能总是极少数，可是为了拥有他们，必须保留能让天才得以成长的沃土。天才只能在自由的空气中自由地呼吸；天赋异禀的人，据该词本义来看，比其他人更为独特，因此比别人更难以把自己不受伤害性压迫的情况下装进任何社会模型之中——社会为其成员提供了少数模型，以免除他们各塑个性之烦劳。倘若他们因胆怯而同意被装进某个模型，从而导致他们个性当中受到压抑而无法伸展的一切特性永远蜷曲下去，社会将对他们的天才无益。倘若他们性格刚强，打破了桎梏，那未能迫使他们降格为平庸凡人的社会就会把他们当作“粗野放荡”“古怪反常”等特征的靶子，指着他们发出严厉的警告。其情景颇像有人竟会抱怨尼亚加拉河[41]为什么不能像荷兰的运河那样，在两岸之间平缓流动。

因此，我坚持强调天赋才能的重要性，以及允许天赋才能在思想和实践中自由展开的重要性。我非常清楚，理论上谁都不会否认这一态度，但我也十分明白，实际上几乎所有人都对此无动于衷。如果天才能让人写出一首动人的诗，或画出一幅画，人们都会认为天才真是样好东西。然而，天才的真正意义是指在思想和行动上的独创性。虽然无人会说，天才这样东西不值得称赞，但几乎所有人都在心中认为，没有天才他们照样过得很好。不幸的是，这件事太稀松平常了，谁都不会大感诧异。独创性就是无独创性的头脑感觉不到其用处的那样东西。缺乏独创性的头脑无法看出，独创性能为它们做什么——它们怎能看得出来呢？倘若它们看得出这一点，所谓的独创性也就不是真正的独创性了。独创性能够为它们做的第一件事就是打开它们的眼睛。这件事一旦充分完成，那么无独创性的头脑自身就有机会变成独创性的了。同时，让它们想一想，它们谁都并未开创任何新事物，一切优秀事物都是独创性的成果；然后它们就应足够谦逊地相信，必定还有需要独创性完成的事物，并更清楚地知道，它们越需要独创性，就越不会感到优秀事物匮乏。

然而现实真相是，无论人们在口头或行动上多么尊敬真正或假定的卓越思想，全世界事物的总体发展趋势却是：平庸正在成为支配人类的力量。在古代历史上、在中世纪，个人本身就是一个统治者；如果他天赋卓著或社会地位极高，就是一个强大的统治者。在封建时代至今漫长的变迁过程中，他的权力渐渐减弱了。到了现在，个人消失在了人群之中。在政治上，“舆论统治了世界”几乎是不值一提的平凡论调；名副其实具有统治力的只有群众和主动成为群众偏好与直觉之喉舌的政府。对于私人生活中道德与社会事务以及公共生活中的种种事务，这一点都千真万确。以舆论为名大行己意的那些人，并不总是同一批公众：在美国，公众指的是全部白人；在英国，则主要指中产阶级。但无论如何，他们都是群众，也就是说，是集体的平庸。要论公众有何新颖之处，就是他们如今不再从教会或世俗政府的权贵显要、冒牌领袖那里或书本当中获取意见了。一些与他们非常相像的人在报纸上替他们做出了思考，告知他们应持什么意见，或者索性直接代表他们发表意见。我并不是在抱怨这一切。我并不是在主张：通常说来，有些事物更适合当前这种低劣的人类精神状态。可这并不会阻碍管辖平庸之才的政府成为平庸的政府。民众或无数贵族控制的政府，无论是其政治活动，还是其所养成的言论、品质和精神状态，都未曾或未能超越平庸。例外的情况是：管理国家的众人能够听从天赋极高、教养极高的某个人或某几个人，让他或他们的建议和影响指引自己（盛世的统治者历来如此）。一切高明或高贵事物的创生都始于或必然始于某些个人，且最初通常始自某一个人。一名普通人的荣誉和辉煌就在于：能够拥护这一倡议，能够在内心响应高明或高贵的事物，且目不转睛地被它们引至近前。我并非在此处支持“英雄崇拜”——此论调赞许天赋异禀的强者紧紧攫取统治世界的大权，让世界服从他而不是它自己的命令。这样的强者所能要求的唯一事物是：允许他向世人指明通往高明或高贵事物路径的自由。以强权迫使他人服从他的指引，不仅触犯了所有他人的自由和发展权利，而且会损害强者自身的利益。不过，完全由普通人组成的群众提出的种种看法，在世界各地都已成为或正在成为主导力量；此时此刻，制衡和矫正这种势头的手段，确实只有那些思想更为高超者越来越彰显的个性了。在这种极为特殊的情境下，不应阻止那些才具非凡的人，而应鼓励他们采取与众不同的行动。在其他时代，他们这么做并无益于事，除非他们的行动不仅与众不同，而且优越超胜。在这个时代，仅仅是特立独行、在惯俗面前挺直腰杆，就大有作用。这全然是因为，舆论已经暴虐到使反常行为成为耻辱；所以要战胜那一暴虐，人们必须言行古怪。在个性力量充足的时代和地方，反常言行总屡见不鲜；在一个社会中，反常言行的数量通常都与其中天才、精神活力和道义勇气的数量成正比。如今无人敢于特立独行，恰恰标志着本时代的主要危机在于何处。

我说过，要让不同寻常的事物享有最大可能的自由，以便及时展现其中的哪些事物适合转化为习俗，这一点十分重要。行动自主和忽视惯例有可能揭示更佳的行为方式、更值得大家采纳的习惯。这些行为不仅仅是为此受到鼓励而已；能够正当地要求以自己的方式过活的人，也不仅仅是那些确实思想优胜的人。要求所有人都必须按照某一种或某些种模型构建其生活方式，这是毫无理由的。若某人拥有基本够用的生活常识和经验，那么他为自己规划的生存方式就是最佳的；之所以这样说，不是因为其生存方式本身是最优的，而是因为那是他自己的生存方式。人类不同于羊群；即便是羊，也并非两两无别而彼此雷同。人若想得到合身的衣服或合脚的靴子，就必须或量身定做，或坐拥整个仓库的鞋服可供挑选。他更容易找到适合他的生活方式还是更容易得到合身的衣服？人与人的整体物质和精神结构更相像还是他们的脚形更相像？仅仅人与人趣味不同这一条，就足以阻止他们必须遵从同一种生活方式的要求。然而，不同人的精神发展也需要不同的条件；他们无法在同一套道德规范下健康生存，就像不同种类的植物无法在同样的物质、空气和气候条件中健康生存。同一组事物，对一人培养其高级天性大有助益，对另一人则是重重障碍。同一种生活模式，能充分调动一人之行动与享受官能，令其精神抖擞、康泰愉悦，而完全阻滞或扰乱了另一人的精神生活，令他心烦气躁、情绪低落。人类就是这样在快乐的源泉、对痛苦的感受以及不同物质和精神因素对其影响等方面都各不相同，如果不允许他们的生活模式相应地多种多样，他们就无法公平享有应得的幸福，也无法发展到其天性足以达到的心智、道德和审美高度。因此，为什么公众意见只能宽容那些迫使大批支持者顺从自己心意的生活趣味和生活模式呢？如今，没有一个地方（某些僧侣机构除外）完全不认可生活趣味的多样化。一个人可以不受指责地喜欢或不喜欢划船、抽烟、音乐、体育运动、下棋、打牌或学习。这是因为，喜欢任何这类事物的人和不喜欢它们的人数量都太大了，谁都无法压制对方。可是，因为做了“谁都不做的事情”或不做“大家都做的事情”而遭到指责的人，尤其是女人，却成为贬议诋谤的对象，仿佛他或她犯了某种极其严重的道德罪行。人们需要拥有某个头衔，或其他等级标志，或位高势重者的关照，才能享受到少许随心所欲的欢愉，而免遭毁谤、保持令名。我重复一下，他们只能享受少许；因为不论何人，若敢肆意随心所欲，就会招致比毁誉更严重的巨大危险——他们可能遭到某个疯癫调查委员会的调查，他们的财产可能被剥夺、分给亲属[42]。

目前舆论有一个发展趋势，尤其可能导致它不能容忍任何显著流露的个性。不仅人类智慧的总体平均值十分普通，而且其偏好的总体平均值也十分中庸：他们丝毫没有能使他们乐于做任何独特事情的强烈趣味或愿望，因此毫不理解那些具有这种强烈趣味或愿望的人，而会把这样的人归入野蛮人和他们通常蔑视的放荡者之列。现今，除了这一普遍现实之外，我们只好断定，一场旨在改进道德规范的强大运动已经出现；我们只好期待的结果已经彰显。近段时间以来，这场运动已经开始，可以感受到，道德规范确实已经日益严格，过分行为也日益减少；到处都洋溢着一种慈善精神，而其理想用武之地，非改进我国同胞之品行和审慎美德莫属。这些时代潮流致使大众比以往任何时候都更乐意规定一般行为准则，更竭力迫使全体社会成员都遵从公推的行为准则——不管是直截了当地明言或心照不宣地默认，该准则都是：不要强烈渴求任何事物。其理想中的人类性格就是毫无性格；人性中凡引人瞩目者、会令某人与常人性格概貌显著有别的部分都要压残折损，如同中国妇女的裹脚一般。

像所有摒弃了一半优良之物的理想那样，目前得到嘉许的道德标准仅仅能够制造出剩余半边的低劣赝品。它的产物不是由健壮理性积极导引下的蓬勃活力，不是严正意志强大监控下的强烈感情，而是脆弱的感情和虚弱的活力，因此其意志或理智毫无力量，仅能在表面上服从道德规则。在我国，大量拥有生龙活虎性格的人都已走进了历史，活力之出口唯余经商一途。可以说，用在了这一方面的活力仍然很可观；其余点滴活力则都耗费在了某种嗜好上，虽然这嗜好也许有点用处，甚或是慈善性的，但它总是某一件具体事物，而且通常都是琐碎小事。今天英国的伟大是整体性的，但从个人角度看它很渺小；我们只是靠习惯性的联合显得似乎能够完成一切伟大的事业罢了，可我们那些道德和宗教慈善家却对此心满意足。不过，那些把英国变成了一个伟大国家的并不是这种人，而是另一类人；阻止英国衰落所需的仍然是那另一类人。

无论何处，习俗之专制都是阻止人类进步的顽固障碍，不停地对抗着那种渴求优于惯常事物之事物的性格特征。这种性格特征在不同形势下有不同的名称，或称自由精神，或称进步精神，或称改良精神。改良精神并非总是自由精神，因为它有可能强迫人们接受改良；而自由精神反对这种强迫人们改良的企图，它有可能局部、暂时地与改良运动的反对者联手。不过，改良之唯一可靠而恒久的源泉就是自由，因为凭借自由才可能产生许多独立的改良运动中心，有多少个人就可能有多少这样的中心。可是，不论进步之天性表现为对自由的热爱还是对改良的热爱，其对立面却是习俗之主宰——进步至少包括摆脱后者的枷锁；二者之间的竞争也构成了人类历史上最引人瞩目的事件。准确说来，大部分世人都没有历史，因为习俗完全统治了他们。整个东方即是如此。在那里，无论何事，最终都要诉诸习俗；正义与权利意味着遵从习俗；除了某个只手遮天、忘乎所以的暴君之外，无人想对抗习俗的意见。其结果我们都看到了。那些东方民族肯定曾拥有创造力，他们并非在地球上甫一出现就人口众多、富有文化、精通各种生活技艺；他们在历史上为自己创造了那一切，成为了世上最伟大、最强大的民族。可现在的他们呢？竟然成为某些部落的臣民或附庸！当那些部落的祖先仍在丛林之中游荡时，他们祖先就已住上了宏伟壮丽的宫殿和华美夺目的庙宇。但习俗仅用自由和进步对他们分别进行了统治。一个民族似乎可以在一段时间的进步之后停滞不前——它停滞于何时呢？就在其成员失去个性的那一刻。倘若同样的变化降临到欧洲各民族头上，变化的形态将不会与东亚完全相同。习俗之专制统治对这些民族的威胁形式并非完全固化不动；它明令禁止特异性，但并不杜绝变化，前提是一切同时发生变化。我们抛弃了祖先那些固定的装束，每个人的穿戴都必须同别人一致，但时装可能一年一变或两变。因此我们非常注意，发生变化的目的只能是为了变化本身，而非为了美丽或便利；这是因为，同一个美丽或便利观念不会同时出现在全部世人的脑海里，也不会在另一时刻被他们同时抛去一边。但我们不仅善变而且不断进步：我们不断发明新的机械装置，并使用至更优的机械装置取代它们那时为止；我们渴望政治、教育甚至道德规范不断改进，尽管我们对道德规范改进的观念主要限于说服或强迫他人同我们一样优秀。我们所反对的并不是进步；恰恰相反，我们自鸣得意地认为我们是有史以来最具进取精神的民族。我们的斗争对象是个性：我们认为，倘若我们全部彼此相同，就是创造了奇迹；我们忘记了，通常说来，正是由于人们彼此差异，才会引起他们注意到自己这一类人的缺点和另一类人的优点，才有可能让他们将双方的优点结合，造就比二者更好的人物。中国就是一个值得引起我们警醒的反例。这个民族天分很高，在某些方面甚至富有智慧。这是因为他们在很早以前就极其幸运地获得了一套格外优良的习俗——这套习俗在一定程度上是一批中国古人的杰作，就连最博洽的欧洲人都必须在一定条件下赋予他们圣贤和哲人的名号。不仅如此，他们还通过其卓越无双的评注作品，明确且尽量多地把他们的最佳理念镌刻在了每个社会成员的思想之中，并确保那些最多吸纳了这些理念的人，会获得荣耀而权重的职位。毫无疑问，中国人通过上述做法已经发现了人类进步的机密，并必定会让自己稳稳居于世界变化的前列。可是，恰恰相反，他们一成不变了——就那样停滞了数千年之久；他们若想继续改进，就只能借助外来者。他们成功地踏入了绝境：全民族的人如出一辙，都用同一套准则和规程调控自己的思想和行为。这就是他们的成果。英国慈善家们也正在为此目标夙夜劳碌。舆论在欧洲的现代统治正是中国组织化教育和政治体制的翻版，只不过形式上无组织罢了。如果个性无法成功地坚持自我主张、抗拒舆论枷锁，一度拥有高贵祖先、自称信奉基督教的欧洲，将会逐渐变成另一个中国。

是什么至今都在保护欧洲免遭此种命运呢？是什么使欧洲各民族成为一个常改常新而非静止不变的人类大家庭呢？答案并非他们有什么更高级的杰出之处——这种杰出之处即便存在，也并非作为原因而存在，而只是作为结果而存在——而是他们有着异常多样的性格和文化。欧洲的个人之间、阶级之间、民族之间历来绝不相同；他们开创出了各种各样的道路，每条道路都通向某种宝贵之物。尽管在每段时期，在不同道路上行进的人们都互不容忍，每人都认为，如果所有别人被迫来追随自己的脚步该有多好，但他们彼此试图阻挠对方发展的行为几乎从来都仅仅成功一时，而且每人都最终坚持了下来，享受到了别人提供的好处。在我看来，欧洲之所以能够历久弥新、多面发展，全系此路径多元性所赐；但是，欧洲对这种益处的享有程度已经开始大幅锐减了，它正在坚定不移地向使万众一面的中国式理想推进。德·托克维尔[43]先生在他最后一本重要著作中评论说，当前的法国人彼此相像的程度甚至远超上一代法国人。这句话也可用来描述英国人，只是他们的趋同程度比法国人要大得多。我在前文引用过威廉·冯·洪堡的一段话，他在其中指出，人类发展有两大让人们彼此不同的必要条件：自由和环境多元。在我国，二者中的第二大条件正逐日减少；围绕着不同阶级和不同个体、塑造着他们各自性格特征的种种环境，正在逐日趋同。从前，不同阶层、不同社区、不同行业和职业的人，可以说是生活在不同的世界之中；如今，他们很大程度上是生活在同一个世界当中。与过去相比，他们如今读的是同样东西，听的是同样东西，见的是同样东西，去的是同样地方，希求同样的目标，恐惧同样的事物，享有同样的权利和自由，用同样的手段维护这些权利和自由。尽管他们的社会身份仍然相差悬殊，但比起那些已经消失的差别，这种身份差异根本不值一提。人们的同化仍在继续。当代的一切政治变迁都助长了这种同化态势，因为所有的政治变革都倾向于提高低贱者的地位、降低高贵者的地位。教育范围的每一扩展都助长了这种同化态势，因为教育将人们置于共同的影响之下，让他们都可获取作为公器的各种事实与观点。通联手段的不断改进助长了这种同化态势，因为这些手段使遥分两地的居民得以直接联系，使人们得以迅速从此地迁居他处。商业和工业增长助长了这种同化态势，因为它们把舒适环境的种种好处更广地传播开去，将人们渴求的一切目标——甚至包括那些最高贵的目标——变成了大众争夺的对象；于是渴望成功不再是某个特定阶级的特点，而成为各个阶级共有的特征。有一股力量甚至超越了这一切因素，使全人类普遍趋同：在我国和其他崇尚自由的国家，舆论已经完全确立了其对政府的支配地位。种种社会声望曾使那些名流闻人敢于漠视大众的意见，如今却渐渐变得平淡无奇；在发现民众确实有某种意志之后，务实的从政者们越来越彻底地从其脑海中抹除了违背民众意志的想法；特立独行再也无法获得任何社会支持——特立独行指的是社会中的任何独立力量，它反对大众的主导地位，乐于挺身而出保护与众不同的看法和意向。

上述所有因素共同导致了大量反个性势力的形成，使人难以预料个性如何才能坚守阵地、毫不退缩。如果不能唤醒民众中的智士感受个性的价值——发现允许差异存在会带来好处，即便这些差异不会产生更好的结果，即便在他们看来某些差异可能还要产生较坏的影响——个性会在维护自我时遭遇越来越大的困难。个性若要宣示其种种主张，目前正当其时，因为眼下尚不具备被彻底同化的诸多条件；只有在同化的初期阶段，个性才能成功抵制同化趋势的蚕食。“所有人都必须像我们一样”这种要求，一旦有所成功便会得寸进尺、越发威风。如果直等到人生已被缩减到几乎仅余一种式样时才奋起抗击，那么对该式样的所有偏离都会被视为不敬、不义之举，甚至是骇人听闻、违反自然的恶行。一旦人类哪怕短暂地习惯了千篇一律，其心智就会迅速失明，再也无法想象出生活会怎样丰富多彩。

四　论社会对个人的权威之限度

那么，个人自主权的正当界限是什么？社会对个人的管制从何处开始？人类生活中哪些部分应属于个人自主？哪些部分应属于社会管制？

倘若个人自主和社会管制各与人类生活中的特定部分有着极为特别的关联，那么二者都会获得对应的应用领域。人类生活中主要涉及个人利益的部分应当归于个人自主范围，而主要涉及社会利益的部分则应属社会管制范围。

虽然社会的构建并非基于契约，尽管为演绎出种种社会责任而捏造某个契约并不能达成任何良好目标，但是无论何人，只要受到了社会的保护，就应为此益处回报社会；人生活在社会中这一客观事实也要求，所有人都责无旁贷，必定要为了他人利益而遵循某种行为方式。首先，这种行为不能损害彼此的利益，或曰某些利益；这些利益或由法律明文规定或由人们不言而喻地认定，都应算作人的权利。第二，这种行为包括：每人为保卫社会或其成员免受伤害和烦扰，要承担自己的那份劳务和牺牲（这一份额要根据某种公正的标准加以确定）。对此，若有些人力图抗拒不从，社会可以完全正当且不惜一切代价地强制他们行动。社会可以做的不仅如此而已。某人的行为可能会伤害他人，或没有预先充分虑及别人的福祉，但未达到侵犯他们既定权利的程度。于是，冒犯者虽不会受到法律惩罚，但有可能受到舆论的公正惩罚。只要某人之行为的任何部分对他人利益造成了有害影响，社会就有权管辖其行为；社会对此行为的干预是否会促进公共福祉，则是一个有待讨论的问题。但若某人之行为的影响仅限于其自身的利益，而与他人毫不相干，或不需影响到他人，除非他们乐意受到影响（所有相关人等都已达法定成年年龄，且对此行为具有常规了解），则上述问题根本就不成立。在所有此类情况下，个人应享有完全的法律和社会自由，能够实施其行为并承担相应后果。

若有人认为，我是在此主张人应自私而冷漠，谎称人类与彼此的生活行为无关，且在不涉及个人利益的时候不应关心彼此的善举与福祉，那么他就完全错解了本文的论点。我并未倡导人们少管闲事；恰恰相反，我要指出的是，现在亟须人们更加公正无私地大力增进他人的利益。但公正无私的善行可以另寻其他手段，而不是靠字面意义和比喻意义上的鞭笞与拷打，来说服人们增进他人的利益。我毫不轻视那些关注自我利益的美德，我认为它们在重要性上仅次于社会美德——倘若它们确实次要的话。教育界的职责是同等地培养这两种美德。可连教育都是靠强制和证明说服两种手段实施的；一旦教育阶段结束，便只能借助证明与说服这种手段，来向人们反复灌输关注自我利益的美德了。人类正是靠互相帮助才区分开了何者为好何者为坏，靠互相鼓励才实现了趋利避害。他们应当永远激励彼此更频繁地运用他们的高级才能，更频繁地把他们的感受和目标导向睿智高明、引人向上的事物与思想，远离愚蠢荒谬、低劣可耻的事物与思想。然而，没有哪个人或哪些人会理直气壮地告诉另一位成年人，说不会为了自己的利益而在决定献身的事物上全力以赴。他是最关注自己福祉的人。与其自身的关注程度相比，和他没有紧密个人关系的任何别人对他福祉的关注都是微不足道的；社会对他个人（他作用于别人的行为除外）的关注极其有限且毫不直接，而对于自己的感受与境遇，最平凡的男女都比任何别人有着无限深刻的认知。社会干预会推翻个人对那些仅仅关乎他自身事物的判断和意图，所以这种干预必须基于种种一般推测。社会的推测有可能完全错误；即便推测正确，也要尽最大可能避免被那些像局外人一般毫不了解内情的人滥用于分析各种个案。因此，在人类事务的这一方面，个性有其特定的作用场域。人类在相互作用的行为中，必须在绝大部分情形下遵循一般规则，以便人们知道他们只能期望什么。但在每个人的个人事务中，他有权任意发挥其独特自发性；其他人可能向他提供参考意见、帮助他做出判断，用规劝勉励他矢志不渝，甚至强迫他接受建议和规劝，但他自己才是最终的裁夺者。他不听建议与忠告而可能犯下的所有错误，其弊端之严重远低于允许别人强制他做认为对他有利的事。

我并不是说，别人对某人的看法和感觉决不应受到他关注自我利益的那些特征或缺点的影响；这种意见既不可能又不可取。如果在那些有助于某人达到自我利益的品格特征之中，某种特征十分显著，那么他就可以正当地受到人们的钦佩；因为他比别人更接近理想中的完美人性。如果他严重欠缺那些性格特征，那么人们就会对他产生与钦佩相反的某种情感。某人的表现可能在一定程度上很愚蠢和一定程度上可以称作趣味低下或堕落；尽管这些性格特征不是应该伤害他的正当理由，但会让他不可避免、毫不冤屈地成为一个惹人讨厌的对象，在某些极端情形下甚至会成为被人轻蔑的对象——人若不能对此种卑劣的性格特征产生厌恶之情，就不能对相反的性格特征产生恰如其分的钦慕之情。尽管他的愚蠢和堕落行为不会妨害任何他人，但会迫使我们把他视作傻瓜，或看成劣等动物。他会竭力避免使这种看法和态度成为现实，因此我们预先警告他这一后果或任何他会自作自受的其他不利后果，乃是在帮他的大忙。实际上，倘若我们不用当前寻常观念所允许的委婉方式，而能够更加直率地提供这种帮助；倘若一人能够诚实地告知另一个人他认为后者有过错，而不会被认为是粗野无礼、专横无耻，那么此事就会顺利圆满。我们还有权根据我们对某人的负面看法，以多种方式采取行动；这样做时，我们不会压制他的个性，而会发挥我们的个性。例如，我们坚决不会与他交好；我们有权避免与他交往（但不会张扬此事），因为我们有权选择最合自己心意的友朋。如果我们认为他的行事或谈话很可能会对他的交往对象产生恶劣影响，就有权——也有责任——劝告别人提防他。我们在可选择地帮助他人时，可以优先帮助别人而不是他，除非我们希望他有所改进而施之以援手。在这种种情况下，此人因仅直接影响他自身的种种缺点，而可能受到来自他人的严厉惩罚。但他如此受到惩罚的必要条件是，这些惩罚都是他的种种缺点自然而然导致的后果，而并非专门为了惩罚而故意强加给他的。倘若有人表现得很粗鲁、顽固、自负——不能以温和适度的方式生活，不能约束自己的有害嗜好，牺牲那些情感和智力上的乐趣去追求兽性的快感——那么，他就只能指望被别人鄙视和厌烦了。但对此他无权抱怨，除非他用极为优秀的社交关系赢得了他们的赞同，并进而获取了能够得到他们帮助的资格——这种资格不受他那些自作自受所犯过失的影响。

我所主张的是：一人只应经受的困扰，仅限于与别人对其否定性评判不可分割的那些繁难，因为他的那些行为和性格仅仅关乎他自己的利益，而丝毫影响不到别人的利益，虽然他们与他有所关联。可若他的行为伤害到了别人，则这类行为需要受到完全不同的处置。侵犯别人的权利；在他不需捍卫自身权利的情况下令别人蒙受损失或伤害；与别人的交易中说谎或欺诈；不公平不慷慨地利用自己的优势欺负别人；自私地不肯保护别人免遭伤害——凡此种种，均应正当地受到道德谴责；如果事情严重，则应正当地受到道德报复和惩罚。不仅这些行为，就连导致这些行为的性情，都完全是邪恶悖德的，均应受到指责甚至憎恨。性情残暴；包藏祸心和居心不良；所有强烈感情中最反社会、最可憎者——妒忌；虚饰和伪善；为鸡毛蒜皮而暴跳如雷和因睚眦小事而恨入骨髓；热衷于盛气凌人；过分地独占所有好处的欲望（古希腊人所谓的贪婪狂）；以贬低别人为乐的自满；认为自己和自己关注的事物最为重要，并以对自己有利的方式解决所有未决问题的利己主义——凡此种种都是道德罪恶，它们组成了一种恶劣、可憎的道德品质。它们不同于上述那些关注自我利益的缺点，因为后者不是准确意义上的道德败坏，无论发挥到何种程度，都算不上邪恶。那些关注自我利益的缺点或许可作为蠢行的证据，或者缺乏人格尊严和自尊心的证据，但当它们导致了未履行对他人义务的失职行为时，只能受到道德谴责，因为当事人理应首先自顾，而后顾他。所谓的对我们自身的责任并不具有社会强制性，除非形势使然，这些对自己的责任同时也成为对他人的责任。“对自己的责任”一词倘若不仅仅意味着审慎，还意味着自我尊重或自我发展；谁都没有义务向他的同类解释这些事项，因为其中没有一项需要他为了全人类的利益而向他们进行解释说明。

一人若不够审慎或缺乏人格尊严，有可能自作自受地引起别人的不敬；他若侵犯别人的权利，就会受到应得的责罚。这二者之间的区分不仅仅是名义上的。他是在我们认为自己有权管制他的事物上触怒了我们呢？还是在我们自知无权管制他的事物上触怒了我们呢？我们对待他的态度和行为因这种区分而差别巨大。倘若他冒犯了我们，我们就可以表明对他的厌恶；我们既可避开某种惹怒我们之物，也可避开惹恼我们之人；但我们不一定因此受到刺激，决心让他的生活麻烦起来。我们应该深思：他已经在承担或将要承担自己的错误带来的惩罚；如果他处置失当、毁掉了自己的生活，我们就不应因此希望对他造成进一步的打击；我们不但不希望惩罚他，相反，还应让他知道，怎样可以避免或消除他的行为会给自己带来的灾祸，从而尽力减轻他所受到的惩罚。对我们而言，他可能是个同情的对象，或讨厌的对象，但不会是恼怒或憎恨的对象；我们不应把他作为社会之仇敌看待。如果我们并不通过表现出对他的兴趣或关注而进行善意干预，那么我们富有正当理由的最严重做法是：对他置之不理。然而，倘若他违犯了那些为保护同类个体或集体所必需的规则，我们就要采取与此截然不同的措施。因为那样的话，他行为造成的恶果并不会落到他自己头上，而会降临到别人身上。社会作为其所有成员的保护者，必须对他进行反击，必须出于明确的惩罚目的而迫使他遭受痛苦，且必须保证这种痛苦足够强烈。在后一种情况下，他是站在我们法庭上的罪犯，我们接受召唤而来，不仅是为了审判他，而且是为了以某种形式执行我们的判决。而在前一种情况下，我们要起的作用不是强迫他忍受苦痛。例外的情形是，我们在自由地管理自己的事务时，不经意地产生了令他痛苦的结果；可是，我们也允许他运用同一种自由管理他自己的事务。

本文区分了个人生活中仅仅涉及自己的部分和涉及别人的部分。许多人都会拒绝承认这种区分。（他们可能会问）一名社会成员之行为的任何部分怎么可能令其他成员无动于衷呢？谁都不是完全与世隔绝的生物；一人若做了严重或长久地有害于他自身的事情，其危害不可能不传播——它至少能影响到他的至爱亲朋，且经常远远超出这一亲友范畴。他若毁坏了自己的财产，就是损害了那些直接或间接以之为生活来源的人的利益，并通常或多或少地减少了社会的财富总量。他若损坏了自己的机体或精神能力，就不仅给所有依靠他获得某种幸福的人带来了灾难，并且会令他本人再无资格为他的全体同类提供分内的服务，也许还会成为他们感情或善行上的负担。倘若这种行为频繁发生，就会超越任何已知罪行，最为严重地耗损社会的利益总量。最后，倘若一人的罪行或蠢行没有直接伤害到他人，可他仍然（人们可能会说）会用自身实例造成危害，因此必须迫使他管制自我，以免那些看到或听说他的行为的人会被其腐化或误入歧途。

（人们会补充说：）即便能够控制行为不端的后果，使它仅影响到邪恶或轻率的实施者自身，难道社会就该放弃那些明显无法控制自我的人，让他们放任自流吗？如果世人公认应该保护儿童和未成年人免受自我伤害，那么社会不该为那些同样不能自我管控的成年人提供同样的保护吗？如果赌博、酗酒、放纵、懒惰、不洁等等，与法律明令禁止的许多或大多数行为一样，危害着人类的幸福、严重阻碍着人类的进步，那么只要符合可行性要求，社会条件适宜，（人们可能会问）难道法律不该也竭力镇压它们吗？作为对法律在所难免之种种不足的补充，难道舆论不能至少组成一支强大的治安力量，对抗这些恶行，用社会处罚严厉惩治那些已知的作恶者吗？（人们可能会说）这些事情与限制个性问题无关，与阻止生活创新实验和尝试新事物问题无关。此处力求制止的只有一类事物：从世界初创至今已经过尝试并宣布为不安全的事物、经验已经证明对任何人的个性培养都无用或不适宜的事物。必须要在一定时段和一定量经验之后，才能认为某个道德或慎重真理已经确立；人们仅仅期望它能阻止一代又一代的人类，使他们不会在祖先殒命的同一处悬崖失足坠落。

我完全承认，一人对自己的损害有可能通过感情渠道和利益渠道严重影响到与其联系密切的人，并在较小程度上影响到全社会。一旦有人做出这种行为，而致使他违背了被清晰明确规定了的、某个或某些他对别人应尽的义务，此事就不再属于关注自我利益的事类范畴，而进入了社会道德层面，要严格接受道德谴责。例如，如果某人因放纵奢侈而无力还债，或虽已承担起养育家庭的道德责任，但因放纵奢侈而无法养活或教育儿女，他就当然应受斥责，且可能受到应有的惩罚。但这种惩罚针对的不是他的奢侈放纵，而是他对家庭或债主所负责任的违背。倘若那些本应交给家人或债主的财富，被他挪用进行最为慎重的投资活动，他仍然犯下了同样的道德罪行。乔治·巴恩威尔[44]害死自己的叔父，为的是给情妇弄到钱财，若他为的是自己从商，则同样要被判处绞刑。再如，有种十分常见的案例是：某人因沉迷恶习给自己的家庭带来了不幸，他因自己的刻薄无情或忘恩负义受到了应有的谴责。若他为了培养无害的习惯而令家人痛苦，则同样应该受到谴责，因为他们要与他终生相伴，或者因个人关系而有赖他提供慰藉。无论何人，只要他在未被某种更紧要的责任所迫，或没有正当理由允准他自行优选某事物的情况下，未按照一般规则尊重别人的正当利益与合理情感，就必须为其冷漠承担责任，&nbsp；接受道德谴责。所以，谴责针对的既不是漠视他人利益与情感的原因，也不是仅仅殃及自身的那些过失——虽然那些过失可能与他的冷漠有着非常细微的因果关系。同样，一旦某人仅仅出于关注自我利益这一角度而有所行动，从而使自己无法履行某项义不容辞、服务公众的具体责任，他就犯有侵犯社会罪。谁都不会仅仅因为醉酒而受到惩罚，但士兵或警察若在值班时喝醉，就应当受到惩罚。总之，不论何时，只要确已出现或必将出现损害个人或公众利益的事物，事件就不再属于自由的范畴，而要置于道德规范或法律的视野中进行考量。

若某人的行为既没有违背对公众应尽的任何特定义务，也没有明显地伤害到除自己之外的特定别人，但他却令社会受到了纯粹偶然性的——或可称作结构性的——伤害，那么对于这种伤害所导致的不幸，为了人类自由这一更重大的利益，社会是能够容忍的。若成年人因未能正常地照顾好自己而受到惩罚，我宁愿那惩罚是为了他们自身的利益，而不希望惩罚的实施者借口说，那是为了防止他们损害到自己为社会创造利益的能力。因为社会不会妄称自己有权苛求那些利益。但我不能同意就此争论下去，似乎社会毫无办法将其成员的素质提升到行为符合理性的平常标准，只能坐等他们做出荒谬之事，然后依法或依道德准则惩办他们。在他们生命的整个早期阶段，社会对他们拥有绝对权力：在他们的整个儿童时期和未成年时期内，社会都可以进行试验，看看能否培养出他们理性处世的能力。现存这代人深知该怎样培育未来一代，也掌控着全部现实情况；但他们确实无法令未来一代变得十足睿智、绝对优秀，因为他们自身就很遗憾地缺乏美德和智慧。在很多事例中，他们虽已竭尽全力，但结果总是未能大获成功。然而，他们完全能够让成长中的这代人在整体上同他们那代人一样良好，且比他们更好一些。如果社会放任相当多的成员在长大后仍然天真幼稚，不能理性地考虑长远动机并据以采取行动，那么它就必须为此后果而责备自己。社会全副武装，不仅拥有教育的一切权势，而且占据着支配地位，某个公认为正确的观点总是借此地位扬威施暴，统治着那些最不适于独立判断事物的头脑；社会还有种种天然惩罚手段作为后援，这些惩罚会无可阻挡地降临到那些令其熟人感到厌恶或蔑视的人的头上。所以不要让社会谎称，它除了所有这些之外，仍然需要更多权力发号施令，强制个人在纯粹私人的事务上也要服从它的意志。根据所有正义原则和行动原理，纯粹私人事务的决定权应当属于那些即将承受后果的人。有些手段能使人类行为转好，有些则令人类行为变坏；没有哪种方法比采取后者更会败坏前者的名誉、阻挠前者的成功了。在社会试图迫使其变得审慎或节制的那些人之中，倘若任何人有着朝气蓬勃、独立自主的性格特质，他们就必然会奋起反抗那套社会枷锁。这些人谁都不会认为别人有权管制他的个人事务，正如他们必将阻止他破坏他们的个人事务。悍然违抗这种篡窃威权、炫耀性地公然抗命与它对着干，此类行为很容易被视为有气概、有胆魄的标志；查理二世[45]时代，人们就曾明目张胆地抗拒清教徒那狂热、偏狭的清规戒律。有人说，必须要保护社会，剔除那些伤风败俗、自我放纵的有害事例。对此，我的回答是：没错，有害的事例确实可能产生致命的影响，特别是做坏事伤害了别人却不受任何惩罚的那种事例。但我们现在所谈的事例是：某行为虽然无损于别人，但可能严重地伤害到行为者本人。我发现，那些坚信这一点的人都认为这个事例总体来讲绝对是利多弊少；除此而外，他们别无他想。因为在他们看来，该事例若展示了上述胡作非为现象，便会同时展示其痛苦或可耻的后果；若该不端行为应受严厉指责，那么其全部或大部分结果必然也应受到大力批判。

但是，在所有反对公众干涉纯粹私人事务的理据中，最强大的莫过于：倘若公众确实进行干涉的话，那么其干涉方式、干涉地点都很可能是错误的。在社会道德、对他人应尽的责任义务等问题上，公众的主张——即居于主导地位的大多数人的主张——虽然常常是错误的，但很可能在更多时候是正确的；因为在这些问题上，他们需要进行的判断仅仅关乎自己的利益，关乎若允许执行某种行为模式，它将会通过什么方式影响到他们。但是，同一批大多数人在关注自身利益之行为的种种问题上，作为法律强加给自身的那种意见，对错概率很可能是各占一半。原因是，在此类情况下，“公认为正确的意见”至多意味着某些人替他们提出了何者为对何者为错的意见；而经常发生的实际情况是，所谓“公认为正确的意见”甚至连这一点都做不到——公众完全漠视他们所指斥的行为者的愿望或利益，只会考虑他们自己的嗜好。许多人因为厌恶某种行为就认为这种行为伤害到他们，而愤恨地说它迫害了他们的情感。例如，某个宗教偏执狂在别人指责他忽视了他们的宗教感情时反驳说，他们顽固地坚持他们那恶劣的宗教礼拜或教义，就是忽视他的感受。但是，一人对自己意见的感受，和另一人因他有此感受而受到冒犯的感受，二者之间毫无平等可言；就像小偷偷窃钱包的欲望和钱包主人要保住钱包的欲望之间毫无平等可言。一人之趣味与他的意见或钱包一样，都是属于他私人专有的事物。任何人都可以轻易想象出一批完美的公众，他们允许个人在一切归属未明的事物上不受干扰地尽情自由选择，而仅仅要求他们规避那些普遍经验已经证明为不恰当的行为模式。然而，有谁在哪里见到过一批界定了其审查权限的公众呢？公众何时自寻烦恼地探索过普遍经验？他们在干涉个人行为时，除了想到这厮竟敢罪恶滔天地采取与己不同的行动、怀有与己不同的情感，什么其他想法都没有。每10个道德家和理论作家之中，有9人都会近乎不加掩饰地把这种评判标准作为宗教命令和哲学规定，展示在人类眼前。这些人教导说，事物之所以正确是因为它们正确，是因为我们感到它们正确。他们告诉我们，要在我们的头脑和心灵深处寻找约束我们自己和所有他人的行为法则。不幸的公众倘若对道德家和理论作家们的态度还算一致，且要对全世界负责，那么除了践行这些教导、自主决定善恶问题之外，还能做什么呢？

上述弊端不仅仅存在于理论之中。有人或许会希望我举出某些实例，以表明当代英国的公众错误地给自己的偏好赋予了道德律条性质。本文论题并非现存道德情感的差错；那个话题十分重大，无法在本文中以例证方式附带论及。然而，我仍需举出几个例子，以证实我所宣称的原则有着多么重大的实践意义，表明我并非在竭力筑起一道屏障，防范假想中的罪恶。而且，通过很多实例不难证明：将可称作“道德治安”事项的边界扩张，扩张到侵犯了最无可置疑地确属个人合法自由的范围，这种行为乃是所有人类习性中最具普遍性者之一。

首先，思考一下人们憎恶的某些事物。与其他一些持有不同宗教主张、奉行不同教规特别是不同饮食禁忌的人的理由相比，他们憎恶那些事物的理由根本好不到哪儿去。权且举一个极其平凡的例子吧：在基督徒的教条或宗教活动中，没有什么比食用猪肉更令穆罕默德的信徒们愤恨不已、恶意相向的了。基督徒和欧洲人对任何事物的憎恶程度，都比不上伊斯兰教徒对食用猪肉这种充饥方法那毫不掩饰的憎恶。第一，食用猪肉是对他们宗教信仰的冒犯。但这一事实绝不足以解释他们那憎恶之情的程度或性质；因为伊斯兰教同样禁止饮酒，所有教徒都认为喝酒是错误的，但并不令人作呕。相反，他们对那种“污秽动物”肉的嫌恶有种很奇异的特点，像是一种本能的反感。“污秽”观念一旦完全沉潜入教徒的情感之中，似乎总能激起哪怕个人生活习惯最为邋遢龌龊的教徒的厌恶之情。印度教教徒对于宗教性污浊的厌恶感十分强烈，这种情感就是一个显著的例子。假设现有一批人，其中大多数是伊斯兰教徒；假设这批大多数人会坚决强调，本国境内不允许食用猪肉——这一点对伊斯兰教国家而言毫不新奇[46]。在舆论的道德威权下，禁止食用猪肉会不会在该国成为合法行为？倘若答案是不会，为什么？在这批公众看来，食用猪肉的行为可是令人极其恶心的。他们还真诚地相信，神憎恨且禁止人们食用猪肉。可是，不能指斥这种禁止是宗教迫害——虽然禁止的原因可能是宗教性的，但既然没有哪个人的宗教要求他必须食用猪肉，所以此种禁止行为并不算是宗教迫害。在谴责这种禁忌时，唯一站得住脚的理由是：对于个人趣味和种种关注自我的纯个人性事务，众人无权妄加干涉。

让我们回到我国附近来吧。大部分西班牙人都认为，用罗马天主教之外的方式礼拜那位至高无上者是极端无礼的公然不敬；所以在西班牙国土上，其他公开敬拜方式都是违法的。在整个南欧的人们看来，一个已婚牧师不仅是没有宗教信仰，而且是放荡、下流、粗俗、令人作呕的。新教徒怎么看待这些十足真诚的情感呢？怎么看待迫使这些情感服务于反对非天主教徒斗争的企图呢？然而，如果人类在那些丝毫无关他人利益的事物上，能够正当地互相干涉彼此的自由，那么能够根据什么前后一贯的原则来排除这类事例呢？若人们希望镇压他们认为神人共愤的某种丑行，谁能够指责他们呢？任何被认为是个人败德行为的产物都会遭到禁止；在证明此种禁令合理的诸事例中，最有力者莫过于那些把它们视为渎神行径、需要镇压的人编造出的东西。我们若采纳迫害者的逻辑，就会乐意宣称：我们是正确的，所以就可以迫害别人；他们是错误的，所以坚决不能迫害我们。如果我们并不赞同这种逻辑，就必须提防自己认可某条己所不欲的原则——若有人把它施加在我们身上，我们会感到极其冤屈和愤恨。

有人可能会不讲理地反驳上述实例，说它们全是些不可能出现在我们身边的意外事件：在我国，舆论根本不可能强制人们不食用某些肉类，不可能干涉人们的礼拜方式，不可能干涉人们按照自己的信条或偏好结婚或不结婚。但是，下一个例子确确实实地展现了自由是如何受到干涉的，而我们却丝毫没有逃脱它带来的一切危险。无论何处，例如在新英格兰[47]，在英国的共和国时期[48]，只要清教徒权力足够大，便会竭尽全力并相当成功地取缔一切大众的和近乎一切私人的娱乐活动，尤其是音乐、舞蹈、公共娱乐或其他以消遣为目的的群体集会、戏剧。如今，仍有大批英国人从自己的道德和宗教观念出发，认为这些消遣活动有害无益。他们中的绝大部分都是中产阶级，主导着王国当前的社会和政治态势，故此，持有这些看法的人会在某个时刻控制议会中的大多数，这绝对是可能做到之事。社会中的其余人等若获准进行娱乐活动，他们是否乐意享受那些加尔文派和卫理公会派[49]更为严厉的宗教和道德感监管下的娱乐呢？难道他们不会非常专横地要求这些虔诚而冒昧的社会成员少管闲事？无论哪国政府、哪国公众，但凡敢妄称谁都不能享受任何它们认定为错误的娱乐，就应该受到此种质问。然而，一旦其标榜的原则得到认可，谁都无法合理地违抗大多数人或本国其他某些主导势力的意见，无法不遵照执行。倘若某种与其观念相类的宗教信仰要成功收复失地——众所周知，许多被认为已经衰落的宗派经常力挽狂澜而重获新生——所有人都必须做好准备，遵奉“基督教共和国”这一观念；新英格兰早期殖民者就认定，存在一个这样的共和国。

想象一下另一个偶然事件，它或许比上一个更有可能变成现实。大家公认，当代世界上有一股很强劲的势头：不管是否有配套的民主政治制度，都要建立一个民主社会。有人断言：在迄今实现该趋势最彻底的那个国家——它拥有最民主的社会和政府——美国，大多数人的感受相当有效地扮演着禁奢法的角色，因为他们一旦发现，存在着任何自己根本无望可及的浮华或奢华生活方式，就会十分恼火；于是，在美国许多地方，收入极丰的人实在难以不受公众责难地找到任何豪奢的消费方式。尽管这种陈述现存事实的说法不无夸张，但它所描述的事态不仅仅是民主意见可以想象并能够想出的画面，而且是它与“公众有权禁止个人的财产消费方式”这一观念共同作用下非常有可能造就的结果。我们只需进一步推测一下，社会党主张广泛传播开来之后，在大多数人眼里，拥有超出了某个菲薄总额数量的财产，或不事体力劳动而获得收入，就会成为伤风败俗的无耻行径。一些与此相仿的意见已经在手工业者阶级中广为流行，沉重地压在了那些听从该阶级特有舆论的人的心头。也就是说，这些意见只会令该阶级自身的成员烦恼不已。众所周知，构成许多工业部门劳动力主体的那些无技能工人，毫无疑问地主张：拙劣工人应当获得与优秀工人相同的工钱；任何人都不应当靠优良技艺或勤奋劳动、以计件工作或其他方式，挣得比那些没有优良技艺、不肯勤奋劳动的人更多的工钱。他们利用一批道德警察——它们有时会变成现实中的警察——恐吓熟练工人和雇主，使前者不敢靠提供更有用的服务获取更高的报酬，使后者不敢为这种更有用的服务支付更高的报酬。倘若公众能拥有任何管辖别人个人事务的权力，我就看不出这些群体有什么过失，也看不出专司管辖任何个人的那批公众声称自己有权管制其个人行为这种说法有何不当——普通大众就是这样坚称他们有权管制普通人群。

但是，不必深思那些假设的事例了。此时此刻，我们的现实生活中就发生着公然侵夺私人生活自由的事件。还有一些事件性质更为严重，且有可能大肆横行；另有论调鼓吹说，公众应该获得无限权力，不仅有权依法禁止任何他们认为错误的事物，而且为了对付这些错误事物，还要有权禁止任何数量的他们承认为无辜的事物。

在防止放纵行为的名义下，某个英国殖民地的人们和几乎半数的美国人，被法律禁止以医学用途之外的任何方式使用任何种类的发酵饮料。因为正如禁酒令的意图所在，禁止售卖发酵饮料事实上就是禁止使用它们。因为根本无法实际执行，所以美国当初通过该法令的几个州已经废除了禁酒法，包括那个因禁酒法得以命名的州[50]。虽然如此，许多自称为慈善家的人已经开始尝试并相当热情投入地煽动人们也在英国设立一条类似的法令。为此目的，他们创建了一个团体，或曰“同盟”——这是它的自称。在英国，只有极个别公众人物坚信，政界人士的主张应当基于某些原则。在这极个别公众人物中，有一人与上述禁酒团体的干事有通信往来。通信内容公开后，该团体一下变得声名狼藉。有些人懂得，斯坦利勋爵[51]在某些公开场合露面时表现出的品性特征，在那些身处政治生活的人中间显得非常罕见，这很不妙。所以他们计划，让斯坦利勋爵借这次通信强化人们已经对他寄予的厚望。那位“同盟”的喉舌曾声称，“若有人歪曲任何原则，来证明顽冥不化和迫害行为的合理性”，他将“强烈谴责认可该原则的行为”。他现在则承诺，要指出那横亘在此类原则与该禁酒团体所遵循原则之间的“不可逾越的宽阔障碍”。他说：“在我看来，一切与思想、意见、良知有关的事项都在法律范围之外；一切与社会行为、习惯、关系有关的事项都在法律范围之内。这是因为，唯一能够支配后者的，乃是国家自身合法拥有的自由决定权，而个人则未被赋予这种自由决定权。”他根本没有提及第三类事物，它们与他所说的两类事项都不相同。这第三类事物即不是社会性而纯属个人性的那些行为和习惯。饮用发酵酒精饮料的行为无疑就属于这一种类。然而，售卖发酵酒精饮料是贸易，而贸易是社会行为。可人们所抗议的侵犯行为侵犯的并非卖家的自由，而是买家兼消费者的自由；因为政府不仅完全可以禁止人饮酒，还完全可以故意让他弄不到酒。但是，那位干事却说：“无论何时，当我的社会权利被另一位公民的社会行为所侵犯，我作为一位公民，就有权通过立法来维权。”现在我们来看看他是如何解释这些“社会权利”的吧。“如果说有什么事侵犯了我的社会权利，那无疑就是非法买卖酒类。它不断地制造和引发社会骚乱，从而破坏了我最基本的安全权。它靠制造不幸获利，可我却得交税替那不幸买单，从而侵犯了我的平等权。它在我的道路四周布满了危险，削弱和腐化了社会，使我难以行使我可从社会中获得他人帮助和交往的权利，从而妨碍了我自由发展自身道德和心智的权利”。这就是他的“社会权利”观。在他之前，很可能没有哪种语言如此显著明确地表达过类似论调。这种见解简直是在表白：所有个人都拥有这一绝对的社会权利；所有他人都应在所有方面规行矩步；无论何人，只要在某方面某个最微眇的细节上有丝毫闪失，便是侵犯了我的社会权利，因而使我有资格要求立法机关为我申冤雪辱。这条骇人听闻的原则比任何干涉自由的行为都危险得多。对于任何侵犯自由的行为，它都能够证明其正当性。它不承认人类享受任何自由权，也许唯一的例外是，它只承认人们可以秘密持有意见但永远不能公之于众的自由。这是因为，我认为有害的某种意见一旦越过了某人的唇齿，便侵犯了该“同盟”赋予我的全部“社会权利”。该团体的学说认为，每个人的道德、心智乃至身体是否完善，都与全人类利益攸关；只是这项利益的具体内容需要由每个利益相关者按照其自己的标准加以确定。

另一个非法干涉个人正当自由的例子是关于安息日制度的立法。它不仅是可能发生的事情，而且是早已取得显著成效的事情。只要生活急务容许，每周都有一天停止日常劳作，进行休息；这种宗教禁忌对犹太人之外的人来说，虽然完全没有义务履行，但实际是一项十分有益的习俗。要遵守这一习俗，就需要工人阶级普遍赞同其成效；因此，只要某些劳动者可强迫他人接受其必要性，那么该关于安息日制度的立法便可暂停某一天的大范围工业作业，从而保证所有人都同该习俗的奉行者一样奉行它。这一辨析依据的理由是：每位个人对该惯例的奉行都直接关乎其他人的利益。但上述辨析并不适用于那些个人自选的职业，因为在这类职业中，个人可能感到利用闲暇工作并无不妥。此外，它也毫不适于用作对法律管制娱乐的理由。确实，有些人的日常工作就是为他人提供娱乐；但许多人的快乐——甚至有用的休闲活动——需要少数人的劳动付出，前提是后者自由选择了这一工作，也可以自由放弃它。工人们完全正确地认为：如果大家都在周日工作，那么7天的工作只能得到6天的工资；但只要各行各业都休息一天，为了别人享受娱乐而必须工作的那一小批人，便会获得相应的工资增长；而且倘若他们也想休闲而不想挣钱，就不必始终从事这些服务工作。若要寻找进一步的解决方案，可以考虑：根据习俗，为这些特定人群在一周当中另选一天，设立为休息日。这样，管制周日娱乐所能找到的唯一理由必然是：从宗教角度看，周日娱乐是错误的。这一立法动机永远不会受到强烈反对。“获罪于神，神其治之。”尚需证明的是：若其任何负责人受到了上天的委任，要报复某一假定的触怒了全能者的罪行——虽然这罪行对人类而言毫不为错。有观念认为，个人有责任使另一人信教。这种观念正是一切宗教迫害暴行的依据；若获得允许，它还会全面证明此类罪行的正当性。人们多次试图阻止火车在周日运行，抵制各种博物馆开放，等等。他们在诸如此类的行为中爆发出的激动情绪并没有古代宗教迫害者的那种残暴，但其中透露出的心态则是根本一致的，即：既然迫害者的宗教规定不准做此事，那就决不容忍别人做其宗教允许的事。这种决心也是一种信念：上帝不仅憎恶邪教徒的行为，而且如若我们放任邪教徒自行其是，还会认定我们有罪。

这些例子表明：人类自由普遍地受到了忽视。除此之外，我忍不住再举一例：我国报刊上骤现的露骨的迫害性语言。不论何时，只要这些报刊感到必须评论摩门教[52]那奇特的现象时，都会使用这种语言。号称从上帝那里获得新启示而创立的摩门教，明显是个破绽百出的骗局，就连其创始人那非凡品质与赫赫威望也无法证明其合理性。但是，在这个报纸林立、铁路通达、电讯便捷的时代，它竟有数十万上百万的信徒，还竟然组建了一个公司！对此匪夷所思、富有教益的事实，可说的实在太多。但我们此处所关注的是，该教像其他较好的宗教一样，也有殉道者；其先知兼创建者因宣传其教义，被一伙暴徒杀害；该教的其他拥护者同样丧命于非法暴力之下；摩门教派作为一个整体，被暴力驱逐出他们最初成长的地区；虽然他们如今已被赶入沙漠中的某个荒山野谷，还有许多英国人公然声称：公正（但又并不方便）的做法是，派遣一支远征军去打击他们，用武力迫使他们遵从其他人的意见。摩门教有一条教义，最令世人忍无可忍，它冲破了宗教宽容的常规限制、激起了强烈的憎恶之情，即准许多妻制。伊斯兰教徒、印度教徒和中国人都允许一夫多妻制，可一旦说英语、声称是某种形式基督徒的人也实施这种制度，似乎就会激起不可遏制的汹汹恨意。我对这一摩门教制度谴责之强烈程度是无人可比的。我之所以如此，是由于在其他原因之外，还有一条主因：这一制度根本不是对自由原则的支持，而是对自由原则的直接违犯——一夫多妻制完全钉牢了束缚着一半摩门教教徒的枷锁，解脱了另一半摩门教教徒对她们应尽的互利义务。此外，我必须要提醒的是，从摩门教有关女教徒方面讲，这种关系同任何其他形态的一夫多妻制情况一样，在很大程度上是自愿的，尽管她们可能被认为是此制度的受害者。我必须要提醒：不论这一事实看起来多么不可思议，都能够在全世界的普通观念和习俗中找到原因。这些观念和风俗教导妇女，使她们认为婚姻是必不可少之物，使她们知道，宁可同许多其他妇女嫁给同一个丈夫，也不能没有丈夫。摩门教并没有要求其他地区和国家认可这种婚姻，也没有要求各地各国让出任何数量的居民，准许他们不再遵守本国法律，而改从摩门教的主张。但是，这些异教徒屈从了教外民众的敌意，做了太多的让步而提出了太少的正当要求。他们离开了那些反对摩门教义的地区，在地球上一个偏远的角落获得了立足之地，作为当地第一批居民，把那里开垦成为适宜人类居住的家园。他们从未侵凌过其他民族，也允许那些对他们做法不满的人完全自由地离去。当他们做了这一切之后，我们很难看出，除了专制主义之外，我们还能根据什么原则，阻止他们在自认为合适的制度下生活在那里。最近有位在某些方面相当优秀的作家提议说（我引用他本人的话）：对这个实行多妻制的组织，应该用教化运动而非征伐运动，以终结其在他看来是令文明倒退的堕落行径。我赞同他对一夫多妻制的这种看法；但我感到，任一社群都无权强迫另一社群走上文明之路。只要那种恶劣制度的受害者们并未祈求其他社群对她们进行救助，我就不能容许与她们毫无关联的人介入，要求终结所有利益直接相关者好像都很满意的某一事态，理由是：在成千上万英里以外、与之丝毫无干的人们看来，此事是一宗丑行。这些局外人如果乐意，完全可以派遣传教团来宣讲该丑行的诸种罪恶，也可以借助任何正当手段（钳噤摩门教传教士不算）来对抗与摩门教类似的教义在这些外部人群中的传播。当世界上充斥的只有野蛮时，如果文明战胜了野蛮，那么在野蛮早已被完全制服之后，文明人还声称因唯恐野蛮会卷土重来，进而征服文明而忧心忡忡，实在太不像话。一种这么容易屈服于其手下败将的文明，必然早已堕落到这种程度，无论是它所指派的牧师和导师，或任何他人，都没有能力或愿意费心来捍卫它了。倘若果真如此，那么这种文明越早收到要求它认输的通知，效果就越好。它只能从朽坏走向更坏，直到（像西罗马帝国那样）被活力蓬勃的蛮族摧毁与重建。

五　论自由原则之应用

这些书页中所坚称的两大原则共同构成了本文的学说整体。我必须让世人更加广泛地承认，它们乃是深入讨论细节的根本依据，而后才可尝试将其前后一致地应用于政府和道德的所有部门，并期望它们的优势充分展现。我将对细节问题所做的观察评论，为的是举例说明这两大原则，不是要将其贯彻到底，直至产生结果。我下文将提出的内容，与其说是这两大准则的用途，毋宁说是其应用样本；这些样本可能会更清楚地展现二者的意义和局限，并在那些难以看出哪条准则适用的案例中，帮助我们在二者之间做出抉择。

这两大准则是：第一，只要个人的活动与他人无关而仅关乎本人，那么他就不必为之向社会负责。如果别人觉得，为了他们自身的利益，必须对他进行忠告、教诲、劝说、躲避，那么这些忠告等等，都不过是社会使用的手段罢了，以便理由充分地表达自己对他行为的厌恶或谴责。第二，个人要对自己有损于他人利益的行为负责，并且可能受到社会制裁或法律制裁——如果社会感到必需其中之一来保护自我。

首先，虽然损害到或可能会损害他人利益就会招致社会的正当干涉，但绝不能因此断定社会干涉永远是正当合理的。在许多情况下，个人在追求某一合法目标时，必然且因而合理地会给他人带来痛苦或损失，或者致使他人有望获得的正当利益功败垂成。这种个人利益间的冲突往往源自恶劣的社会制度，只要这种制度仍然存在，此种冲突就不可避免；其中的某些冲突在任何制度下都是不可避免的。不论何人，只要在同行过多的职业或竞争激烈的考试中取得成功，只要在他与别人为获得同一个目标的竞争中胜出，就是从别人的失败、徒然努力和失望中获利。可是，无人否认，人们不应被这种结果所震慑，而应继续追求其目标；这样做更利于提升人类的总体利益。换言之，社会并未赋予那些失望的竞争者有任何法律或道义权利，使他们能够免于这种苦痛。只有当他们的对手为取得成功而使用违背人类总体利益的禁用手段——即造假或诈骗、暴力——时，社会才会感到有责任进行干预。

同样，贸易也是一种社会行为。任何向公众出售任何类型商品的人，都是在从事影响他人利益和社会总体利益的工作。因此，他的行为在原则上属于社会的管辖范畴。于是，过去，在一切被认为价值重大的问题上，定价和控制生产过程都被认为是政府的职责所在。但如今人们已经认识到——虽然是经过漫长的努力才产生了这种认识：要有效促成价廉物美商品的供应，就要给予生产者和销售者完全的自由；唯一的审查手段是，让购买者享有同样的自由，他们可到别处购买别的商品。这就是所谓的自由贸易理论。该理论的依据与本文主张的个人自由原则有所不同，但二者同样坚实可靠。对贸易的限制或对为贸易而进行的生产的限制，都是实实在在的限制。任何限制都是罪恶。但此处所论的限制，仅仅影响人类行为中社会应当限制的部分；之所以称这些限制是错误的，只是因为它们并未真正产生社会期望的结果。个人自由原则与自由贸易理论无关，也与关于该理论之应用界限的绝大部分问题无关。那些问题很多，例如：为防止掺假欺诈，可允许多大程度的公共管控；为保护从事危险职业的雇工，应该在多大程度上强制雇主采取卫生预防措施或条件。在其他条件不变的情况下，让人们自行其便总是优于管制他们；仅当此时，上述那类自由贸易理论之应用界限问题才涉及对自由因素的考虑。虽说如此，但为了达到上述目的而合法地管制他们，从原则上讲也是完全可行的。另一方面，一些与干涉贸易相关的问题，在本质上也是事关自由的问题。例如，前文已提到的《禁酒法》问题、禁止向中国输入鸦片问题、限制有毒物质销售问题，等等。简而言之，所有以使人无法或难以获得某种特定商品为目的的社会干涉案例，都属于这类问题。这些干涉行为之所以应该反对，不是因为它们侵犯了生产者或销售者的自由，而是因为它们侵犯了购买者的自由。

其中的一例，就是关于有毒物质销售，这引发了一个新的问题：可称为“公共管制职责”的恰当界限在哪里？或曰，为了预防犯罪或意外事故，可在多大程度上合法地侵犯个人自由？政府无可争议的职责之一，就是不仅要在犯罪行为发生后查明案情、惩罚罪犯，而且要采取预防措施，防患于未然。可是，政府对犯罪的防范职能远比其惩罚职能更容易被滥用，而损害个人自由；因为在个人合法的行为自由当中，没有哪个部分不会被描述为——而且被清清楚楚地描述为——增强了这种或那种犯罪的便利条件。然而，倘若某个政府部门，甚至某个个人，发现有人显然在准备实施犯罪，他们不一定要袖手旁观地等到犯罪行为发生之后再采取行动，而可以积极干预，及时阻止。如果购买或使用有毒物质的唯一目的是进行谋杀犯罪，那么正当的做法是严禁制造和销售毒物。然而，人们购买这些毒药的目的可能不但清白无辜而且颇有益处，而限制条款则不可能在一个案例中被强制实施，到了另一案例中就销声匿迹。同理，预防意外事件也是公权机关的一项正当职能。倘若某个公职人员或另外的人发现，有人打算要经过一座已经查明的危桥，但已来不及向他发出危险警告了，他们可以抓住他把他拉回来；这根本算不上对他个人自由的干涉，因为自由意味着做自己想做的事情，而他并不想掉进河里。不过，有时，某件事并不必然会产生危害，而只是有产生危害的风险，除当事者本人之外，谁都无法判断他究竟在多大程度上愿意承受可能的风险；在这种情况下，我认为，（除非他是个未成年人，或神志不清，或处于某种亢奋或沉迷状态而不能充分调用其反应能力）别人就应当只是提醒他有潜在的危险，而不应强迫他远离危险。将上述需考虑因素应用于销售有毒物质这类问题，同样能使我们判定，在所有可能的管控模式中，哪些有理，哪些无理。例如，用某个能充分表现其毒性的词命名那种毒物，这样的预防措施不会侵犯个人自由，可以强制推行；购买者不会不希望知道，他拥有的这件东西是有毒之物。但若无论如何都要求购买者出具开业医师证书，会令他总要付出高价才能获得——有时甚至无法获得——该物品。我发现，只有一个方法值得考虑，它既能为犯罪设置重重困难，又不会侵犯那些为其他目的而需要此毒物者的自由。套用边沁[53]那贴切的术语来讲，这个方法就是：提供“预先约定的证据”。众所周知，这一预备措施的常见应用就是契约。在签署契约时，通常且正确的做法是：法律会要求订约双方履行一些正式手续作为契约实施的条件，例如签名、证人的证词等等，以便日后出现纠纷时，能有证据证明该契约已经真正订立，证明在这种情况下什么都无法令它丧失法律效力。其效果就是，设置巨大障碍，防止出现假契约或者在已知将破坏其合法性的情形下签订的契约。在销售可被用作犯罪手段的物品时，可以采取与此同样性质的预防措施。例如，可要求销售者在一个登记簿上注明该笔交易的准确时间、购买者的姓名与地址、商品的精确类型和数量；他还要询问该商品的购买用途，并记录买方的回答。若购买者没有携带医学处方，就需要有第三方在场，确保购买者清楚全部实情，以防日后他有将该物品用于犯罪目的的借口。通常而言，这些管制措施不会实质性地妨碍购买者获得该商品，但会严重阻碍他不被人察觉地违法使用它。

社会防卫自己免遭犯罪这一天然权利，表露了本文所述个人行为自由准则的明显界限：对于纯粹关注自我利益的错误行为，为了预防或惩罚目的而胡乱干涉并不恰当。例如，在普通情况下，法律干预手段并不适用于酗酒。但倘若某人有前科，曾在酒精作用下对他人犯有暴行，就应针对他个人设置某种特殊法律限制。例如，以后若再发现他醉酒，就要进行处罚；若他再次在醉酒状态下犯罪，那么对其罪行的惩罚将更加严厉。我认为，这种处罚是完全合法的。一个一旦醉酒就会危害他人的人，若把自己灌醉，就是在对他人犯罪。同样，对于游手好闲行为，不能暴力地进行法律惩处，除非这种行为来自某个受到公众救济的人，或是构成了违背契约的行为。但是，如果无论是出于懒散或其他本可避免的原因，某人未能履行他对别人的法定责任——例如，抚养亲生儿女——那么在别无他法的情况下，用强制劳动迫使他履行此责任，就不是暴举。

同理，许多行为只会直接伤害到施为者本人，所以不应当被法律所禁止；但是若他们公开实施这种行为，就是粗暴无礼，因而属于冒犯他人的行为范畴了，要依法禁止。此外，许多行为本身无可指摘，也不应受到指摘，但人们同样强烈地反对传扬这类行为；有伤风化罪指的就是此类行为，但它们与本文主题并无直接关联，我就不必详加论述了。

另有一个亟待解决的问题与本文所主张的两大原则一脉相承。在一些事例中，个人行为虽可谓有过失，但对个人自由原则的遵守却会使社会无法阻止或惩罚这类行为，因为其直接恶果完全降临到了施为者的头上。施为者能够自由从事的事情，其他人应该同样自由地劝告或怂恿他吗？这个问题难以回答。一人请求另一人采取某一行动，严格地讲，这样的事例并非关注自我利益的行为。对任何人进行劝告或诱导是一种社会行为，因此，同能够影响他人的一般活动一样，应该可以受到社会的管控。但是稍加反思，就可以意识到上述第一印象的错误之处：即便此事并不严格符合个人自由的界定，可个人自由原则所依据的理由也完全可以用作它的理由。如果人们在任何仅仅关乎自己的事情上，都必须能够以其自认为最好的方式、后果自负地采取行动，那么他们就必须能够同等自由地彼此咨询，探讨什么做法适合前述目的，也能够同等自由地交换意见、提出和接受建议。凡是获准做的事情，都必须获准接受建议。仅当建议者因其建议而获得某种个人利益时，仅当他为了生计或钱财受益，以促成社会或国家认为是罪恶的事为职业时，才会变得疑点重重。实际上，那时会出现一种新的复杂化因素，即：存在某一类人，他们的利益与被认为是公共福利的事物相对立，他们的生活方式恰恰基于对公共福利的违背。应该对这件事进行干涉吗？还是不该？例如，必须容忍通奸现象，也必须容忍赌博现象；但是人能够自由地成为皮条客，或拥有赌场吗？这个例子同许多事例一样，恰恰处于两大原则之间的分界线上，乍看之下，无法判断将它归属哪一原则更为恰当。同意干涉和不同意干涉的双方都振振有词。建议采取容忍态度的一方可能会说：从事任何职业借以谋生或从中获利这件事，不可能蓄养出其他生存方式会容许的罪犯；这种谋生行为或者被始终允许，或者始终禁止；倘若我们至今捍卫的原则真实有效，那么社会作为社会就无权判断任何仅仅关乎个人的事物为错；此种谋生行为不可能无法劝阻，正如一人应拥有说服的自由，另一人应拥有劝阻的自由。反对容忍的一方可能会主张：尽管公众或国家无法保证能够权威地断定，仅仅影响个人利益的某行为是好还是坏，而需要对其实施压制或惩罚，但它们完全有理由假定，若视之为坏事，那么该行为的好坏至少还是个可以商榷的问题。在这样假定之后，公众或国家在竭力消除利益相关的诱惑者或有所偏向的怂恿者之影响时，就不会举措失误。某行为被断定为好或坏直接关系到那些怂恿者的个人利益，他们所赞同的判断，国家却相信是错误的；他们公然宣扬该行为的好处或坏处，完全是为了个人利益。有人可能会极力建议，可以这样安排事务：人们必须自作主张，聪明或愚蠢地做出自主选择，尽量避免有些人诡计多端地为了个人利益和目的而怂恿他们选择某种做法；这么一来，就能够确保万无一失，人们的利益就不会受损。这样（有人可能会说），虽然针对非法游戏的法规完全站不住脚，虽然所有人都应自由地在自家或别人家，或他们自费建起、仅对成员或访客开放的聚会场所赌博，但是不应准许公共赌场的存在。确实，禁令从未奏效，不论赋予了警方多大的暴力执法权，赌场都总能改头换面而长期存在；但它们也许被迫在某种程度的机密或神秘状态下运营，除了那些找寻它们的赌客之外，谁都对它们一无所知；除此之外，社会不应再对它们有其他企图。这些说法相当有力，我不敢贸然断定它们是否足以证明下述道义反常现象的合理性：惩罚从犯而允准（且必然允准）主犯逍遥法外；受到罚款或监禁的是皮条客而非通奸者，是赌场老板而非赌客。根据类似理由，平常的买卖行为受到的干涉应当更少。近乎所有被买卖的商品都会被滥用，卖家为了多赚钱，会鼓励买家过度使用那些商品。但是，这并不能作为依据，来论证《禁酒法》之类的社会干涉行为是多么卓越。因为烈性饮料的经销商群体虽然很乐于人们酗酒，但必然会被要求保证这些烈性酒得到合理使用。然而，这些经销商若怂恿人们放纵，便是真正犯下了恶行，因此，国家可正当地迫使他们接受管制、要求他们提交保证金；若非出于这一正当理由，国家的上述做法就是干涉了他们的合法自由。

接下来的问题是，虽然情况容许，但国家是否应当间接阻止它认为会违背施为者最佳利益的行为呢？例如，国家是否应采取措施，让导致人们喝醉的手段变得更加昂贵？或通过限制销售点的数量，使人们难以获得这些商品？与大部分其他现实问题一样，在这件事上，要进行多重区分。仅仅为了让人们更难以获得这些兴奋性饮料而对它们课税，这种措施与完全禁止只是在程度上有别而已，而且仅当它正当时它才会是正当的。对那些囊中羞涩、望价兴叹的人而言，每次提价都是一次禁令；而对那些钱包鼓胀、出得起价的人而言，提价是对他们满足自己某种特殊偏好的一种惩罚。在他们履行过自己对国家和对个人的法定与道德义务后，他们选择什么样的消遣方式、怎样花光收入的消费方式，都是他们的私事，必须由他们自主判断。乍看之下，这些意见似乎是在谴责那种为收税而把酒类作为特别课税对象的做法。但我们必须牢记：为财政目的而征税是绝对必要的；在绝大多数国家，这类税收之中相当大的部分必须是间接征收的；因此，国家不得不对人们使用某消费品的行为进行罚款。对某些人而言，这种罚款过于昂贵、承受不起。因此，国家在征税时有责任考虑，消费者最好不买哪些商品；更不容置疑的是，它有责任优先选择那些用量一旦超出某个适度数值，就肯定会产生危害的商品。于是，对酒类征收的税率高达能够带来最大数额财政收入的程度（假设国家需要酒税带来的全部税收），这不仅可以容许，而且应当赞许。

可否让销售这些商品变成一个或大或小的专属特权？这个问题必须根据限制手段所要服务的目的，来给出不同的回答。所有公共聚集地点都需要治安力量控制秩序，这类地方异常需要治安管理，是因为针对社会的罪行特别容易在那里产生。所以，恰当的做法就是：限制酒类商品的销售权，只能卖给那些已知或已有人保证的行为得体的人（至少是当场饮用）；还要明文规定商家开门关门的具体营业时间，以便公众监督之需；如果某酒馆老板的纵容或无能导致此处反复发生违反治安事件，或如果该酒馆成为犯罪分子谋划和准备犯罪行为的集合地点，就要撤销其酒类销售许可证书。我想象不出，此外还有什么其他在原则上无可非议的限制手段。举例来说，为了增加人们获得酒类的难度、减少他们受到诱惑的机会这一明确目标，限制销售啤酒和烈性酒酒馆的数量，这种做法不仅会给全社会制造麻烦，而且仅适用于某种特定的社会状态。说它会制造麻烦是因为有些人会滥用这一点；在那种特定的社会状态下，劳动阶级被公然当作儿童或野蛮人加以对待，并被置于束缚式的教育之下，好把他们打造得适合在未来获准进入自由的特权。但是，任何自由国家在表面上都绝非照此原则来管理其劳动阶级；真正看重自由的人没有谁会支持劳动阶级受到这般统治，除非社会和国家已经竭尽各种努力，教给他们自由、把他们作为自由人来管理，但最终证明他们只能像儿童那样接受管控。这种对其他可能性的赤裸陈述表明，认为上述努力无论如何都已做出，这是多么荒谬的假定！我们就此讨论一下这个荒谬假定。正因为我国的体制与习俗是一团矛盾百出的乱麻，所以原本属于专制政府或所谓父权制政府体制下的事物找到机会溜进了我们的日常生活，而我国体制与习俗中的普遍自由使我们无法对其进行必要的适度管控，无法以道德教育形式对其实施任何卓有成效的限制措施。

前文已然指出，个人在仅仅关乎自身利益事物上的自由意味着，任何数量的个人群体能够通过相互协定，自由地管理与他们自己共同相关——与他们这一群体之外的别人无关——的事情。只要事情涉及的所有人的意志始终不变，这一相互协定、自我管理问题就不难解决。但众人的意志可能会改变，所以他们经常相互签订契约；一旦他们签订了契约，那么按照一般规则，他们就应遵守约定。不过，很可能在每个国家的法律中，这种一般规则都有某些例外情况：法律不仅要求签约双方信守那些侵犯了第三方权益的契约，而且还会以某契约也会伤害双方当事人的自身利益为充分理由，解除他们的约定关系。例如，在英国和其他大多数文明国家，若某份契约规定一人将自己或允许他人将他卖作奴隶，那么这就是一份无效契约，不会受到法律或舆论的强制执行。为什么如此限制自愿卖掉自己一生命运的权力呢？其原因不言而喻，在此极端情况下清清楚楚地展现在了人们面前：人们之所以不干涉某人的自愿行为，若非为了别人的利益，就是为了尊重个人自由。他的自主选择证明：他所选择的事物对他来说是理想之物，或至少是可以忍受之物；允许他采用自己的方法追求该事物，总体而言，就是最充分地保障了他的利益。然而，将自身卖作奴隶时，就是放弃了他的个人自由；此举之后，他完全放弃了对个人自由的任何使用权。这样一来，他就在自己的案例中违背了自己的本意，而他的本意恰恰就是证明允许他卖掉自己是正当做法的理据。他失去了自由，此后就处于一种他若自愿停留其中就会如愿以偿的状态，而这种状态是无法再做出自主自利的假定的。个人自由原则不可能规定，他可以自由地决定自己要失去自由。为同意他放弃自己的自由，而批准给他的并不是自由。上述原因的巨大力量在此特异个案中得到了十分醒目的展现。显而易见，这些原因有着更为广阔的应用范围。但种种生活必然性处处都给它们设下了界限，并不断对我们提出要求：不是要求我们必须真的放弃个人自由，而是要求我们同意那卡在了我们个人自由两端的限界。可是，前述准则之一要求，个人在仅仅涉及他们自己的所有活动中都拥有无限的自由；这条原则规定意味着：那些被仅涉及当事双方、无干第三方的事物协定密切联系在一起的人，应当能够互相解除对方的契约义务。甚至可以说，如果没有这种自发的解除义务行为，或许根本就没有契约或约定，但与钱财或钱财价值有关的契约除外。对于与钱财有关的契约，人们敢说，根本就不应当有任何撤销的自由。威廉·冯·洪堡男爵在我前文曾引用过的那篇文章中说道：他确信，关于人际关系或个人服务的协定，超出一定时限之后，应当不再具有法律约束力；这类协定中最重要的就是婚姻；婚姻的特殊之处是，若夫妻双方不能琴瑟和谐，那么双方都会十分沮丧；因此，解除婚姻的要求只有一条——夫妻之任一方宣布其离婚意愿即可。婚姻这个话题过于重要，也过于复杂，本文无法附带论及，所以我只是出于例证之需，在此略提几句。洪堡男爵的宏论若非极其简洁概括，使他在此论题上满足于不谈前提就直接阐明结论，那么他肯定已经意识到，这个问题不可能根据他所宣称的那类简单理由而获得解决。倘若某人的明确承诺或成功行为促使另一人相信，他会继续按某一方式行动——使对方建立起对他的期望和估计，并根据这一预测冒险制定了其人生计划的任何部分——他就向对方担负起了一系列新的道德义务。对于那些新的道德义务，他虽然可以拒绝，但是却无法忽视。同理，如果订约双方的关系产生了影响到他人的结果，如果双方关系使第三方处于某种特殊位置，或者像上述婚姻案例中那样，甚至导致产生了第三方，那么订约双方便都对这些处于第三方状态的人负有新的义务。要履行这些新义务，或总之要采取什么履行方式，都必然受到当初订约双方的关系仍然存续或已经中断这一状态的剧烈影响。这并不意味着，且我也不承认，这些新义务甚至包括，要求订约双方为了被动卷入的第三方的福祉，不惜一切代价地履行契约。但这些新增义务是整个问题中无法回避的因素。即便像冯·洪堡所称，它们对订约双方解除契约的合法自由毫无影响（我也同意，它们不应当造成很大影响），但必然会对其道义自由造成重大影响。人在决定采取某个可能影响到他人重大利益的步骤之前，必须要通盘考虑全部情况；倘若他不能正确地重视他人的重大利益，就已经在道义上犯了错误，而应负相应责任。这些观点浅显明白，我在此论述它们，是为了更清晰地说明个人自由这一普遍原则，而并非因为它们对婚姻问题不可或缺。可实际情况与此恰恰相反，在通常对婚姻问题的讨论中，似乎孩子的利益便是全部，而父母的利益无关紧要。

我已注意到，由于缺乏任何公认的一般原则，在本应给予自由的场合反倒经常拒不准许自由；在本应拒绝自由的场合反倒经常给予自由。在当今欧洲世界的很多事实中，自由之情十分强烈。其中一例在我看来，是完全错误地寄托了这种沸腾的自由之情。在仅关乎个人的事物上，人应当能够自由地依愿行事；但当代表别人时，就不应借口别人的事务就是他本人的事务而随心所欲。国家一方面尊重每个人在私人事务中的个人自由，另一方面也必须警惕地保持对他运用自由的管控，以防其利用个人自由获得凌驾于他人之上的权力，并对他们为所欲为。但是，在家庭关系上，国家的这项责任几乎被彻底漠视了。家庭直接影响着人类的福祉，它的重要性超过其他一切影响因素之和。本文不需详述丈夫对妻子近乎暴君式的专横权力；为彻底消除这种罪恶，唯一要做的是让妻子拥有与所有他人同样的权利、获得与法律给予所有他人的同样方式的保护。因为，在这个问题上，既定不公习俗的拥护者们根本不肯采纳我们对自由的辩解，而是作为强权的捍卫者公然站了出来。正是在涉及孩子们的案件中，各种被滥用的自由观念构成了阻止国家履行其职责的真正障碍。人们几乎会认为：一个男人的儿女应该是他的一部分——这不是比喻，而是实实在在的看法——所以，他对他们拥有绝对的、独享的支配权；法律只能在最低限度上实施对这种父权的干涉。这种见解实在是太谨慎了，几乎比所有干涉他自身行为自由的意见都更加慎重——在大多数人心目中，权力比自由重要得多。例如，想想教育这件事吧。国家应该要求和强制所有生而为其公民的人接受达到某种程度的教育，这难道不是自明之理吗？然而，有谁毫不畏惧地认识到并坚决提出了这一真理呢？事实上，没有谁会否认，父母（或者，按照法律和习俗的观点，父亲）在把一个人带到这个世界中来之后，其最神圣的责任之一就是给予他某种教育，使他能够在生活中为别人和自己扮演好他的角色。然而，尽管人们一致公认这是为父者的责任，但我国几乎谁都不忍听到某个父亲被迫履行该责任的传闻。没有人要求他为了让孩子接受教育而费尽心力或做出牺牲；恰恰相反，教育是免费提供的，他只需选择接受与否！人们尚未认识到的是：若既无能力为孩子的肉体存活和成长提供食物，又无能力为孩子的心智存在和发展提供教导和训练，在这种黯淡的前景下生育孩子，就是对那个不幸的孩子和对社会的道德犯罪；倘若那个做父亲的没有履行其责任，国家就应在尽量由该父亲承担全部费用的情况下，确保这一责任得到履行。

一旦人们接受了国家强制实施普及教育的职责，那么国家该教授什么内容、以什么方式教授等纷争便会终止；而如今的争执已把教育问题变成了一个诸党众派较量的战场，致使那本应花在教育上的时间与精力，都浪费在了围绕教育发生的争吵上面。倘若国家肯下定决心，要求所有儿童都受到良好教育，那么它就可能省掉了提供教育的麻烦。国家可允许父母在他们满意的地方、以他们满意的方式让孩子获得教育；国家自己则满足于帮助贫困儿童缴纳学费，支付那些无其他收入来源孩子们的全部学杂费用。那些合理反对国家教育的主张，并没有请求国家强制推行教育，而是请求它主动承担指导教育的责任，二者完全不同。我同任何人一样，坚决反对“应把全部或任意大部分的教育民众权交到国家手里”的意见。前文就保持个人特征、观点多元和行为方式多样之重要性所讲的一切，实则也包括教育多样化那难以言传的同等的重要性。普及性国家教育完全是一种把民众塑造成如出一辙的人为手段。用来塑造他们的铸模是政府中的主导势力——无论它是某个君主、某个神职人员集团、某个贵族阶层，还是当代人中的大多数——感到满意的形态，所以这个铸模越有效、越成功，那主导势力就越高兴。这样，政府中的主导势力就会确立对心灵的专制统治，继而自然而然地建立起对肉体的专制统治。国家创建并控制的教育倘若果真存在，也只能作为一种试验，与许多相互竞争的试验共存，为了起到范例和激励作用而坚持进行，以便使其他教育试验达到某种优秀标准。事实上，除非全社会普遍处于某种落后状态，不能或不愿为自己提供任何适当的教育机构，否则，政府就不能承担该任务；确实，直到那时，政府作为两大祸患之中的较轻者，才能主动承担起创办中小学校和大学的责任，就像该国在尚未产生适合承担重大工业业务的私营企业形态时，政府才能主动接过创办和经营股份公司的任务。但一般而言，如果该国存在数量足够的合格人才，能够在政府主持下提供教育，那么他们就会有能力、有意愿，在义务教育法为其提供工资保障、国家帮助贫困生支付所有开销的条件下，提供同样优质的义务制教育。

强制实施义务制教育法律的手段非统考莫属。所有儿童都要在很小时参加这些统考。可以规定每名儿童必须在几岁参加考试，以查明他（或她）是否识字。如果考试结果表明某个儿童不识字，那么其父亲就要被处以适量的罚款，必要时让他以工代罚，以便为该儿童接受学校教育付费。统考每年都要举办一次，考试科目逐步增多，考查范围逐步扩大，以便儿童普遍学习和记住某种最低限度的一般知识——实际上即必须掌握的知识。在那一最低限度之外，所有科目还应有各科的自愿考试，凡是能达到某种水平标准的考生，都可以获得一个合格证书。为防止国家通过这些安排不正当地影响舆论，应当把通过某项考试所需的知识范围（即语言及其用法之类工具性知识之外的知识）完全限定为事实类和实证科学类知识，即便那些等级较高的考试也是如此。对宗教、政治和其他有争议话题的考查内容不应是判断各种观点的正误，而应是事实本身，例如，某作者、某学派或某教派根据某理由提出了某论点。在这种制度下，关于所有存在争议的事实，年轻一代面临的窘境就不会比如今这代更糟。他们将与现在一样，被培养成为牧师或持异议者；国家仅需确保他们是有教养的牧师，或有教养的持异议者。如果他们的父母决定让他们学习宗教，那么他们就可以在教授其他知识的同一所学校里，不受任何妨碍地学习宗教。国家若试图影响其公民对有争议问题的结论，就是犯罪；但它可以非常正当地帮助查清和证明，某人具备任一值得关注问题的相关必要知识，能够得出自己的结论。学习哲学的学生不论更赞同洛克[54]还是更赞同康德[55]，或哪位都不赞成，若他有能力通过考查二人学说的考试，就是优秀的学生。若考查一个无神论者学生关于基督教的征兆问题，而不要求他宣称相信那些迹象，则通达事理的人都不会反对此项考试。但我认为，在较高知识分支领域的考试应该是完全自愿的。倘若允许政府阻止任何人从事许多职业，甚至允许它能以不够资格为借口，拒绝任何人从事教师职业，就是把一种极为危险的权力交给了政府。我同威廉·冯·洪堡一样认为：所有参加考试并通过了测验的人，都应该获得学位或其他公开表明持有者具备了科学或职业技能的证书；但是，除了舆论可能对其证明价值的推崇之外，这些文凭不应给予其持有者任何超过竞争对手的优势。

定位不当的自由概念使人们既认识不到父母对孩子应负的道德义务，也无法强制他们负起对孩子的法律责任，这种情况不仅仅出现于教育问题当中。无论何处，只要一直存在着前一问题最为顽固的基础，它也就经常会成为后一问题坚不可摧的根据。导致一个人生存于世这一事情本身，乃是人类生活当中责任最为重大的行为之一。担负起这一责任——把一个或祸端或福分的生命赋予某个生物——乃是对那个生物犯罪，除非那个被赋予生命的生物即将拥有至少是很普通的获得良好生存条件的机会。在一个人口已经过剩或者即将过剩的国家，生育儿女的数量若超过某个很小的数值，且其生存竞争导致了工资减少的后果，那么超额生育便是对那些靠工资过活的劳动者犯下了严重罪行。许多欧陆国家的法律规定，若当事人不能证明他们有能力养活一个家庭，那么他们就不能结婚。这些法规并没有超出国家的合法权力范畴，不论它们是否得当（这个问题主要取决于当地的具体情况和人们的感受），都没有令人厌恶地触犯个人自由。这些法规是国家为禁止某种恶行而采取的干预措施，因为该行为会伤害他人，应当受到谴责，并背负社会耻辱，即便人们认为并不适合对其追加法律惩罚方法。可是，当前人们对自由的看法虽然很容易屈从于外界对私人事务中个人自由的真实侵犯，却会成功抵制试图约束个人之偏好的限制手段——倘若此人沉迷嗜好的后果是一代或几代儿孙在悲惨、堕落的生活中饱受煎熬，并影响到与他过从甚密的亲友的生活，令他们蒙受多种灾祸。人类对自由充满了多么奇怪的敬意！他们对自由又是多么奇怪地缺乏尊重！当我们把这两种现象相比时，可伴以这样的想象：某人拥有伤害他人的绝对必要权利，却丝毫无权在不给他人造成痛苦的情况下取悦自己。

我把一大类关于政府干涉之限度的问题留待最后讨论，是因为它们虽然与本文论题密切相关，但在严格意义上，却不属于本文范畴。在这类问题中，反对政府干涉的理由与自由原则无关；问题的核心不是限制人们的行动，而是要帮助他们；问题的内容是政府是否应当主动或被动地为他们的利益做某事，而不是让他们自己或自发组织起来去完成某事。

许多政府干涉行为尚未达到侵犯个人自由的程度。这时，对其干涉行为的反对意见可以分为三类。

第一类，个人很可能会比政府更好地完成目标事项的情况。一般而言，无人能够比那些本身非常感兴趣的人更胜任某个行业的事务，或更善于判断该怎样或由谁来执行该事务。这一原理表明，立法机关或政府官员曾普遍干预产业界常规作业进程，那是错误的做法。但问题的这一方面已经被政治经济学家们非常充分地阐述清楚了，并且与本文探讨的自由原则没有特殊关联。

第二类反对意见与本文主题关联度更大一些。在许多情况下，虽然人们做某件特定事情的能力平均而言并不如政府官员强，但值得让他们去尝试，而不交由政府完成。这是一种他们教育自己心智的方法，借此方法，他们能够加强其实践才能、锻炼其判断力、通晓摆在其面前的问题。这就是参加陪审团审案（非政治性案件）、自由的公共地方机构和市政机构、民间志愿社团经营的工业企业和慈善事业的可取之处。这些都不是自由问题，而仅在趋势上与自由有着间接关系；但它们都是发展问题。本文受主题所限，不便对这些属于国民教育范畴的事情详加讨论。实际上，这些事情是对公民的专门培训，是对自由民众的政治教育中的实践部分。这些手段能使他们跳出个人与家庭私利的狭小圈子，逐渐领悟到共同利益的意义和共同事业的经营——使他们习惯于根据公共性或半公共性的动机采取行动，并用使其团结一心而非分崩离析的目标指引他们的行为。若不形成这些习惯和力量，自由宪法将既无法得以实施，也无从得到保护。有些国家的政治自由过于经常地转瞬即逝，就是典型的例子。其原因就在于，这些国家的政治自由并不是以各种局部自由为充分基础建立起来的。正如前文所述，发展的个性化和行为方式的多样化会产生众多益处。这些益处充分表明：由各地管理其完全地方性的事务，由自愿提供资金的人联合管理各大工业企业，都是极为可取的做法。各国的政府工作都大同小异。而若让个人和民间志愿社团参与进来，就会出现形形色色的试验，获得无限多样的经验。国家所能做的有用之事，就是让自己成为一个中心仓库兼敏捷的循环器和扩散器，储存、流通和扩散从大量试验中获得的经验。国家的任务不是仅仅容忍自己的试验，而是帮助每个试验者从其他人的试验中获益。

第三类，也是反对者限制政府干涉的最令人信服的理由，就是多余地增加它自身的权力。这是政府的重大罪行。除了政府的现有功能之外，继续为其增加的每项功能，都会大幅扩散政府对人们种种希望和恐惧的影响，并越来越多地把公众中的积极分子和野心家变成政府的攀附者，或某个志在组阁的政党的攀附者。如果各公路、各铁路、各银行、各保险公司、各大股份公司、各大学、各慈善机构都成为政府的分支；此外，如果各地市政当局、各地方董事会接受了下放给他们的责权利，成为中央行政机关的部门；如果所有这些不同单位的员工都由政府任命和发薪，指望政府给予他们每次升职机会；那么，即便有着完整的出版自由，即便立法机构由平民组成，也不都能使英国或任何其他国家获得真正的自由，而非名义上的自由。行政机构的构造越高效、越科学——它为自身获取能力最强的专业人才和领袖人物所做的安排越巧妙——它所产生的罪恶就越严重。在英国，最近有人提议，政府文职部门的所有人员都应当通过竞争性考试选拔，以便为那些岗位获得才智最超群、教养最良好的可得人才。对此提议，人们或口头或书面地表达了大量的赞成意见和反对意见。反对者们强调最多的论据之一是，终生从事国家公务员的工作，并不能提供获取足够高薪水、居足够高职位的光明前景，所以难以吸引顶尖人才；顶级人才总是能够在那些专业性很强的职业或公司及其他公共机构中找到更具吸引力的毕生事业。如果这条证据被提议者们用来回答针对其提议的诘难，谁都不会感到奇怪；可令人称奇的是，这条证据竟然来自反对者一边。有条被竭力主张的反对意见是：这套选拔考试体制的安全阀是什么？确实，倘若一个国家的全部高素质人才都能够被吸引到政府公务员队伍中，那么旨在产生此种结果的提议很可能会令人焦虑不安。社会事业需要有条不紊、同心协力的团队，或视野开阔、考虑周全的人才，倘若这项事业的方方面面都掌握在政府手里，倘若所有的政府岗位都让最有才干的人占据，那么本国所有的开明教养和熟练天才都会集中在无数的官僚身上。社会的其他成员只能从他们那里寻求一切：群众向他们寻求执行各种任务的指示和命令；有才干有志向的人向他们寻求个人晋升的机会。获准进入这个官僚体制，并在成为其中一员后青云直上，就成为人们雄心壮志中的唯一目标。在这种体制下，不仅外部民众因缺乏实践经验而无法恰切地批判或制止整个官僚机构的运转模式，而且即便专制机构的意外事件或平民机构的正常工作偶尔把一个或一群具有改革意向的统治者推上了权力之巅，也不会产生任何违反官僚集团利益的改革。这就是俄罗斯帝国的悲惨境况，那些拥有充分条件的观察者就是这样描述它的。沙皇自己根本无法对抗整个官僚集团；他能够把他们中的任何人流放到西伯利亚，却不能抛开他们或违背他们的意愿，独自统治国家。对于他的任何命令，他们都心照不宣地默然否决——他们只需毫不作为、不加执行就够了。在文明程度更高、造反精神更强的国家，民众已经习惯了等待国家为他们做好一切，或至少是：国家若不请求他们做某事，甚至虽然请求过但没有告诉他们如何做，他们就不会为自己做此事。这些国家的民众自然而然地相信，国家应该对所有发生在他们身上的坏事负责；倘若那些坏事令他们忍无可忍，他们就会起而反抗政府，造成可谓革命的事件。于是，统治者之外的某个人，不论有否得到全国民众认可的合法权威，就会跃上统治者的宝座，向官僚集团发号施令，一切又像从前那样运转起来。官僚集团依然如故，外来者谁都无法取而代之。

在一个惯于自己办理所有事务的民族中，会发现一派迥异景象。在法国，大多数民众都服过兵役，其中许多人至少获得过军士军衔；所以每次民众起义中都会有一群干将带头，当场制定出某项不错的行动计划。正如法国人在军事上富有才干，美国人在所有种类的国家事务上都极富才干。倘若美国人没有政府，任何美国人团体都能当场组成一个政府，机智灵活、条理井然、坚决果断地继续进行面前那项或其他的公共事务。他们是所有自由民族应该学习的榜样，能够这样做的民族定然是自由的民族；自由的民众绝不容许自己受到任何人或任何组织的奴役，因为他们足以掌握和驾驭中枢行政机构。哪个官僚集团都无法希望让这样的民众执行或忍受他们不喜欢的任何事情。但是，不论哪个国家，只要凡事都得通过官僚机构实行，那么对官僚集团不利的任何事情都根本无法实行。这类国家的宪法是一种组织，它把全体国民的经验和实践能力组织起来，交给一个训练有素的团体，让他们来控制其他民众。那个组织自身越完备，越能成功地从全社会所有阶层中为自己吸引和训练最有才干的人员，它就越彻底地奴役着全体国民——包括官僚集团的所有成员。这是因为，统治者是自己组织和纪律的奴隶，正如被统治者是统治者的奴隶。中国的政府高官同其最低贱的农民一样，都是专制制度的工具和产物。单个的耶稣会士是修会中极度卑微的奴隶，虽然修会自身因其所有成员的集体力量和名望而存在[56]。

而且，我们不能忘记，将全国之主要干才集中于管理团体，早晚会毁灭该团体自身的精神动力和先进性质。这个被聚集在一起的群体——他们操纵着一个系统，而那个系统像所有系统一样，必须在很大程度上按固定的规则运行——这个官员团体一直处于这些诱惑之下：沉沦到懒散的常规日程之中消磨时光；或者，如果他们时而丢开那种拉磨马儿转不完的磨坊路，能有某个领导者突发奇想，带领团队不经思考地率直行动。对这两种乍看相反、实则紧密相联的倾向，唯一的制约手段，同时也是能够保持团队自身能力处于很高水平的唯一激励因素，就是向来自本团体之外、与其能力旗鼓相当的警示与批判负责。因此，必须要存在某种独立于政府的手段，以塑造这一能力，为之提供机会和经验，使之对各种重大的实践性事务做出正确判断。倘若我们能永远拥有一个老练、高效的官吏团体——它首先是一个有能力主动进步、有意愿采纳改良措施的团体，如果我们不希望我们的官僚机构堕落为一个迂腐的学究统治集团，就必须禁止这个群体垄断所有能够塑造和培养治理人类所需的各种才能的职业。

社会在其公认领袖人物的指挥下，凝心聚力，全力铲除阻挠社会福祉的障碍。威胁着人类自由和进步的种种可怕罪恶到底从何而起？或曰，它们从何时开始超过了社会运用其力量时伴生的益处呢？怎样确定这一时刻，怎样既尽可能多地获得权力和智力集中的种种好处，又防止过多的社会活动转入政府渠道，乃是管理艺术中最困难、最复杂的问题之一。在很大程度上，这是个细节问题，在处理这个问题时，有很多不同的因素必须要加以考虑，而且无法制定绝对的规则。但我相信，包含着安全的实践原则、需要牢记的理想目标、用来检验为克服困难而做出的所有部署的标准，都可以在下列语句中得到表达：为实现高效率而最大限度地分权，但要尽最大可能地集中情报并从中心传播出去。因此，在内政方面，需要像新英格兰各州那样，在各地选出的不同政府官员之间进行极为精细的分工，让他们负责所有不适合由直接利益相关者管理的事务；但除此之外，在各个地方事务部门中还要设立一个监管中心，构成政府整体中的一个分支。这个监管机构会如同聚焦一般把各种情报和经验汇集到一起：有的来自各地的公共事务部门，有的来自与外国做法相似的一切，有的来自政治学的一般原则。该中枢机构应该有权了解所发生的一切事情，其特殊职责应该是令一个地区获得的消息能为其他地区所知晓。居高临下的地位和全方位的观察视角使此中枢监管机构摆脱了地方性的琐碎偏见和狭隘视野，所以其建议应该自然而然地权威可靠。但我觉得，它作为一个常设机构，只能强制地方官员服从那些为指引他们而制定的法律，这就是它实际权力应到达的极限。对于普遍性法规之外的事物，应该允许那些官员自主裁量，对他们的选民负责；他们若违反法规，就应受到法律的制裁——那些法规本身应该由立法机构制定。中枢监管部门只负责监管这些法规的执行情况；倘若它们未能得以正确实施，该部门就要根据案件性质，诉请特别法庭秉公执法，或诉请选民们罢免那些歪曲法律精神、滥权执法的官吏。这就是英国成立济贫法事务局，从而对全国收取贫民救济税的行政官吏实行中央监管的总体构想。在那个特殊案件中，无论该事务局越界使用了什么权力，都是正当、必要的；因为它必须要彻底消除弊政之根深蒂固的种种陋习——很多不仅深刻影响着各个地区，而且影响着全英国的事务都深受其荼毒。在道德上，哪个地方都没有权利用错误的管理方式在本地筑起一个贫穷的温床，并不可避免地让贫穷蔓延到其他地方，损害整个劳工群体的道德与身体状态。济贫法事务局拥有行政强制权和从属立法权（但这些权力因受到了舆论对此问题的看法态势影响，几乎没有使用过），虽然用在某桩引发全国高度关注的案件中完全正当合理，但若用在对纯属地方利益的监管中，则是完全失当。然而，一个为所有地区提供情报和指示的中央机构，对所有行政部门而言都同样是宝贵的。那类不会妨碍个人的努力与发展，而会帮助和激励其努力与发展的活动，政府不能举办太多。一旦政府不是唤起个人和团体的自发活动与自身力量，而是代之以它自己的活动；一旦它不用影响、规劝手段或在必要时用谴责手段使他们劳作，而是让他们戴着枷锁劳作，或命令他们退到一边，替他们完成工作；这时危害就会出现。长远看，国家的价值就是其所有成员个人价值的总和。一个国家若将拓展和提升国民心智的利益置于次要位置，却把行政技能或体现在烦琐事务中的类似实践技能这类细枝末节放在首位；一个国家若为使国民变成自己手中更温驯的工具——即便出于对他们有利的目的——而阻遏他们成长；那么它将会发觉：这群卑微弱小的国民令它无法真正成就任何伟大的事业；而它牺牲一切建造得尽善尽美的政府机制，到头来毫无益处；因为那个机制完全没有生命力——为了让它运转得更加平稳，国家已经根除了这一关键要素。

[1]阿克巴大帝（Akbar，1543—1605）：印度莫卧儿王朝最伟大的皇帝（1556—1605在位），也是印度历史上的伟大帝王之一。他征服了北印度地区，建立了幅员辽阔的帝国，并推行灵活务实的内政外交政策，包括宗教宽容政策。——译者注

[2]查理大帝（Charlemagne，742—814）：也称作查里曼、查里大帝、卡尔大帝，法兰克王国加洛林王朝国王（768—814年在位），800年由教皇利奥三世加冕于罗马，成为神圣罗马帝国第一任皇帝（一说962年加冕的德意志国王、萨克森王朝的奥托一世是神圣罗马帝国第一任皇帝）。他于中世纪早期统一了西欧大部分地区，为现代的法、德两国奠定了基础，享有“欧洲之父”的美誉。他在帝国的经济、行政、军事、文教、宗教等方面都建树卓越。——译者注

[3]奥古斯特·孔德（Auguste Comte，1798—1857）：法国哲学家，社会学、实证主义的创始人，著有《实证哲学教程》《实证主义概论》《实证政治体系》等，被后人尊为“社会学之父”。——译者注

[4]我正待写出这些文字时，就出现了1858年的政府控告出版物事件（指1858年后半年，法国政府控告并审讯查尔斯·蒙塔朗贝尔伯爵事件。事情的起因是蒙塔朗贝尔伯爵写了一篇名为《在英国议会辩论印度问题》的文章。法国政府认为，该文中的某些段落“富有煽动性地批判了现任政府”。——译者注），似乎是要故意高调反驳我似的。然而，那场对公共言论自由的轻率干涉并未促使我更改本文中的片言只语，也丝毫没有削弱我的信念。我坚信，除了恐慌时期之外，我国用痛苦和惩罚对付政治言论的时代已经结束。这是因为，首先，那些控告并未顽固坚持下去；第二，它们也并不是严格意义上的政治控告。1858年事件中被指控的罪行并非抨击某些机构，或抨击当政者们的行为或人身，而是传播一种被认为不道德的学说——诛杀暴君是合法的。＜br/＞倘若本章的探讨正当合理，那么作为道德信念，就应该存在最充分的表达和讨论任何学说的自由，无论别人认为该学说如何悖德。因此，诛杀暴君的学说是否悖德与本文无关，不宜在此加以考察。我将满足于声称，该问题始终是诸未决道德问题之一；满足于说明，若某罪犯通过凌驾于法律之上而使自己免于法律惩罚或管制，那么，在所有民族的心目中，在人类一些睿智的佼佼者心目中，某公民个人击毙该罪犯的行为历来都不是罪行，而是高尚的德行；满足于表明，此事不论对错，都不属于暗杀性质，而属内战性质。同样，我认为，在某具体案件中，可以惩罚煽动刺杀行为，但前提是随后出现了实际刺杀行动，并且该行动与煽动行为之间至少可以建立起可能性较大的联系。即便如此，也要由遭到攻击的政府本身，而不是某个外国政府，来进行自卫，依法惩处那些企图颠覆它的袭击行为。

[5]封圣（canonization）：指天主教会、东正教会和英国国教宣布某个已故教徒为圣徒的行为。——译者注

[6]各各他（Calvary）：据基督教《圣经》称，各各他是耶路撒冷城墙外一个形似骷髅的小山的名字，因此又译骷髅地；耶稣在此被钉死在十字架上。——译者注

[7]据《马太福音》第26章记载：耶稣被带到大祭司该亚法那里去当众受审。大祭司该亚法要求耶稣当着永生神起誓告诉人们，他是神子基督。耶稣承认这一点后，说：然而我告诉你们，后来你们要看见人子坐在那权能者的右边，驾着天上的云降临。听到此言，该亚法就撕开衣服，说耶稣说了亵渎神灵的话，诱请在场的人要求处死他。＜br/＞在普通犹太人当中，在听到噩耗或令人惊悚的事情时，常常要撕裂衣服，露出胸口，表示悲痛、惊恐或义愤。但是，根据《利未记》，祭司不许执行这一风俗。无论在任何情形之下，祭司都不可撕裂自己的衣服。头上倒过膏油、受过圣职、穿了金色圣衣的大祭司尤其要严守这一规定，不可蓬头散发、不许撕裂衣服，也不可挨近尸体等不洁之物，哪怕是他父母的尸体。这是因为，他的穿戴、态度、言语和精神，都要完全无瑕，象征上帝的圣洁、荣耀和完全。大祭司若敢撕裂衣服或穿着撕裂的衣服执行圣职，就是损毁上帝的象征，丧失了代表上帝的身份，必然要被判死刑。——译者注

[8]耶稣死后，作为异教徒的基督教徒曾惨遭迫害。本来笃信犹太教的圣保罗在基督教形成初期，激烈反对这种新宗教，并积极参加迫害活动，力图消灭它。但在去大马士革的一次旅途中，他受到耶稣显灵的感化，从此改变信仰，变成了基督教最有力的支持者和最早的传教者。他的传教足迹遍布1世纪时罗马帝国东部的古希腊、小亚细亚、叙利亚和巴勒斯坦等地区，说服了大量的非犹太人，并在欧洲和小亚细亚建立了多个教会团体。另外，传统上认为，《新约》27部书中，有14部都是保罗所作。因此他对基督教思想的影响十分巨大。——译者注

[9]马可·奥勒留·安东尼努斯（Marcus Aurelius Antoninus，121—180）是古罗马帝国安东尼王朝皇帝（161—180在位）。他从小受到了良好的教育，温和宽厚、学识渊博、为政勤勉、公正开明，富有军事天才但又热爱和平，是西方历史上的著名贤君、斯多亚派哲学家，他用希腊文写成的《沉思录》为传世名作。奥勒留在位期间，迫害基督徒案件的数量和严重程度都有显著增加。——译者注

[10]康斯坦丁大帝（Constantine，272—337）是第一位信仰基督教的罗马皇帝。在他的政策鼓励下，基督教迅速发展壮长为主导欧洲的宗教。——译者注

[11]约翰逊博士即萨缪尔·约翰逊（Samuel Johnson，1709—1784），英国诗人、作家、道德家、编辑、词典编纂家，对英国文学贡献巨大。——译者注

[12]披麻蒙灰指身披麻衣或麻布，洒满灰烬，表示自己如同尘芥一般卑微。基督教《圣经》中多次记载人们披麻蒙灰、禁食祈祷，进行忏悔。——译者注

[13]洛克里斯人（Locrians）是生活在古希腊中部地区的一个希腊部族。洛克里斯人扎莱乌库斯设计出了第一部希腊成文法典，称为《洛克里斯法典》。——译者注

[14]路德指马丁·路德（1483—1546），德国人，16世纪欧洲宗教改革倡导者，基督教新教路德宗创始人。——译者注

[15]布雷西亚的阿诺德（Arnold of Brescia，1090—1155）是意大利伦巴第地区的基督教神职人员。他呼吁教会改革，放弃财产权，倡导苦修。他的影响巨大，几度遭教皇流放。1143年回到罗马后，他参加了罗马公社（1144—1193），热情洋溢地站在民众一边，迅速成为公社的智力领袖，疾呼自由和民主权利。他与几任教皇的斗争互有胜负，但最终于1155年被抓，被教廷当作叛徒审判，处以绞刑后又遭焚尸。教廷憎恨他在民间和低层神职人员中的威望和美名，把他的骨灰抛进台伯河，以免他的墓地成为殉道圣地而受到敬仰。——译者注

[16]多尔齐诺（Fra Dolcino，1250—1307）是意大利的激进基督教牧师，反对教阶制度和封建体制，提倡教会回归谦卑和贫穷的原始典范，提倡人类的完全解放，创建彻底平等、互助互尊的共产社会组织。他曾领导一群激进改革者对抗教会。十字军抓住他后处死了他。——译者注

[17]萨沃纳罗拉（Girolamo Savonarola，1452—1498）意大利文艺复兴时期佛罗伦萨多明我会的修道士和牧师。他预言了佛罗伦萨的壮美革新、世俗艺术和文化的毁灭，批判教士阶级的腐化，呼吁基督教的重建，谴责专制统治以及富人对穷人的剥削。他获得了佛罗伦萨民众的敬重和梵蒂冈的仇恨。1498年，萨沃纳罗拉和另两位教友被囚禁，遭到折磨，被教会和市政当局处以绞刑和火刑。他们的骨灰被抛入了亚诺河。——译者注

[18]阿尔比教派（The Albigeois）：阿尔比是法国南部的一个城市，从主教座堂发展而来。12—13世纪，活跃于西欧的一个中世纪基督教派别卡特里派（又译清洁派）传入阿尔比城，因此又称阿尔比派。他们是二元论者，认为精神世界属于善神，包括肉体在内的物质世界属于恶神。善恶两神不断斗争。他们认为，地上的一切事物都是朽坏的、恶的，耶稣、圣灵都不是神，而是受造的事物；连教会和教界都与物质世界沆瀣一气，所以反对教阶制度、神职人员财产权和天主教圣礼。他们还反对杀生、婚姻、战争和死刑，主张完全素食、禁欲和脱离轮回。教会对这一派深恶痛绝，宣布他们为异端。1209年，教皇英诺森三世发起了一场阿尔比圣战，历时20年，重创了阿尔比教派。1234年，宗教裁判所创立，对不肯悔改的阿尔比派信徒实施背负十字架朝圣、囚禁和火刑等种种惩罚手段。几十年的武力镇压、强迫改宗、典籍毁灭和组织破坏，使该教派式微，进入14世纪后，则逐渐消亡。——译者注

[19]韦尔多派（The Vaudois或The Waldensians）是1170年代晚期出现于里昂的一个教派。其创始人彼得·韦尔多本是里昂一个有学问的富商，在1160年前后经历的系列事件使他成为一个激进基督徒。他把自己的财产分给了家人和穷人，开始了使徒式的清贫余生。他专心传道和钻研《圣经》，为了让不懂拉丁语的普通人懂得基督教《圣经》，他资助把《福音书》等书籍翻译成当地人使用的普罗旺斯语。他吸引了大批的平民信徒，但他以平民信徒身份传道和破坏教会规矩翻译经书等行为很快招致了罗马天主教会的不满。1215年，教会宣布韦尔多派为异端，开始大肆迫害他们。1229年，十字军结束了讨伐阿尔比派的战争之后，开始攻击韦尔多教派。宗教裁判所也迅速加入进来，严惩他们。韦尔多派活动转入地下，许多信徒逃到了普罗旺斯地区和意大利。到了16世纪，他们加入了新教运动，开始公开活动，却屡遭屠杀和镇压。其中最惨烈的就是1545年的普罗旺斯地区梅兰多村大屠杀（The Massacre of Mérindol）。17世纪时几乎灭绝。——译者注

[20]罗拉德派（The Lollards）又称威克利夫派，是14世纪中期至16世纪英国宗教改革期间发生于英国的一个政治和宗教运动。创始人约翰·威克利夫是著名神学家，就读并随后任教于牛津大学，他学识渊博，影响极大，1369年起任英王的神父，后兼任教区长、皇家神学顾问等职。1376年，他反对教会和教皇的腐化，提倡回归《圣经》本身，主张各国教会应隶属于本国国王，而遭到教皇的谴责逮捕与坎特伯雷大主教的通缉。他1381年被逐出牛津大学。威克利夫及其在牛津大学的同事们形成了第一批罗拉德派，他们不顾坎特伯雷大主教的威迫继续扩张，把基督教《圣经》译成了英文。1399年，亨利四世继位，他伙同教廷一起禁止私人翻译或拥有《圣经》，称违反者将作为异端被施以火刑，开始了对罗拉德派的镇压。在严厉惩罚措施的压迫下，15世纪早期，罗拉德派被迫转入地下。14至15世纪，英国多次处死罗拉德派信徒。高压之下，罗拉德派渐趋式微，最终并入新教教派。——译者注

[21]胡斯派是14至15世纪之交出现在捷克的宗教改革运动。其先行者扬·胡斯（约1369—1415）是捷克宗教改革者，继约翰·威克利夫之后的著名宗教改革理论家，对新教影响巨大。康斯坦茨宗教会议将胡斯诱骗到了康斯坦茨，宣判他为异端并处以火刑。捷克的胡斯派信徒视此为国耻，随后发动了胡斯战争（1419—约1434），针对教廷进行宗教和政治斗争。1434年，战争结束，胡斯派同意服从波西米亚国王和教廷的权威。——译者注

[22]佛兰德斯（Flanders）是中世纪的一个西欧国家，位于今欧洲西北部地区，在北海沿岸，包括法国西北部部分地区、现比利时的东佛兰德省、西佛兰德省以及荷兰的西南部部分地区。——译者注

[23]玛丽女王指玛丽一世（Mary I，1516—1558）是亨利八世和凯瑟琳王后的独生女，英格兰和爱尔兰女王（1553—1558在位），都铎王朝第四任君主。她继承的是乃弟爱德华六世（Edward VI，1537—1553）的王位（1546—1553在位）。9岁即位的爱德华六世是英国第一位新教徒国王，他在位期间对宗教事务十分感兴趣，确立了新教的地位，实施了一些宗教改革措施。他在1553年病逝时，指定信奉新教的珍·格雷为王位继承人。玛丽是爱德华六世的同父异母姐姐，信仰天主教。她用武力废黜了珍·格雷，自任女王。她在位的短短5年期间处死了许多新教徒，被对手称为“血腥玛丽”。——译者注

[24]伊丽莎白女王指伊丽莎白一世（Elizabeth I，1533—1603），是亨利八世与其第二任妻子安妮王后的独生女，英格兰和爱尔兰女王（1558—1603在位），都铎王朝第五任君主。伊丽莎白是爱德华六世的同父异母姐姐、玛丽一世的同父异母妹妹，信仰新教。玛丽一世在位时，因恐她支持新教徒反叛，把她囚禁了将近一年。伊丽莎白上任之初，就建立了一个英国新教教会，自任最高总管。该教会后来发展为英国国教会。她在位期间，实施温和的宗教自由政策，避免宗教迫害活动。——译者注

[25]指1857年7月31日，博德明巡回法庭，托马斯·普雷。当年12月，国王特赦了他。

[26]指1857年8月17日，乔治·雅各布·霍利约克；1857年7月，爱德华·特鲁拉夫。

[27]指1857年8月4日，万宝路大街治安法庭，格雷肯男爵。

[28]我们需要高度警惕，迫害者的狂热情绪中掺杂着我国民族性中的劣根性。这种劣根性在印度民族起义时（指1857年5月—1858年6月北部和中部印度反对英国殖民统治的民族起义。这次起义以东印度公司的印度士兵哗变开始，以英国胜利、印度再次成为其殖民地告终。——译者注）展露无遗。教堂讲坛上狂热分子或骗子的疯言乱语也许不值一顾，但福音派头头们的声明不容忽视。他们宣布：他们管理印度教教徒和伊斯兰教徒的规则是：任何不教授基督教《圣经》的学校都不能获得公款资助；与此相应的必然结果是，任何不是真正或伪装的基督徒的人都不能获得公职。据称，一位副国务大臣（威廉·纳·梅西）在1857年11月12日向其选民发表的演说中提到：“对他们信仰的宽容”（一亿英属国国民的信仰），“英国政府称之为宗教的那种迷信已经产生了妨碍英国声誉的效果，阻碍了基督教的健康发展……宗教宽容是我国宗教自由的伟大基石，但休让他们滥用了宽容这一珍贵的语词。照他看来，宗教宽容意味着所有人的完全自由，意味着基督徒的敬拜自由，因为他们敬拜的基础相同；意味着容忍基督徒的所有宗派和教派，因为他们相信的中介相同。”我希望诸位注意这一事实：一个被认为适合充任我国政府要职、在自由派内阁领导下工作的人，竟然发表这种言论，主张将所有不信仰基督神性的人排除在宗教宽容的围栏之外。听到这番蠢话之外，谁还能沉醉在错觉之中，相信宗教迫害已经一去不返了呢？

[29]自然哲学（natural philosophy）：自然科学特别是物理学的旧称。——译者注

[30]燃素说是17世纪后期至18世纪，化学家们针对燃烧和生锈等燃烧现象提出的解释。他们认为，可燃物中普遍存在着一种火一样的、被称为燃素的物质。燃烧就是可燃物中的燃素释放的过程。——译者注

[31]加尔文（John Calvin，1509—1564）：著名法国宗教改革家、神学家，基督教新教加尔文宗的创始人。——译者注

[32]诺克斯（John Knox，1514—1572）：苏格兰宗教改革家、神学家，苏格兰长老会的创始人。曾受教于加尔文。——译者注

[33]卢梭（Jean-Jacques Rousseau，1712—1788）：法国启蒙时代的思想家、作家，法国大革命的思想先驱。他是一个生活与思想充满悖论的人。例如：他是当时的杰出作家之一，却没受过正规教育，并娶了一个文盲女工；他专门论述过教育问题，却把自己的孩子们都送进了育婴堂；他讨厌革命，但被法国大革命的领袖们奉为偶像；他被认为是领导启蒙运动的哲学家，却称赞无知，反对艺术和科学。他的主要著作有《论人类不平等的起源和基础》《社会契约论》《爱弥儿》《忏悔录》等。——译者注

[34]福音书（Gospel）：指《新约》中的《马太福音》《马可福音》《路加福音》和《约翰福音》四卷福音书。——译者注

[35]即耶稣。——译者注

[36]《古兰经》（Koran）：又译《可兰经》，伊斯兰教经典。——译者注

[37]威廉·冯·洪堡（Wilhelm von Humboldt，1767—1835）：德国哲学家、教育改革家、外交官、语言学家。——译者注

[38]诺克斯能力卓越。他作为苏格兰教会的改革者，据说参与了1546年杀害苏格兰最后一任红衣主教大卫·比顿的谋杀案，干预了苏格兰王后、法国吉斯王族的玛丽的摄政，被流放至英格兰。流放期间，他参加了英格兰圣公会的工作，并步步高升，成为英王爱德华六世的王室牧师。1553年，爱德华六世去世，玛丽一世即英格兰王位后复辟罗马天主教，诺克斯被迫辞职，转赴日内瓦和法兰克福。最后，他回到苏格兰，与当地信仰新教的贵族一起领导了苏格兰的新教改革运动。——译者注

[39]亚西比德（Alcibiade，约450—404），雅典政治家、演说家、军事家。他极富政治和军事天才，不循常规，为其所服务的政权屡建奇功；但同时，他性情不拘，所到之处也屡树强敌，导致自己无法久留。在伯罗奔尼撒战争（前430—404）中，因本邦政敌作对，他从雅典逃到斯巴达，不久又迫于斯巴达的政敌势力，逃往波斯；虽然后被雅典的盟友召回，但其政敌几年后再次成功流放了他。——译者注

[40]伯里克利（Pericles，约495—429），雅典政治家、演说家、军事家。他当政期间（约461—429），把提洛同盟变成了一个雅典帝国，取得了对波斯战争的最终胜利。他鼓励文艺事业，使雅典成为当时希腊的世界文化和教育中心。伯里克利时代，雅典民主政治获得了较大发展，其中包括公民的言论自由。——译者注

[41]尼亚加拉河是位于北美洲五大湖区、加拿大和美国交界处的河流，全程水位落差很大，水力资源丰富。河上有著名的尼亚加拉瀑布。——译者注

[42]近几年来，根据某种卑劣而可怕的证据，能依法宣布任何人不适宜管理自己的事务；并且，如果某人的财产足以支付诉讼费用——诉讼费要从这笔财产中划出——就会在他死后宣布他对自己财产的处理方案无效。他日常生活的所有细枝末节都会被打探得清清楚楚；通过卑劣者中之最卑劣者的感受和描述来看，只要他的行为表现中有任何蛛丝马迹不像是十足平庸寻常之事，就会被作为他精神失常的证据提交到陪审团的面前，且经常胜诉。这是因为，与上述证人相比，那些陪审员几乎同样粗鄙无知；而办案的法官则与向来令我们震惊的英国律师一样，因对人性与人生极度无知，经常误导那些陪审员。这些审判深刻地说明了大众对人类自由所持的态度与看法。在一干法官和陪审员人等眼中，非但个性没有任何价值——他们非但不尊重任何个人在无干他人的事物上根据自己的判断和偏好采取行动的权利，而且甚至无法设想一个神志正常的人会希望拥有这种自由。从前，有人提议烧死无神论者时，宅心仁厚的人都常常会建议不要烧死他们，而要把他们关进疯人院；如今，如果我们目睹此类事情发生，亦应不足为怪；建议者们也甚为得意，因为他们没有实施宗教迫害，而用如此仁爱、高尚的方式对待这些不幸的人——同时，看到这些“不幸者”咎由自取，他们心中也无不暗自满意。

[43]德·托克维尔（Alexis-Charles-Henri Clérel de Tocqueville，1805—1859）：法国政治思想家、历史学家。早年热心参政，曾任议员、外交部部长等职。著有《论美国的民主》（1835年、1840年）、《旧制度与大革命》（1856年）等。——译者注

[44]乔治·巴恩威尔（George Barnwell）是17世纪一首英国民谣中的主人公。该民谣说的是发生于英格兰什普罗郡的一场谋杀案。乔治·巴恩威尔与妓女萨拉·米尔伍德私通，并在后者的唆使下，为谋取钱财杀死了自己的叔父。事发后，二犯被处以绞刑。1731年，这个故事被英国作家乔治·利洛（George Lillo）写成悲剧《伦敦商人》（The London Merchant, or the History of George Barnwell），搬上了舞台，受到观众普遍欢迎。——译者注

[45]查理二世（Charles II of England, Scotland, and Ireland，1630—1685，在位1660—1685）：英国内战中被处死的英王查理一世的儿子，内战中曾与清教徒代表、后成为护国公的克伦威尔作战，败逃欧陆，在法国、荷兰等国流亡，1660年复辟。他机警灵变，在政治上与议会达成了妥协，并实施宗教宽容政策。他因个人生活放荡，被称为“快活王”。——译者注

[46]孟买的帕西人就是一个很奇特的例子。这个勤劳刻苦、勇于进取的民族的祖先是波斯拜火教教徒。在历代哈里发大军的驱赶下，那些拜火教徒逃离了自己的祖国，来到了印度西部。当地的印度教君主们对他们实行宽容政策，但条件是他们不能食用牛肉。后来，印度西部各地被攻陷，成为伊斯兰教征服者的领地，帕西人又得到了这些伊斯兰教统治者的宗教宽容，但条件是他们不能食用猪肉。这种原本是对威权的顺从变成了帕西人的第二天性，他们至今都忌食牛肉和猪肉。这一双重禁忌虽然并非他们的宗教规定，但已经在历史过程中演变为他们民族的习俗。在东方，习俗就是一种宗教。

[47]新英格兰（New England）指美国东北部的一个地区，由今天的康涅狄格州、缅因州、马萨诸塞州、新罕布什尔州、罗得岛州和佛蒙特州6个州组成。1620年，著名的五月花号将一批躲避查理一世宗教迫害的独立派新教徒带到了这里；此后，清教徒陆续到达，并在这一带繁衍。这一地区的殖民者以自耕农为主，他们自给自足的生活方式同清教工作伦理非常契合。另外，据信，他们还发扬了《五月花号公约》精神，创建了根深蒂固的民主传统。——译者注

[48]英国的共和国（the Commonwealth）时期指1649—1660间的英格兰、苏格兰和爱尔兰共和国。第二次英国内战以奥利弗·克伦威尔等人领导的议会军的胜利和国王查理一世领导的保皇派的失败告终，1649年1月，查理一世被处决；5月，英国宣布为共和国。在内战前和内战过程中，克伦威尔因其坚定的清教信仰和赫赫战功而威望日隆。1653年，他从议会手中谋取了全部权力，自任“英格兰、苏格兰和爱尔兰共和国”的护国公，直至1659年逝世。此间他虽拒绝了国王之名，但握有国王之实，故这几年又称为护国公执政时期。克伦威尔实施了一系列卓有成效的内政建设与外交策略，许多政策带有明显的清教特色。他的儿子李查·克伦威尔继任护国公，但威望和能力均不胜任。在多股国内外势力反复较量之后，1660年，在欧洲流亡的查理二世回到伦敦，复辟王位，英国共和国时期结束。清教盛期也随之结束。——译者注

[49]卫理公会派（the Methodists）：18世纪英国圣公会牧师、神学家约翰·卫斯理（John Wesley，1703—1791）创建的一支新教派别，又译循道宗、循道公会、卫斯理宗等。与加尔文派的绝对预定论神学观点不同，该派相信自由意志，承认传统的三位一体神性论，宣称忠于《圣经》教义，所有人都有可能得救、受到神的保护。该派强调帮助穷人和平民，注重通过社会服务建立与他人的友善联系，并培养人的完善品格。——译者注

[50]指缅因州。最初由新英格兰清教徒发起的禁酒运动虽屡有争议，但不断发展，于19世纪中期取得了不少成果。其标志之一是，缅因州于1851年通过了《禁酒法》（Maine Law），禁止生产和售卖含酒精饮料。该法令受到了许多工人和移民的抵制，最显著者为1855年波特兰市的骚乱事件。1856年该法令被废止。但《禁酒法》得到了国际认可。受其影响，英国于1853年成立了禁酒组织“联合王国同盟”（United Kingdom Alliance），并把曼彻斯特市的一条街改名为“缅因街”，以纪念该法令。——译者注

[51]此斯坦利勋爵即爱德华·亨利·斯坦利（Edward Henry Stanley，15th Earl of Derby，1826—1893），英国政治世家、保守党中坚力量斯坦利家族的成员，第十五任德比伯爵。斯坦利家族是英国历史上最富有的大地主之一。其父爱德华·乔治·杰奥弗里·史密斯-斯坦利曾三度出任英国首相。1866—1868和1874—1878斯坦利本人曾两度出任英国外交大臣之职。但在政治上，他更同情自由党而不是保守党。——译者注

[52]摩门教（Mormonism）是美国人约瑟夫·史密斯（Joseph Smith，1805—1844）创建的宗教派别。生于纽约州一个商人兼农夫家庭的史密斯适逢美国号称第二次大觉醒的宗教兴盛时期。他参加了教堂的学习班，读了《圣经》。根据他的回忆，他多次在祈祷中受到了神启。1823—1827，他自称一位天使指引他挖掘到了一本美洲原住民写在金片上的经书，又赋予他语言神力进行翻译。该书于1829年完成翻译，1830年出版，是为《摩门经》。该经书自叙是美洲原住民的一部编年史，把他们描述为信仰宗教的犹太人，并且在基督降生之前几百上千年前就已经信仰他了。摩门教主史密斯一方面是个宗教狂，另一方面熟悉多种骗术。他教导、欺骗、引诱、谋害过别人，也被别人暴打、追捧、驱逐、支持、背叛、崇拜、通缉、审讯、监禁、批判过。例如：在1837年，他与其他几位教派领袖创建了一个名为柯特兰安全社（Kirtland Safety Society）的股份公司，作为准银行运营。然而不到一个月，这个公司就垮掉了。1838年，爆发了摩门教战争。1839年前后，他派使团去欧洲传教，吸引了无数人入教，其中包括大批工厂工人。1843—1844，他还竞选过美国总统。1844年，他被控犯有叛国罪收监，随后被一伙蒙面人枪杀在监狱中。在他的“神谕”指引下，摩门教在发展壮大的同时，也不断遭到周围民众的憎恶和围攻而被迫转移，在纽约州、宾夕法尼亚州、俄亥俄州、密苏里州、伊利诺伊州等地流动。史密斯死后，该教派在与教外民众不断冲突的压力下，继续转移，在内布拉斯加州短暂停留后，把总部确定在了后来成为犹他州、内华达州和怀俄明州的部分地区、科罗拉多州的西部荒漠和山区一带。摩门教历史上几度更名，1851年起采用的正式名称是耶稣基督后期圣徒教会（The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints）。与传统的新教不同，他们相信圣父、圣子、圣灵并非三位一体，而是三个独立的实体，但三者在思想、行动和目标上是一体的，因此通常把此集合体叫作“一神”或“神性”。该派认为，全人类作为神的子孙，都能得到提升，继承神的一切，会像耶稣那样得道成神。该教派奉行一夫多妻制，因此而屡次遭到外界激烈批判；迫于压力，1890年时任教主宣布废止该制度。——译者注

[53]边沁（Jeremy Bentham，1748—1832）：英国哲学家、法理学家、经济学家、社会改革家，现代功利主义哲学创始人。他的政治思想激进，积极影响了社会福利制度的发展。除了著名的“最大幸福原则”论之外，他提倡个人和经济自由、政教分离、言论自由、男女权利平等、动物权利等主张，呼吁废除奴隶制、死刑、体罚等制度。著有《政府片论》（1776年）、《道德与立法原则导论》（1780年、1789年）等。他影响了詹姆斯·穆勒及其子约翰·斯图亚特·穆勒、罗伯特·欧文、米歇尔·福柯等一大批人。——译者注

[54]洛克（John Locke，1632—1704）：英国哲学家，欧洲启蒙时代最伟大的思想家之一，被称作“古典自由主义之父”。他的思想尤其对认识论和政治哲学贡献巨大，伏尔泰、卢梭、苏格兰启蒙思想家群体、美国革命者们等都深受他的影响。主要作品：《论宗教宽容》（1689年）、《政府论》（1689年）、《人类理解论》（1690年）等。——译者注

[55]康德（Immanuel Kant，1724—1804）：德国哲学家，近代西方哲学的核心人物，对形而上学、认识论、伦理学、政治学、美学均有巨大而深远的影响。主要作品：《纯粹理性批判》（1781年）、《实践理性批判》（1788年）、《判断力批判》（1790年）等。——译者注

[56]耶稣会（the Society of Jesus）是天主教中的一个男修会，由原西班牙贵族骑士、后成为隐士和神父的伊格内修斯·罗耀拉（Ignatius of Loyola，1491—1556）于1534年与另外6人共同创建，1540年被教皇保罗三世正式批准。因为罗耀拉的军事背景，耶稣会仿照军队建制，实行高度的中央集权，有着严密的组织和纪律；其成员要“希望成为天主（上帝）的战士”，要绝对服从上级，要特别努力地捍卫天主教信仰的传播，时刻准备在世界各地接受天主和总会长的命令，包括忍受各种极端境况。罗耀拉1541年就任耶稣会第一任总会长（Superior General，字面义：“高级将军”）。耶稣会会员称为耶稣会士（Jesuit），属于托钵僧，他们誓守贫穷、贞洁、顺从的生活，还特别立誓，绝对服从教皇的差遣。作为16世纪宗教改革运动中发展起来的组织，耶稣会吸取了改革派的成功经验，注重传教和神学研究，并为此目的，在世界各地开办学校、大学和神学院等机构，一度是天主教会中最具文化修养的群体。——译者注

导读

孔丘（公元前551—前479），字仲尼，后世尊称为孔子，是活跃于春秋时代的教育家与哲学家，儒家学派的创始人。孔子出生于鲁国，祖上是一个没落的宋国贵族，而且相传其父母的婚姻也并不合礼制。三岁时，孔子的父亲病逝，开始由母亲单独抚养，二人过着极为清贫艰辛的生活。不过孔子却并不以此为意，依然十分好学上进，还常常以演练礼仪为幼年时的游戏。三十岁前的孔子在鲁国初入仕途，担任一些无关紧要的职位，只能算是小有名气；自三十岁开始，孔子渐露锋芒，其政治理念受到齐景公等贵族赏识，而且还开私学广收徒，得到各个阶层的支持。这就是孔子所谓的“三十而立”（《论语·为政》）。公元前517年，由于鲁国的内乱，孔子也背井离乡来到齐国，以期实现自己“君君臣臣父父子子”（《论语·颜渊》）的政治理念，不过碍于政治斗争，最后当然以失败告终，不得不于两年后返回鲁国暂别仕途。又经过了十年磨砺的孔子，此时对诸多人生问题的看法越发透彻，也即“四十不惑”（《论语·不惑》）。直到前501年，时年51岁的孔子才再次出仕鲁国，并凭政绩一路迁升至大司寇之位，也因此得罪了掌权的“三桓”势力。慢慢地，孔子越发觉得自己的政治抱负难以在鲁国实现，于是在55岁时带着众位徒弟开始了一段长达十四年的列国游历，所到之处包括卫、曹、宋、郑、陈、蔡等国，虽受万般尊敬，却皆不受重用。晚年的孔子终于返回鲁国，专心整理经典，授徒讲道。

相传孔子精通“六艺”（礼、乐、射、御、书、数），又广收门徒，共弟子三千、贤人七十二，更编撰《诗》《书》《礼》《易》《乐》《春秋》。孔子是儒家的至圣先师，其思想脱胎于周的礼乐传统，以“仁”“义”“礼”（孟子与董仲舒又相继添入“智”与“信”合称“五常”）为道德观，而“仁”又是核心。不过，孔子却从未对“仁”这一概念有过明确的解释，由此可见，“仁”是一个极其复杂、包罗万象的综合性概念——是一种道德规范，是一种人格境界，是一种治国理念，是一种社会制度，也是一种哲学思辨。

《论语》并非由孔子所撰，而是孔子的弟子及再传弟子记录孔子言行的语录体经典，其中包括大量的对话，具有明显的口语特色，简练平白、朴实无华、意蕴深远，也因此能被世世代代争相传诵。《论语》与《大学》《中庸》《孟子》并称“四书”，是儒家学子终生的无上经典。全书现存共20卷（篇），每篇以该篇正文首两（或三）字为名，分别为“学而”“为政”“八佾”“里仁”“公冶长”“雍也”“述而”“泰伯”“子罕”“乡党”“先进”“颜渊”“子路”“宪问”“卫灵公”“季氏”“阳货”“微子”“子张”与“尧曰”。

“伟大的思想”系列收录《论语》一书，选萃其中前十篇：

“学而”，为《论语》首篇，从道德修身方面劝喻修学之士。

“为政”，讲述孔子的治国理政之道。

“八佾”，讲述孔子的礼乐观念。

“里仁”，讲述仁义等概念。

“公冶长”，记录孔子对古今人物的评价。“雍也”，记录孔子弟子的言行。

“述而”，讲述孔子的治学教育理念。

“泰伯”，记录孔子对古代先王的评价。

“子罕”，记录孔子的行事方法。

“乡党”，记录孔子衣食住行的规范。

当然，仅凭寥寥数语，自然是难以详述每篇意旨，还需要读者仔细研读，方能得其一二。

纵观孔子一生，出仕为官、周游列国、著书立说、传道授业，无不在为实现心中理想而努力。只可惜造化弄人，孔子始终未能跳脱出那个只需要霸道秩序的战乱天下，也未能等到儒家理想实现的一天。直到三百多年后，大汉王朝早已天下一统，又先后经历“文景之治”与“汉武盛世”，更是四海归心、天下咸服，逐渐成形的中华民族社会亟须在道德与文化层面建立起一种普世的秩序规范，故而以“仁”为核心的儒家思想才开始真正得到统治阶层与民间社会的普遍重视，并被重新认知与发掘，更在之后的近两千年岁月里，逐渐成为中华民族最重要的精神脊梁。可以说，儒家思想在某种程度上正代表了中华民族的性格，甚至成了东方人的共同标签。

当今天的读者重读这本意蕴丰富的经典，品读那一字一句的智慧语录之时，必定能一窥先人的伟大思想。

柴尔

卷一

1.子曰：“学而时习[1]之，不亦说[2]乎？有朋自远方来，不亦乐乎？人不知[3]而不愠[4]，不亦君子乎？”

孔子说：“将学到的东西不断地用于实践不是一件很开心的事吗？有志同道合的朋友从远方来看望自己难道不会很快乐吗？自己的学识、抱负没有人认可或知道而不心存怨恨，这难道不是君子吗？”

2.有子[5]曰：“其为人也孝弟[6]，而好犯上者[7]，鲜[8]矣；不好犯上，而好作乱者，未之有也[9]。君子务本[10]，本立而道[11]生。孝弟也者，其为仁之本与[12]？”

有子说：“一个人很孝顺父母且敬爱兄长，却又经常对别的长辈或地位比自己高的人不恭敬，这样的人是很少存在的；不会对比自己年长的人或地位高的人不恭，却又经常胡作非为的人我从来没有见过。君子专心致力于根本的事务，基础建立了，治国做人的原则也就有了。孝顺父母、敬爱兄长，这就是仁的根本啊！”

3.子曰：“巧言令色[13]，鲜[14]矣仁。”

孔子说：“总是花言巧语，假装和颜悦色的人很少是仁慈的。”

4.曾子[15]曰：“吾日三省吾身[16]。为人谋而不忠乎？与朋友交而不信乎？传不习[17]乎？”

曾子说：“我每天都会反省自己很多次，帮别人做事是否尽心尽力？与朋友交往有没有不守信用？学到的知识是否不断温习或应用起来？”

5.子曰：“道[18]千乘之国[19]，敬事而信，节用而爱人[20]，使民以时。”

孔子说：“治理大国的人应该做到：做事兢兢业业、信守承诺，认真严谨地处理国家政事，节约财政开支，友爱同僚，役使民众而不误他们的农时。”

6.子曰：“弟子[21]入则孝，出则弟[22]，谨而信，泛爱众，而亲仁[23]。行有余力，则以学文。”

孔子说：“年轻人在家要孝敬父母，出门要友敬爱兄长，为人处事谨慎而又言而有信，尊敬爱护每一个人，亲近有仁德的人。做到了这些并且有余力就可以继续学习各种文化知识。”

7.子夏[24]曰：“贤贤[25]易[26]色；事父母，能竭其力；事君，能致其身[27]；与朋友交，言而有信。虽曰未学，吾必谓之学矣。”

子夏说：“尊敬贤德的人并不断向他们学习，改正自己错误的做法；侍奉父母要尽心尽力，竭尽自己的力量；服务君王能全身心地奉献；与朋友交往重诺守义，言而有信。即使这样的人没有读过一天书，我一定说他是很有学问的。”

8.子曰：“君子不重[28]则不威；学则不固[29]。主忠信[30]。无[31]友不如己者[32]；过[33]则勿惮[34]改。”

孔子说：“一个人不自重自爱就不会有威严；不断学习才不会鄙陋；恪守忠信，与志同道合的人做朋友；有了过错要去改正，不要害怕改变。”

9.曾子曰：“慎终[35]，追远[36]，民德归厚矣。”

曾子说：“慎重地对待丧礼，虔诚地举行祭祀，民风就会慢慢转好的。”

10.子禽[37]问于子贡[38]曰：“夫子[39]至于是邦[40]也，必闻其政，求之与，抑[41]与之与？”子贡曰：“夫子温、良、恭、俭、让[42]以得之。夫子之求之也，其诸[43]异乎人之求之与？”

子禽向子贡请教问题：“老师（孔子）每到一个国家就总是能知道这个国家的政令、政风，这是老师去请求得来的呢，还是有人主动告诉他的呢？”子贡回答说：“老师温良如玉、恭敬俭朴谦让，所以才会有资格知道这些事。老师得到的方法大概与别人的方法不同吧！”

11.子曰：“父在，观其[44]志；父没，观其行[45]；三年[46]无改于父之道[47]，可谓孝矣。”

孔子说：“父亲在世的时候，应该观察儿子的思想、志向；父亲去世以后应该观察儿子的所作所为。如果过了很长一段时间儿子都没有改变当时好的作为，就可以说他是很孝顺的了。”

12.有子[48]曰：“礼之用，和为贵。先王[49]之道，斯为美，小大由之。有所不行，知和而和，不以礼节之，亦不可行也。”

有子说：“礼的应用，以和谐为关键。先代圣王的治国方法最可贵的地方就在于他们做所有的事都以此为出发点。如果不能做到这一点，只为求和谐的目的而去做，但不以‘礼’的精髓制约行为，也是行不通的。”

13.有子曰：“信近[50]于义[51]，言可复[52]也；恭近于礼，远[53]耻辱也；因[54]不失其亲，亦可宗[55]也。”

有子说：“信守承诺的行为合乎于‘义’，这样的言辞才能够被履行；态度容貌的庄重矜持要符合于礼，这样的行为才不至于遭受侮辱；所依靠的人都是关系亲密、值得依靠的人，这样才可靠。”

14.子曰：“君子食无求饱，居无求安，敏于事而慎于言，就[56]有道[57]而正[58]焉，可谓好学也已。”

孔子说：“君子（代指一般有德行的人）在饮食上不求饱足，果腹即可；住所上不求安逸，栖身则已；对事情有敏锐的看法而又慎于言辞，向有道德的人看齐并不断端正自己的行为，这样就算是好学的人了。”

15.子贡曰：“贫而无谄[59]，富而无骄，何如[60]？”子曰：“可也。未若贫而乐[61]，富而好礼者也。”子贡曰：“《诗》云，‘如切如磋！如琢如磨’[62]，其斯之谓与？”子曰：“赐[63]也！始可与言《诗》已矣，告诸往而知来者[64]。”

子贡说：“没钱而不谄媚别人，有钱而不骄奢待人，怎么样呀？”孔子说：“这样的人也算是不错了，但是不如虽然贫穷却乐观地生活，富贵而谦恭好礼的人呀！”子贡说：“《诗经》讲，要像对待骨、角、象牙、玉石一样，切磋它，琢磨它，这就是做人或做学问的方法吧？”孔子赞叹道：“赐啊！已经可以和你讲解《诗经》了，你已能从我讲的过去的事情中领会到另外没有说到的意思了。

16.子曰：“不患[65]人[66]之不己知，患不知人也。”

孔子说：“不担心别人不知道自己，而担心自己不了解别人啊！”

卷二

1.子曰：“为政以德[67]，譬如北辰[68]，居其所而众星共[69]之。”

孔子说：“如果君王以‘德’治理国家，那就会像北极星一样，安居在自己的位置而其余众星有序地环绕在它的周围（随它的方向前进）。”

2.子曰：“《诗》三百[70]，一言以蔽之，曰：‘思无邪[71]。’”

孔子说：“《诗经》的全部内容用一句话来概括就是：思想纯正。”

3.子曰：“道[72]之以政，齐之以刑，民免而无耻；道之以德，齐之以礼，有耻且格[73]。”

孔子说：“如果用行政命令来训导民众，用严刑峻法来整束民众，民众只会千方百计避免获罪而丧失廉耻之心；如果用道德引导民众，用礼仪约束民众，民众就会有羞耻之心并且努力（改正自己）以达到要求。”

4.子曰：“吾十有[74]五而志于学，三十而立[75]，四十而不惑[76]，五十而知天命[77]，六十而耳顺[78]，七十而从心所欲不逾矩[79]。”

孔子说：“我十五岁的时候立下了学习的志向，三十岁时说话做事都很得当，四十岁时掌握了知识开始不因外界事物困惑，五十岁时知晓天命，六十岁对不利于自己的意见也会正确对待，七十岁以后则能行动都随自己的心意而又不会越过世俗规矩。”

5.孟懿子[80]问孝。子曰：“无违[81]。”樊迟[82]御，子告之曰：“孟孙问孝于我，我对曰‘无违’。”樊迟曰：“何谓也？”子曰：“生，事之以礼；死，葬之以礼，祭之以礼。”

孟懿子向孔子请教关于“孝”的问题。孔子回答他说：“不要违背。”当樊迟为孔子驾车的时候，孔子告诉他说：“孟孙（孟懿子）问我什么是孝，我告诉他就是‘不要违背’。”樊迟问道：“这是什么意思呢？”孔子回答道：“父母在世，以礼来侍奉他们；父母过世，以礼来安葬他们，以礼来祭祀怀念他们。”

6.孟武伯[83]问孝，子曰：“父母唯其疾之忧[84]。”

孟武伯问孔子什么是“孝”，孔子回答说：“孝顺父母就是要（时刻）关心他们的身体，为他们的疾病担忧。”

7.子游[85]问孝，子曰：“今之孝者，是谓能养。至于犬马，皆能有养[86]，不敬，何以别乎？”

子游向孔子请教什么是“孝”，孔子说：“今天我们说到‘孝’，就说是能够赡养老人就可以了。但我们对家里的狗、马也能做到很好地喂养它们。所以，如果没有用恭敬的态度对待父母，那么这种赡养与喂养家里的动物有什么区别呢？”

8.子夏问孝，子曰：“色难[87]。有事，弟子服其劳[88]；有酒食，先生[89]馔[90]，曾是以为孝乎？”

子夏问孔子什么是“孝”，孔子说：“要做到和颜悦色，始终恭敬最不容易。如果只是父母长辈有什么事，晚辈子女帮他们完成，服侍他们，有好的饮食也都先拿来奉给他们，你以为这样就是做到‘孝’了吗？”

9.子曰：“吾与回[91]言，终日不违[92]，如愚。退而省其私[93]，亦足以发，回也不愚。”

孔子说：“每次我跟颜回说些什么，一整天他都不会提出什么相反的意见或问题来，就好像很愚钝一样。但通过观察他私下里与其他人的言行，其实对我们平时讨论的问题有很多阐发。颜回也并不是很愚钝呀！”

10.子曰：“视其所以[94]，观其所由[95]，察其所安[96]，人焉廋[97]哉？人焉廋哉？”

孔子说：“（要考察一个人）只要看他所做过的事情，观察他曾经的经历，看他的秉性涵养，这样一个人怎么能掩藏起自己来呢？怎么能掩藏起自己来呢？”

11.子曰：“温故而知新[98]，可以为师矣。”

孔子说：“不断温习以前学到的知识，不断从中阐发出新的体会，这样的人可以做老师了。”

12.子曰：“君子不器[99]。”

孔子说：“君子不会像器皿一样只具备某一方面的才能。”

13.子贡问君子。子曰：“先行其言而后从之。”

子贡问孔子怎样做一个君子。孔子说：“对于要说的话，先将它付诸于行动，然后再将它说出来（这样才是君子）。”

14.子曰：“君子周[100]而不比[101]，小人[102]比而不周。”

孔子说：“君子与人相处合群而不勾结，小人则是与人勾结而不合群。”

15.子曰：“学而不思则罔[103]，思而不学则殆[104]。”

孔子说：“单纯学习知识但不去思索就会茫然、迷惑，只是不断空想但不学习实践就会迷惑茫然。

16.子曰：“攻[105]乎异端[106]，斯[107]害也已[108]。

孔子说：“（不讲道理地）攻击反对不同于己的言论或事物，这种行为也是错误的。”

17.子曰：“由[109]，诲女[110]，知之乎？知之为知之，不知为不知，是知也。”

孔子说：“由啊，我教导你的你明白吗？对一件事，知道就是知道，不知道就是不知道，这就是有智慧啊。”

18.子张[111]学干禄[112]，子曰：“多闻阙[113]疑[114]，慎言其余，则寡尤[115]；多见阙殆，慎行其余，则寡悔。言寡尤，行寡悔，禄在其中矣。”

子张问怎样求取官职。孔子回答说：“多听取别人的意见，有疑问的就先将它搁置在一边，对有把握的事也不要轻易地谈论，这样说话就会少犯错误；遇到事情要多观察，有怀疑的就先不做，对有把握的事也要谨慎地去处理，这样做事就不会有太多悔恨。做到少说错话、少做错事，官职俸禄自然就能得到。”

19.哀公[116]问曰：“何为则民服？”孔子对曰[117]：“举直错诸枉[118]，则民服；举枉错诸直，则民不服。”

鲁哀公问孔子：“怎样做才能使民众臣服？”孔子回答说：“选拔任用正直公平的人，把不正直的人放置一旁，那么人民就会臣服；任用不正直的人而将正直无私的人放置不予任用，则民众不会臣服。”

20.季康子[119]问：“使民敬、忠以[120]劝[121]，如之何？”子曰：“临[122]之以庄，则敬；孝慈[123]，则忠；举善而教不能，则劝。”

季康子问孔子：“要使民众恭敬、忠厚，并且自勉努力，应该怎样做呢？”孔子说：“对待民众庄重威严，他们就会态度恭敬；通过自己的行为引导百姓孝敬父母、慈爱兄弟，则民风忠厚；提拔良善的人而教导能力差的人，人们就会自勉努力了。”

21.或[124]谓孔子曰：“子奚[125]不为政？”子曰：“《书》[126]云：‘孝乎惟孝，友于兄弟，施于有政[127]。’是亦为政，奚其为为政？”

有人对孔子说：“先生为什么不从事政治呢？”孔子回答道：“《尚书》里说过，孝就是孝敬父母，友爱兄弟。用这孝的风气去影响当政者，也就是从政了，难道只有做官才能算是从事政治吗？”

22.子曰：“人而无信，不知其可也。大车无輗[128]，小车无軏[129]，其何以行之哉？”

孔子说：“一个人做事没有信誉，会让人不知道他到底想做什么，让人无所适从。就像牛车上没有輗，小车上没有一样，它凭什么来行进呢？”

23.子张问：“十世[130]可知也？”子曰：“殷因[131]于夏礼，所损益[132]可知也；周因于殷礼，所损益可知也。其或继周者，虽百世，可知也。”

子张问孔子：“今后十世（的礼仪制度）可以知道吗？”孔子回答说：“殷代沿用夏代的礼制，周代沿用殷代的礼制，他们在因循的过程中对这些礼制的修整变化是可以考察到的。以后别的继承周代的国家就算历任百世，他的礼制也可以推出来。”

24.子曰：“非其鬼[133]而祭之；谄[134]也。见义[135]不为，无勇也。”

孔子说：“不是自己家的祖先而去祭祀他，这是谄媚的行为，见到应该做的事而不做是没有勇气。”

卷三

1.孔子谓季氏[136]：“八佾[137]舞于庭，是可忍[138]，孰不可忍也！”

孔子评论季平子说：“季家用违反礼仪的八佾在自家庭院里演出，如果这种事情都能容忍的话，还有什么事情不能容忍呢？”

2.三家[139]者以《雍》彻[140]。子曰：“‘相维辟公，天子穆穆’[141]，奚取于三家之堂[142]？”

在鲁国当政的孟孙氏、叔孙氏、季孙氏三家在祭祖完毕撤去祭品时，也命乐工唱《雍》这篇诗。孔子评论说：“‘助祭的是诸侯，天子严肃静穆地在那里主祭。（诗《雍》中的两句）’这样的意思，怎么能用在你们三家祭祖的庙堂里呢？”

3.子曰：“人而不仁，如礼何？人而不仁，如乐何？”

孔子说：“为人没有仁德，他要怎样实行礼制呢？为人没有仁德，他要怎样运用乐制呢？”

4.林放[143]问礼之本。子曰：“大哉问！礼，与其奢也，宁俭；丧，与其易[144]也，宁戚[145]。”

林放向孔子询问“礼”的根本。孔子回答说：“这是多么重要的问题呀！礼仪，与其奢侈宁愿俭朴；丧礼，与其仪式铺张不如内心悲戚。”

5.子曰：“夷狄[146]之有君，不如诸夏[147]之亡[148]也。”

孔子说：“蛮荒之地的人即使有君主统治也不如中原礼仪之邦的人没有君主统治。”

6.季氏旅[149]于泰山，子谓冉有[150]曰：“女[151]弗能救[152]与？”对曰：“不能。”子曰：“呜呼！曾谓泰山不如林放[153]乎？”

季氏将要祭祀泰山，孔子问冉有：“你难道不能劝阻他这种不合礼制的行为吗？”冉有回答说：“不能。”孔子叹道：“唉！难道泰山神还不如林放知礼而接受不合规矩的祭礼吗？”

7.子曰：“君子无所争，必也射[154]乎！揖[155]让而升，下而饮，其争也君子。”

孔子说：“君子没有什么争强好胜的心，如果有的话，那就在射箭比赛上表现最明显了。开始比赛时，先拱手行礼以示尊敬，相互礼让后上场，射完箭又相互作揖，再退下来一起喝酒。这种争的方式也是君子的做法。”

8.子夏问曰：“‘巧笑倩兮，美目盼兮，素以为绚兮’。[156]何谓也？”子曰：“绘事后素[157]。”曰：礼后乎？”子曰：“起予者商也[158]，始可与言《诗》已矣。”

子夏问孔子说：“《诗经》上说，乖巧的笑容多迷人，美丽的眼睛多灵动，用素粉来打扮多漂亮啊。这几句话是什么意思呢？”孔子回答道：“这是说先有白底然后才能画画。”子夏又问道：“那么说礼也是后起的事了？”孔子答道：“商，你真是能启发我的人，现在可以同你一起讨论《诗经》了。”

9.子曰：“夏礼吾能言之，杞[159]不足征[160]也；殷礼吾能言之，宋[161]不足征也。文献[162]不足故也。足，则吾能征之矣。”

孔子说：“夏代的礼制我还能说出来，但单凭杞国现存的礼制已不足以证明我所说的了；殷代的礼制我能说出来，但凭宋国的礼制也已经不能证明我所说的了。这是因为他们的文献资料和贤人不足的缘故啊。如果足够的话，我就能证明给你们看了。”

10.子曰：“褅[163]自既灌[164]而往者，吾不欲观之矣[165]。”

孔子说：“对于行褅礼的仪式，从第一次献酒以后，我就不愿意再往下看了。”

11.或问褅之说[166]，子曰：“不知也。知其说者之于天下也，其如示诸斯[167]乎！”指其掌。

有人向孔子询问关于褅祭的规定，孔子回答说：“我不知道。真正懂得‘褅’这个文化精神的人，看天下国家事务的道理，就好像是呈现在这里这么清楚明白。说完指指掌心。”

12.祭如在，祭神如神在。子曰：“吾不与祭，如不祭。”

祭祀祖先就要像祖宗在自己面前一样（恭敬），祭神就要像真正面对神灵一样虔诚。孔子说：“如果我没有全心投入到祭祀中去，不如不去祭祀。”

13.王孙贾[168]问曰：“与其媚[169]于奥[170]，宁媚于灶[171]，何谓也？"子曰：“不然。获罪于天[172]，无所祷也。”

卫国大臣王孙贾问孔子：“（有人说）与其向奥神献媚，不如向灶神献媚，这是什么意思？”孔子回答道：“不是这样的。当所做的事为天理难容时，无论向谁祈祷都没有用。”

14.子曰：“周监[173]于二代[174]，郁郁[175]乎文哉，吾从周。”

孔子说：“周代承继借鉴了夏商两朝的礼仪文化，它的礼制文化非常丰富、伟大与光辉，我遵从周代的礼制。”

15.子入太庙[176]，每事问。或曰：“孰谓鄹[177]人之子知礼乎？入太庙，每事问。”子闻之，曰：“是礼也。”

孔子到了太庙每遇一件事都会详细询问。有人说：“不是说孔子对礼制很有研究吗，那为什么进了太庙事无巨细都要询问呢？”孔子听到后说：“这件事（对每一件事都详细询问）本身就是懂礼制的表现啊！”

16.子曰：“射不主皮[178]，为力不同科[179]，古之道也。”

孔子说：“比赛射箭时不在于能让箭穿透靶子，因为各人的力气大小不同。这是自古以来就有的规矩。”

17.子贡欲去告朔[180]之饩羊[181]。子曰：“赐也！尔爱[182]其羊，我爱其礼。”

子贡想要取消每月初一祭祀时用的活羊。孔子知道后说：“赐啊！你舍不得你的羊，但我舍不得的是我的礼呀！”

18.子曰：“事君尽礼，人以为谄也。”

孔子说：“侍奉君王一切都按照礼制的要求去做，别人却以为是在向君主献媚。”

19.定公[183]问：“君使臣，臣事君，如之何？”孔子对曰：“君使臣以礼，臣事君以忠。”

鲁定公问孔子：“君主役使臣子，臣子侍奉君主，都应该怎样去做啊？”孔子回答道：“君王让臣子做事应该以礼待臣；臣子应以忠心报君，全心侍奉君主。”

20.子曰：“《关雎》[184]，乐而不淫，哀而不伤。”

孔子说：“《关雎》这首诗，快乐而不放荡，悲哀而不痛苦。”

21.哀公问社[185]于宰我，宰我[186]对曰：“夏后氏以松，殷人以柏，周人以栗，曰：使民战栗[187]。”子闻之，曰：“成事不说，遂事不谏，既往不咎。”

鲁哀公问宰我土地神的神主应该用什么树木制作，宰我说：“夏代用松树，殷代用柏树，周代用栗树，取其‘让民众恐惧、发抖’之意。”孔子听说后说：“已经做过的事就不用提了，已经完成的事就不用再去劝阻了，已经过去的事也就不必再追究了。”

22.子曰：“管仲[188]之器小哉！”或曰：“管仲俭乎？”曰：“管氏有三归[189]，官事不摄[190]，焉得俭？”“然则管仲知礼乎？”曰：“邦君树塞门[191]，管氏亦树塞门；邦君为两君之好有反坫[192]，管氏亦有反坫。管氏而知礼，孰不知礼？”

孔子说：“管仲的器量还是太小了呀！”有人问：“管仲节俭吗？”孔子说：“管仲收取人民大量市租，他家里的管事也是一人一职而不兼任，这怎么会是节俭呢？”有人又问：“那么管仲懂得礼制吗？”孔子回答说：“齐君在大门口筑了一道照壁，管仲也在大门口筑一道照壁；齐君为招待别国国君而设置用来放置献过酒的空杯子的台子，管仲也设置一个。如果说管仲知道礼制，那还有谁是不知礼的呢？”

23.子语[193]鲁大师[194]乐，曰：“乐其可知也：始作，龛[195]如也；从[196]之，纯[197]如也，皦[198]如也，绎[199]如也，以成。”

孔子告诉鲁太师演奏音乐的道理：“音乐的演奏是有规律的。刚开始演奏的时候，各种乐音和谐地配合，轻轻地舒展开，慢慢地发声；继续展开下去，音乐由小而大，悠扬悦耳，音节分明，到了高潮，或激昂慷慨或非常庄严肃穆，最后这个乐曲演奏完了，但还是余音缭绕，后面好像还有悠悠未尽之意。”

24.仪封人[200]请见，曰：“君子之至于斯也，吾未尝不得见也。”从者见之[201]。出，曰：“二三子何患于丧[202]乎？天下之无道也久矣，天将以夫子为木铎[203]。”

仪地镇守边疆的官员请求拜见孔子，他说：“凡是来到这里的有德行的人，没有一个是我不能见到的。”于是孔子的学生请求孔子接见他。官员拜见完孔子后对学生说：“你们为何要担心失去官职呢？天下文化礼制丧失已久，上天让孔子降生，就是想以他来警醒世人啊！”

25.子谓《韶》[204]：“尽美[205]矣，又尽善[206]也。”谓《武》[207]：“尽美矣，未尽善也。”

孔子谈论到《韶》乐的时候说：“这支乐舞的音调、舞蹈美极了，表现的思想也善极了。”当谈到《武》乐的时候则说：“这支乐舞美极了，但还没做到善极。”

26.子曰：“居上不宽，为礼不敬，临丧不哀，吾何以观之哉？”

孔子说：“居于统治地位而不宽以待人，行礼的时候也不庄严肃穆，对待丧事不真心哀戚，这种样子我怎么能看得下去呢？”

卷四

1.子曰：“里仁为美[208]，择不处[209]仁，焉得知[210]？”

孔子说：“跟仁德的人做邻居才好，如果居住时不选择住在贤德的人的附近，我们又怎么能得到智慧呢？”

2.子曰：“不仁者不可以久处约[211]，不可以长处乐。仁者安仁[212]，知者利仁。”

孔子说：“没有仁德之心的人不能长久地处在贫困中，也不能长久地处于安乐中。有仁德的人安于仁道，有智慧的人则是知道仁对自己有利才去实行仁道的。”

3.子曰：“唯仁者能好[213]人，能恶[214]人。”

孔子说：“唯有仁德的人能正确地喜欢一个人、厌恶一个人。”

4.子曰：“苟志于仁矣，无恶也。”

孔子说：“如果立定志向实行仁道的话，总是没有坏处的。”

5.子曰：“富与贵，是人之所欲也，不以其道得之，不处也；贫与贱，是人之所恶也，不以其道得之，不去也。君子去仁，恶乎成名？君子无终食之间违仁，造次必于是，颠沛必于是。”

孔子说：“财富与地位是每一个人所向往的，但不是以正当方式得到的，君子是不会接受的。贫穷与卑微是每个人所厌恶的，如果不是用正当的手段去改变这种境况，君子宁愿不改变。君子如果离开了仁德，又怎么能叫君子呢？君子不会在哪怕一顿饭的时间里背离仁德，即使在最紧迫的时刻也必须按照仁德办事，就是在颠沛流离的时候，也一定会按仁德去办事。”

6.子曰：“我未见好仁者，恶不仁者。好仁者，无以尚之；恶不仁者，其为仁矣，不使不仁者加乎其身。有能一日用其力于仁矣乎？我未见力不足者。盖有之矣，我未之见也。”

孔子说：“我没有见过爱好仁德的人，也没有见过厌恶不仁的人。爱好仁德的人，那是不能再好的了；厌恶不仁的人，在实行仁德的时候，只是不想让不仁德的人或事影响自己。有能每天都把自己的力量用在实行仁德上的人吗？我没有见过力量不够的（只是没有人去这样做罢了）。这种人大概也还是有的，但我没见过。”

7.子曰：“人之过也，各于其党。观过，斯知仁矣。”

孔子说：“一个人的过错各属于一定类型。通过仔细考察这个人所犯的错误，就可以知道他是什么样的人了。”

8.子曰：“朝闻道，夕死可矣。”

孔子说：“如果在早上听闻了真理，即使晚上就会死去也没有什么遗憾了。”

9.子曰：“士志于道，而耻恶衣恶食者，未足与议也。”

孔子说：“如果读书人立志要探求真理，却又对吃粗粮穿破衣的生活感到羞耻，这种人是不足以与他谈论人生至理的。”

10.子曰：“君子之于天下也，无适[215]也，无莫[216]也，义[217]之与比[218]。”

孔子说：“君子对于天下的人和事，没有固定的厚薄亲疏，怎样合理恰当，便怎样做。”

11.子曰：“君子怀[219]德，小人怀土[220]；君子怀刑[221]，小人怀惠。

孔子说：“君子时刻不忘记德行，小人时刻惦记的只是乡土；君子关心法度，小人关心恩惠。”

12.子曰：“放[222]于利而行，多怨[223]。”

孔子说：“只是为了追求利益而去做事，很容易招致别人的怨恨。”

13.子曰：“能以礼让为国乎，何有[224]？不能以礼让为国，如礼何[225]？”

孔子说：“能够用礼让的原则来治理国家，那还有什么困难的呢？不能用礼让的原则来治理国家，怎么能实行礼制呢？”

14.子曰：“不患无位，患所以立；不患莫己知，求为可知也。”

孔子说：“（君子）不担心没有地位，只担心自己没有学到得以安身立命的知识；不担心没有人知道自己，只求自己能成为有真才实学，值得为人们知道的人。”

15.子曰：“参[226]乎，吾道一以贯之。”曾子曰：“唯。”子出，门人问曰：“何谓也？”曾子曰：“夫子之道，忠恕[227]而已矣。”

孔子说：“参呀，我的学说是由一个基本的思想贯彻始终的。”曾子说：“是的。”孔子出去以后，别的学生问曾子：“先生说的是什么意思呀？”曾子说：“老师的学说，主要是讲忠和恕罢了。”

16.子曰：“君子喻于义，小人喻于利[228]。”

孔子说：“君子明白的是义，小人只知道利。”

17.子曰：“见贤思齐焉，见不贤而内自省[229]也。”

孔子说：“看见贤德的人就要努力学习向他靠齐，看见不贤德的人就要立即反省自己有没有类似的缺点。”

18.子曰：“事父母几[230]谏，见志不从，又敬不违，劳[231]而不怨。”

孔子说：“侍奉父母，（当他们有错的时候）要婉转地进行劝谏，如果他们不听从自己的意见，那也要态度恭敬而不要忤逆违背他们的意愿，要为他们担忧操劳而不要心存怨恨。”

19.子曰：“父母在，不远游[232]，游必有方[233]。”

孔子说：“父母在世的时候，不要离开他们去很远的地方，（避免他们没有人照顾，）不得已而外出必须要告诉他们要去的地方。”

20.子曰：“三年无改于父之道，可谓孝矣。”

孔子说：“如果过了很长一段时间儿子都没有改变父亲在世时的好的作为，就可以说他是很孝顺的了。”

21.子曰：“父母之年，不可不知也。一则以喜，一则以惧。”

孔子说：“父母的年龄是不可以不知道的。一方面可以为他们的长寿而开心，另一方面也要为他们的年老而担忧。”

22.子曰：“古者言之不出，耻躬之不逮也。”

孔子说：“古代的人言语不轻易说出口，因为他们担心自己的行为会有做不到的地方。”

23.子曰：“以约[234]失之者鲜[235]矣。”

孔子说：“时刻以礼制约束自己而又总犯错误的人是很少见的呀。”

24.子曰：“君子欲讷[236]于言而敏[237]于行。”

孔子说：“君子言语要谨慎，行动要勤敏。”

25.子曰：“德不孤，必有邻。”

孔子说：“有道德的人是不会孤独的，一定会有志同道合的人来与他做伴。”

26.子游曰：“事君数[238]，斯[239]辱矣；朋友数，斯疏矣。”

子游说：“侍奉君主过于烦琐，就会招致羞辱；对待朋友太过烦琐反而会导致疏远。”

卷五

1.子谓公冶长[240]：“可妻也。虽在缧绁[241]之中，非其罪也。”以其子[242]妻之。

孔子评论公冶长说：“（这个人），可以将女儿嫁给他。虽然现在身陷监牢，但这并不是他的过错造成的。”于是就将自己的女儿嫁给了公冶长。

2.子谓南容[243]：“邦有道[244]，不废[245]；邦无道，免于刑戮[246]。”以其兄之子妻之。

孔子评价南宫适说：“国家政治清明时，他是不会被埋没的；国家政治昏暗时，他也能善于自处，免去刑戮。”于是就将自己兄长的女儿嫁给南宫适。

3.子谓子贱[247]：“君子哉若人[248]！鲁无君子者，斯焉取斯[249]？”

孔子评论子贱说：“这个人是君子呀！假若鲁国没有君子，那么这种人又是从哪里培养出这种好品德的呢？”

4.子贡问曰：“赐也何如？”子曰：“女，器也。”曰：“何器也？”曰：“瑚琏[250]也。”

子贡问孔子：“我这个人怎么样啊？”孔子说：“你好比是一个器具。”子贡问道：“什么器具呀？”孔子回答道：“你就是宗庙里盛黍稷的瑚琏。”

5.或曰：“雍[251]也仁而不佞[252]。”子曰：“焉用佞？御人以口给[253]，屡憎于人，不知其仁[254]。焉用佞？”

有人评论冉雍说：“冉雍这个人很有仁德但是没有口才。”孔子说：“要那么好的口才干什么呢？靠伶牙俐齿和人辩论，常常会招致别人的厌恶，这样的人我不知道他是不是能做到有仁德。那么冉雍又何必一定要能言善辩呢？”

6.子使漆雕开[255]仕。对曰：“吾斯之未能信。”子说[256]。

孔子让漆雕开去做官。漆雕开说：“我对做官这件事还没有信心。”孔子听后很高兴。

7.子曰：“道不行，乘桴[257]浮于海，从[258]我者，其由与！”子路闻之喜。子曰：“由也好勇过我，无所取材。”

孔子说：“如果我的主张最终不能实现，那我就会乘一个木筏子去海外了。跟随我的人恐怕只有仲由吧。”子路听说后非常高兴。孔子见了说道：“仲由这个人太冲动鲁莽了，这种好勇的精神大大超过了我，这样的话做事就会缺少明断。”

8.孟武伯问子路仁乎？子曰：“不知也。”又问。子曰：“由也，千乘之国，可使治其赋[259]也，不知其仁也。”“求也何如？”子曰：“求也，千室之邑[260]，百乘之家[261]，可使为之宰[262]也，不知其仁也。”“赤[263]也何如？”子曰：“赤也，束带立于朝[264]，可使与宾客[265]言也，不知其仁也。”

孟武伯问孔子子路算不算有仁德，孔子回答说：“不知道。”孟武伯又继续询问，孔子说：“仲由这个人啊，在有一千乘马车的大国里，可以让他负责兵役和军政的工作。至于他有没有仁德，我不晓得。”

孟武伯又问：“冉求这个人怎么样呢？”孔子说：“冉求呢，在有千户人家的公邑或有百辆兵车的采邑里当总管是可以的。至于他有没有仁德，我不晓得。”

孟武伯问：“公西赤又怎么样呢？”孔子说：“公西赤嘛，可以让他穿着礼服，站在朝堂上接待贵宾，但我也不知道他是不是做到了仁。”

9.子谓子贡曰：“女与回也孰愈[266]？”对曰：“赐也何敢望回？回也闻一以知十[267]，赐也闻一以知二[268]。”子曰：“弗如也。吾与[269]女弗如也。”

孔子对子贡说：“你和颜回谁的学问更好一些呢？”子贡说：“我怎么可以和颜回相比呢？颜回听到一件事就可以推知十件事，而我知道一件事只能推知两件事。”孔子说：“是不如他呀，我同意你说的，是不如他。”

10.宰予昼寝，子曰：“朽木不可雕也，粪土[270]之墙不可圬[271]也，于予与何诛[272]！”子曰：“始吾于人也，听其言而信其行；今吾于人也，听其言而观其行。于予与[273]改是。”

宰予大白天在屋里睡觉。孔子说：“腐烂了的木头没有办法在上面雕刻，腐土垒起的墙壁没有办法粉刷；至于宰予嘛，我又怎么能去责备他呢？”孔子又说：“最开始的时候，我观察一个人，听到他所说的话，便相信他的行为；现在我观察一个人，会在听到他的话后，继续考察他的行为。宰予这件事以后，我才改变了态度的。”

11.子曰：“吾未见刚者。”或对曰：“申枨[274]。”子曰：“枨也欲，焉得刚？”

孔子说：“我没有见过刚毅不屈的人。”有的人回答道：“申枨就是呀。孔子说：“申枨做事情还是会存有一些欲望，这样的人又怎么会刚毅不屈呢？”

12.子贡曰：“我不欲人之加诸我也，吾亦欲无加诸人。”子曰：“赐也，非尔所及也。”

子贡说：“我不希望别人强加给我一些事，我也不会强加给别人事情。”孔子说：“赐啊，这样的事你还做不到呢。”

13.子贡曰：“夫子之文章[275]，可得而闻也；夫子之言性[276]与天道[277]，不可得而闻也。”

子贡说：“先生在诗书礼乐等各方面的学问我们可以（在日常学习中）学到，先生关于人性和天道命运方面的学识则是我们怎么学也学不到的。”

14.子路有闻，未之能行，唯恐有闻。

子路听到一个道理但没有能够亲自实行的时候，唯恐又听到新的道理。

15.子贡问曰：“孔文子[278]何以谓之‘文’也？”子曰：“敏[279]而好学，不耻下问，是以谓之‘文’也。”

子贡问孔子：“孔文子的谥号为什么是‘文’呢？”孔子说：“聪明勤勉而又刻苦学习，遇到不懂的问题，随时向人请教，而不在乎别人身份地位的高低，所以谥号为‘文’。”

16.子谓子产[280]有君子之道四焉：“其行己也恭，其事上也敬，其养民也惠，其使民也义。”

孔子评价子产有四种行为合于君子之道：“他自己的行为举止庄严肃穆，他对待君王恭敬有礼，他教导人民恩惠有加，他役使百姓合于义理法度。”

17.子曰：“晏平仲[281]善与人交，久而敬之[282]。”

孔子说：“晏平仲很会跟人交往，交往越久，别人对他越恭敬有礼。”

18.子曰：“臧文仲[283]居蔡[284]，山节藻棁[285]，何如其知也！”

孔子说：“臧文仲养了一只大龟，龟室的斗拱雕成山的形状，短柱上画以水草花纹，他这个人又怎么能算是有智慧的人呢？”

19.子张问曰：“令尹子文[286]三仕为令尹，无喜色；三已[287]之，无愠色。旧令尹之政，必以告新令尹。何如？”子曰：“忠矣。”曰：“仁矣乎？”曰：“未知。焉得仁？”“崔子[288]弑[289]齐君[290]，陈子文[291]有马十乘，弃而违之，至于他邦，则曰：‘犹吾大夫崔子也。’违之。之一邦，则又曰：‘犹吾大夫崔子也。’违之，何如？”子曰：“清矣。”曰：“仁矣乎？”曰：“未知，焉得仁？”

子张问孔子说：“楚国的令尹子文几次做楚国宰相，没有显出高兴的样子，几次被免职，也没有显出怨恨的样子；他每次被免职时一定把以前的政务都告诉给来接任的新宰相。这个人怎么样啊？”孔子说：“可算尽忠于国家了。”子张问：“算得上仁了吗？”孔子说：“不知道。这怎么能算仁呢？”

子张又问：“崔杼杀了他的君主齐庄公，陈文子家很富有，有四十匹马，都舍弃不要而离开了齐国，到了另一个国家，他说，这里的执政者也和我们齐国的大夫崔杼差不多，于是就离开了。到了另一个国家，又说，这里的执政者也和我们的大夫崔杼差不多，又离开了。这个人你看怎么样？”孔子说：“可以算得上清高了。”子张说：“这算不算仁呢？”孔子说：“不知道。这怎么能算得上仁呢？”

20.季文子[292]三思而后行。子闻之，曰：“再，斯[293]可矣。”

季文子每做一件事都要考虑很多次才行动。孔子听说后，说：“想两次就可以了。”

21.子曰：“宁武子[294]，邦有道则知，邦无道则愚[295]，其知可及也，其愚不可及也。”

孔子说：“宁武子这个人，在国家太平时节他就显得聪明，当国家无道昏暗时，他就装傻。他的那种聪明别人可以做得到，他那种装傻别人就做不到了。”

22.子在陈[296]曰：“归与！归与！吾党之小子[297]狂简[298]，斐然[299]成章，不知所以裁[300]之。”

孔子在陈国，说：“回去吧！回去吧！我们家乡的学生有远大志向，但行为粗率简单；文采斐然可观，但还不知道怎样来约束自己。”

23.子曰：“伯夷叔齐[301]不念旧恶[302]，怨是用希[303]。”

孔子说：“伯夷、叔齐这两兄弟不记念过去的仇恨，因此别人对他们的怨恨也就很少。”

24.子曰：“孰谓微生高[304]直？或乞醯[305]焉，乞诸其邻而与之。”

孔子说：“谁说微生高这个人直率？有人向他借点醋，他不直说自己没有，却跑到邻居家里讨了点转借给人。”

25.子曰：“巧言令色足恭[306]，左丘明[307]耻之，丘亦耻之。匿怨而友其人，左丘明耻之，丘亦耻之。”

孔子说：“花言巧语，伪善的脸色，逢迎的姿态，低三下四的恭顺，这种态度，左丘明认为可耻，我也认为可耻。内心怀有怨恨，表面上却装出友好的样子，这种行为，左丘明认为可耻，我也认为可耻。”

26.颜渊、季路侍[308]。子曰：“盍[309]各言尔志。”子路曰：“原车马，衣轻裘，与朋友共，敝之而无憾。”颜渊曰：“愿无伐[310]善，无施劳[311]。”子路曰：“愿闻子之志。”子曰：“老者安之，朋友信之，少者怀之[312]。”

颜渊、子路两人侍立在孔子身边。孔子说：“何不各人说说自己的志向？”子路说：“愿意把我的车马、衣服、皮袍与朋友共同使用，即使用坏了也不抱怨。”颜渊说：“我愿意不夸耀自己的长处，不表白自己的功劳。”子路向孔子说：“希望听听您的志向。”孔子说：“我的志向是让年长者生活安逸，让朋友们信任我，让年轻的子弟们得到关怀。”

27.子曰：“已矣乎！吾未见能见其过而内自讼者也。”

孔子说：“算了吧，我还从来没见过能够看到自己的错误便能从内心责备自己的人。”

28.子曰：“十室之邑，必有忠信如丘者焉，不如丘之好学也。”

孔子说：“就是在只有十户人家的小村子，也一定会有像我这样讲忠信的人，只是不如我那样好学罢了。”

卷六

1.子曰：“雍也可使南面。”

孔子说：“冉雍这个人，可以让他去做（某一方面的）长官。”

2.仲弓问子桑伯子[313]，子曰：“可也，简[314]。”仲弓曰：“居敬[315]而行简[316]，以临[317]其民，不亦可乎？居简而行简，无乃[318]大[319]简乎？”子曰：“雍之言然。”

仲弓向孔子询问桑伯子这个人。孔子说：“这个人还可以，可以用‘简单、豁达’来评价。”仲弓又问：“如果依礼严格要求自己，做事简明扼要，用这种方式来为百姓处理事务，不也可以吗？而如果用只求简单、少找麻烦的态度简单处理政务，不是太不负责任了吗？”孔子听了说：“冉雍，你说的很对啊。”

3.哀公问：“弟子孰为好学？”孔子对曰：“有颜回者好学，不迁怒[320]不贰过[321]，不幸短命死矣[322]。今也则亡[323]，未闻好学者也。”

鲁哀公问孔子：“你的学生里面哪一个最好学呀？”孔子回答说：“有一个叫颜回的学生很好学，他从不迁怒于别人，也从不犯同样的过错。但很不幸很早就死了。现在学生里已经没有这样的人了，没有听说谁好学。”

4.子华[324]使于齐，冉子[325]为其母请粟[326]。子曰：“与之釜[327]。”请益。曰：“与之庾[328]。”冉子与之粟五秉[329]。子曰：“赤之适齐也，乘肥马，衣轻裘。吾闻之也：君子周[330]急不继富。”

公西赤出使齐国，冉有替他的母亲向孔子请求补助一些谷米。孔子说：“给她一釜。”冉有请求再增加一些。孔子说：“再给她一庾。”冉有却给她五秉。孔子说：“公西赤去齐国，乘着骏马拉的车子，穿着暖和轻便的皮袍。我听说过，君子只是雪中送炭周济急需，而不是锦上添花为富人增富。”

5.原思[331]为之宰[332]，与之粟九百[333]，辞。子曰：“毋，以与尔邻里乡党[334]乎！”

原宪做孔子家的总管，孔子给他俸米九百，原宪推辞不要。孔子说：“你不要推辞。（如果有多的）给你的邻里（中需要它们的人）吧。”

6.子谓仲弓，曰：“犁牛[335]之子驿且角[336]。虽欲勿用[337]，山川[338]其舍诸[339]？”

孔子评价仲弓说：“耕牛产下了长着红色的毛、端正的角的牛犊，人们虽然不想用它做祭品，但山川之神难道会舍弃它吗？”

7.子曰：“回也，其心三月[340]不违仁，其余则日月[341]至焉而已矣。”

孔子说：“颜回这个人，他的心可以长久不离仁德，其余的学生则只能在短时间内做到或者想到仁罢了。”

8.季康子[342]问：“仲由可使从政也与？”子曰：“由也果[343]，于从政乎何有？”曰：“赐也可使从政也与？”曰：“赐也达[344]，于从政乎何有？”曰：“求也可使从政也与？”曰：“求也艺[345]，于从政乎何有？”

季康子问孔子：“仲由这个人，可以让他管理国家政事吗？”孔子说：“仲由做事果断，让他管理国家政事有什么困难呢？”季康子又问：“端木赐这个人，可以让他管理国家政事吗？”孔子说：“端木赐通达事理，他管理政事又能有什么困难呢？”季康子又问道：“冉求这个人，可以让他管理国家政事吗？”孔子说：“冉求多才多艺，他管理国家政事有什么困难呢？”

9.季氏使闵子骞[346]为费[347]宰，闵子骞曰：“善为我辞焉！如有复我[348]者，则吾必在汶上[349]矣。”

季氏派人请闵子骞做费邑的长官，闵子骞（对来请他的人）说：“请你替我好好地推辞掉吧！如果再来召我，那我一定会逃跑到汶水那边（的齐国）去的。”

10.伯牛[350]有疾，子问之，自牖[351]执其手，曰：“亡之[352]，命矣夫[353]，斯人也而有斯疾也！斯人也而有斯疾也！”

冉耕生病了，孔子去探望他。孔子从窗户外面握着他的手说：“没办法呀，这大概是命里注定的吧！这样的人竟会得这样的病啊，这样的人竟会得这样的病啊！”

11.子曰：“贤哉回也，一箪[354]食，一瓢饮，在陋巷[355]，人不堪其忧，回也不改其乐[356]。贤哉回也。”

孔子说：“颜回的品德多么高尚啊！一竹笸篮饭，一瓢水，住在简陋的地方，别人都忍受不了这种穷苦的生活，颜回却没有改变他好学的天性。颜回的品德多么高尚啊！”

12.冉求曰：“非不说[357]子之道，力不足也。”子曰：“力不足者，中道而废。今女画[358]。”

冉求说：“我不是不喜欢老师的学说，而是我的能力不够呀。”孔子说：“能力不够的话应该是走到半路才停下来，而现在是你自己给自己划定界限不往前走呀。”

13.子谓子夏曰：“女为君子儒，无为小人儒。”

孔子对子夏说：“你要做君子式的儒者，不要做小人般的儒者。”

14.子游为武城[359]宰。子曰：“女得人焉尔[360]乎？”曰：“有澹台灭明[361]者，行不由径[362]，非公事，未尝至于偃[363]之室也。”

子游做了武城的长官。孔子问他：“你在那里找到人才了吗？”子游回答说：“有一个叫澹台灭明的人，从来不走邪路，不是公事，绝不到我居处来。”

15.子曰：“孟之反[364]不伐[365]，奔[366]而殿[367]，将入门，策其马，曰：‘非敢后也，马不进也。’”

孔子说：“孟之反这个人从来不自夸。（当在抵御齐国的战役中右翼的）军队溃退时，他走在最后，掩护全军；快要进城门的时候，他便鞭打着自己的马说：‘不是我勇于殿后，而是马跑得不快的缘故。’”

16.子曰：“不有祝鮀[368]之佞，而[369]有宋朝[370]之美，难乎免于今之世矣。”

孔子说：“没有祝鮀那样的口才，也没有宋朝那样的美貌，那在今天的社会上处世立足就比较困难了。”

17.子曰：“谁能出不由户，何莫由斯道也？”

孔子说：“有谁能不经过屋门而走出去呢，为什么没有人走（我所指出的）这条道路呢？”

18.子曰：“质胜文则野，文胜质则史[371]。文质彬彬[372]，然后君子。”

孔子说：“质朴多于文采，就会流于粗俗；文采多于质朴，就流于虚伪浮夸。只有质朴和文采配合恰当，才能成为君子。”

19.子曰：“人之生也直，罔[373]之生也幸而免。”

孔子说：“一个人生存是靠正直，至于不正直的人也能生存，那是他侥幸地避免了灾祸。”

20.子曰：“知之者[374]不如好之者，好之者不如乐之者。”

孔子说：“（对任何学问和事业，）懂得它的人，不如爱好它的人；爱好它的人，又不如以它为乐的人。”

21.子曰：“中人以上，可以语上也；中人以下，不可以语上也。”

孔子说：“具有中等以上才智的人，可以给他讲授高深的学问；只有中等水平以下才智的人，就不能告诉他太高深的知识。”

22.樊迟[375]问知。子曰：“务民之义，敬鬼神而远之，可谓知矣。”问仁。曰：“仁者先难而后获[376]，可谓仁矣。”

樊迟问孔子怎样才算是智，孔子说：“专心教导百姓遵从义理道德，对鬼神心存敬畏但又要远离它，这样就算是智了。”

樊迟又问什么是仁，孔子说：“有仁德的人先付出力量，然后再求收获，这可以说是仁了。”

23.子曰：“知者乐水，仁者乐山[377]；知者动，仁者静；知者乐，仁者寿。”

孔子说：“聪明的人爱水（因为他像水一样灵动），仁德的人爱山（因为他像山一样稳重）。聪明人活泼，仁德人沉静。聪明人快乐，仁德人长寿。”

24.子曰：“齐一变，至于鲁；鲁一变，至于道。”

孔子说：“齐国（的政治和教育）稍微改变一下，便可以达到鲁国的程度了；鲁国（的政治和教育）再稍有变革，便能合乎大道了。”

25.子曰：“觚[378]不觚，觚哉！觚哉！”

孔子说：“觚不像觚了，这也算是觚吗，这也算是觚吗？”

26.宰我问曰：“仁者虽告之曰井有仁[379]焉，其从之也？”子曰：“何为其然也？君子可逝[380]也，不可陷[381]也；可欺也，不可罔也。”

宰我问孔子：“有仁德的人，就是告诉他井里掉下去一位仁人了，他会跟着下去吗？”孔子说：“为什么要这样做呢？可以叫君子远远走开不再回来，却不可以陷害他；可以欺骗他，却不可以愚弄他。”

27.子曰：“君子博学于文[382]，约之以礼，亦可以弗畔[383]矣夫。”

孔子说：“君子广泛地学习古代的文化典籍，再用礼仪约束自己，就可以不离经叛道了。”

28.子见南子[384]，子路不说[385]。夫子矢[386]之曰：“予所否[387]者，天厌之！天厌之！”

孔子去和南子见面，子路很不高兴。孔子发誓道：“如果我做什么不正当的事，让上天谴责我吧！让上天谴责我吧！”

29.子曰：“中庸[388]之为德也，其至矣乎！民鲜久矣。”

孔子说：“中庸作为一种道德，应该是最高的了吧！人们缺少这种道德已经很久了。”

30.子贡[389]曰：“如有博施于民而能济众，何如？可谓仁乎？”子曰：“何事于仁？必也圣乎！尧、舜[390]其犹病诸！夫仁者，己欲立而立人，己欲达而达人[391]。能近取譬[392]，可谓仁之方也已。”

子贡说：“假若有一个人，他能广泛地给人民好处，又能帮助大家生活得很好，怎么样，可以算是仁人了吗？”孔子说：“这怎么会只是仁者，一定是圣德了！就连尧、舜都不一定能做到这样呢！仁是什么呢？就是自己要站得住，同时也帮助别人站得住；自己要事事行得通，同时也帮助别人事事行得通。凡事能就近以自己作比，而推及别人，可以说就是实行仁的方法了。”

卷七

1.子曰：“述而不作[393]，信而好古，窃比于我老彭[394]。”

孔子说：“只传述而不创作，相信并且喜好古代的东西，我私下里把自己比作老彭。”

2.子曰：“默而识[395]之，学而不厌，诲人不倦，何有于我哉[396]？”

孔子说：“把所学到的知识默默地记在心里，努力学习而不厌烦，教导别人而不疲倦，这对我有什么困难呢？”

3.子曰：“德之不修，学之不讲，闻义不能徙[397]，不善不能改，是吾忧也。”

孔子说：“品德不培养，学问不讲习，听到义不能去做，有了缺点不能改正，这些都是我所忧虑的事情。”

4.子之燕居[398]，申申[399]如也；夭夭[400]如也。

孔子闲居在家里的时候，衣冠整洁，仪态温和，悠闲自在。

5.子曰：“甚矣吾衰也！久矣吾不复梦见周公[401]。”

孔子说：“我衰老得多厉害呀！我已经很长时间没再梦见周公了！”

6.子曰：“志于道，据于德，依于仁，游于艺[402]。”

孔子说：“以道为志向，以德为根据，以仁为凭借，游憩于礼、乐、射、御、书、数六艺之中。”

7.子曰：“自行束脩[403]以上，吾未尝无诲焉。”

孔子说：“只要自愿拿学礼来见我的人，我从来没有不教导的。”

8.子曰：“不愤[404]不启，不悱[405]不发。举一隅不以三隅反，则不复也。”

孔子说：“教导学生，不到他想求明白而不得的时候，不去开导他；不到他想说却说不出来的时候，不去启发他。教给他事物的一个方面，他却不能由此而推知其他几个方面，那就不用再教他了。”

9.子食于有丧者之侧，未尝饱也。

孔子在服丧的人旁边吃饭，从来没有吃饱过。

10.子于是日哭，则不歌。

孔子如在一天曾哭泣，就不再唱歌了。

11.子谓颜渊曰：“用之则行，舍之则藏[406]，惟我与尔有是夫[407]！”子路曰：“子行三军[408]，则谁与[409]？”子曰：“暴虎[410]冯河[411]，死而无悔者，吾不与也。必也临事而惧[412]，好谋而成者也。”

孔子对颜渊说：“如果任用我，我就去干；不用我，我就隐藏起来，只有我和你才能做到这样吧！”

子路问孔子：“老师您如果统帅三军，那么将与谁在一起共事呢？”孔子说：“赤手空拳和老虎搏斗，徒步涉水过河，死了都不会后悔的人，我是不会和他一起共事的。我要找的，一定是遇事小心谨慎，善于谋划，最终能完成任务的人。”

12.子曰：“富[413]而可求[414]也，虽执鞭之士[415]，吾亦为之。如不可求，从吾所好。”

孔子说：“如果富贵合乎于道就可以去追求，即使是做地位低下的下等差事，我也愿意。如果得到富贵的方法不合于道，那就还是按我的爱好去干事吧。”

13.子之所慎：齐[416]、战、疾。

孔子小心慎重对待的事有三件：斋戒、战争、疾病。

14.子在齐闻《韶》[417]，三月不知肉味，曰：“不图为乐之至于斯也。”

孔子在齐国听到《韶》乐后，有很长时间尝不出肉的滋味，他说：“想不到《韶》乐的美达到了这样迷人的程度。”

15.冉有曰：“夫子为[418]卫君[419]乎？”子贡曰：“诺[420]，吾将问之。”入，曰：“伯夷、叔齐何人也？”曰：“古之贤人也。”曰：“怨乎？”曰：“求仁而得仁，又何怨？”出，曰：“夫子不为也。”

冉有（问子贡）说：“老师会帮助卫国的国君吗？”子贡说：“嗯，我去问问他。”

于是子贡进去拜见老师，问道：“伯夷、叔齐是什么样的人呢？”孔子说：“古代的贤人。”子贡问：“他们（互相推让，都不肯做孤竹国的国君，结果都跑到国外，）有怨恨吗？”孔子说：“他们求仁而得到了仁，为什么有怨恨呢？”子贡出来对冉有说：“老师不会帮助卫君。”

16.子曰：“饭疏食[421]，饮水，曲肱[422]而枕之，乐亦在其中矣。不义而富且贵，于我如浮云。”

孔子说：“吃粗粮，喝白水，弯起胳膊当枕头，乐趣也就在这里面了。用不正当的手段得来的富与贵，对我来说就像空中一吹即散的云彩一样。”

17.子曰：“加[423]我数年，五十以学易[424]，可以无大过矣。”

孔子说：“假如再多给我几年时间，到五十岁时候去学习《易经》，就可以没有什么大过错了。”

18.子所雅言[425]，《诗》、《书》、执礼，皆雅言也。

孔子有用普通话的时候，如他读《诗》、《书》、赞礼，都用普通话。

19.叶公[426]问孔子于子路[427]，子路不对。子曰：“女奚不曰，其为人也，发愤忘食，乐以忘忧，不知老之将至云尔[428]。”

叶公问子路孔子是什么样的人，子路没回答。后来孔子对子路说：“你为什么不这样说：他的为人，用功便忘记吃饭，快乐便忘记忧愁，不晓得衰老会到来，如此而已。”

20.子曰：“我非生而知之者，好古，敏以求之[429]者也。”

孔子说：“我不是生来就有知识的人，只是爱好古代文化，勤奋敏捷去求索知识的人。”

21.子不语怪、力、乱、神。

孔子不谈论关于怪异、强力、叛乱和鬼神的事。

22.子曰：“三人行，必有我师焉。择其善者而从之，其不善者而改之。”

孔子说：“几个人在一起做事，其中一定有可以为我所取的人：我选择他善的品德向他学习，看到他不善的地方就作为借鉴，改掉自己的缺点。”

23.子曰：“天生德于予，桓魋[430]其如予何？”

孔子说：“上天把高尚的品德赋予了我，桓魋又能把我怎么样呢？”

24.子曰：“二三子[431]以我为隐乎？吾无隐乎尔。吾无行而不与二三子者，是丘也。”

孔子说：“学生们，你们以为我（在教导你们方面）对你们有什么隐瞒的吗？我丝毫没有隐瞒。我没有什么知识是不教授给你们的。我孔丘就是这样的人。”

25.子以四教：文[432]、行[433]、忠[434]、信[435]。

孔子教授学生四项内容：历代文献，社会生活的实践，对待别人的忠诚，与人交际的信实。

26.子曰：“圣人吾不得而见之矣！得见君子者，斯[436]可矣。”子曰：“善人吾不得而见之矣！得见有恒[437]者，斯可矣。亡而为有，虚而为盈，约[438]而为泰[439]，难乎有恒矣。”

孔子说：“圣人我是不可能看到了，能看到君子也就可以了。”孔子又说：“善人我不可能看到了，能见到有一定操守的人也就可以了。本来没有，却装作有；本来空虚，却装作充足；本来穷困，却装作富足，这样的人便难以保持一定操守了。”

27.子钓而不纲[440]，弋[441]不射宿[442]。

孔子只用有一个渔钩的钓竿钓鱼，而不用有许多渔钩的大绳钓鱼；只射飞鸟，而不射归巢歇宿的鸟。

28.子曰：“盖有不知而作之者，我无是也。多闻，择其善者而从之，多见而识之，知之次也。”

孔子说：“大概有一种人，他什么都不懂却在那里凭空创造，但我没有这样做过。广泛听取见解，选择其中好的来学习；多观察事物，然后记在心里，这是次一等的智慧。”

29.互乡[443]难与言，童子见，门人惑。子曰：“与[444]其进[445]也，不与其退也，唯何甚？人洁己[446]以进，与其洁也，不保其往[447]也。”

（孔子认为）很难与互乡那个地方的人交流，但互乡的一个年轻人却受到了孔子的接见，学生们为此都感到迷惑不解。孔子说：“我们肯定他的进步，不肯定他的倒退。何必做得太过分呢？别人改正了错误以求进步，我们要肯定他改正了错误，不要总抓住他的过去不罢休。”

30.子曰：“仁远乎哉？我欲仁，斯仁至矣。”

孔子说：“仁德离我们很远吗？只要我们想达到仁德，仁德就会来。”

31.陈司败[448]问：“昭公[449]知礼乎？“孔子曰：“知礼。”孔子退，揖[450]巫马期[451]而进之曰：“吾闻君子不党[452]，君子亦党乎？君取[453]于吴，为同姓[454]谓之吴孟子[455]。君而知礼，孰不知年礼？”巫马期以告。子曰：“丘也幸，苟有过，人必知之。”

陈司败向孔子询问鲁昭公懂不懂礼，孔子说：“懂礼。”孔子出去以后，陈司败便向巫马期行礼，请他走近自己，对他说：“我听说君子无所偏袒，难道孔子也包庇别人吗？鲁君从吴国娶了位夫人，吴和鲁是同姓国家，（因不便叫她作吴姬，）于是称她为吴孟子。如果鲁君算是知礼，还有谁不知礼呢？”巫马期将这些话转告给孔子。孔子说：“我真幸运，一旦有错，别人一定会给我指出来。”

32.子与人歌而善，必使反之，而后和之。

孔子与别人一起唱歌，如果（那个人）唱得好，（孔子）一定请他再唱一遍，然后一起唱和他。

33.子曰：“文，莫[456]吾犹人也。躬行君子，则吾未之有得。”

孔子说：“就书本上的学问来说，大概我和别人知道的差不多。但要做一个身体力行的君子，我还没有做到。”

34.子曰：若圣与仁，则吾岂敢？抑[457]为之[458]不厌，诲人不倦，则可谓云尔[459]已矣。”公西华曰：“正唯弟子不能学也。”

孔子说：“讲到圣和仁，我怎么敢当？我不过是向圣与仁的方向不断努力去做而不感厌烦，教导别人也从不感觉疲倦，只不过如此罢了。”公西华说：“这正是我们学不会的呀。”

35.子疾病[460]，子路请祷[461]。子曰：“有诸[462]？”子路对曰：“有之。《诔》[463]曰：‘祷尔于上下神祇[464]。’”子曰：“丘之祷久矣。”

孔子病情严重，子路向鬼神祈祷。孔子问：“有这回事吗？”子路回答道：“有的。《诔》文上说过：‘替你向天地神灵祈祷。’”孔子说：“我早就祈祷过了。”

36.子曰：“奢则不孙[465]，俭则固[466]。与其不孙也，宁固。”

孔子说：“奢侈了就会越礼，节俭了就会寒酸。与其越礼，宁可寒酸。”

37.子曰：“君子坦荡荡[467]，小人长戚戚[468]。”

孔子说：“君子心胸宽广，小人总是忧愁。”

38.子温而厉，威而不猛，恭而安。

孔子温和而又严肃，有威仪而不凶狠，庄重而又安详。

卷八

1.子曰：“泰伯[469]，其可谓至德也已矣。三[470]以天下让，民无得而称焉[471]。”

孔子说：“泰伯可以说是品德最高尚的人了，多次把王位让给季历，老百姓都找不到恰当的词语来称赞他。”

2.子曰：“恭而无礼则劳，慎而无礼则葸[472]，勇而无礼则乱，直而无礼则绞[473]。君子笃于亲，则民兴于仁；故旧不遗，则民不偷[474]。”

孔子说：“只是注重态度的恭敬而不以礼来指导，就未免劳倦；只知言行的谨慎却不知礼，就流于畏缩懦弱；有敢作敢为的胆量，却不用礼来制约，就会冲动招祸；太心直口快而不知礼，就会尖刻刺人。在上位的人如果厚待自己的亲属，老百姓当中就会兴起仁德的风气；在上位的人如果不遗弃老同事、老朋友，那老百姓就不会对人冷淡无情了。”

3.曾子有疾，召门弟子曰：“启[475]予足！启予手！《诗》云[476]：‘战战兢兢，如临深渊，如履薄冰。’而今而后，吾知免[477]夫，小子[478]！”

曾参病得很重，他把学生召集到身边来说道：“看看我的脚！看看我的手！《诗经》上说：‘小心谨慎呀！好像站在深渊旁边，好像踩在薄冰上面。’从今以后，我知道自己的身体已经不会再受到损伤了！学生们！”

4.曾子有疾，孟敬子[479]问[480]之。曾子言曰：“鸟之将死，其鸣也哀；人之将死，其言也善。君子所贵乎道者三：动容貌[481]，斯远暴慢[482]矣；正颜色[483]，斯近信矣；出辞气[484]，斯远鄙倍[485]矣。笾豆之事[486]则有司[487]存。”

曾子有病，孟敬子去探望他。曾子对他说：“鸟快死了，它的叫声是悲哀的；人快死了，他说的话是善意的。君子待人接物时有三方面事项应该注重：使自己的仪态威严，这样可以避免粗暴、放肆；使自己的脸色庄重，这样就接近于诚信；使自己说话的言辞和语气谨慎小心，这样就可以避免鄙陋粗俗和错误。至于礼仪的细节，自有主管这些事务的官吏来负责。”

5.曾子曰：“以能问于不能，以多问于寡，有若无，实若虚；犯而不校[488]——昔者吾友[489]尝从事于斯矣。”

曾子说：“自己有才能却向没有才能的人请教，自己知识渊博却向知识少的人请教，有学问却像没学问一样，知识很充实却好像很空虚；纵被人欺侮，也从不计较——从前我的朋友就是这样做的。”

6.曾子说：“可以托六尺之孤[490]，可以寄百里之命[491]，临大节而不可夺也。君子人与？君子人也。”

曾子说：“可以托付年幼的君主，可以托付国家的政权，面临生死存亡的紧急关头而不动摇屈服。这样的人是君子吗？是君子啊！”

7.曾子曰：“士不可以不弘毅[492]，任重而道远。仁以为己任，不亦重乎？死而后已，不亦远乎？”

曾子说：“读书人不可以不刚强而有毅力，因为他责任重大，路程遥远。以实现仁德于天下为自己的责任，难道还不重大吗？奋斗终身，死而后已，难道路程还不遥远吗？”

8.子曰：“兴[493]于《诗》，立于礼，成于乐。”

孔子说：“（人的修养）开始于学习《诗》，自立于学习《礼》，完成于学习《乐》。”

9.子曰：“民可使由之，不可使知之。”

孔子说：“对于老百姓，可以让他们按照我们所引导的道路去走，但不可以让他们知道那是为什么。”

10.子曰：“好勇疾[494]贫，乱也。人而不仁[495]，疾之已甚[496]，乱也。”

孔子说：“喜好勇敢却又厌恶贫困，是一种祸患。太憎恨不仁德的人或事，也会出乱子。”

11.子曰：“如有周公之才之美，使骄且吝，其余不足观也已。”

孔子说：“即使一个人有周公那样美好的才能，如果骄傲自大而且吝啬小气，那其他方面也就不值得一看了。”

12.子曰：“三年学，不至于谷[497]，不易得也。”

孔子说：“读书三年并不存做官的念头，这是难得的。”

13.子曰：“笃信好学，守死善道，危邦不入，乱邦不居。天下有道则见[498]，无道则隐。邦有道，贫且贱焉，耻也；邦无道，富且贵焉，耻也。”

孔子说：“坚定信念并努力学习，誓死捍卫并完善治国与为人的大道；不进入政局不稳的国家，不居住在动乱的国家。天下政治清明就出来工作；天下混乱就隐居。国家有道、政治清明而自己贫贱，是耻辱；国家无道、政治黑暗而自己富贵，也是耻辱。”

14.子曰：“不在其位，不谋其政。”

孔子说：“不在那个职位上，就不要去考虑属于那个职位才应该做的事。”

15.子曰：“师挚之始[499]，《关雎》之乱[500]，洋洋乎盈耳哉！”

孔子说：“从太师挚演奏的音乐的序曲开始，到最后演奏《关雎》的结尾，丰富而优美的音乐就一直在我耳边回荡。”

16.子曰：“狂[501]而不直，侗[502]而不愿[503]，悾悾[504]而不信，吾不知之矣。”

孔子说：“狂妄而不正直，无知而不谨慎，表面上诚恳而不信守承诺，我不知道有这样的人。”

17.子曰：“学如不及，犹恐失之。”

孔子说：“做学问就好像（在追逐什么东西似的，）生怕赶不上；（赶上了，）还生怕丢掉了。”

18.子曰：“巍巍[505]乎，舜禹[506]之有天下也而不与[507]焉！”

孔子说：“舜和禹多崇高伟大呀！他们虽贵为天子，富有四海，却完全不是为了自己。”

19.子曰：“大哉尧[508]之为君也！巍巍乎，唯天为大，唯尧则[509]之。荡荡[510]乎，民无能名[511]焉。巍巍乎其有成功也，焕乎其有文章！”

孔子说：“尧这样的君主真伟大，真崇高啊！只有天最高最大，只有尧才能效法天的高大。他的恩德多么广博啊，百姓们不知道该用什么语言来称赞他。他的功绩多么崇高，他制定的礼仪制度多么光辉灿烂啊！”

20.舜有臣五人[512]而天下治。武王曰：“予有乱臣十人[513]。”孔子曰：“才难，不其然乎？唐虞之际[514]，于斯[515]为盛，有妇人焉[516]，九人而已。三分天下有其二[517]，以服事殷。周之德，其可谓至德也已矣。”

舜有五位贤臣，天下就被治理好了。周武王也曾说过：“我有十个帮助我治理国家的臣子。”孔子因此说：“人才难得，难道不是这样吗？唐尧和虞舜时代到周武王这个时期，人才最为兴盛。但武王的十个大臣中有一人是妇女，实际上只是九个人罢了。周文王已经统治了商朝疆土的三分之二，仍然殷勤侍奉商纣，周朝的道德，可以说是最高的了。”

21.子曰：“禹，吾无间[518]然矣。菲[519]饮食而致[520]孝乎鬼神，恶衣服而致美乎黻冕[521]；卑[522]宫室而尽力乎沟洫[523]。禹，吾无间然矣。”

孔子说：“对于禹，我没有什么可以挑剔的。他自己吃的饮食很简单却把祭品办得极丰盛；他平时穿的衣服很简朴，而祭祀时尽量穿得华美；他自己住的宫室很低矮，而把力量完全用于修治水利事宜。对于禹，我确实没有什么可以挑剔的。”

卷九

1.子罕[524]言利与命与仁。

孔子很少主动谈到功利、命运和仁德。

2.达巷党人[525]曰：“大哉孔子！博学而无所成名[526]。”子闻之，谓门弟子曰：“吾何执？执御乎？执射乎？吾执御矣。”

达巷有人说：“孔子真伟大啊！他学问广博，可惜没有足以树立名声的专长。”孔子听说后对他的学生说：“我要专长于哪个方面呢，驾车呢，还是射箭呢？我还是驾车吧。”

3.子曰：“麻冕[527]，礼也；今也纯[528]，俭[529]，吾从众。拜下[530]，礼也；今拜乎上，泰[531]也。虽违众，吾从下。”

孔子说：“礼帽用麻料制作，这是合于传统礼制规定的；今天大家都用黑色丝绸制作，这样比过去节省了，我赞成大家的做法。臣见国君首先要在堂下跪拜，然后升堂时又磕头，这是符合传统礼制的。今天大家都免去了堂下跪拜的礼节，只在升堂后磕头，这是倨傲的表现。虽然违反大家意愿，我仍然主张要先在堂下跪拜。”

4.子绝四：毋意[532]，毋必[533]，毋固[534]，毋我[535]。

孔子杜绝了四种毛病：“不主观猜疑，不绝对肯定，不拘泥固执，不唯我独是。”

5.子畏于匡[536]，曰：“文王[537]既没，文不在兹[538]乎？天之将丧斯文也，后死者[539]不得与[540]于斯文也；天之未丧斯文也，匡人其如予何[541]？”

孔子被匡地的人们围困时，他说：“周文王死了以后，周代的礼乐文化不都在我这里吗？上天如果想要消灭这种文化，那我也不会掌握它们了；上天如果不消灭这种文化，那么匡人又能把我怎么样呢？”

6.太宰[542]问于子贡曰：“夫子圣者与？何其多能也？”子贡曰：“固天纵[543]之将圣，又多能也。”子闻之，曰：“太宰知我乎？吾少也贱，故多能鄙事[544]。君子多乎哉？不多也。”

太宰问子贡说：“孔先生是位圣人吧，为什么这样多才多艺呢？”子贡说：“这一定是上天让他成为圣人，而且使他多才多艺。”孔子听到后说：“太宰怎么会了解我呢？我小时候穷苦，所以会许多卑贱的技艺。君子会有这么多的技艺吗？不会的。”

7.牢[545]曰：“子云：‘吾不试[546]，故艺。’”

牢说：“孔子说过：‘我（年轻时）没有去做官，所以学会了许多技艺。’”

8.子曰：“吾有知乎哉？无知也。有鄙夫[547]问于我，空空如也[548]。我叩[549]其两端[550]而竭[551]焉。”

孔子说：“我有知识吗？没有啊。有一个乡下人问我，我对他问的问题本来一点也不知道。我只是从问题的两端去问，这样就把这个问题全部搞清楚了。”

9.子曰：“凤鸟[552]不至，河不出图[553]，吾已矣夫！”

孔子说：“凤凰不飞来了，黄河中也不出现八卦图了，我这一生恐怕是完了吧！”

10.子见齐衰[554]者，冕衣裳者[555]与瞽[556]者，见之，虽少，必作[557]；过之，必趋[558]。

孔子遇见居丧的人、当官的人和盲人时，即使他们比自己年轻，也一定要站起来；从他们面前经过时，一定要快步走过以示恭敬。

11.颜渊喟[559]然叹曰：“仰之弥[560]高，钻[561]之弥坚，瞻[562]之在前，忽焉在后。夫子循循然善诱人[563]，博我以文，约我以礼，欲罢不能。即竭吾才，如有所立卓尔[564]。虽欲从之，末由[565]也已。”

颜渊感叹地说：“对于老师的学问与道德，越抬头看，越觉得高；越用力钻研，越觉得深。看着它好像在前面，忽然又像在后面。虽然他的学问这样高深和不容易捉摸，可老师善于有步骤地诱导我们，用各种典籍来丰富我的知识，又用各种礼节来约束我的言行，使我想停止学习都不可能。我尽我所有的才能、力量跟他学习，感觉很成功，好像自己已经能独立站起来了，但要想再向前迈进一步，又不知怎样去做了。”

12.子疾病，子路使门人为臣[566]。病间[567]，曰：“久矣哉，由之行诈也。无臣而为有臣。吾谁欺？欺天乎？且予与其死于臣之手也，无宁[568]死于二三子之手乎？且予纵不得大葬[569]，予死于道路乎？”

孔子病得很厉害，子路便命孔子的学生做家臣，负责料理后事。后来，孔子的病好一些了，就说道：“仲由干这种弄虚作假的勾当居然这么久呀！我本不该有治丧的组织，却一定要派人组织治丧。我骗谁呢，欺骗上天吗？与其在家臣的侍候下死去，我宁可在你们这些学生的侍候下死去，这样不是更好吗？而且即使不能隆重地办理丧葬，难道我就会被丢在路边没人埋吗？”

13.子贡曰：“有美玉于斯，韫椟[570]而藏诸？求善贾[571]而沽诸？”子曰：“沽[572]之哉，沽之哉！我待贾者也。”

子贡道：“这里有一块很好的玉，是把它放在匣子里藏起来呢，还是找一个识货的商人卖掉呢？”孔子道：“卖掉吧，卖掉吧！我正在等着识货的人呢。”

14.子欲居九夷[573]。或曰：“陋[574]，如之何？”子曰：“君子居之，何陋之有？”

孔子想搬到九夷去住。有人说：“那地方非常落后闭塞、不开化，怎么能住呢？”孔子说：“有君子去住，就不闭塞落后了。”

15.子曰：“吾自卫反鲁[575]，然后乐正[576]，《雅》、《颂》[577]各得其所。”

孔子说：“我从卫国回到鲁国后，才把乐曲各篇整理出来，使《雅》《颂》都有合适的安置。”

16.子曰：“出则事公卿，入则事父兄，丧事不敢不勉，不为酒困，何有于我哉。”

孔子说：“在外侍奉长官，在家孝敬父兄，有丧事不敢不尽力去办，不被酒食困扰，这些事对我来说有什么困难呢？”

17.子在川上曰：“逝者如斯夫，不舍昼夜。”

孔子在河边，感叹道：“消逝的时光就像这河水一样啊，日夜不停地向前流去。”

18.子曰：“吾未见好德如好色者也。”

孔子说：“我没有看见过追求道德胜过追求美貌的人。”

19.子曰：“譬如为山，未成一篑[578]，止，吾止也；譬如平地，虽覆一篑，进，吾往也。”

孔子说：“（做学问）好比堆土成山，只要再加一筐土便完成了，但如果这时停下来，那是自己要停止的。又好比在平地上堆山，虽然只是刚刚倒下一筐土，如果决心努力前进，那还是自己坚持前进的呀！”

20.子曰：“语之而不惰者，其回也与！”

孔子说：“听我教导而能始终不懈怠的，大概只有颜回一个人吧！”

21.子谓颜渊曰：“惜乎！吾见其进也，未见其止也。”

孔子谈到颜渊时说道：“可惜（他死了）呀！（在做学问方面）我从来都只看见他不断地进步，没见他停止过。”

22.子曰：“苗而不秀[579]者有矣夫；秀而不实者有矣夫！”

孔子说：“庄稼出了苗而不吐穗扬花的情况是有的，吐穗扬花而不结果的情况也是有的呀！”

23.子曰：“后生可畏，焉知来者之不如今也？四十、五十而无闻焉，斯亦不足畏也已。”

孔子说：“年轻人是值得敬畏的，怎么就知道后一代不如前一代呢？如果一个人到了四五十岁时还默默无闻，那他就没有什么值得敬畏的了。”

24.子曰：“法语之言[580]，能无从乎？改之为贵。巽与之言[581]，能无说[582]乎？绎[583]之为贵。说而不绎，从而不改，吾末[584]如之何也已矣。”

孔子说：“用严肃而符合礼法的语言进行规劝，谁能不接受呢？但（只有按它来）改正自己的错误才是可贵的。恭顺赞许的话，谁听了能不高兴呢？但只有认真分析鉴别它（的真伪是非）才是可贵的。只是高兴而不去分析，只是表示听从而不改正错误，这样的人我拿他也没有办法。”

25.子曰：“主忠信，毋友不如己者，过则勿惮改。”

孔子说：“恪守忠信，与志同道合的人做朋友，有了过错要去改正，不要害怕改变。”

26.子曰：“三军[585]可夺帅也，匹夫[586]不可夺志也。”

孔子说：“一国军队，可以使它丧失主帅；但一个男子汉，却不能强迫他放弃自己的志向。”

27.子曰：“衣[587]敝缊袍[588]，与衣狐貉[589]者立而不耻者，其由也与？‘不忮不求[590]，何用不臧？’”子路终身诵之。子曰：“是道也，何足以臧？”

孔子说：“穿着破旧的丝绵袍子与穿着狐貉皮袍的人站在一起而不认为是羞耻的，大概只有仲由吧。《诗经》上说：‘不嫉妒，不贪求，为什么会不好呢？’”子路听了，便反复吟诵这句诗。孔子见了又说：“只做到这个样子，怎么能说够好了呢？”

28.子曰：“岁寒，然后知松柏之后凋也。”

孔子说：“只有到了寒冷的季节，才知道松树和柏树是最后凋零的。”

29.子曰：“知者不惑，仁者不忧，勇者不惧。”

孔子说：“聪明人不会被迷惑，有仁德的人不会忧愁，勇敢的人无所畏惧。”

30.子曰：“可与共学，未可与适道[591]；可与适道，未可与立[592]；可与立，未可与权[593]。”

孔子说：“可以一起学习的人，未必可以与他一起追求真理；可以一起追求至真道理的人，未必可以一起坚持真理而不改变；可以一起坚守真理的人，未必可以一起通权达变。”

31.“唐棣[594]之华，偏其反而[595]。岂不尔思，室是远而[596]。”子曰：“未之思也，夫何远之有？”

古代有一首诗说：“唐棣树的花朵啊，随风翩翩摇摆。怎么会是我不想念你呢？只是由于家住得太遥远了。”孔子说：“他还不是真的想念啊，如果真的想念，又怎么会有什么遥远呢？”

卷十

1.孔子于乡党，恂恂[597]如也，似不能言者。其在宗庙、朝廷，便便[598]言，唯谨尔。

孔子在本乡显得很温和恭敬，像是不会说话的样子。但他在宗庙里、朝堂上，却很善于言辞，只是说得比较谨慎而已。

2.朝，与下大夫言，侃侃[599]如也；与上大夫言，訚訚[600]如也。君在，踧踖[601]如也，与与[602]如也。

孔子上朝的时候，（如果君主还没有到来，）他同下大夫说话，是温和而快乐的样子；同上大夫说话，是正直而恭敬的样子。如果君主来了，又是恭敬而心中不安、小心谨慎、威仪适中的样子。

3.君召使摈[603]，色勃如也[604]；足躩[605]如也。揖所与立，左右手，衣前后，襜[606]如也。趋进，翼如也[607]。宾退，必复命曰：“宾不顾矣。”

国君派孔子去接待宾客，孔子的脸色立即矜持庄重，脚步也快起来，他向站在两旁的人行礼，手或向左或向右作揖，衣服前后摆动，却整齐不乱；快步走的时候，像鸟儿舒展开双翅一样。宾客辞别后一定向君主回报说：“客人已经不回头张望了。”

4.入公门，鞠躬如[608]也，如不容。立不中门，行不履阈[609]。过位，色勃如也，足躩如也，其言似不足者。摄齐[610]升堂，鞠躬如也，屏气似不息者。出，降一等[611]，逞[612]颜色，怡怡如也。没阶[613]，趋进，翼如也。复其位，踧踖如也。

孔子走进朝堂大门，是谨慎而恭敬的样子，就好像没有他的容身之地一样。站的时候绝不站在门的中间；走的时候不踩门槛。当经过国君的座位时，面色立刻庄重起来，脚步也加快起来，也没有太多的言辞。提起衣服下摆向堂上走的时候，恭敬谨慎的样子，憋住气好像不呼吸一样。退出来，刚走下一级台阶，脸色便舒展开了，怡然自得的样子。走完了台阶，快快地向前走几步，姿态像鸟儿舒展翅膀。回到自己的位置上时，是恭敬而内心不安的样子。

5.执圭[614]，鞠躬如也，如不胜。上如揖，下如授。勃如战色[615]，足蹜蹜[616]，如有循[617]。享礼[618]，有容色。私觌[619]，愉愉如也。

孔子出使其他诸侯国时，拿着圭，恭敬谨慎，像是举不起来的样子。向上举时好像在作揖，放在下面时好像是在交给别人。脸色庄重得像战栗的样子，步伐也紧凑狭促，好像沿着一条直线往前走。在举行赠送礼物的仪式时，显得和颜悦色。以私人身份和外国君臣会见时，显得轻松愉快。

6.君子不以绀饰[620]，红紫不以为亵服[621]。当暑，袗絺绤[622]，必表而出之[623]。缁衣[624]，羔裘[625]，素衣，麑[626]裘；黄衣，狐裘。亵裘长，短右袂[627]。必有寝衣[628]，长一身有半。狐貉之厚以居[629]。去丧，无所不佩。非帷裳[630]，必杀之[631]。羔裘玄冠[632]不以吊[633]。吉月[634]，必朝服而朝。

君子不用深青透红或黑中透红色的布镶边，不用近乎赤色的浅红色和紫色布来做居家的衣服。夏天穿着粗或细的葛布单衣，但一定着内衣。黑色的衣配黑色的羔羊皮袍，白色的衣配白色的鹿皮袍，黄色的衣配黄色的狐皮袍。平常在家穿的皮袍做得长一些，但右边的袖子要做得短些。睡觉一定有睡衣，而且一定要长过身体。用狐貉的厚皮毛做坐垫。服丧期满以后，什么东西都可以佩带。如果不是礼服，一定要加以剪裁。不穿着黑色的羔羊皮袍和戴着黑色的帽子去吊丧。每月初一，一定穿着朝服去朝拜君主。

7.齐[635]，必有明衣[636]，布。齐必变食[637]，居必迁坐[638]。

斋戒沐浴的时候，一定要有布做的浴衣。斋戒的时候，一定要改变平常的饮食，居处也一定要搬移到别处，（不与妻妾同房）。

8.食不厌精，脍[639]不厌细。食饐[640]而餲[641]，鱼馁[642]而肉败，不食。色恶，不食。臭恶，不食。失饪[643]，不食。不时，不食，割不正，不食。不得其酱，不食。肉虽多，不使胜食气[644]。唯酒无量，不及乱[645]。沽酒市脯[646]，不食。不撤姜食，不多。

粮食不嫌舂得精，鱼和肉不嫌切得细。粮食霉烂发臭了，鱼和肉腐烂了，都不吃。食物的颜色改变了，不吃。气味变了，不吃。烹调不当，不吃。不是吃饭的时间，不吃。不是按一定方法切割的肉，不吃。佐料放得不适当，不吃。席上的肉虽多，但吃的量不超过主食。只有酒不限量，但从不喝醉。从市上买来的肉干和酒，不吃。每餐必须有姜，但也不多吃。

9.祭于公，不宿肉[647]，祭肉[648]不出三日。出三日，不食之矣。

孔子参与国家祭祀典礼时分到的肉，不会把它留到第二天。别的祭祀用过的肉留存也都不超过三天。超过三天，就不吃了。

10.食不语，寝不言。

吃饭的时候不交谈，睡觉的时候不说话。

11.虽疏食菜羹[649]，瓜祭[650]，必齐[651]如也。

即使是糙米饭蔬菜汤，吃饭前也要取出一些来祭祖，而且表情一定恭恭敬敬，就像正式斋戒时那样严肃恭敬。

12.席[652]不正，不坐。

坐席摆放的方法与位置不合礼制，不坐。

13.乡人饮酒[653]，杖者[654]出，斯出矣。

行乡饮酒礼的仪式结束后，孔子一定要等老年人都出去了，自己才出去。

14.乡人傩[655]，朝服而立于阼阶[656]。

本地举行迎神驱鬼的宗教仪式时，孔子总是穿着朝服站在东边的台阶上。

15.问[657]人于他邦，再拜而送之[658]。

孔子托人向在其他诸侯国的朋友问候送礼时，在送行时总要向受托者行两次礼。

16.康子馈药，拜而受之。曰：“丘未达，不敢尝。”

季康子给孔子赠送药品，孔子拜谢之后接受了，却说道：“我对药性不很了解，不敢轻易尝试。”

17.厩焚。子退朝，曰：“伤人乎？”不问马。

孔子的马棚失火了。孔子从朝堂回来知道这件事后问道：“伤人了吗？”而没有问马的情况。

18.君赐食，必正席先尝之。君赐腥[659]，必熟而荐[660]之。君赐生，必畜之。侍食于君，君祭，先饭。

国君赐给熟食，孔子一定摆正座位先尝一尝。国君赐给生肉，一定煮熟了先给祖宗上供。国君赐给活物，一定要饲养起来。同国君一起吃饭，在国君举行饭前祭礼的时候，一定要先尝一尝。

19.疾，君视之，东首[661]，加朝服，拖绅[662]。

孔子病了，国君来探视，他便头朝东躺着，把上朝的礼服披在身上，系上大带子。

20.君命召，不俟驾行矣。

国君召见孔子，他不等车马驾好就先步行向前了。

21.入太庙，每事问。

孔子一进太庙，就问这问那，几乎每一件事他都问到了。

22.朋友[663]死，无所归，曰：“于我殡[664]。”

孔子的朋友死了，没有亲属来负责敛埋，孔子便说：“丧事由我来料理吧。”

23.朋友之馈，虽车马，非祭肉，不拜。

朋友的赠品，即使是车马，只要不是祭肉，孔子在接受的时候都是不行礼的。

24.寝不尸，居不客。

孔子睡觉时不像死尸一样直躺着，平日家居也不像接见客人或出门做客时一样跪着两膝在席上。

25.见齐衰[665]者，虽狎[666]，必变。见冕者与瞽者[667]，虽亵[668]，必以貌。凶服[669]者式[670]之。式负版者[671]。有盛馔[672]，必变色而作[673]。迅雷风烈必变。

孔子看见穿丧服的人，即使是关系很亲密的，也一定改变态度，表示同情。看见当官的和盲人，即使是彼此很熟悉，也一定要有礼貌。在乘车时遇见穿丧服的人，便把身体向前俯，手扶着车前的横木，表示同情。遇见背负国家图籍的人，也这样做以示敬意。做客时，如果有丰盛的菜肴，一定改变神色，站起来致谢。遇见迅雷大风的天气，一定要改变神色以示对上天的敬畏。

26.升车，必正立，执绥[674]。车中，不内顾[675]不疾言[676]不亲指[677]。

孔子上车时，一定先端正地站好，然后拉着扶手带上车。在车上不回头张望，不高声说话，不用手指指画画。

27.色斯举矣[678]，翔而后集[679]。曰：“山梁雌雉[680]，时哉时哉[681]！”子路共[682]之，三嗅而作[683]。

孔子在山谷中行走，看见几只野鸡。孔子的脸色一动，野鸡便飞向天空，盘旋一阵，然后又都停在一处。孔子道：“这些山梁上的母野鸡，得到了它们的时运呀，得到了它们的时运呀！”子路向它们拱拱手，它们又振一振翅膀飞走了。

Book Ⅰ

1．The Master said, 'Is it not a pleasure, having learned something, to try it out at due intervals? Is it not a joy to have friends come from afar? Is it not gentlemanly not to take offence when others fail to appreciate your abilities?'

2．Yu Tzu said, 'It is rare for a man whose character is such that he is good as a son and obedient as a young man to have the inclination to transgress against his superiors; it is unheard of for one who has no such inclination to be inclined to start a rebellion. The gentleman devotes his efforts to the roots, for once the roots are established, the Way will grow therefrom. Being good as a son and obedient as a young man is, perhaps, the root of a man's character.'

3．The Master said, 'It is rare, indeed, for a man with cunning words and an ingratiating face to be benevolent.'

4．Tseng Tzu said, 'Every day I examine myself on three counts. In what I have undertaken on another's behalf, have I failed to do my best? In my dealings with my friends have I failed to be trustworthy in what I say? Have I passed on to others anything that I have not tried out myself?'

5．The Master said, 'In guiding a state of a thousand chariots, approach your duties with reverence and be trustworthy in what you say; avoid excesses in expenditure and love your fellow men; employ the labour of the common people only in the right seasons.'

6．The Master said, 'A young man should be a good son at home and an obedient young man abroad, sparing of speech but trustworthy in what he says, and should love the multitude at large but cultivate the friendship of his fellow men. If he has any energy to spare from such action, let him devote it to making himself cultivated.'

7．Tzu-hsia said, 'I would grant that a man has received instruction who appreciates men of excellence where other men appreciate beautiful women, who exerts himself to the utmost in the service of his parents and offers his person to the service of his lord, and who, in his dealings with his friends, is trustworthy in what he says, even though he may say that he has never been taught.'

8．The Master said, 'A gentleman who lacks gravity does not inspire awe. A gentleman who studies is unlikely to be inflexible.

'Make[【1】] it your guiding principle to do your best for others and to be trustworthy in what you say. Do not accept as friend anyone who is not as good as you.

'When you make a mistake, do not be afraid of mending your ways.'

9．Tseng Tzu said, 'Conduct the funeral of your parents with meticulous care and let not sacrifices to your remote ancestors be forgotten, and the virtue of the common people will incline towards fullness.'

10．Tzu-ch'in asked Tzu-kung, 'When the Master arrives in a state, he invariably gets to know about its government. Does he seek this information? or is it given him?'

Tzu-kung said, 'The Master gets it through being cordial, good, respectful, frugal and deferential. The way the Master seeks it is, perhaps, different from the way other men seek it.'

11．The Master said, 'Observe what a man has in mind to do when his father is living, and then observe what he does when his father is dead. If, for three years, he makes no changes to his father's ways, he can be said to be a good son.'[【2】]

12．Yu Tzu said, 'Of the things brought about by the rites, harmony is the most valuable. Of the ways of the Former Kings, this is the most beautiful, and is followed alike in matters great and small, yet this will not always work: to aim always at harmony without regulating it by the rites simply because one knows only about harmony will not, in fact, work.'

13．Yu Tzu said, 'To be trustworthy in word is close to being moral in that it enables one's words to be repeated. To be respectful is close to being observant of the rites in that it enables one to stay clear of disgrace and insult. If, in promoting good relationship with relatives by marriage, a man manages not to lose the good will of his own kinsmen, he is worthy of being looked up to as the head of the clan.'

14．The Master said, 'The gentleman seeks neither a full belly nor a comfortable home. He is quick in action but cautious in speech. He goes to men possessed of the Way to be put right. Such a man can be described as eager to learn.'

15．Tzu-kung said, '"Poor without being obsequious, wealthy without being arrogant." What do you think of this saying?'

The Master said, 'That will do, but better still "Poor yet delighting in the Way, wealthy yet observant of the rites."'

Tzu-kung said, 'The Odes say,

　　Like bone cut, like horn polished,

　　Like jade carved, like stone ground.

Is not what you have said a case in point?'

16．The Master said, 'Ssu, only with a man like you can one discuss the Odes. Tell such a man something and he can see its relevance to what he has not been told.'

The Master said, 'It is not the failure of others to appreciate your abilities that should trouble you, but rather your failure to appreciate theirs.'

注释

【1】　The whole of what follows is found also in Ⅸ.25.

【2】　This sentence is found again in Ⅳ.20.

Book Ⅱ

1．The Master said, 'The rule of virtue can be compared to the Pole Star which commands the homage of the multitude of stars without leaving its place.'

2．The Master said, 'The Odes are three hundred in number. They can be summed up in one phrase,

　　Swerving not from the right path.'[【1】]

3．The Master said, 'Guide them by edicts, keep them in line with punishments, and the common people will stay out of trouble but will have no sense of shame. Guide them by virtue, keep them in line with the rites, and they will, besides having a sense of shame, reform themselves.'

4．The Master said, 'At fifteen I set my heart on learning; at thirty I took my stand; at forty I came to be free from doubts; at fifty I understood the Decree of Heaven; at sixty my ear was atuned;[【2】] at seventy I followed my heart's desire without overstepping the line.'

5．Meng Yi Tzu asked about being filial. The Master answered, 'Never fail to comply.'

Fan Ch'ih was driving. The Master told him about the interview, saying, 'Meng-sun asked me about being filial. I answered, "Never fail to comply."'

Fan Ch'ih asked, 'What does that mean?'

The Master said, 'When your parents are alive, comply with the rites in serving them; when they die, comply with the rites in burying them; comply with the rites in sacrificing to them.'

6．Meng Wu Po asked about being filial. The Master said, 'Give your father and mother no other cause for anxiety than illness.'

7．Tzu-yu asked about being filial. The Master said, 'Nowadays for a man to be filial means no more than that he is able to provide his parents with food. Even hounds and horses are, in some way, provided with food. If a man shows no reverence, where is the difference?'

8．Tzu-hsia asked about being filial. The Master said, 'What is difficult to manage is the expression on one's face. As for the young taking on the burden when there is work to be done or letting the old enjoy the wine and the food when these are available, that hardly deserves to be called filial.'

9．The Master said, 'I can speak to Hui all day without his disagreeing with me in any way. Thus he would seem to be stupid. However, when I take a closer look at what he does in private after he has withdrawn from my presence, I discover that it does, in fact, throw light on what I said. Hui is not stupid after all.'

10．The Master said, 'Look at the means a man employs, observe the path he takes and examine where he feels at home. In what way is a man's true character hidden from view? In what way is a man's true character hidden from view?'

11．The Master said, 'A man is worthy of being a teacher who gets to know what is new by keeping fresh in his mind what he is already familiar with.'

12．The Master said, 'The gentleman is no vessel.'[【3】]

13．Tzu-kung asked about the gentleman. The Master said, 'He puts his words into action before allowing his words to follow his action.'

14．The Master said, 'The gentleman enters into associations but not cliques; the small man enters into cliques but not associations.'

15．The Master said, 'If one learns from others but does not think, one will be bewildered. If, on the other hand, one thinks but does not learn from others, one will be in peril.'

16．The Master said, 'To attack a task from the wrong end can do nothing but harm.'

17．The Master said, 'Yu, shall I tell you what it is to know. To say you know when you know, and to say you do not when you do not, that is knowledge.'

18．Tzu-chang was studying with an eye to an official career. The Master said, 'Use your ears widely but leave out what is doubtful; repeat the rest with caution and you will make few mistakes. Use your eyes widely and leave out what is hazardous; put the rest into practice with caution and you will have few regrets. When in your speech you make few mistakes and in your action you have few regrets, an official career will follow as a matter of course.'

19．Duke Ai asked, 'What must I do before the common people will look up to me?'

Confucius answered, 'Raise the straight and set them over the crooked and the common people will look up to you. Raise the crooked and set them over the straight and the common people will not look up to you.'

20．Chi K'ang Tzu asked, 'How can one inculcate in the common people the virtue of reverence, of doing their best and of enthusiasm?'

The Master said, 'Rule over them with dignity and they will be reverent; treat them with kindness and they will do their best; raise the good and instruct those who are backward and they will be imbued with enthusiasm.'

21．Someone said to Confucius, 'Why do you not take part in government?'

The Master said, 'The Book of History says, "Oh! Simply by being a good son and friendly to his brothers a man can exert an influence upon government." In so doing a man is, in fact, taking part in government. How can there be any question of his having actively to "take part in government"?'

22．The Master said, 'I do not see how a man can be acceptable who is untrustworthy in word. When a pin is missing in the yoke-bar of a large cart or in the collar-bar of a small cart, how can the cart be expected to go?'

23．Tzu-chang asked, 'Can ten generations hence be known?'

The Master said, 'The Yin built on the rites of the Hsia. What was added and what was omitted can be known. The Chou built on the rites of the Yin. What was added and what was omitted can be known. Should there be a successor to the Chou, even a hundred generations hence can be known.'

24．The Master said, 'To offer sacrifice to the spirit of an ancestor not one's own is obsequious.

'Faced with what is right, to leave it undone shows a lack of courage.'

注释

【1】　This line is from Ode 297 where it describes a team of horses going straight ahead without swerving to left or right.

【2】　The expression erh shun is very obscure and the translation is tentative.

【3】　i.e., he is no specialist, as every vessel is designed for a specific purpose only.

Book Ⅲ

1．Confucius said of the Chi Family, 'They use eight rows of eight dancers each[【1】] to perform in their courtyard. If this can be tolerated, what cannot be tolerated?'

2．The Three Families[【2】] performed the yung[【3】] when the sacrificial offerings were being cleared away. The Master said,

　　'In attendance were the great lords,

　　In solemn dignity was the Emperor.

What application has this to the halls of the Three Families?'

3．The Master said, 'What can a man do with the rites who is not benevolent? What can a man do with music who is not benevolent?'

4．Lin Fang asked about the basis of the rites. The Master said, 'A noble question indeed! With the rites, it is better to err on the side of frugality than on the side of extravagance; in mourning, it is better to err on the side of grief than on the side of formality.'

5．The Master said, 'Barbarian tribes with their rulers are inferior to Chinese states without them.'

6．The Chi Family were going to perform the sacrifice to Mount T'ai.[【4】] The Master said to Jan Ch'iu,[【5】] 'Can you not save the situation?'

'No. I cannot.'

The Master said, 'Alas! Who would have thought that Mount T'ai would suffer in comparison with Lin Fang?'[【6】]

7．The Master said, 'There is no contention between gentlemen. The nearest to it is, perhaps, archery. In archery they bow and make way for one another as they go up and on coming down they drink together. Even the way they contend is gentlemanly.'

8．Tzu-hsia asked,

　　'Her entrancing smile dimpling,

　　Her beautiful eyes glancing,

　　Patterns of colour upon plain silk.

What is the meaning of these lines?'

The Master said, 'The colours are put in after the white.'

'Does the practice of the rites likewise come afterwards?'

The Master said, 'It is you, Shang, who have thrown light on the text for me. Only with a man like you can one discuss the Odes.'

9．The Master said, 'I am able to discourse on the rites of the Hsia, but the state of Ch'i does not furnish sufficient supporting evidence; I am able to discourse on the rites of the Yin, but the state of Sung does not furnish sufficient supporting evidence. This is because there are not enough records and men of erudition. Otherwise I would be able to support what I say with evidence.'

10．The Master said, 'I do not wish to witness that part of the ti sacrifice[【7】] which follows the opening libation to the impersonator.'[【8】]

11．Someone asked about the theory of the ti sacrifice. The Master said, 'It is not something I understand, for whoever understands it will be able to manage the Empire as easily as if he had it here,' pointing to his palm.

12．'Sacrifice as if present' is taken to mean 'sacrifice to the gods as if the gods were present.'

The Master, however, said, 'Unless I take part in a sacrifice, it is as if I did not sacrifice.'

13．Wang-sun Chia said,

　　'Better to be obsequious to the kitchen stove

　　Than to the south-west corner of the house.[【9】]

What does that mean?'

The Master said, 'The saying has got it wrong. When you have offended against Heaven, there is nowhere you can turn to in your prayers.'

14．The Master said, 'The Chou is resplendent in culture, having before it the example of the two previous dynasties.[【10】] I am for the Chou.'

15．When the Master went inside the Grand Temple,[【11】] he asked questions about everything. Someone remarked, 'Who said that the son of the man from Tsou[【12】] understood the rites? When he went inside the Grand Temple, he asked questions about everything.'

The Master, on hearing of this, said, 'The asking of questions is in itself the correct rite.'

16．The Master said,

　　'In archery the point lies not in piercing the hide,[【13】]

　　For the reason that strength varies from man to man.

This was the way of antiquity.'

17．Tzu-kung wanted to do away with the sacrificial sheep at the announcement of the new moon. The Master said, 'Ssu, you are loath to part with the price of the sheep, but I am loath to see the disappearance of the rite.'

18．The Master said, 'You will be looked upon as obsequious by others if you observe every detail of the rites in serving your lord.'

19．Duke Ting asked, 'What is the way the ruler should employ the services of his subjects? What is the way a subject should serve his ruler?'

Confucius answered, 'The ruler should employ the services of his subjects in accordance with the rites. A subject should serve his ruler by doing his best.'

20．The Master said, 'In the kuan chü[【14】] there is joy without wantonness, and sorrow without self-injury.'

21．Duke Ai asked Tsai Wo about the altar to the god of earth. Tsai Wo replied, 'The Hsia used the pine, the Yin used the cedar, and the men of Chou used the chestnut (li), saying that it made the common people tremble (li).'

The Master, on hearing of this reply, commented, 'One does not explain away what is already done, one does not argue against what is already accomplished, and one does not condemn what has already gone by.'

22．The Master said, 'Kuan Chung was, indeed, a vessel of small capacity.'

Someone remarked, 'Was Kuan Chung frugal, then?'

'Kuan Chung kept three separate establishments, each complete with its own staff. How can he be called frugal?'

'In that case, did Kuan Chung understand the rites?'

'Rulers of states erect gate-screens; Kuan Chung erected such a screen as well. The ruler of a state, when entertaining the ruler of another state, has a stand for inverted cups; Kuan Chung had such a stand as well. If even Kuan Chung understood the rites, who does not understand them?'

23．The Master talked of music to the Grand Musician of Lu, saying, 'This much can be known about music. It begins with playing in unison. When it gets into full swing, it is harmonious, clear and unbroken. In this way it reaches the conclusion.'

24．The border official of Yi requested an audience, saying, 'I have never been denied an audience by any gentleman who has come to this place.' The followers presented him. When he came out, he said, 'What worry have you, gentlemen, about the loss of office? The Empire has long been without the Way. Heaven is about to use your Master as the wooden tongue for a bell.'[【15】]

25．The Master said of the shao[【16】] that it was both perfectly beautiful and perfectly good, and of the wu[【17】] that it was perfectly beautiful but not perfectly good.

26．The Master said, 'What can I find worthy of note in a man who is lacking in tolerance when in high position, in reverence when performing the rites and in sorrow when in mourning?'

注释

【1】　A prerogative of the Emperor.

【2】　The three noble families of the state of Lu: Meng-sun, Shu-sun and Chi-sun.

【3】　Ode 282, from which the couplet quoted comes.

【4】　Not being the lord of the state of Lu, the head of the Chi Family was not entitled to perform the sacrifice to Mount T'ai and it would be a violation of the rites for Mount T'ai to accept the sacrifice.

【5】　Who was in the service of the Chi Family.

【6】　See Ⅲ.4 above where Lin Fang showed a concern for the basis of the rites.

【7】　An important sacrifice performed by the Emperor, but the privilege of performing it was granted to the Duke of Chou, the founder of the state of Lu.

【8】　The young boy or girl who impersonates the dead ancestor to whom the offerings are made.

【9】　By 'the south-west corner of the house', which is the place of honour, Wang-sun Chia, being a minister of Wei, presumably meant to refer to the lord of Wei and by 'the kitchen stove' to himself.

【10】　The Hsia and the Yin.

【11】　The temple of the Duke of Chou, the founder of the state of Lu.

【12】　The man from Tsou refers to Confucius' father.

【13】　i.e., the bull's eye fixed in the centre of a cloth target.

【14】　The first ode in the Odes.

【15】　To rouse the Empire.

【16】　The music of Shun who came to the throne through the abdication of Yao.

【17】　The music of King Wu who came to the throne through overthrowing the Yin by military force.

Book Ⅳ

1．The Master said, 'Of neighbourhoods benevolence is the most beautiful. How can the man be considered wise who, when he has the choice, does not settle in benevolence?'

2．The Master said, 'One who is not benevolent cannot remain long in straitened circumstances, nor can he remain long in easy circumstances.

'The benevolent man is attracted to benevolence because he feels at home in it. The wise man is attracted to benevolence because he finds it to his advantage.'

3．The Master said, 'It is only the benevolent man who is capable of liking or disliking other men.'

4．The Master said, 'If a man sets his heart on benevolence, he will be free from evil.'

5．The Master said, 'Wealth and high station are what men desire but unless I got them in the right way I would not remain in them. Poverty and low station are what men dislike, but even if I did not get them in the right way I would not try to escape from them.[【1】]

'If the gentleman forsakes benevolence, in what way can he make a name for himself? The gentleman never deserts benevolence, not even for as long as it takes to eat a meal. If he hurries and stumbles one may be sure that it is in benevolence that he does so.'

6．The Master said, 'I have never met a man who finds benevolence attractive or a man who finds unbenevolence[【2】] repulsive. A man who finds benevolence attractive cannot be surpassed. A man who finds unbenevolence repulsive can, perhaps, be counted as benevolent, for he would not allow what is not benevolent to contaminate his person.

'Is there a man who, for the space of a single day, is able to devote all his strength to benevolence? I have not come across such a man whose strength proves insufficient for the task. There must be such cases of insufficient strength, only I have not come across them.'

7．The Master said, 'In his errors a man is true to type. Observe the errors and you will know the man.'

8．The Master said, 'He has not lived in vain who dies the day he is told about the Way.'

9．The Master said, 'There is no point in seeking the views of a Gentleman who, though he sets his heart on the Way, is ashamed of poor food and poor clothes.'

10．The Master said, 'In his dealings with the world the gentleman is not invariably for or against anything. He is on the side of what is moral.'

11．The Master said, 'While the gentleman cherishes benign rule, the small man cherishes his native land. While the gentleman cherishes a respect for the law, the small man cherishes generous treatment.'[【3】]

12．The Master said, 'If one is guided by profit in one's actions, one will incur much ill will.'

13．The Master said, 'If a man is able to govern a state by observing the rites and showing deference, what difficulties will he have in public life? If he is unable to govern a state by observing the rites and showing deference, what good are the rites to him?'

14．The Master said, 'Do not worry because you have no official position. Worry about your qualifications. Do not worry because no one appreciates your abilities. Seek to be worthy of appreciation.'

15．The Master said, 'Ts'an! There is one single thread binding my way together.'

Tseng Tzu assented.

After the Master had gone out, the disciples asked, 'What did he mean?'

Tseng Tzu said, 'The way of the Master consists in doing one's best and in using oneself as a measure to gauge others. That is all.'

16．The Master said, 'The gentleman understands what is moral. The small man understands what is profitable.'

17．The Master said, 'When you meet someone better than yourself, turn your thoughts to becoming his equal. When you meet someone not as good as you are, look within and examine your own self.'

18．The Master said, 'In serving your father and mother you ought to dissuade them from doing wrong in the gentlest way. If you see your advice being ignored, you should not become disobedient but remain reverent. You should not complain even if in so doing you wear yourself out.'

19．The Master said, 'While your parents are alive, you should not go too far afield in your travels. If you do, your whereabouts should always be known.'

20．The Master said, 'If, for three years, a man makes no changes to his father's ways, he can be said to be a good son.'

21．The Master said, 'A man should not be ignorant of the age of his father and mother. It is a matter, on the one hand, for rejoicing and, on the other, for anxiety.'

22．The Master said, 'In antiquity men were loath to speak. This was because they counted it shameful if their person failed to keep up with their words.'

23．The Master said, 'It is rare for a man to miss the mark through holding on to essentials.'

24．The Master said, 'The gentleman desires to be halting in speech but quick in action.'

25．The Master said, 'Virtue never stands alone. It is bound to have neighbours.'

26．Tzu-yu said, 'To be importunate with one's lord will mean humiliation. To be importunate with one's friends will mean estrangement.'

注释

【1】　This sentence is most likely to be corrupt. The negative is probably an interpolation and the sentence should read: 'Poverty and low station are what men dislike, but if I got them in the right way I would not try to escape from them.'

【2】　The word 'unbenevolence' has been coined because the original word has a positive meaning lacking in 'non-benevolence'.

【3】　The distinction here between 'the gentleman' and 'the small man' is not, as is often the case, drawn between the ruler and the ruled but within the class of the ruled.

Book Ⅴ

1．The Master said of Kung-yeh Ch'ang that he was a suitable choice for a husband, for though he was in gaol it was not as though he had done anything wrong. He gave him his daughter in marriage.

2．The Master said of Nan-jung that when the Way prevailed in the state he was not cast aside and when the Way fell into disuse he stayed clear of the humiliation of punishment. He gave him his elder brother's daughter in marriage.

3．The Master's comment on Tzu-chien was 'What a gentleman this man is! If there were no gentlemen in Lu where could he have acquired his qualities?'

4．Tzu-kung asked, 'What do you think of me?'

The Master said, 'You are a vessel.'

'What kind of vessel?'

'A sacrificial vessel.'[【1】]

5．Someone said, 'Yung is benevolent but does not have a facile tongue.'

The Master said, 'What need is there for him to have a facile tongue? For a man quick with a retort there are frequent occasions on which he will incur the hatred of others. I cannot say whether Yung is benevolent or not, but what need is there for him to have a facile tongue?'

6．The Master told Ch'i-tiao K'ai to take office. Ch'i-tiao K'ai said, 'I cannot trust myself to do so yet.' The Master was pleased.

7．The Master said, 'If the Way should fail to prevail and I were to put to sea on a raft, the one who would follow me would no doubt be Yu.' Tzu-lu, on hearing this, was overjoyed. The Master said, 'Yu has a greater love for courage than I, but is lacking in judgement.'

8．Meng Wu Po asked whether Tzu-lu was benevolent. The Master said, 'I cannot say.' Meng Wu Po repeated the question. The Master said, 'Yu can be given the responsibility of managing the military levies in a state of a thousand chariots, but whether he is benevolent or not I cannot say.'

'What about Ch'iu?'

The Master said, 'Ch'iu can be given the responsibility as a steward in a town with a thousand households or in a noble family with a hundred chariots, but whether he is benevolent or not I cannot say.'

'What about Ch'ih?'

The Master said, 'When Ch'ih, putting on his sash, takes his place at court, he can be given the responsibility of conversing with the guests, but whether he is benevolent or not I cannot say.'

9．The Master said to Tzu-kung, 'Who is the better man, you or Hui?'

'How dare I compare myself with Hui? When he is told one thing he understands ten. When I am told one thing I understand only two.'

The Master said, 'You are not as good as he is. Neither of us is as good as he is.'

10．Tsai Yü was in bed in the daytime. The Master said, 'A piece of rotten wood cannot be carved, nor can a wall of dried dung be trowelled. As far as Yü is concerned what is the use of condemning him?' The Master added, 'I used to take on trust a man's deeds after having listened to his words. Now having listened to a man's words I go on to observe his deeds. It was on account of Yü that I have changed in this respect.'

11．The Master said, 'I have never met anyone who is truly unbending.'

Someone said, 'What about Shen Ch'eng?'

The Master said, 'Ch'eng is full of desires. How can he be unbending?'

12．Tzu-kung said, 'While I do not wish others to impose on me, I also wish not to impose on others.'

The Master said, 'Ssu, that is quite beyond you.'

13．Tzu-kung said, 'One can get to hear about the Master's accomplishments, but one cannot get to hear his views on human nature and the Way of Heaven.'

14．Before he could put into practice something he had heard, the only thing Tzu-lu feared was that he should be told something further.

15．Tzu-kung asked, 'Why was K'ung Wen Tzu called "wen"?'

The Master said, 'He was quick and eager to learn: he was not ashamed to seek the advice of those who were beneath him in station. That is why he was called "wen".'

16．The Master said of Tzu-ch'an that he had the way of the gentleman on four counts: he was respectful in the manner he conducted himself; he was reverent in the service of his lord; in caring for the common people, he was generous and, in employing their services, he was just.

17．The Master said, 'Yen P'ing-chung excelled in friendship: even after long acquaintance he treated his friends with reverence.'

18．The Master said, 'When housing his great tortoise, Tsang Wen-chung had the capitals of the pillars carved in the shape of hills and the rafterposts painted in a duckweed design. What is one to think of his intelligence?'

19．Tzu-chang asked, 'Ling Yin[【2】] Tzu-wen gave no appearance of pleasure when he was made prime minister three times. Neither did he give any appearance of displeasure when he was removed from office three times. He always told his successor what he had done during his term of office. What do you think of this?'

The Master said, 'He can, indeed, be said to be a man who does his best.'

'Can he be said to be benevolent?'

'He cannot even be said to be wise. How can he be said to be benevolent?'

'When Ts'ui Tzu assassinated the Lord of Ch'i, Ch'en Wen Tzu who owned ten teams of four horses each abandoned them and left the state. On arriving in another state, he said, "The officials here are no better than our Counsellor Ts'ui Tzu." He left and went to yet another state. Once more, he said, "The officials here are no better than our Counsellor Ts'ui Tzu," and he again left. What do you think of this?'

The Master said, 'He can, indeed, be said to be pure.'

'Can he be said to be benevolent?'

'He cannot even be said to be wise. How can he be said to be benevolent?'

20．Chi Wen Tzu always thought three times before taking action. When the Master was told of this, he commented, 'Twice is quite enough.'

21．The Master said, 'Ning Wu Tzu was intelligent when the Way prevailed in the state, but stupid when it did not. Others may equal his intelligence but they cannot equal his stupidity.'

22．When he was in Ch'en, the Master said, 'Let us go home. Let us go home. Our young men at home are wildly ambitious, and have great accomplishments for all to see, but they do not know how to prune themselves.'

23．The Master said, 'Po Yi and Shu Ch'i never remembered old scores. For this reason they incurred little ill will.'

24．The Master said, 'Who said Wei-sheng Kao was straight? Once when someone begged him for vinegar, he went and begged it off a neighbour to give it to him.'

25．The Master said, 'Cunning words, an ingratiating face and utter servility, these things Tso-ch'iu Ming found shameful. I, too, find them shameful. To be friendly towards someone while concealing one's hostility, this Tso-ch'iu Ming found shameful. I, too, find it shameful.'

26．Yen Yüan and Chi-lu were in attendance. The Master said, 'I suggest you each tell me what it is you have set your hearts on.'

Tzu-lu said, 'I should like to share my carriage and horses, clothes and furs with my friends, and to have no regrets even if they become worn.'

Yen Yüan said, 'I should like never to boast of my own goodness and never to impose onerous tasks upon others.'

Tzu-lu said, 'I should like to hear what you have set your heart on.'

The Master said, 'To bring peace to the old, to have trust in my friends, and to cherish the young.'

27．The Master said, 'I suppose I should give up hope. I have yet to meet the man who, on seeing his own errors, is able to take himself to task inwardly.'

28．The Master said, 'In a hamlet of ten households, there are bound to be those who are my equal in doing their best for others and in being trustworthy in what they say, but they are unlikely to be as eager to learn as I am.'

注释

【1】　Made of jade.

【2】　This was the title in the state of Ch'u for the prime minister.

Book Ⅵ

1．The Master said, 'Yung could be given the seat facing south.'[【1】]

2．Chung-kung asked about Tzu-sang Po-tzu. The Master said, 'It is his simplicity of style that makes him acceptable.'

Chung-kung said, 'In ruling over the common people, is it not acceptable to hold oneself in reverence and merely to be simple in the measures one takes? On the other hand, is it not carrying simplicity too far to be simple in the way one holds oneself as well as in the measures one takes?'

The Master said, 'Yung is right in what he says.'

3．When Duke Ai asked which of his disciples was eager to learn, Confucius answered, 'There was one Yen Hui who was eager to learn. He did not vent his anger upon an innocent person, nor did he make the same mistake twice. Unfortunately his allotted span was a short one and he died. Now there is no one. No one eager to learn has come to my notice.'

4．Jan Tzu asked for grain for the mother of Tzu-hua who was away on a mission to Ch'i. The Master said, 'Give her one fu.'[【2】] Jan Tzu asked for more. 'Give her one yü.' Jan Tzu gave her five ping of grain.

The Master said, 'Ch'ih went off to Ch'i drawn by well-fed horses and wearing light furs. I have heard it said, A gentleman gives to help the needy and not to maintain the rich in style.'

5．On becoming his[【3】] steward, Yüan Ssu was given nine hundred measures of grain which he declined. The Master said, 'Can you not find a use for it in helping the people in your neighbourhood?'

6．The Master said of Chung-kung, 'Should a bull born of plough cattle have a sorrel coat and well-formed horns, would the spirits of the mountains and rivers allow it to be passed over even if we felt it was not good enough to be used?'

7．The Master said, 'In his heart for three months at a time Hui does not lapse from benevolence. The others attain benevolence merely by fits and starts.'

8．Chi K'ang Tzu asked, 'Is Chung Yu good enough to be given office?'

The Master said, 'Yu is resolute. What difficulties could there be for him in taking office?'

'Is Ssu good enough to be given office?'

'Ssu is a man of understanding. What difficulties could there be for him in taking office?'

'Is Ch'iu good enough to be given office?'

'Ch'iu is accomplished. What difficulties could there be for him in taking office?'

9．The Chi Family wanted to make Min Tzu-ch'ien the steward of Pi. Min Tzu-ch'ien said, 'Decline the offer for me tactfully. If anyone comes back for me, I shall be on the other side of the River Wen.'[【4】]

10．Po-niu was ill. The Master visited him and, holding his hand through the window, said, 'We are going to lose him. It must be Destiny. Why else should such a man be stricken with such a disease? Why else should such a man be stricken with such a disease?'

11．The Master said, 'How admirable Hui is! Living in a mean dwelling on a bowlful of rice and a ladleful of water is a hardship most men would find intolerable, but Hui does not allow this to affect his joy. How admirable Hui is!'

12．Jan Ch'iu said, 'It is not that I am not pleased with your way, but rather that my strength gives out.' The Master said, 'A man whose strength gives out collapses along the course. In your case you set the limits beforehand.'

13．The Master said to Tzu-hsia, 'Be a gentleman ju,[【5】] not a petty ju.'

14．Tzu-yu was the steward of Wu Ch'eng. The Master said, 'Have you made any discoveries there?'

'There is one T'an-t'ai Mieh-ming who never takes short-cuts and who has never been to my room except on official business.'

15．The Master said, 'Meng chih Fan was not given to boasting. When the army was routed, he stayed in the rear. But on entering the gate, he goaded his horse on, saying, 'I did not lag behind out of presumption. It was simply that my horse refused to go forward.'

16．The Master said, 'You may have the good looks of Sung Chao, but you will find it difficult to escape unscathed in this world if you do not, at the same time, have the eloquence of the Priest T'uo.'

17．The Master said, 'Who can go out without using the door? Why, then, does no one follow this Way?'

18．The Master said, 'When there is a preponderance of native substance over acquired refinement, the result will be churlishness. When there is a preponderance of acquired refinement over native substance, the result will be pedantry. Only a well-balanced admixture of these two will result in gentlemanliness.'

19．The Master said, 'That a man lives is because he is straight. That a man who dupes others survives is because he has been fortunate enough to be spared.'

20．The Master said, 'To be fond of something is better than merely to know it, and to find joy in it is better than merely to be fond of it.'

21．The Master said, 'You can tell those who are above average about the best, but not those who are below average.'

22．Fan Ch'ih asked about wisdom. The Master said, 'To work for the things the common people have a right to and to keep one's distance from the gods and spirits while showing them reverence can be called wisdom.'

Fan Ch'ih asked about benevolence. The Master said, 'The benevolent man reaps the benefit only after overcoming difficulties. That can be called benevolence.'

23．The Master said, 'The wise find joy in water; the benevolent find joy in mountains. The wise are active; the benevolent are still. The wise are joyful; the benevolent are long-lived.'

24．The Master said, 'At one stroke Ch'i can be made into a Lu, and Lu, at one stroke, can be made to attain the Way.'

25．The Master said, 'A ku[【6】] that is not truly a ku. A ku indeed! A ku indeed!'

26．Tsai Wo asked, 'If a benevolent man was told that there was another benevolent man in the well, would he, nevertheless, go and join him?'

The Master said, 'Why should that be the case? A gentleman can be sent there, but cannot be lured into a trap. He can be deceived, but cannot be duped.'

27．The Master said, 'The gentleman widely versed in culture but brought back to essentials by the rites can, I suppose, be relied upon not to turn against what he stood for.'

28．The Master went to see Nan Tzu.[【7】] Tzu-lu was displeased. The Master swore, 'If I have done anything improper, may Heaven's curse be on me, may Heaven's curse be on me!'

29．The Master said, 'Supreme indeed is the Mean as a moral virtue. It has been rare among the common people for quite a long time.'

30．Tzu-kung said, 'If there were a man who gave extensively to the common people and brought help to the multitude, what would you think of him? Could he be called benevolent?'

The Master said, 'It is no longer a matter of benevolence with such a man. If you must describe him, "sage" is, perhaps, the right word. Even Yao and Shun would have found it difficult to accomplish as much. Now, on the other hand, a benevolent man helps others to take their stand in so far as he himself wishes to take his stand,[【8】] and gets others there in so far as he himself wishes to get there. The ability to take as analogy what is near at hand[【9】] can be called the method of benevolence.'

注释

【1】　The seat of the ruler.

【2】　Fu, yü and ping are dry measures in ascending order of capacity.

【3】　i.e., Confucius'.

【4】　i.e., over the border into the state of Ch'i.

【5】　The original meaning of the word is uncertain, but it probably referred to men for whom the qualities of the scholar were more important than those of the warrior. In subsequent ages, ju came to be the name given to the Confucianists.

【6】　A drinking vessel with a regulation capacity.

【7】　The notorious wife of Duke Ling of Wei.

【8】　It is on the rites that one takes one's stand. Cf. 'Take your stand on the rites' (Ⅷ.8).

【9】　viz., oneself.

Book Ⅶ

1．The Master said, 'I transmit but do not innovate; I am truthful in what I say and devoted to antiquity. I venture to compare myself to our Old P'eng.'[【1】]

2．The Master said, 'Quietly to store up knowledge in my mind, to learn without flagging, to teach without growing weary, these present me with no difficulties.'

3．The Master said, 'It is these things that cause me concern: failure to cultivate virtue, failure to go more deeply into what I have learned, inability, when I am told what is right, to move to where it is, and inability to reform myself when I have defects.'

4．During his leisure moments, the Master remained correct though relaxed.

5．The Master said, 'How I have gone downhill! It has been such a long time since I dreamt of the Duke of Chou.'

6．The Master said, 'I set my heart on the Way, base myself on virtue, lean upon benevolence for support and take my recreation in the arts.'

7．The Master said, 'I have never denied instruction to anyone who, of his own accord, has given me so much as a bundle of dried meat as a present.'

8．The Master said, 'I never enlighten anyone who has not been driven to distraction by trying to understand a difficulty or who has not got into a frenzy trying to put his ideas into words.

'When I have pointed out one corner of a square to anyone and he does not come back with the other three, I will not point it out to him a second time.'

9．When eating in the presence of one who had been bereaved, the Master never ate his fill.

10．On a day he had wept, the Master did not sing.

11．The Master said to Yen Yüan, 'Only you and I have the ability to go forward when employed and to stay out of sight when set aside.'

Tzu-lu said, 'If you were leading the Three Armies whom would you take with you?'

The Master said, 'I would not take with me anyone who would try to fight a tiger with his bare hands or to walk across the River[【2】] and die in the process without regrets. If I took anyone it would have to be a man who, when faced with a task, was fearful of failure and who, while fond of making plans, was capable of successful execution.'

12．The Master said, 'If wealth were a permissible pursuit, I would be willing even to act as a guard holding a whip outside the market place. If it is not, I shall follow my own preferences.'

13．Fasting, war and sickness were the things over which the Master exercised care.

14．The Master heard the shao[【3】] in Ch'i and for three months did not notice the taste of the meat he ate. He said, 'I never dreamt that the joys of music could reach such heights.'

15．Jan Yu said, 'Is the Master on the side of the Lord of Wei?'[【4】] Tzu-kung said, 'Well, I shall put the question to him.'

He went in and said, 'What sort of men were Po Yi and Shu Ch'i?'

'They were excellent men of old.'

'Did they have any complaints?'

'They sought benevolence and got it. So why should they have any complaints?'

When Tzu-kung came out, he said, 'The Master is not on his side.'

16．The Master said, 'In the eating of coarse rice and the drinking of water, the using of one's elbow for a pillow, joy is to be found. Wealth and rank attained through immoral means have as much to do with me as passing clouds.'

17．The Master said, 'Grant me a few more years so that I may study at the age of fifty and I shall be free from major errors.'

18．What the Master used the correct pronunciation for: the Odes, the Book of History and the performance of the rites. In all these cases he used the correct pronunciation.

19．The Governor of She asked Tzu-lu about Confucius. Tzu-lu did not answer. The Master said, 'Why did you not simply say something to this effect: he is the sort of man who forgets to eat when he tries to solve a problem that has been driving him to distraction, who is so full of joy that he forgets his worries and who does not notice the onset of old age?'

20．The Master said, 'I was not born with knowledge but, being fond of antiquity, I am quick to seek it.'

21．The topics the Master did not speak of were prodigies, force, disorder and gods.

22．The Master said, 'Even when walking in the company of two other men, I am bound to be able to learn from them. The good points of the one I copy; the bad points of the other I correct in myself.'

23．The Master said, 'Heaven is author of the virtue that is in me. What can Huan T'ui do to me?'[【5】]

24．The Master said, 'My friends, do you think I am secretive? There is nothing which I hide from you. There is nothing I do which I do not share with you, my friends. There is Ch'iu for you.'

25．The Master instructs under four heads: culture, moral conduct, doing one's best and being trustworthy in what one says.

26．The Master said, 'I have no hopes of meeting a sage. I would be content if I met someone who is a gentleman.'

The Master said, 'I have no hopes of meeting a good man. I would be content if I met someone who has constancy. It is hard for a man to have constancy who claims to have when he is wanting, to be full when he is empty and to be comfortable when he is in straitened circumstances.'

27．The Master used a fishing line but not a cable;[【6】] he used a corded arrow but not to shoot at roosting birds.

28．The Master said, 'There are presumably men who innovate without possessing knowledge, but that is not a fault I have. I use my ears widely and follow what is good in what I have heard; I use my eyes widely and retain what I have seen in my mind. This constitutes a lower level of knowledge.'

29．People of Hu Hsiang were difficult to talk to. A boy was received and the disciples were perplexed. The Master said, 'Approval of his coming does not mean approval of him when he is not here. Why should we be so exacting? When a man comes after having purified himself, we approve of his purification but we cannot vouch for his past.'[【7】]

30．The Master said, 'Is benevolence really far away? No sooner do I desire it than it is here.'

31．Ch'en Ssu-pai asked whether Duke Chao was versed in the rites. Confucius said, 'Yes.'

After Confucius had gone, Ch'en Ssu-pai, bowing to Wu-ma Ch'i, invited him forward and said, 'I have heard that the gentleman does not show partiality. Does he show it nevertheless? The Lord took as wife a daughter of Wu, who thus is of the same clan as himself,[【8】] but he allows her to be called Wu Meng Tzu.[【9】] If the Lord is versed in the rites, who isn't?'

When Wu-ma Ch'i recounted this to him, the Master said, 'I am a fortunate man. Whenever I make a mistake, other people are sure to notice it.'[【10】]

32．When the Master was singing in the company of others and liked someone else's song, he always asked to hear it again before joining in.

33．The Master said, 'In unstinted effort I can compare with others, but in being a practising gentleman I have had, as yet, no success.'

34．The Master said, 'How dare I claim to be a sage or a benevolent man? Perhaps it might be said of me that I learn without flagging and teach without growing weary.' Kung-hsi Hua said, 'This is precisely where we disciples are unable to learn from your example.'

35．The Master was seriously ill. Tzu-lu asked permission to offer a prayer. The Master said, 'Was such a thing ever done?' Tzu-lu said, 'Yes, it was. The prayer offered was as follows: pray thus to the gods above and below.' The Master said, 'In that case, I have long been offering my prayers.'

36．The Master said, 'Extravagance means ostentation, frugality means shabbiness. I would rather be shabby than ostentatious.'

37．The Master said, 'The gentleman is easy of mind, while the small man is always full of anxiety.'

38．The Master is cordial yet stern, awe-inspiring yet not fierce, and respectful yet at ease.

注释

【1】　It is not clear who Old P'eng was.

【2】　In ancient Chinese literature, 'the River' meant the Yellow River.

【3】　The music of Shun. Cf. Ⅲ.25.

【4】　i.e., Che, known in history as the Ousted Duke, son of Prince K'uai K'ui who was son of Duke Ling. After failing in an attempt to kill Nan Tzu, the notorious wife of his father, Prince K'uai K'ui fled to Chin. On the death of Duke Ling, Che came to the throne. With the backing of the Chin army, Prince K'uai K'ui managed to install himself in the city of Ch'i in Wei, waiting for an opportunity to oust his son. At that time Confucius was in Wei, and what Jan Yu wanted to know was whether he was for Che.

【5】　According to tradition, this was said on the occasion when Huan T'ui, the Minister of War in Sung, attempted to kill him.

【6】　Attached to a net.

【7】　It has been suggested that this sentence should stand at the beginning of Confucius' remark.

【8】　Bearing the name Chi.

【9】　when she should be called Wu Chi. Calling her Wu Meng Tzu was an attempt to gloss over the fact that she shared the same clan name of Chi.

【10】　Being a native of Lu, Confucius would rather be criticized for partiality than appear to be openly critical of the Duke.

Book Ⅷ

1．The Master said, 'Surely T'ai Po can be said to be of the highest virtue. Three times he abdicated his right to rule over the Empire, and yet he left behind nothing the common people could acclaim.'

2．The Master said, 'Unless a man has the spirit of the rites, in being respectful he will wear himself out, in being careful he will become timid, in having courage he will become unruly, and in being forthright he will become intolerant.

'When the gentleman feels profound affection for his parents, the common people will be stirred to benevolence. When he does not forget friends of long standing, the common people will not shirk their obligations to other people.'

3．When he was seriously ill Tseng Tzu summoned his disciples and said, 'Take a look at my hands. Take a look at my feet. The Odes say,

　　In fear and trembling,

　　As if approaching a deep abyss,

　　As if walking on thin ice.[【1】]

Only now am I sure of being spared,[【2】] my young friends.'

4．Tseng Tzu was seriously ill. When Meng Ching Tzu visited him, this was what Tseng Tzu said,

　　'Sad is the cry of a dying bird;

　　Good are the words of a dying man.

There are three things which the gentleman values most in the Way: to stay clear of violence by putting on a serious countenance, to come close to being trusted by setting a proper expression on his face, and to avoid being boorish and unreasonable by speaking in proper tones. As for the business of sacrificial vessels, there are officials responsible for that.'

5．Tseng Tzu said, 'To be able yet to ask the advice of those who are not able. To have many talents yet to ask the advice of those who have few. To have yet to appear to want. To be full yet to appear empty.[【3】] To be transgressed against yet not to mind. It was towards this end that my friend[【4】] used to direct his efforts.'

6．Tseng Tzu said, 'If a man can be entrusted with an orphan six ch'ih[【5】] tall, and the fate of a state one hundred li square, without his being deflected from his purpose even in moments of crisis, is he not a gentleman? He is, indeed, a gentleman.'

7．Tseng Tzu said, 'A Gentleman must be strong and resolute, for his burden is heavy and the road is long. He takes benevolence as his burden. Is that not heavy? Only with death does the road come to an end. Is that not long?'

8．The Master said, 'Be stimulated by the Odes, take your stand on the rites and be perfected by music.'

9．The Master said, 'The common people can be made to follow a path but not to understand it.'

10．The Master said, 'Being fond of courage while detesting poverty will lead men to unruly behaviour. Excessive detestation of men who are not benevolent will provoke them to unruly behaviour.'

11．The Master said, 'Even with a man as gifted as the Duke of Chou, if he was arrogant and miserly, then the rest of his qualities would not be worthy of admiration.'

12．The Master said, 'It is not easy to find a man who can study for three years without thinking about earning a salary.'

13．The Master said, 'Have the firm faith to devote yourself to learning, and abide to the death in the good way. Enter not a state that is in peril; stay not in a state that is in danger. Show yourself when the Way prevails in the Empire, but hide yourself when it does not. It is a shameful matter to be poor and humble when the Way prevails in the state. Equally, it is a shameful matter to be rich and noble when the Way falls into disuse in the state.'

14．The Master said, 'Do not concern yourself with matters of government unless they are the responsibility of your office.'

15．The Master said, 'When Chih, the Master Musician, begins to play and when the Kuan chü[【6】] comes to its end, how the sound fills the ear!'

16．The Master said, 'Men who reject discipline and yet are not straight, men who are ignorant and yet not cautious, men who are devoid of ability and yet not trustworthy are quite beyond my understanding.'

17．The Master said, 'Even with a man who urges himself on in his studies as though he was losing ground, my fear is still that he may not make it in time.'

18．The Master said, 'How lofty Shun and Yü were in holding aloof from the Empire when they were in possession of it.'

19．The Master said, 'Great indeed was Yao as a ruler! How lofty! It is Heaven that is great and it was Yao who modelled himself upon it. He was so boundless that the common people were not able to put a name to his virtues. Lofty was he in his successes and brilliant was he in his accomplishments!'

20．Shun had five officials and the Empire was well governed. King Wu said, 'I have ten capable officials.'

Confucius commented, 'How true it is that talent is difficult to find! The period of T'ang and Yü[【7】] was rich in talent.[【8】] With a woman amongst them, there were, in fact, only nine.[【9】] The Chou continued to serve the Yin when it was in possession of two-thirds of the Empire. Its virtue can be said to have been the highest.'

21．The Master said, 'With Yü I can find no fault. He ate and drank the meanest fare while making offerings to ancestral spirits and gods with the utmost devotion proper to a descendant. He wore coarse clothes while sparing no splendour in his robes and caps on sacrificial occasions. He lived in lowly dwellings while devoting all his energy to the building of irrigation canals. With Yü I can find no fault.'

注释

【1】　Ode 195.

【2】　i.e., to have avoided, now that he was on the point of death, the risk of the mutilation of his body — a duty which he owed to his parents.

【3】　This is in contrast to the man 'who claims to have when he is wanting, to be full when he is empty' (Ⅶ.26).

【4】　According to tradition, this refers to Yen Hui.

【5】　The ch'ih in Tseng Tzu's time was much shorter than the modern foot.

【6】　The first ode in the Odes.

【7】　T'ang here is the name of Yao's dynasty and Yü the name of Shun's dynasty, not to be confused with T'ang the founder of the Yin or Shang dynasty and Yü the founder of the Hsia dynasty.

【8】　Yet Shun had only five officials.

【9】　In the case of King Wu.

Book Ⅸ

1．The occasions on which the Master talked about profit, Destiny and benevolence were rare.

2．A man from a village in Ta Hsiang said, 'Great indeed is Confucius! He has wide learning but has not made a name for himself in any field.' The Master, on hearing of this, said, to his disciples, 'What should I make myself proficient in? In driving? or in archery? I think I would prefer driving.'

3．The Master said, 'A ceremonial cap of linen is what is prescribed by the rites. Today black silk is used instead. This is more frugal and I follow the majority. To prostrate oneself before ascending the steps is what is prescribed by the rites. Today one does so after having ascended them. This is casual and, though going against the majority, I follow the practice of doing so before ascending.'

4．There were four things the Master refused to have anything to do with: he refused to entertain conjectures or insist on certainty; he refused to be inflexible or to be egotistical.

5．When under siege in K'uang, the Master said, 'With King Wen dead, is not culture (wen) invested here in me? If Heaven intends culture to be destroyed, those who come after me will not be able to have any part of it. If Heaven does not intend this culture to be destroyed, then what can the men of K'uang do to me?'

6．The t'ai tsai[【1】] asked Tzu-kung, 'Surely the Master is a sage, is he not? Otherwise why should he be skilled in so many things?' Tzu-kung said, 'It is true, Heaven set him on the path to sagehood. However, he is skilled in many things besides.'

The Master, on hearing of this, said, 'How well the t'ai tsai knows me! I was of humble station when young. That is why I am skilled in many menial things. Should a gentleman be skilled in many things? No, not at all.'

7．Lao[【2】] said, 'The Master said, "I have never been proved in office. That is why I am a Jack of all trades."'

8．The Master said, 'Do I possess knowledge? No, I do not. A rustic put a question to me and my mind was a complete blank. I kept hammering at the two sides of the question until I got everything out of it.'[【3】]

9．The Master said, 'The Phoenix does not appear nor does the River offer up its Chart.[【4】] I am done for.'

10．When the Master encountered men who were in mourning or in ceremonial cap and robes or were blind, he would, on seeing them, rise to his feet, even though they were younger than he was, and, on passing them, would quicken his step.[【5】]

11．Yen Yüan, heaving a sigh, said, 'The more I look up at it the higher it appears. The more I bore into it the harder it becomes. I see it before me. Suddenly it is behind me.

'The Master is good at leading one on step by step. He broadens me with culture and brings me back to essentials by means of the rites. I cannot give up even if I wanted to, but, having done all I can, it[【6】] seems to rise sheer above me and I have no way of going after it, however much I may want to.'

12．The Master was seriously ill. Tzu-lu told his disciples to act as retainers.[【7】] During a period when his condition had improved, the Master said, 'Yu has long been practising deception. In pretending that I had retainers when I had none, who would we be deceiving? Would we be deceiving Heaven? Moreover, would I not rather die in your hands, my friends, than in the hands of retainers? And even if I were not given an elaborate funeral, it is not as if I was dying by the wayside.'

13．Tzu-kung said, 'If you had a piece of beautiful jade here, would you put it away safely in a box or would you try to sell it for a good price?' The Master said, 'Of course I would sell it. Of course I would sell it. All I am waiting for is the right offer.'

14．The Master wanted to settle amongst the Nine Barbarian Tribes of the east. Someone said, 'But could you put up with their uncouth ways?' The Master said, 'Once a gentleman settles amongst them, what uncouthness will there be?'

15．The Master said, 'It was after my return from Wei to Lu that the music was put right, with the ya and the sung[【8】] being assigned their proper places.'

16．The Master said, 'To serve high officials when abroad, and my elders when at home, in arranging funerals not to dare to spare myself, and to be able to hold my drink — these are trifles that give me no trouble.'

17．While standing by a river, the Master said, 'What passes away is, perhaps, like this. Day and night it never lets up.'

18．The Master said, 'I have yet to meet the man who is as fond of virtue as he is of beauty in women.'

19．The Master said, 'As in the case of making a mound, if, before the very last basketful, I stop, then I shall have stopped. As in the case of levelling the ground, if, though tipping only one basketful, I am going forward, then I shall be making progress.'

20．The Master said, 'If anyone can listen to me with unflagging attention, it is Hui, I suppose.'

21．The Master said of Yen Yüan, 'I watched him making progress, but I did not see him realize his capacity to the full. What a pity!'

22．The Master said, 'There are, are there not, young plants that fail to produce blossoms, and blossoms that fail to produce fruit?'

23．The Master said, 'It is fitting that we should hold the young in awe. How do we know that the generations to come will not be the equal of the present? Only when a man reaches the age of forty or fifty without distinguishing himself in any way can one say, I suppose, that he does not deserve to be held in awe.'

24．The Master said, 'One cannot but give assent to exemplary words, but what is important is that one should rectify oneself. One cannot but be pleased with tactful words, but what is important is that one should reform oneself. I can do nothing with the man who gives assent but does not rectify himself or the man who is pleased but does not reform himself.'

25．The Master said, 'Make it your guiding principle to do your best for others and to be trustworthy in what you say. Do not accept as friend anyone who is not as good as you. When you make a mistake do not be afraid of mending your ways.'

26．The Master said, 'The Three Armies can be deprived of their commanding officer, but even a common man cannot be deprived of his purpose.'

27．The Master said, 'If anyone can, while dressed in a worn-out gown padded with old silk floss, stand beside a man wearing fox or badger fur without feeling ashamed, it is, I suppose, Yu.

　　Neither envious nor covetous,

　　How can he be anything but good?'[【9】]

Thereafter, Tzu-lu constantly recited these verses. The Master commented, 'The way summed up in these verses will hardly enable one to be good.'

28．The Master said, 'Only when the cold season comes is the point brought home that the pine and the cypress are the last to lose their leaves.'

29．The Master said, 'The man of wisdom is never in two minds;[【10】] the man of benevolence never worries;[【11】]the man of courage is never afraid.'

30．The Master said, 'A man good enough as a partner in one's studies need not be good enough as a partner in the pursuit of the Way; a man good enough as a partner in the pursuit of the Way need not be good enough as a partner in a common stand; a man good enough as a partner in a common stand need not be good enough as a partner in the exercise of moral discretion.'

31．

　　The flowers of the cherry tree,

　　How they wave about!

　　It's not that I do not think of you,

　　But your home is so far away.[【12】]

The Master commented, 'He did not really think of her. If he did, there is no such thing as being far away.'

注释

【1】　This is the title of a high office. It is not clear who the person referred to was or even from which state he came.

【2】　The identity of the person referred to here is uncertain.

【3】　The whole section is exceedingly obscure and the translation is tentative.

【4】　Both the Phoenix and the Chart were auspicious omens. Confucius is here lamenting the hopelessness of putting the Way into practice in the Empire of his day.

【5】　as a sign of respect.

【6】　Throughout this chapter the 'it' refers to the way of Confucius.

【7】　When Confucius, no longer in office, was not in a position to have them.

【8】　The ya and the sung are sections in the Odes.

【9】　Ode 33.

【10】　About right and wrong.

【11】　About the future.

【12】　These lines are not to be found in the present Odes.

Book Ⅹ

1．In the local community, Confucius was submissive and seemed to be inarticulate. In the ancestral temple and at court, though fluent, he did not speak lightly.

2．At court, when speaking with Counsellors of lower rank he was affable; when speaking with Counsellors of upper rank, he was frank though respectful. In the presence of his lord, his bearing, though respectful, was composed.

3．When he was summoned by his lord to act as usher, his face took on a serious expression and his step became brisk. When he bowed to his colleagues, stretching out his hands to the left or to the right, his robes followed his movements without being disarranged. He went forward with quickened steps, as though he was gliding on wings. After the withdrawal of the guest, he invariably reported, 'The guest has stopped looking back.'

4．On going through the outer gates to his lord's court, he drew himself in, as though the entrance was too small to admit him.

When he stood, he did not occupy the centre of the gateway;[【1】] when he walked, he did not step on the threshold.

When he went past the station of his lord, his face took on a serious expression, his step became brisk, and his words seemed more laconic.

When he lifted the hem of his robe to ascend the hall, he drew himself in, stopped inhaling as if he had no need to breathe.

When he had come out and descended the first step, relaxing his expression, he seemed no longer to be tense.

When he had reached the bottom of the steps he went forward with quickened steps as though he was gliding on wings.

When he resumed his station, his bearing was respectful.

5．When he held the jade tablet, he drew himself in as though its weight was too much for him. He held the upper part of the tablet as though he was bowing; he held the lower part of the tablet as though he was ready to hand over a gift. His expression was solemn as though in fear and trembling, and his feet were constrained as though following a marked line.

When making a presentation, his expression was genial.

At a private audience, he was relaxed.

6．The gentleman avoided using dark purple and maroon coloured silk for lapels and cuffs. Red and violet coloured silks were not used for informal dress.

When, in the heat of summer, he wore an unlined robe made of either fine or coarse material, he invariably wore it over an underrobe to set it off.

Under a black jacket, he wore lambskin; under an undyed jacket, he wore fawnskin; under a yellow jacket, he wore fox fur.

His informal fur coat was long but with a short right sleeve.

He invariably had a night robe which was half as long again as he was tall.[【2】]

Their fur being thick, pelts of the fox and the badger were used as rugs.

Once the period of mourning was over, he placed no restrictions on the kind of ornament that he wore.

Other than skirts for ceremonial occasions, everything else was made up from cut pieces.

Lambskin coats and black caps were not used on visits of condolence.

On New Year's Day, he invariably went to court in court dress.

7．In periods of purification, he invariably wore a house robe made of the cheaper sort of material.

In periods of purification, he invariably changed to a more austere diet and, when at home, did not sit in his usual place.

8．He did not eat his fill of polished rice, nor did he eat his fill of finely minced meat.

He did not eat rice that had gone sour or fish and meat that had spoiled. He did not eat food that had gone off colour or food that had a bad smell. He did not eat food that was not properly prepared nor did he eat except at the proper times. He did not eat food that had not been properly cut up, nor did he eat unless the proper sauce was available.

Even when there was plenty of meat, he avoided eating more meat than rice.

Only in the case of wine did he not set himself a rigid limit. He simply never drank to the point of becoming confused.

He did not consume wine or dried meat bought from a shop.

Even when he did not have the side dish of ginger cleared from the table, he did not eat more than was proper.

9．After assisting at a sacrifice at his lord's place, he did not keep his portion of the sacrificial meat overnight. In other cases, he did not keep the sacrificial meat for more than three days. Once it was kept beyond three days he no longer ate it.

10．He did not converse at meals; nor did he talk in bed.

11．Even when a meal consisted only of coarse rice and vegetable broth, he invariably made an offering from them and invariably did so solemnly.

12．He did not sit, unless his mat was straight.

13．When drinking at a village gathering, he left as soon as those carrying walking sticks had left.

14．When the villagers were exorcizing evil spirits, he stood in his court robes on the eastern steps.[【3】]

15．When making inquiries after someone in another state, he bowed to the ground twice before sending off the messenger.

16．When K'ang Tzu sent a gift of medicine, [Confucius] bowed his head to the ground before accepting it. However, he said, 'Not knowing its properties, I dare not taste it.'

17．The stables caught fire. The Master, on returning from court, asked, 'Was anyone hurt?' He did not ask about the horses.

18．When his lord gave a gift of cooked food, the first thing he invariably did was to taste it after having adjusted his mat. When his lord gave him a gift of uncooked food, he invariably cooked it and offered it to the ancestors. When his lord gave him a gift of a live animal, he invariably reared it. At the table of his lord, when his lord had made an offering before the meal he invariably started with the rice first.

19．During an illness, when his lord paid him a visit, he would lie with his head to the east, with his court robes draped over him and his grand sash trailing over the side of the bed.

20．When summoned by his lord, he would set off without waiting for horses to be yoked to his carriage.

21．When he went inside the Grand Temple, he asked questions about everything.

22．Whenever a friend died who had no kin to whom his body could be taken, he said, 'Let him be given a funeral from my house.'

23．Even when a gift from a friend was a carriage and horses — since it lacked the solemnity of sacrificial meat — he did not bow to the ground.

24．When in bed, he did not lie like a corpse, nor did he sit in the formal manner of a guest when by himself.

25．When he met a bereaved person in mourning dress, even though it was someone he was on familiar terms with, he invariably assumed a solemn expression. When he met someone wearing a ceremonial cap or someone blind, even though they were well-known to him, he invariably showed them respect.

On passing a person dressed as a mourner he would lean forward with his hands on the cross-bar of his carriage to show respect; he would act in a similar manner towards a person carrying official documents.

When a sumptuous feast was brought on, he invariably assumed a solemn expression and rose to his feet.

When there was a sudden clap of thunder or a violent wind, he invariably assumed a solemn attitude.

26．When climbing into a carriage, he invariably stood squarely and grasped the mounting-cord.

When in the carriage, he did not turn towards the inside, nor did he shout or point.

27．Startled, the bird rose up and circled round before alighting. He said, 'The female pheasant on the mountain bridge, how timely her action is, how timely her action is!' Tzu-lu cupped one hand in the other in a gesture of respect towards the bird which, flapping its wings three times, flew away.

注释

【1】　A position which would have been presumptuous.

【2】　It has been suggested that this sentence has got out of place and should follow the first sentence in the next section.

【3】　The place for a host to stand.

导读

人为何要读书？普鲁斯特在这些启迪心灵的文章中，阐述了约翰·罗斯金的思想及其作品之美，展现了他孩提时代沉浸于文学作品时那种忘我的欢乐，也借此探寻了我们阅读书籍时获得的种种愉悦、作出的种种尝试。

阅读普鲁斯特的作品是项挑战。部分原因是，读者没有那么多时间可用来熟悉他的写作风格。这也正是我首次阅读普鲁斯特的作品时的感受。他的文风引人入胜，令我对那些从未亲历的时代与地点充满怀恋。

普鲁斯特的许多文章貌似都是东拉西扯，但他在闲散漫谈时用的语言却清晰而简洁。读者每次随他“漫游”后总能回到话题原点，而且深觉不虚此行。

阅读普鲁斯特的作品是一大乐事，但读者们对他的写作手法持不同态度。我在阅读时，不得不改变心态，学会感受他文字的氛围，而非像通常那般随着情节或思路而感觉自己有所收获。开始的几页令人备感折磨，但知道作者将从容道来，读者便会任自己随他“漫游”，或者和他一起品味对生活的缓缓沉思。

本书首篇文章谈的是约翰·罗斯金如何增进了人们对艺术和建筑的理解与鉴赏，特别是他如何受到了基督教的启迪，揭示了艺术是如何在数个世纪里反映了基督教的伟大（当它确实如此时）并深入我们的情感，文中的每一实例都是与往古的一次亲密交流。这篇文章颂扬了我们的创造力所能创获的成就，也研究了我们自身。

儿童的脑海中总是充满了天马行空的纯真想象，因此那些回忆儿时的文章，特别是回忆儿时读书时光的文章读来十分回肠荡气。普鲁斯特展现了重读图书如何令往日时光重现，再现了艺术自古以来如何深刻地影响了人类思想，也再现了往昔的思想如何塑造了现代生活，遑论那些永恒的角色、书籍，以及那久久流传、人人同庆的欢乐。

“只要阅读这位‘煽动者’，能用它神奇的钥匙为我们打开内心深处我们本不懂得如何进入的所在，那么这‘煽动’也不无裨益。”

普鲁斯特的文章常常离题万里，句子结构纷纭多变，但却比狄更斯某些精推细敲的篇章更易理解。如今，我们的时间已经非常匮乏，书籍推荐每天都会新增无数，为何还要专门留出时间阅读普鲁斯特的作品呢？读者浸入书中的沉思乃是对作者人生的间接体验。就我而言，这种体验从未如此深透。上文所引已自证了本书的品质，此外我还可以找出更多例子来充分证明这一点。

本书同企鹅出版社其他“伟大的思想”系列图书一样，没有前言或注释（除非作者本人写作过程中加了自注），却价廉质优。尽管普鲁斯特不会适合所有人的口味，但我这篇简短的导读不会花费您太多时间，却可使您洞悉伟大的思想。希望您将来能充分享受深入探索思想的乐趣。

史蒂夫·约翰逊著
牛云平译

约翰·罗斯金[1]

1.一个个地，如同“离开了父亲阿波罗而为世界带去光明的缪斯”，罗斯金的思想相继离开那诞生它们的神圣头颅，化身在鲜活的书籍里，为各民族带去启示。罗斯金退隐于孤独之中：先知们的生命经常于此终结，直到这苦修者完成了自己超人的工作，上帝一时高兴将他召回。人们只能透过圣洁之手拉下的面纱来猜测那正在实现的神迹，那蕴藏了不朽于后世的易逝头脑的缓慢毁灭。

2.今天，死亡使人类拥有了罗斯金留下的巨大遗产。因为天才只有以其自身所承载的人类的榜样为蓝本，而非依据其凡人形象，才能创造出不朽的作品。他的思想在某种意义上暂时与他相伴一生。他死之后它们便回归全人类并予以启示。就像居斯塔夫·莫罗[2]在世时，人们知道居住在拉罗什富科街的尊贵家族是莫罗一家，而他死后那里便成为莫罗博物馆。

3.约翰·罗斯金博物馆（位于谢菲尔德）久已存在。博物馆目录仿佛是所有艺术与科学的缩影。大师绘画作品的照片与矿藏品相邻，就像在歌德的居所。同罗斯金博物馆一样，罗斯金的作品无所不包。他追寻真理，即便在编年表和社会法则里也能找到美。但逻辑学家们对“美术”的定义既然将矿物学和政治经济学排除在外，我在此便只谈及作为美学家和艺术批评家的罗斯金，以及他在一般意义上的“美术”作品。

4.有人说他是现实主义者。不错，他经常重申，艺术家应该致力于对自然的纯粹模仿，“不对任何事物加以摒弃、蔑视和选择”。

5.有人说他是知性论者，因为他写到，最好的绘画包含着最崇高的思想。论及在透纳[3]的《迦太基的建筑》一画的前景中玩耍小船的孩子们时，他总结道：“这一场景表现的是一种主导性的激情，那新兴城市的伟大未来便由此产生……此绝妙场景用词语和颜料均可表达，同绘画技巧无关，寥寥数笔亦可同精心设色的图画一样向心灵传达同样的思想。这思想远远高于所有艺术，它是最高意义的史诗。”密勒桑[4]引用了此段文字并补充道：“同样，在分析丁托列托[5]的《圣家庭》时，罗斯金凭借一段残垣和一个刚开工的建筑物发现了大师的不同凡响，艺术家以此让我们从象征意义上理解到耶稣的诞生是犹太经济的终结和新联盟的兴起。这位威尼斯画家的另一件作品《耶稣受难》被罗斯金视为杰作，因为艺术家通过一个表面上无足轻重的细节，即在受难地背景中啃食棕榈叶的一头驴子，来表达一种深刻的思想，即正是犹太物质主义——伴随着它对纯现世意义上救主的期待和进入耶路撒冷时的幻灭——从根本上导致了对耶稣所倾泻的仇恨及其死亡。”

6.有人说他过于强调科学在艺术中的作用，以至抹杀了想象力。他难道这样说过吗？“……画家必须以地质学和气象学的精确度了解每种岩石、土壤和云朵……每种地质构成都有其特点；决定性的裂纹造成了岩石和土壤的固定形态；特殊的植物还要因气候与海拔的不同加以细分……[画家]需观察植物色彩形状的每一特点……把握其或僵直或静穆……的线条……观察其当地习性，其对特定地点的偏爱或厌憎，某些特殊影响对它的滋养或摧残。他在头脑中把这一切同植物生活环境的所有特征结合起来……他必须用雨丝一般轻柔精妙的笔触表现出坍塌中的土壤那细微的裂纹、下降的曲线、还有波动的阴影……最伟大的绘画当最大限度地向观者传达最伟大的思想。”

7.相反，有人说他给予想象太大的空间，以至于毁了科学。不错，下面这段话不禁让人想起贝纳丹·德·圣皮埃尔[6]那天真的终极论，他说上帝将瓜果分成片只是为了方便人们享用：“……上帝在自己的创造物上使用色彩作为其最纯洁、最无辜、最珍贵之处的永恒陪衬；而在仅仅是有贵重物质用途或者有害的东西上则使用普通的颜色……看看鸽子的颈部，再比较一下蝰蛇的灰色后背……同样，鳄鱼是灰色的，而无辜的蜥蜴则有着美丽的绿色。”

8.有人说他使艺术沦为科学的附庸，因为他的理论认为艺术品使我们认识到事物的性质，甚至声称“一幅透纳的作品要比任何学院都能更多地呈现出岩石的属性”，以及“像丁托列托这样的艺术家举手之间便能揭示出关于肌肉活动的大量真相，足以令全世界的解剖学家汗颜”，但也有人说他在艺术面前贬低科学。

9.最后，有人说他是唯美主义者，他唯一的宗教便是美，因为事实上他一生热爱美。

10.另一方面，还有人说他甚至不是艺术家，因为他在对美的欣赏中掺入了别的思考，这些思考可能高于审美，但显然与审美无关。《建筑七灯》开宗明义，阐明建筑师需使用最珍贵最持久的材料，这一要求源于耶稣的牺牲，以及上帝所认可的这一牺牲的永久条件，我们没有理由认为这些条件已更改，因为上帝并未明确告知我们。在《现代画家》一书中，为解决色彩论与明暗论者之间谁对谁错的问题，他所采纳的论据之一是：“……从更广阔的角度来看自然界，将彩虹、日出、玫瑰、紫罗兰、蝴蝶、鸟雀、金鱼、红宝石、蛋白石、珊瑚等笼统地同鳄鱼、河马……鲨鱼、蛞蝓、骨殖、菌类、苔藓，以及所有那些腐蚀性的、尖锐的、毁坏性的东西相比较，你就能领悟到这问题在色彩论和明暗论者之间应如何定位——谁这边是自然与生命，谁那边是罪恶和死亡。”

11.既然关于罗斯金有这么多互相矛盾的说法，结论便是他就是自相矛盾的。

12.有关罗斯金面貌的许多个侧面，因为我们曾经见过而最熟悉的肖像，或者——如果我可以这么说的话——最令人着力研究、最成功、最震撼和最广为人知的肖像便是那个终其一生只以美为唯一宗教的罗斯金。

13.对美的顶礼膜拜是罗斯金终其一生的活动，这可能是千真万确的。但我认为他生命的目标，他深刻、秘密而长久的意图藏于他处，我这么说并非为了反对德·拉·西兹拉纳[7]的观点，而是为了防止用一种错误的但却似乎是自然而然、不可避免的解释使读者在心目中低估这些观点。

14.不仅罗斯金的主要信仰是宗教本身（我稍后将回到这一点，因为它支配并反映了他的美学观），只在目前就其“美的宗教”而言，我们的时代必须警醒地认识到，如果我们想要忠实于罗斯金，我们就不能说出这个词而不重新考虑其含义，因为人们很容易赋予其浅薄的唯美意义。实际上，在这个猎奇的唯美时代，所谓美的膜拜者是这样的人，他不奉行其他信仰，也不承认任何其他神祇，终生沉溺于对艺术品心醉神迷的观赏。

15.但是，出于一些超出这篇短文范畴的纯粹超验的原因，如果人们只是因为快感而热爱美的话，这热爱便难成正果。正如为幸福而寻求幸福只会使人感到乏味，要找到幸福必须寻找别的什么，同样，如果我们为了美而热爱美，把它当作存在于身外，远比它带来的快乐重要得多的真实的事物，我们会额外地获得审美快感。罗斯金远非浅薄猎奇的唯美主义者，恰好相反，他是卡莱尔[8]式的人物，天生警惕所有享乐的虚荣，本能地察觉到身边那永恒现实的存在。这类人天赋超群，拥有把握现实的能力，并满怀激情，好像听命于灵魂一般将自己短暂流逝的一生献给这全能而永恒的现实，并为之带来价值。他们关注而焦虑地面对着等待解释的宇宙，某位引领他们的神灵、某种他们听得到的声音为他们宣示着这现实的一些部分，使之昭显于天才的永恒灵感。罗斯金的特殊天赋在于美感，无论在自然界还是在艺术中。他的天纵禀赋驱使他在美中追寻现实，从而将全部的宗教生命投身于审美之中。但他并不将自己为之献身的美视为享乐，而是把它看作无上重要的现实，宁愿为此献出生命。你会看到罗斯金的全部美学便来源于此。你首先要理解的是，他认识一个新的建筑或绘画流派的年代很可能是他道德生命的重要里程碑。在谈到哥特式建筑向他呈现的年代时，他就如基督徒谈到真理昭示的日子，带着同样的肃穆，同样反复的感动，以及同样的安详态度。他一生中的事件均属于灵智的范畴，那些重要的日子是这样一些时刻，比如当他洞察了一种新的艺术形式的时候，那一年他理解了阿布为利[9]，那一年他理解了鲁昂[10]，还有那天，他感到提香[11]的绘画及其画作上的阴影要比鲁本斯[12]的绘画及阴影更加高贵的时刻。

16.随后你要理解的是，和卡莱尔一样，对于罗斯金来说，诗人便是誊写者，听从自然的指示书写其或多或少重要的秘密，而艺术家的第一要务就是丝毫不将自己的印记加诸神示。从这个高度来看，对罗斯金的指责，无论说他是现实主义还是知性主义，都可以像笼罩大地的云彩一般烟消云散了。这样的批评意见是无的放矢，因为它们瞄准得还不够高。它们站错了高度。艺术家必须记录的现实既是物质的又是精神的。物质是真实的，因为它是心灵的表现。没有人比罗斯金更擅长嘲讽那些认为艺术品是单纯模仿表象的人。他说：“无论模仿的主题是英雄还是他的马，单纯模仿的乐趣都将正好是同样的程度（如果准确度可以相等的话）……我们既可以认为眼泪是出于痛苦，也可以认为是出于艺术，但不能认为同时出于两者。如果我们把它当作艺术的眼泪而惊叹，那我们就不可能把它当作痛苦的眼泪而感动。”如果说他如此看重事物的外表，那是因为单从外表便可揭示出其深刻的本性。德·拉·西兹拉纳出色地翻译过罗斯金的一段话，其中说明一棵树的“主导”线条可以让我们发现哪些惹事的树曾把它挤到一边，什么样的风曾折磨过它，等等。一个物体的构形不单单是其本性的形象，还是其命运的线索和历史的痕迹。

17.这种对艺术的看法还产生了另一个后果，那就是：如果现实是唯一的，天才是能够看到这现实的人，那么，他用来表现这现实的物质，无论是绘画、雕塑、交响乐、法律还是行为，又有什么重要性呢？在《英雄与英雄崇拜》中，卡莱尔将莎士比亚和克洛维尔[13]，穆罕默德和彭斯[14]相提并论。爱默生[15]则将斯维登堡[16]和蒙田[17]一并列入他的《代表人物》。该体系的过火之处在于未能对反映这唯一现实的不同方式加以足够深刻的区分。卡莱尔说因为薄伽丘[18]和彼特拉克[19]是优秀的诗人，他们便一定会是优秀的外交家。罗斯金犯了同样的错误，他说：“绘画之美能够到达这样的程度，即它用画面所传达的思想独立于画面的语言。”如果说罗斯金的思想体系有任何偏差，那在我看来便体现于此。因为绘画无法达到事物的整体现实，因而无法同文学竞争，除非它不是文学性的。

18.罗斯金规定艺术家的职责便是严格服从自身天才的“声音”去传达现实，因为他本人有过这样的经验，了解什么是真正的灵感，什么是不息的热情和丰饶的景仰。尽管在我们每个人身上激起热情与景仰并启发灵感的原因各不相同，但我们最终都会赋予它一种尤为神圣的特征。可以说，对于罗斯金，这启示和向导就是《圣经》。

19.在此，在罗斯金美学的重心处，像在一个定点，让我们稍作停留。这样看来，他的宗教感指引着他的审美感。首先，对于这类观点，即认为他的美感因之而变质，认为他在对建筑、雕塑和绘画的欣赏中掺入了本不应有的宗教思考，我的回答是正好相反的。罗斯金在艺术品所激发的情感中深刻地体会到一种神圣，正是这情感的深邃与独特之处，决定了他的品位而不会使之变味。与人们常常认为的相反，他在表达这情感时带着虔诚的景仰，小心翼翼不加丝毫歪曲，这使他从来不会在对艺术品的感受中掺入任何与之无关的矫饰的思辨。因此，把他看成一个道德家或布教者，热爱艺术中非艺术的东西，或者无视他审美情感的深刻本质，将之混同于享乐的唯美主义，这两种观点同样是错误的。所以，最终，他的宗教热忱标志并巩固着他审美的真诚，并使之免受任何外界的干扰。他那崇高美学中的某一概念是否有误对我们来说无关紧要。所有对天才的发展规律略知一二的人都知道，天才更多是由其信仰的力量来衡量，而不在于这信仰的对象从常识角度看所带来的某种满足感。但既然罗斯金的基督教精神便是其精神气质的本质，他同样深邃的艺术爱好必然与之有着密切关系。所以，正如他对透纳风景画的热爱与他对为自己带来巨大快乐的自然的热爱相对应，与他思想中深刻的基督教本质相对应的是他对法国中世纪的建筑与雕塑及意大利中世纪的建筑、雕塑和绘画等可称为基督教艺术的恒久不变的钟爱，它支配着他全部的生命，全部的作品。无需在其生活中寻找痕迹，他的著作便可证明他对这些艺术品的无私热情。他的阅历是如此丰富，以致他在一部作品中所显示出的最精深的学识，在别的作品中，即便是恰如其分，也常常不再利用，甚至连提都不提，哪怕是稍作暗示。他的学识极为渊博，不但将其言论供我们借鉴，而且送给我们不再收回。比如，你知道他就亚眠[20]大教堂写了一本书。你可能会得出结论认为那是他最热爱或最了解的教堂。但在《建筑七灯》中，鲁昂大教堂提到了40次，贝叶[21]大教堂提到了9次，亚眠则一次未曾提及。在《阿诺河谷》中，他吐露最令他心醉的哥特教堂是特鲁瓦[22]的圣于尔班教堂。但在《建筑七灯》和《亚眠的圣经》中却只字未提该教堂。就《建筑七灯》不曾提及亚眠大教堂一事，你也许会猜想是因为他快到生命结束时才认识亚眠？绝非如此。1859年，在肯辛顿的一次讲演中，他将亚眠大教堂的金圣母雕像同夏尔特尔[23]大教堂中支撑西门廊的雕像进行了长时间的比较，认为后者在艺术技巧上稍逊一筹，但有着更深刻的情感。而在人们认为他集中了自己所有关于亚眠的思想的《亚眠的圣经》中，在许多讨论金圣母雕像的篇幅里，他只字未提夏尔特尔大教堂的雕像。这便是他无比丰富渊博的爱与学识。通常，一名作家会一再援引自己喜爱的例子，甚至重复某些观点的阐发，这提醒我们，面前是一个凡人，他有特定的生活，有特定的知识来取代一些别的知识，他还会尽量利用自己有限的经验。但只要查看一下罗斯金著作中的索引就可以知道，他引用的作品永远是新的，他会轻易舍弃仅用过一次的某样知识，甚至永不再使用，这让我们感到某种超人的东西，或者不如说给我们留下这样的印象，即每部书都是由不同的作者写就，他拥有不同的知识，不同的经验，另类的人生。

20.他用自己无穷无尽的财富从事着一场愉快的游戏，从他奇妙的记忆珠宝箱中永远能取出新的珍宝：今天是亚眠大教堂珍贵的玫瑰窗，明天是阿布维利门廊上的金色花边，又将它们融合于令人眩目的意大利宝藏。

21.他的确能这样从一个国家转换到另一个国家，因为他在比萨[24]的石刻中顶礼膜拜的灵魂同样赋予了夏尔特尔石刻不朽的形式。对于从阿诺河岸延伸到索姆河岸的中世纪基督教艺术，没有人拥有他那样的整体感，他在我们心中实现了那些伟大的中世纪主教们对“基督教的欧洲”的梦想。如果像人们所说，他的名字必然同前拉斐尔派[25]密切相连，那么我们应该明白这里所说的前拉斐尔派不是透纳之后，而是源于拉斐尔之前。今天，我们可以忘记他对亨特、罗塞蒂、米莱斯所做的工作，但不能忘记他对乔托、卡尔帕乔、贝利尼[26]所作的贡献。他天神般的工作不在于唤醒生者，而在于使死者复活。

22.在一些篇章里，他的想象力用来自意大利的神奇光芒照亮了法国的石像，这难道不是处处显示出中世纪基督教艺术的整体性吗？刚才我们看到他在《英国的快乐》中比较亚眠大教堂中的爱德雕像和乔托笔下的爱德女神。在《哥特式的性质》中，且看他如何以鲁昂的圣马克鲁教堂的门廊为例，将意大利哥特式和法国哥特式建筑对火焰饰的处理进行比较。在《建筑七灯》中，请看意大利的色彩是如何变幻于这同一座门廊的灰色石刻的。

23.“门楣中心处浮雕的主题是末日审判，其地狱部分带有一种力量，那令人生畏的丑怪只能让我描述为奥尔卡涅[27]和贺加斯[28]思想的混合。那些恶魔可能比奥尔卡涅的更加可怕。对极端绝望中堕落人类的表现也至少能与英国画家贺加斯相媲美。同样狂野的是想象力，它将愤怒与恐惧体现在所有雕像的安排上。一名恶天使扇动翅膀，带领被判罪的众人从审判椅前经过……这些人被他如此狂怒地驱赶着，不仅一直被赶到此场景的尽头——该场景被雕塑家限定在门楣中心的其他地方——而且出了门楣进入到拱顶的壁龛里。而追随他们的火焰仿佛在天使翅膀的猛击下弯曲，也一路迸发着直冲入壁龛，最下面的三个壁龛表现为正在熊熊燃烧，其通常为拱形凸起的顶盖各被一个恶魔占据，他翅膀合拢，在黑影中。”

24.他并不仅仅停留于对不同种类的艺术和不同国家的类比，他将有更深入的发现。异教形象和基督教形象中某些宗教思想的一致性将令他震惊。阿利·勒南[29]十分深刻地指出在居斯塔夫·莫罗的普罗米修斯中已含有耶稣的成分。罗斯金对基督教艺术的虔诚从未使他蔑视异教艺术，他怀着审美感和宗教感比较了圣热罗姆[30]的狮子与尼米亚猛狮[31]，维吉尔[32]与但丁[33]，参孙[34]与赫拉克勒斯，忒修斯[35]与黑王子[36]，以赛亚[37]与库米女预言家[38]的预言。罗斯金和居斯塔夫·莫罗当然没有可比之处，但我们可以说对原始艺术的了解在他们身上孕育出一种自然的倾向，使他们两人都反对在艺术中表现狂暴的情感，至于对象征形象的研究，这一倾向使他们对形象本身的崇拜带有某种拜物性，不过这种拜物性并无甚危险，因为他们的思想植根于形象所代表的情感，可以在各个形象间转换，不会为单纯表象的多样化所羁绊。说到在艺术中全面禁止表现狂暴的情感，除了《米开朗基罗与丁托列托之关系》[1]中的篇章，哪里还能找到对勒南称为“美丽的无为”的原则更好的定义？难道不正是对中世纪法国和意大利艺术的研究使他对象征形象产生了几乎排他性的崇拜吗？由于他在艺术品之下寻找的是时代的灵魂，夏尔特尔教堂大门的雕像与比萨壁画之间的相似之处必然会触动他，让他认为这表明了启发艺术家灵感的典型的精神特质，而其不同之处则恰好证明了后者的多样性。换成任何其他人，审美感受都有可能被推理所冷却。但对他而言，一切均是爱，他心目中的圣像研究不如称为圣像崇拜。在这一点上，艺术批评让位给一些可能更加崇高的东西。它几乎具有科学的程序，是对历史的贡献。教堂的门廊上出现的一些新的特征使我们得知不仅在艺术史而且在文明史上所产生的变化，就如同出现在地球上的新物种让地质学家所了解到的文明史上的变化同样深刻。自然界的鬼斧神工并不比艺术家的雕刻更具启发性，一件保存着古老神怪的石刻也并不比一件表现一个新的神祇的石刻对我们更有意义。

25.从这个角度看，伴随罗斯金文字的绘画意义重大。在同一个图版上你可以看到出现在利兹由、贝叶、维罗纳和帕多瓦的同样的建筑图案，就好像某一品种的蝴蝶在不同气候地区的变种。但他如此热爱的石刻对他来说从来就不是抽象的例子。每一块石刻上都凝聚着那流逝岁月的细微变化与许多个世纪的色彩。他告诉我们：“……赶在太阳从塔尖上落下之前跑过街道再去看一看圣维尔佛朗大教堂，这就是我们珍存过去——直到最终的原因。”他甚至走得更远。他并不将教堂本身与其背景，即它们浮现于其中的那些河流和山谷区分开来，就像在原始绘画中一样。最能说明这一点的是“我们的父辈告诉我们”中题为“亚眠，死者纪念日”的第二幅版画作品。在那些因为罗斯金的驻留而不朽的城市，如亚眠、阿布维尔、博韦和鲁昂，他或者在教堂写生（“而不受教徒们的干扰”），或者在露天写生。他带领的素描者和版画家在这些城市是多么可爱而转瞬即逝的一群人，就像柏拉图为我们描绘的跟随着普罗泰哥拉[39]辗转于各个城市的智者们，又像喜欢栖息在教堂的古老屋顶和塔楼上的群燕。也许我们还能与罗斯金的一些弟子偶遇，他们伴随着他去到了重新皈依的索姆河岸，仿佛又回到了圣佛尔明和圣萨尔瓦的时代，他们在聆听这位新使徒的言谈，他像解释《圣经》一样解释亚眠时，记下的不是笔记，而是速写，而保存着这些优美记录的文件当能在一些英国博物馆找到，我猜想它们会以维奥莱—勒—杜克[40]的风格对现实略加改动。版画《亚眠，死者纪念日》看上去美得不真实。难道仅仅是那将亚眠大教堂和圣洛教堂拉近的加宽的索姆河岸的远景不真实吗？不错，罗斯金可能会再次把他在《鹰巢》中引用过的透纳的话拿来回答我们，德·拉·西兹拉纳将之翻译如下：“……早年的透纳心情好时会向人展示他的创作。一天他正在画一幅普利茅斯港的画，其上可见逆光处距离一两英里远的一些船只。他向一位海军军官展示这幅画，那军官惊奇地端详了一阵，以十分正当的不满抗议说那些船只没有舷窗。‘没有，’透纳说，‘当然没有。如果你登上艾支康布山，逆着夕阳观看那些船只，你会发现你看不到舷窗。’‘不错，可是，’海军军官仍然不满地说，‘你明知是有舷窗的。’‘是的，’透纳说，‘我很清楚。但我的工作是画我所看到的，而不是我知道的。’”

26.如果在亚眠，站在朝向屠宰场的方向，你会看到和版画里一样的景象。你会看到，由于距离的缘故，以艺术家虚幻而美妙的眼光来看，建筑物的分布方式有所改变，但如果你走近些，它们又会回到早先十分不同的位置。比如，你会看到一座水塔的形状印在大教堂的正面，因而从三维几何中产生出一种平面效果。但如果你还是发现从你的角度看到的饶有意味的景象仍然同罗斯金的画作有所不同，你不妨归咎于在罗斯金逗留过后几乎20年的时光给城市外观带来的变化，就像他本人谈到他热爱的另一处：“从我上次在那儿作画或者思考以来，发生了很多的改观。”

27.但至少《亚眠的圣经》中的这幅版画会在你的回忆中将索姆河岸和大教堂紧密相连，要比你亲眼所见更加密切，无论你处在城市的哪个位置。这幅画比我所说的一切都更好地证明罗斯金从不将大教堂之美同其所处的乡村魅力分割开来，每个参观者都能领会到这种魅力，它依然存在于那独特的充满诗意的乡村，还有他在那里度过的下午时分或朦胧或金色的回忆。不仅《亚眠的圣经》的第一章命名为“在水边”，罗斯金计划撰写的关于夏尔特尔大教堂的书也将题为《厄尔之泉》。因此他不仅仅在绘画中将教堂置于河岸，而且将哥特式大教堂的伟大同优美的法国风光联系在一起。[2]我们会更加敏锐地感受到某处风景的个性魅力，如果我们不是拥有那魔法靴似的高速火车的话，如果我们还像从前那样，为到达某个偏远之地，不得不途经许多个乡村，它们与我们的目的地渐趋一致，就好像渐次递进的和谐之地，让外界元素难以进入，并以一种温柔而神秘的方式保护着它，使之免于雷同，不仅在自然界将之环绕，也在我们的头脑中为看到它作好了准备。

28.罗斯金对基督教艺术的研究仿佛印证着他的基督教思想，还有其他我们无法在此阐发的思想，其中最著名的应该稍后让罗斯金本人进行定义：即他对机械主义和工业艺术的厌恶。“所有美好的事物都创造于中世纪，当人们笃信基督教纯粹、欢乐与美好教义的时候。”从那之后他认为艺术随着信仰一同衰落，技巧取代了情感。当他看到创造美的力量是信仰时代的专利时，他只会更加强烈地信奉信仰的善。他最后的著作《我们的父辈告诉我们》中的每一卷（只有第一卷已完稿）都将包括四个章节，其中前三章讨论信仰，最后一章研究因信仰而诞生的杰作。就这样，孕育了罗斯金审美情感的基督教被无上神圣化了。当他领着身为新教徒的女读者来到圣母像前的时候，他嘲笑她道：“你必须理解，无论是玛利亚崇拜还是任何其他女性崇拜……都从未对任何人造成过伤害”，或者在圣奥诺雷的雕像前，哀叹“在以他命名的巴黎市郊，人们现在很少谈起”这位圣徒，随后，他还可能像在《阿诺河谷》的结尾处那样说：“世人哪，耶和华指示你何为善，他向你所要的是什么呢？只要你行公义，好怜悯，存谦卑之心，与上帝同行。”如果你关注人类的生存境遇，你会发现这样的遵从总是会得到现世赐福的报偿。如果你背离那可悲可悯的残酷野心，那无所皈依的轻慢信仰，而去关注那些无人在意的芸芸众生，关注他们在沉默中的劳作，谦卑中的膜拜，就如基督教王国的雪带来了耶稣诞生的回忆，或者春日阳光让人想起他的复生，你就会了解伯利恒天使的许诺的确成了现实；你就会祈祷如阿诺河岸一般欢乐的英国田野还能将其最纯洁的百合奉献给花中的圣玛丽。

29.最后，罗斯金的中世纪研究，加之他坚信信仰之善，证实了他的信念，即人类需要工作来获得自由、欢乐与个性，无需机械主义的干扰。在此我录下一段极具罗斯金特点的话，你就能更好地理解这一点。他谈到的是鲁昂大教堂书商门廊处数百个微型雕像中一个仅几厘米高的小人像。

30.“……这狡黠的家伙看上去不安而困惑。他的手用力压着自己的面颊骨，眼睛下面的肌肉因这压力皱了起来。如果你把它同精细的版画相比，整个形象看上去的确拙劣粗糙。但考虑到它只是为了填充教堂大门外部的缝隙，而且是三百多个雕像中的一个（我的估计还不包括外部基座），它证明了当时艺术中蕴含的极为高贵的生命力……”

31.“我们有些工作是为了谋生，那需付出辛苦；其他工作是为了乐趣，那需要热忱：这两种工作都需要意愿，不能够三心二意；不值得付出努力的便根本不必去做。也许我们所做的一切只不过是对心灵和意志的训练，其本身毫无用处。但无论怎样，如果不值得我们动手出力，它可能有的那一点用处也无必要了。同我们的尊严不相称的投机取巧，或者忍受某种本无必要的器械夹在中间，这都配不上我们的不朽：情愿不用自己的双手而用器械去创造的人也会，如果可能的话，送给天堂里的天使们一些手摇风琴以便他们更轻松地演奏音乐。人类生活中已然充斥着白日梦、世俗性和感官享受，无需我们将少有的闪亮时刻机械化。既然我们的生命充其量不过是转瞬即逝的气体，就让它至少像高空的云朵般浮现，而不是像笼罩在狱火和转轮之上的浓重黑影。”

32.我承认，在罗斯金去世之时重读这段文字的时候，我产生了想去看一看这小人像的欲望。于是我去了鲁昂，仿佛听命于某种遗嘱，仿佛罗斯金在临终时将这可怜的造物托付给了他的读者，这造物因他的文字而复生，并且在不知情中永远失去了这个同最初的雕刻者一样对自己意义重大的人。但当我走近那巨大的教堂，站在阳光沐浴下满是圣徒像的门前时，我向上看，从刻满了伟大国王的柱廊一直到我以为空无一物的最高处，但就在那里，一位隐修士离群索居，任鸟儿在他的额上停留，另一处，在一群鸽子飞翔的翅影下，一群使徒正在聆听身边一位合拢翅膀的天使的预言，不远处，一个背负孩子的人像正以一种突兀却亘古的姿势转过头来。当我看到门廊前或塔楼栏杆处这成排的雕像，这座神秘城市中呼吸着阳光或清晨的阴凉的石雕客人们，我意识到我不可能在这非凡的群像中找到一个几厘米高的人像。我还是去了书商门廊处。但如何从数百座雕像中认出那一个小人呢？突然，一位年轻有为、前途远大的雕塑家L.伊特曼女士对我说：“这个看上去很像。”我们稍往下看，看到……就在那儿。它还没有十厘米高。已相当残损，但那目光仍在，石头上仍然有托出瞳孔的洞，那表情让我认出它来。就在那儿，在上千座雕刻中，一个死去已几百年的艺术家留下了这个小人，它每天死去一点，它早已死去多时，永远，失落在那众多雕像中。但他把它安放在那儿。一天，来了一个人，一个对他来说不存在死亡，不存在物质的无穷尽，不存在遗忘的人，他把那压迫我们的虚无远远抛开，去追求支配他一生的目标，那些他无法全部实现而我们却缺乏的目标，这个人来了，他为那些仿佛波涛般参差的石雕逐个命名，从中看出了生命的所有法则，灵魂的所有思想，并说着：“看，这是这个，这是那个。”正像不远处表现的审判日，他的声音如天使长的号角一般回响：“那些活过的还会活着，物质无关紧要。”的确，就像在这门楣不远处所表现的死者，他们被天使长的号角唤醒，起来重新恢复了自己的形状，再次充满生机，让人可以辨认，同样，那小人像也重新复活，恢复了他的目光，审判长说：“你已活过，你应活着。”他自己并非不死的法官，他的身体会死去。但那有什么！他从事着不朽的工作，就好像他不会死去，并不在意那占据他时间的物体的大小，并且，虽然只有一次人生，他却面对一座教堂无数雕像中的一个消磨数日的时光。他把它画下来，毫不在意自己已近暮年。对他来说它应和着头脑中旋转的思想。他画下它，谈论它。那丑陋的、与世无争的小人便从那似乎比所有其他雕像都要绝对的死亡中复苏，它湮灭于无数因相像而籍籍无名的群体，唯有天才才能让我们迅速指出它来。在那里重新发现这小人像，我们只有感动。它好像还活着，还在凝视着，或者不如说就在那凝视中被死亡攫去，就像那些动作戛然中止的庞贝人。实际上被静止的岩石所凝固于此的正是雕刻家的思想。在那里再次发现它让我感动。曾经活着的都没有死去，无论是雕刻家的思想还是罗斯金的思想。

33.与这小人像的邂逅对罗斯金是必要的，他罕有的几幅作为插图（《建筑七灯》）的版画之一便以它为主题，因为对他来说它是其思想真实而持久的一部分，这邂逅对我来说则是愉快的，因为他的思想对我是不可或缺的，他指引着我自己的思想，我们两人在途中不期而遇，我们感到自己同那些在门楣上雕刻了末日审判群像的艺术家们心意相接，他们相信个体，作为个人及其意志的最独特之处，不会死去，而是保存在上帝的回忆中，终将复活。哈姆雷特和掘墓人，一个看到的仅仅是个头盖骨，另一个因之浮想联翩，他们两人谁对呢？科学会说：掘墓人；但它忽略了莎士比亚，他会令这冥想的回忆持续下去，即使那头盖骨已成灰烬。在天使的召唤下，每个死者都还在那里，各得其所，而我们以为他们早已归于尘土。在罗斯金的召唤下，我们发现了那最小的人像，它构成一个微小的四叶饰，从其形态中复生，以其不变的目光，那占据了不到岩石一毫米见方的目光凝视着我们。无疑，可怜的小丑八怪，我本眼拙，本无法从这城市成千上万的石块中找到你，辨认你，还你以个性，呼唤你，令你复活。无穷、无数、虚无压垮了我们，并非由于它们强大，而是因为我的心灵不够强大。不错，你真是毫无美感。我本来永远不会注意到你凄惨的面容，你并无有趣的表情，不过你当然有，就像每一个人都有他人从不具有的表情一样。但既然你曾活着，继续用那同样歪斜的目光凝视着，能让罗斯金注意到你，并在他说出你的名字之后，让他的读者能认出你，你现在是否活得足够，是否被爱得足够？人们想着你的时候只会充满温情，尽管你神情丑恶，因为你是活的造物，因为，在那漫长的世纪里，你早已死去，没有复活之望，又因为你复活了。这些天里也许另一个人会在那大门上寻找你，温情地注视你倾斜丑怪的面庞，那已复苏的面庞，因为出自一个人的心灵的东西会在某一天截获另一个心灵，后者又深深吸引我们的心灵。你是对的，待在那儿，无人理睬，逐渐塌裂。从那物质中你毫无指望，置身其中你不过是虚无。但那些小小的人像无须惧怕什么，死者也是一样。因为有时神灵会造访尘世。他所过之处死者复生，那些几乎被忘却的面容重新凝眸注视着生者，后者为了这些面容抛开那些不再活着的生者，只在神灵启示之处，在早已化为尘土但却仍然包含着人类思想的石块中找寻生命。

34.阳光以其飘忽的微笑投向那些古老教堂亘古的美丽，这个人用更多的爱与欢乐笼罩着它们，如果我们用心去了解，他是不会错的。精神世界便如同物质世界，一座喷泉的高度超不过水最开始降落的高度。文学之大美对应着一些什么，在艺术中，激情便是真理的标准。假设作为批评家的罗斯金对一部作品价值的判断有时不甚准确，但他错误判断中的美常常超出他所评判的作品的美，并对应着一些虽非作品本身，但只会同样珍贵的东西。罗斯金论及“亚眠的美丽神像”时说“没有一座雕像能够或者应该满足懂得信仰基督的热忱灵魂的希望。但这座雕像所传达的温柔慈爱在当时已无其他作品能及”，而于斯曼先生[41]将这同一座亚眠的神像称为“长着绵羊脸的矜骄子弟”，我们并不相信罗斯金是错误的，也不认为于斯曼是正确的，但正确与否无关紧要。那“亚眠的美丽神像”是否如罗斯金所想，这对我们毫不重要。正如布丰[42]所说：“（一种美丽风格）所具有的智性之美，及其所有的组合关系，都构成了有益的真理，而且，对公众思想来说，也许比其所针对的主题的真相还要宝贵。”那么，在《圣经》一书中，讨论有关亚眠之美丽神像的段落之美自有其真理和价值，独立于雕像本身之美，但罗斯金若以轻蔑的口气谈论这雕像，他就无从发现这些真理，只要拥有热情，他便拥有了发现真相的力量。

35.我们将永远无从知道，也无论如何无法在此探寻的，是他那了不起的灵魂是以怎样的忠实反映宇宙的，而谎言是以怎样令人迷惑的形式潜入了他理智的诚实中。无论答案如何，如果我们想要了解和热爱美的一个新的部分，那么我们中间即使是天生聪颖的人也需要那些“天才”的指引，而罗斯金便是其中之一。我们这代人在思想交流中所说的许多话都带有他的印记，就好像硬币上君主的肖像。在冥界他继续启迪着我们，就像那些早已熄灭的星星，其光芒仍然照耀着我们，他在透纳去世时所说的话我们可以用在他身上：“通过这深深坟茔中永远闭合的双眼，尚未出生的后世将看到自然。”

36.“谎言是以怎样诱人而华美的形式潜入了他理智诚实的深处……”我想说的是：没有人比罗斯金本人在《艺术演讲录》中更好地定义了偶像崇拜：“我大体上如此认为，虽说这也会产生一些良好的后果，因为每种大恶都在其逆流中带有些许的善——我认为，无论是在异教的还是在基督教的土地上，无论是体现为华丽的言辞还是色彩，抑或美丽的形式，艺术的致命功能在深层意义上确实可称为偶像崇拜——它令我们竭尽心智服务于我们为自己创造的一些或珍贵或悲伤的幻象，当我们违背了主耶稣的现世召唤，他没有死去，也没有昏倒在十字架下，而要求我们掮起我们自己的十字架。”

37.现在看来在罗斯金工作的基础上，在他天才的源头，确实存在着这种偶像崇拜。无疑他从不允许它完全掩盖——即便是作为修饰——他的理智和道德的真诚，完全使之僵硬、瘫痪并最终毁掉它。他写下的每一句话，如同他生命中的每一刻，都表现出他需要用真诚与偶像崇拜相对抗，真诚宣布着偶像崇拜的虚荣，并令美屈从于义务，即便这义务是不美的。关于这一点我不会从他的生活中寻找例子（他并不像拉辛、托尔斯泰或梅特林克，他们的生活中审美为先，道德为后，在他的生命中道德感从一开始就在其美学思想的最中心确立了特权——同时从未像我刚刚提到的这些大师那样完全、释放它。）我无需重复这道德感的各个阶段，它们已广为人知，比如早期他为一边喝茶一边观看提香的画作而感到羞愧，直到后来，把父亲留给他的500万尽数花在社会和慈善事业上之后，他决定卖掉透纳的作品。但唯美主义在他身上并不是以一种主动外在的方式（他已将之克服）表现出来，而以一种更加隐秘的形式存在，他的偶像崇拜和他的诚实感之间的真正决斗并不发生在他生活的某些时刻，也不在他著作的某些段落，而是终其一生，在那些最深最隐秘之处，那些我们自己几乎未知的地方，在那里我们的性格从我们的想象中获得意象，从理智中获得思想，从回忆中获得词语，并不断地从中作出选择以证明自己，不断地在某种意义上以我们的道德与精神生活的命运为赌注。我感到在那些地方，罗斯金从未停止过犯下偶像崇拜的罪过。就在他鼓吹真诚的时候他却缺乏真诚，不是其内容而是其方式。他的教诲是道德的而非审美的，但他却为了美而选择教义。由于他想呈现的并非其美而是其真，他不得不就选择它们的真正原因对自己撒谎。因此他不断地违背良心，以至于对他思想的正直诚实性来说，更危险的可能是那些言不由衷、屈从于他不曾承认的审美偏爱的道德宣言，倒不如他去真诚地鼓吹不道德的信条。事实上，选择对一件事情如何解释，对一件作品如何评价，以及如何遣词造句时，他不断地犯下这罪——最终导致虚伪的态度，而心灵总是退让。为让读者能够更好地评判罗斯金的障眼法——出自他笔下的障眼法不但为别人，也是为他自己——我将引用在我看来他最美但其罪过也最昭彰的一段文字。你会看到，如果说在理论上（在表面上，也就是说一个作者思想的内容始终是表象，其形式则是现实）美是从属于道德感和真理的话，在实际上则是真理和道德感从属于审美感，一种多少被那些无休止的妥协所扭曲的美感。引文的主题是“威尼斯衰落的原因”。

38.“大理石凿就透明的力量，拱门排列成虹彩，这并非出于财富的挥霍，也并非为了徒劳地满足感观的欲望或人生的自豪。在那色彩中写着一个预言，它曾经写在血液里；在那穹顶中回响着一个声音，它有一天将回荡在天堂的穹顶，——‘他将回来作出判决并带来公正。’他赋予威尼斯强大，只要她将之铭记：当她遗忘，她将毁灭；她无可挽回地毁灭了，因为她毫无理由地遗忘。从没有一座城市有过更加光彩夺目的圣经群像。在北方的国度里，粗糙阴郁的雕像以其混乱难以辨认的图像充满了庙宇。但在威尼斯，东方的技艺和珍宝为每一个字母镀金、为每一幅书页敷彩，直到那圣书如同伯利恒之星在远处闪闪发光。在其他城市，人们常常在与宗教无关的地方聚会，常常导致暴力和变乱。在那些危机四伏的城墙的茅草中，在那些混乱街道的尘土里所达成的一些事务或协约，我们若不能为之正名，有时尚可以原谅它们。但威尼斯的罪恶，无论是在宫殿还是在广场，都是在她右手持着《圣经》的时候犯下的。篆刻着基督戒条的大理石墙同保护着城市议会或关押着政治犯的围墙只有数英寸之隔。当她在最后的时光抛开所有的羞耻与约束，当城市广场为全世界的疯狂所充斥，请记住她的罪行是加倍的严重，因为这罪行就发生在闪耀着主的法则的上帝的殿堂前面。骗子们和戴假面具者狂笑而去；并非没有预警的沉默随之而来；在这一切中间，穿越无数个世纪积聚的虚荣和腐烂的罪恶，圣马可大教堂白色的穹顶对威尼斯死去的双耳说道：‘记住，为所有这一切上帝会带来他的审判。’”

39.如果罗斯金对自己完全诚实的话，他就不会认为威尼斯人的罪行要比其他人的更不可原谅，应受到更严厉的惩罚，因为他们的教堂不是用石灰岩而是用华彩的大理石建成，因为总督的宫殿就在圣马可大教堂旁边而不是在城市的另一头，还因为在拜占庭教堂里，用镶嵌画构成的《圣经》篇章不像在北方教堂的雕像那样朴素，而是伴以摘自福音书或预言录的烫金字母。不错，这段出自《威尼斯之石》的文字优美动人，尽管难以解释其缘由。这美在我看来是建立在谎言之上，我不愿对它低头。

40.但这其中必定是有些真理的。在严格的意义上没有完全错误的美，因为伴随着对真理的发现而产生的愉悦正是审美愉悦。难以判断的是这段文字给读者带来的强烈的愉悦感所对应的是何种真理。这段话本身便是神秘的，同时充满了美和宗教的意象，正如圣马可教堂，在那里所有出自《旧约》和《新约》的形象都呈现在一种华美的黑暗和闪烁明灭的灿烂背景之上。我记得我第一次读到这段文字时恰好在圣马可教堂，在一个风雨大作的黑暗时分，当那些镶嵌画只以自身的物质之光，以一种内在的、尘世的和古老的金色而闪耀，即便是威尼斯的太阳，那令钟楼上的天使仿佛在燃烧一般的太阳都无法再增加其光芒。在所有这些衬着四周黑暗的明亮天使中间，我在读到这段文字时产生的情感十分强烈，但也许并不十分纯洁。正如我在看到这些美丽而神秘的形象时油然而生欢乐一样，但当我看到在它们笼罩着光环的额头旁边以拜占庭手写体出现的经文时，那欢乐便因这学识的愉悦而黯淡，同样，罗斯金的意象之美因他对《圣经》的贸然影射而活跃并遭到损害。这欢乐中难免有自恋的回归自我，其中学识掺杂了艺术，审美愉悦也许能更强烈但无法保持纯洁。因此，《威尼斯之石》中的这段文字之美也许首先在于它恰恰让我感到了在圣马可教堂所感到的那种混合的欢乐，因为它正像那拜占庭教堂一般，在阴影衬托下炫目如镶嵌画般的文体的意象旁撰刻着《圣经》的语录。更何况，这段文字难道不是正如圣马可教堂的镶嵌画吗，其目的在于说教，不在于艺术之美？今天，除了愉悦它再不能给予我们任何东西。而这说教带给学者的乃是一种自私的愉悦，艺术家所感受到的最无私的愉悦仍然来自于美，那些以教育为目的的人轻蔑甚或无视这美，把它当成额外之物。

41.在《亚眠的圣经》的最后一页，“如果……你将在意那承诺”这段话是一个类似的例子。还是在《亚眠的圣经》里，罗斯金以这句话结束关于埃及的部分：“她是摩西的监护人和耶稣的主人。”我们可以接受摩西的监护人这一说法：为了教育的目的有些说教是必要的。但耶稣的“女主人”一说也许能为句子增色，但它真的适用于对埃及神灵之美德的理性评估吗？

42.我一直在与自己最珍视的审美印象作斗争，试图将理智之真诚推向极限。还需要补充吗，如果我耽于这广义的评释，或在某种意义上耽于这绝对性，这并非针对罗斯金的作品，更多的是有感于其深刻的启迪性和美感，而他对我来说仍然是所有时代和国度最伟大的作家之一。我并非抨击罗斯金特有的某一缺点，而是试图将他作为特别有利于思考的“主题”，来探索人类思想中固有的缺陷。读者一旦完全理解了这“偶像崇拜”的含义，他便可以对自己解释为什么罗斯金在评论中极其看重艺术品中的烫印文字（我在序言中过于简略地指出了他重视文字的另一个原因），以及为什么他错用了“不敬的”和“傲慢的”这两个词：“我们无需破解的秘密，或我们因傲慢而想要去攻克的困难”“让艺术家别信任选择的精神，那是一种傲慢的精神”“一个不敬的人很可能认为中殿太窄，而不是拱顶太高”，等等——以及这两个词所揭示的精神状态。想着这偶像崇拜的时候（我也想到了罗斯金将句子均衡排列时感到的愉悦，似乎这种均衡为他的思想带来了对称感，而不是由思想来指导语句的对称）[3]，我说过：“我不必寻找那些令人迷惑的形式，谎言借此潜入了他理智之诚实的深处。”但正好相反，我本应寻找它们，而且如果我继续躲在这种本质上是罗斯金式的崇敬形式之后的话，本会犯下同样的偶像崇拜罪。并非我不了解崇拜的益处，它正是爱的条件。但在爱中止的地方，敬仰永远不能代替爱，让我们不加辨别地相信，并在信任的基础上崇拜。更何况罗斯金会第一个赞同我不赋予他的文字以绝对的权威，因为他甚至对《圣经》都拒绝这权威：“……将绝对真理同任何形式的人类语言联系起来是毫无可能的……”但他喜欢“敬仰”的态度，他相信“破解秘密是傲慢的”。为把偶像崇拜的问题作一个了结，也为了更确定我和我的读者之间关于这点不再有误解，我想请来一位我们时代最为人所称道的人物（他在其他地方同罗斯金毫无相似之处！），他在其谈话中，而不是作品中，表现出了这个错误，而且表现得如此淋漓尽致，很容易让人辨认和演示，再不需要费力地放大它。在谈话中他被偶像崇拜所——愉快地——折磨着。那些曾经听过他谈话的人会发现我的“模仿”颇为生硬，他的风趣迷人在其中荡然无存，不过人们仍然能从下面的叙述中猜出我想援引的是哪位同代人。这个人曾满怀仰慕地从一位悲剧女演员身上看出与居斯塔夫·莫罗的画作《年轻人与死神》中死神所穿的同样的衣料，或者发现一位女性友人的长裙和发型与“卡迪央王妃第一次见到大丹士[43]那天一模一样”。他在看到那女演员的衣料或者那上流女子的长裙时为这高贵的联想而感动，惊呼：“多美啊！”但这美并非衣物之美，而是因为它出于莫罗的画作或巴尔扎克的描写，因而变得永恒地神圣……对于这位偶像崇拜者。在他的卧室你会看到一种牡丹花，或插在瓶中，或由他的画家朋友绘在墙上，因为这种花出现在韦兹莱[44]的圣玛德莱娜教堂。同样，他怀着虔诚的崇敬珍藏着一些曾属于波德莱尔或米什莱或雨果的物品。这种敬奉以其特殊的愉悦，给予我们的偶像崇拜者以灵感，让他的即兴谈话机智而风趣，令我极为享受，甚至深深为之吸引，丝毫不愿为此与他纠缠不休。

43.但就在我极度享受这谈话的同时，我问自己，这无与伦比的谈话者——还有让他一直说下去的听众——是否同样犯了不诚实的罪；是否因为一朵花（受难花）上带有耶稣受难的印记，把它送给异教徒便是渎神，或者一所房子是否因为曾是巴尔扎克的居所（如果那里不再有什么关于巴尔扎克的东西）就更加美丽？如果仅仅因为一个女子的名字同《吕西安·娄凡》[45]的女主角一样是巴蒂尔德，我们是否真的应该，除了赞扬她的美貌之外，还要更偏爱她呢？

44.卡迪央夫人的衣着是巴尔扎克的美妙发明，因为它让我们获悉她的艺术趣味，以及她希望在大丹士身上留下的印象和她的一些“秘密”。但是一旦去除了它所包含的意义，它就只不过是一个去掉了含义的符号，亦即空无；如若继续对它顶礼膜拜，甚至在一个现实生活中的女人身上发现它时达到心醉神迷的程度，那就是真正的偶像崇拜。这是艺术家们钟爱的理智之罪，他们中很少有人能不为之倾倒。幸运之罪啊！你会情不自禁这样说，当你看到它使他们创造出多少美妙作品的时候。但他们至少不应该毫无反抗地屈服。自然界任何一种特殊的形式，无论多美，其价值均只在于它自身所代表的那一部分无限之美。就连盛开的苹果花和粉色的山楂花亦然。我对这些花儿的爱是无限的，每年春天因离它们太近而产生的烦恼（花粉病）足以证明我的爱并非人人能及。但即使是对它们，对这些毫无文学意义、无关任何审美传统的花朵，这些并非用罗斯金的话来说是“丁托列托某幅画中所能看到的实际的花朵”，也并不出现在我们的那位同代人会提到的列奥纳多的某幅素描中（在他为我们揭示的许多事物中，有一样就是现在人人谈论但在他之前无人注意的——威尼斯学院素描），我也总是要小心避免产生一种排他的崇拜感，这种崇拜感可能在令我愉悦之外赋予这些花儿一些别的东西，并且，因了这种崇拜，我可能以自恋的方式使它们成为“我的”花朵，并且用描绘着它们的艺术品装饰我的卧室来专门向它们致敬。不，我不会因为艺术家在前景中描绘了一朵山楂花而认为这幅画更美，尽管我不知道还有比山楂花更美的东西，因为我想保持真诚，我知道一幅画的美与其所画的东西无关。我不会收集山楂花的图像。我不会对山楂花顶礼膜拜，我只去观赏并呼吸它的芬芳。在此我任由自己短暂地进入了当代文学的领域——这绝非冒犯——因为在我看来经过这般放大，尤其是经过如此大力的鉴别之后，读者便能够清楚地看出罗斯金身上蕴藏的偶像崇拜的特征。无论如何，我请求我的这位同代人，如果他在我这张拙劣的速写中认出自己，请相信我毫无恶意，正如我说过的，我需要走到对自己真诚的极限才能就这一点对罗斯金提出批评，并在我对他的绝对景仰中发现这一脆弱之处。因此，不仅“同罗斯金共享批评丝毫无损其名誉”，而且我认为赞美他的最好方式就是把对罗斯金的批评用在他身上。我几乎遗憾自己过于谨慎，没有吐露他的名字。因为当一个人被允许来到罗斯金的身边，即便只是处于奉献的态度，只是为了举起他的书来好让别人更好地阅读，那也是一种荣誉而非惩罚。

45.回到罗斯金。我对他已如此“习以为常”，因此要想掌握这偶像崇拜的证据，研究其性质，并探索在那最深切的文学愉悦感之外我有时感受到的轻微的虚假造作之感，我需要深深进入自我。但在我刚开始热爱他的著作时，这偶像崇拜一定曾常常令我震惊，随后我才逐渐对这缺陷视若无睹，就好像恋爱一样。同一个人的恋爱有时会以利欲开始，随后才得到净化。一个男人接近一个女人是因为她能帮他达到一个与她无关的目标。一旦他了解了她，他便因为她本身而爱她，并毫不犹豫地为她牺牲那在她帮助下实现的目标。所以最早在我对罗斯金著作的热爱中掺杂了一些自私的东西，即我能在智识上从中获益的愉快。事实上，从最初的阅读中感觉到那力量和魅力后，我便努力不去抵制它们，不同我自己过度争辩，因为我感到，如果有一天罗斯金的思想对我的吸引力扩大到他触及过的一切，简言之，如果我彻底迷醉于他的思想，那么我在此之前一直未知的一切，包括哥特式教堂，还有英国和意大利的绘画，将大大丰富我的世界，因为这一切将唤醒我身上沉睡的渴望，而没有它便永远不会有真正的知识。因为罗斯金的思想与诸如爱默生[46]等人的思想不同，后者将一切囊括于一本书中，是某种抽象的东西，纯粹自身的符号。而与罗斯金的思想密不可分并贯彻其中的并不是非物质的东西，它散落在地球的表面。人们必须到处寻找，去比萨、佛罗伦萨、威尼斯、国家美术馆、鲁昂、亚眠，以及瑞士的山脉。这样的思想有其自身之外的物质实体，在空间自我实现，不再是无限而自由的，而是受到限制和约束，化身于大理石雕像、白雪覆盖的山峦、绘画中的面庞。也许不如纯粹的思想神圣，但它令宇宙，至少是某些部分，某些叫得出名字的部分更美，因为它触动了这些部分，促使我们去爱——如果我们愿意理解的话——进而去了解。

46.是的，宇宙突然间又为我呈现出无尽的价值。我对罗斯金的景仰使得他让我学会去热爱的东西变得无比重要，在我看来比生命本身还要珍贵。事实的确如此，有一次我认为自己来日无多。我出发去威尼斯，为的是在死前去接近、触摸那化身于中世纪本土建筑宫殿中的罗斯金的思想，那些宫殿虽然在衰败中，却依然挺立，依然鲜活。像威尼斯这样一座如此特殊而具体地定位于时空的城市，对于一个即将告别人世的人来说，到底具有什么样的重要性和现实意义呢？我可能在那里研究并从活生生的例子中验证的有关本土建筑的理论又如何能够成为“支配死亡，让我们对它无所畏惧，甚至使我们热爱它的真理”（勒南）呢？天才的力量在于让我们热爱美，让我们感到它比我们自身还要真实，它存在于那些他人看来和我们自身同样特殊而易逝的东西之中。

47.诗人说：“如果你的眼睛这么说，我便说它们是美的。”这并非完全正确，如果诗里的眼睛指的是被爱者的眼睛。在某种意义上，同样从诗歌的立场来看，无论爱可能为我们带来怎样精彩的补偿，自然总会因之失去诗意。对于恋爱中的男子，地球充其量是为情人那“可爱的孩子般的双足所准备的地毯”，而自然无非是“她的庙宇”。爱情一方面为我们揭示了许多心理方面的深刻道理，另一方面又使我们对自然不再具有诗意的感受，因为它将我们封闭在一种自私的心理状态中（爱情是最高程度的自私，但仍然是自私），使我们很难产生诗意。相反，对某人思想的崇敬则在每一步都激发美，因为它不断激起对美的欲望。凡俗的人通常以为听凭我们所崇拜的书籍的引导会使我们失去独立判断能力。“罗斯金所感与你何关：你自己去感受。”这种看法犯了心理学的错误，不会为有信仰的人所认可，因为信仰使他们的理解力和感受力都得到了无限提高，而且从未损害其批判力。因了这纯粹的天恩惠顾，我们所有的能力、批判意识及其他意识都大为提高。因此这种自愿的服从是自由的开始。感受自我的最好方式便是努力去感受大师之所感。从这深深的努力中我们同大师的思想一道发现了自己的思想。只有拥有目标，我们才有自由的人生：我们早已揭穿那关于冷漠的自由的诡辩。那些不断掏空自己的思想，试图摆脱所有外界影响以保持个性的作者其实是在无意中听从一种同样天真的诡辩。事实上，我们唯一真正能够完全依赖自己理智的全部力量的时候，恰恰是我们不相信我们是在独立行动的时候，是我们不为自己的努力任意选择一个目标的时候。小说家的主题，诗人的意象，哲学家的真理，它们均以一种几乎是必然的方式强加于他们，可以说外在于他们的思想。正是通过把自己的思想用于传达那意象、接近那真理，艺术家才真正变成他自己。

48.但是在谈到对罗斯金思想的激情——开始多少有些矫饰但到后来如此深刻的时候——我谈到的是由回忆之光所照亮的，仅限于追述事实，“但丝毫无法重新拥有遥远过去”的回忆。只有当我们生命中的某些时段永远结束，当我们即使仿佛拥有那力量和自由时也被禁止偷偷开启通向它们的大门，当我们连一刻也无法回到我们曾经久处其中的状态时，只有在这些时候我们才拒绝接受这些事已被彻底抹去了。我们无法再歌唱它们，因为我们未能听从歌德智慧的告诫，即只有在我们还能够感知的事物当中才有诗歌。但如果无法重新点燃过去的火苗，我们希望至少还能收拾其灰烬。因为无法复活我们业已无能为力的东西，我们希望至少还能描述它、了解它，带着我们保存的关于它的冰冷回忆——关于那些事实的回忆，它告诉我们：“你曾是这样或那样的”，但我们已无法回去，它证实了失落的天堂，不可能在回忆中复原。只有当罗斯金离我们远去的时候我们才诠释他的著作，试图尽可能近似地把握他思想的特点。因此你将听到的并非出自我们的信仰或爱的声音，你将在这儿那儿窥见的只是我们的虔诚，它寂静漠然，像那个底比斯的处女般忙于修复一座坟茔。

【注释】

[1]同样，在《阿诺河谷》中，圣马可雄狮是尼米亚雄狮的直接后代，其鬃毛就是在加马里纳的赫拉克勒斯头上可见的，在书中其他地方指出其区别在于“那个赫拉克勒斯杀死了野兽并用它的皮做成头盔和斗篷；希腊人则让野兽皈依并使它成为布教士”。（《阿诺河谷》，8，cciii.）

我引用这段文字不是为了给尼米亚雄狮找到另一个神圣的后裔，而是为了强调《亚眠的圣经》这一章结尾处的总体思想，即“存在着神圣的古典艺术”。罗斯金不想将希腊（《阿诺河谷》）同基督教相比，而只想将它同哥特艺术相比，“因为圣马可同赫拉克勒斯一样是希腊人”。在这里我们接触到了罗斯金最重要的思想之一，或更确切地说他为希腊和基督教艺术品的思考与研究带来的最独特的情感之一，要想完整地传达这情感必须摘录《圣马可的栖息》中的一段，这段文字在我看来最清晰地表现出罗斯金独特的思想态度，即他并不看重基督教的降临，却在异教作品中认出一种基督教艺术之美，并描绘出一直贯穿到中世纪作品中的顽强的希腊理想。很肯定地，这种在我看来是完全审美的思想态度至少在本质上是符合逻辑的，如果说在来源上不遵守时代顺序的话，罗斯金将这思想系统化，扩大至历史和宗教批评。但即使是当罗斯金将希腊王权同法兰克王权相比（见《阿诺河谷》中的“法国化”一章），或者在《亚眠的圣经》中宣称“基督教并未过多改变人类道德与幸福的理想”，或者像我们在前面所述谈到贺拉斯的宗教时，他所作的一切都是从审美愉悦中得出理论性的结论，就像他在重新发现诸如希罗底的女像柱、天使中的哈比、拜占庭庙宇中的一只希腊花瓶时一样。下面就是这段出自《圣马可的栖息》的文字：“不光拜占庭艺术，这一点适于所有的希腊艺术……今天让我们别再用……‘拜占庭’这个词。只有一个希腊学院，从荷马的时代一直到塞尔沃总督的时代。圣马可的这些镶嵌画是真正蕴含着代达罗斯的力量，带有希腊的建筑灵感……就像库普赛罗的胸膛或厄瑞克修姆庙的门柱。”

罗斯金随后进入圣马可洗礼堂，说道：“大门上方是希律的宴会。希罗底的女儿头上顶着施洗者约翰的头颅在舞蹈，——完全是希腊花瓶上希腊女子头顶水瓶的翻版……现在接着进入穹顶深处更远的小教堂。那里更加黑暗，非常黑暗。——我的昏花老眼几乎分辨不出什么，但你若有一双年轻明亮的眼睛，你应看出那美，因为它确是贝利尼、契马和卡尔帕乔所绘的所有金顶的根源；它本是一只希腊花瓶，带着新的神祇。在圣坛后的壁龛里有一只十翼天使，胸上有一圈的文字，‘智慧充盈’。这确是圣灵的呼吸。但它曾经是一个希腊哈比，其鸟爪般的四肢虽已毁损但仍依稀可见肌肉……其上，耶稣在一群天使的环绕下出现并降落，正如同贝利尼和卡尔帕乔的天顶画不过是这哈比天顶的放大，丁托列托的天堂亦不过是这狭窄穹顶所包含的思想的最终结果……毫无疑问这些镶嵌画不会早于13世纪。然而它们在所有的思想方式和表达形式上都是绝对希腊式的。那火焰和喷泉完全是客迈拉和佩瑞涅的形状；那舞蹈的少女，尽管是13世纪身穿袖口镶白鼬皮长袍的公主，却一如阿卡狄亚泉边汲水的甜美的希腊少女。”（《圣马可的栖息》，第92页及以下。引文不是连续的。）又比如罗斯金说：“我相信我是唯一还同希罗多德一道思考的人。”任何一个思想敏锐、足以被一名作家的面貌特征所吸引的人，一个不为有关罗斯金的种种无聊说法——说他是先知、预言家、新教徒等其他无甚意义的说法——所动的人，都会感到他的面貌特征，尽管是次要的，却是十分“罗斯金式”的。罗斯金同所有时代的伟大灵魂生活在一起，他只在意他们能够回答那些永恒的问题，对他来说没有什么古典和现代之分，他可以像谈论一个当代人那样谈论希罗多德。古人对他来说除了在“目前”能够对我们的日常思考有所帮助之外没有别的价值，他便并不把他们当作古人。因此他们所说过的所有那些未因过时而被抛弃、也不被视为只属于某一特定时代的话语对他来说更加重要，它们在某种意义上将其曾经拥有但为时间所剥夺的科学价值保存了下来。从荷拉斯描绘班都斯亚泉的方式，罗斯金推断说他是虔诚的，“以弥尔顿的方式”。就在13岁时，他为了消遣阅读阿那克里翁的赞歌，从中发现“非常肯定地，希腊人就像我一样喜爱鸽子、燕子和玫瑰，后来对希腊艺术的研究证明这一点对我极为有利”。（Praeterita,lxxxi.）显然，对于爱默生这样的人，“文化”有着同样的价值。但我们暂不去耽于两者之间的深刻差别，为了强调罗斯金面貌的特殊之处，让我们首先指出，由于他对科学和艺术一视同仁，他在谈到作为科学家的古人和谈到作为艺术家的古人一样满怀崇敬。关于自然史的发现，他引用了第104篇赞美诗，关于一个宗教史问题他同意希罗多德的观点（恰同当代科学家的观点相反），他很欣赏卡尔帕乔的一幅画，认为它为鹦鹉的描述史作出了重大贡献（《圣马可的栖息》：“奴隶的圣坛”）。显然我们很快应该回到他的古典神圣艺术观，“只有一个希腊艺术，圣热罗姆和赫拉克勒斯，等等”，每一个这样的观念又引向其他。但此刻我们面前只有这样一个深深留恋着自己藏品的罗斯金，他对科学和艺术一视同仁，相信一项科学理论能够始终正确，正如一件艺术品能够始终美丽（他从未明确提出这一观点，但它暗中支配着其他所有的观点，没有它其他都将成为不可能），他会为了自然史或思辨哲学去求证于一首古代赞歌或者一件中世纪浮雕，因为他深信任何年代任何国度的智者都比哪怕是当代的愚人更值得去咨询。当然，他恰如其分的批判意识始终约束着这一倾向，让我们对他可以完全信任，他的夸张仅仅是为了开个诸如“13世纪昆虫学”等的小玩笑。

[2]从英国人眼中看法国风景，这会是多么有趣的展品：透纳笔下的法国河流；波宁顿的“凡尔赛”；沃尔特·佩特的“奥塞尔”或“瓦朗西安”，“韦兹莱”或“亚眠”；斯蒂文森的“枫丹白露”；还有更多更多！

[3]我现在没有时间阐明这一缺憾，但我猜想通过我的翻译——尽管它很乏味——读者能够看出，就像透过强光照亮的厚厚的鱼缸玻璃，思想被语句迅速地驱赶，在瞬间受到损害。

阅读的日子（一）

1.我的童年过得最充实的日子也许就是那些我以为我不曾生活过的日子，那些伴随着一本心爱的书度过的日子。在那些日子里，每一件与他人有关的事，每一件被我当作是对那神奇享受的庸俗妨碍而推开的事：正读到最有趣的段落有小伙伴来找我玩耍，讨厌的蜜蜂或一束阳光使我不得不从书页中抬起头来或者变换姿势，为我端来的茶点放在旁边一动未动，而在头顶的蓝天，太阳的威力正在减弱，我必须回去用晚餐，其间唯一的念头就是饭后直接上楼读完剩余的章节。阅读本应让我觉得这些事不胜其烦，但相反，它们镌刻在我心中的回忆是如此甜美（在我现在的感受中要比当时如此全心阅读的东西珍贵得多），以至于到今天，我有时还会去翻阅这些过去的书籍，那只不过是将它们作为唯一保存了逝去日子的日历，希望在那些书页中还能找到早已消失不在的房屋和池塘的影子。

2.谁会不记得，如我回忆之中，那些假期中的阅读时光，一天中所有那些安宁不受干扰、足以庇护阅读的时光。上午，从公园回来之后，当其他人都去散步时，我会溜进餐厅，在那儿，一直到尚遥远的午餐时间，除了年迈寡言的费利西之外没有人会进来，我唯一的、最尊重阅读的同伴，便是挂在墙上的彩盘，刚刚撕下前一页的日历，自言自语不求回答的钟表和炉火，它们的窃窃私语不具意义，不像人类的话语一般用别的意义取代你正在阅读的语句。我会坐在一张椅子上，在一小堆柴火旁边，关于这火我那早起的照管花园的叔叔会在午餐时说：“这可不碍什么事！我们容得下这点儿火的，你知道六点钟的时候菜园里可真冷。想想吧，离复活节只有一星期了！”离我不得不中断阅读的午餐时间还有整整两小时。时而能听到要流出水的水泵的声音，让我抬头透过关着的窗户注视它，那儿紧挨着小花园的一条幽径，环绕着用砖和半月形陶瓷装饰的三色堇花坛：这些三色堇好像是从天上摘下来的，那无比美好、色彩斑斓、仿佛倒映在有时能从村庄的房顶之间看到的教堂彩窗上的天空，有时出现在暴风雨之前的惨淡天空，或者在那之后，很晚了，暮色即将降临。不幸的是，厨娘会早早进来安放餐具，要是她能不说话该有多好！可她觉得自己有必要说：“您看上去不太舒服，我把桌子挪近点好吗？”仅只回答一句：“不用，谢谢。”我就得将嘴里的声音从远处召回，令它戛然中止，而它正在无声而流利地念诵着眼睛看到的所有词语。我得停下，再发出声音，还它以早已遗失的日常表象和应答的语调，只为了礼貌地发出一句“不用，谢谢”。时间在流逝，常常离午餐时间还早就开始有人来到餐厅，有人走累了，选了一条捷径，从“梅塞格里斯路”回来，或者有人要“写点东西”，那天早晨没有出去散步。当然，他们会说：“我不想打扰你。”但他们立刻开始走近柴火，看看时间，表示现在就吃饭也不错。无论是谁“留下来写点东西”，他们都会带着一种特别的敬意含笑对他或她说：“您在保持通信呐。”这笑容里含着尊敬、神秘、猥亵和小心，就好像这小小的“通信联系”既是国家机密，又是一种特权、一种暧昧关系和一种病态。有人不再等待，早早坐在自己的位置上。这真叫人难过，因为他们给后来者树立了个坏榜样，让他们以为已经是中午了，我的父母便会过早地说出那句致命的话：“好了，合上书，我们要吃午饭了。”万事倶备，桌布上摆好了每个人的餐具，没有上桌的只是在餐后才会摆上来的器具，比如我那既是园丁又是厨师的叔叔用来在桌上亲手泡制咖啡的玻璃壶，那好像物理仪器般复杂、味道芳香的管状器皿，看着那突然产生的沸腾泡沫升上玻璃罩，将芬芳的褐色余渣留在充满蒸汽的内壁，这实在让人愉快。还有奶油和草莓，我这位叔叔总是以同样的比例将之调和，以五彩画家的经验和美食家的预见性精确地达到他要求的粉色。这午餐显得多么漫长啊！我的婶祖母对每道菜肴浅尝辄止，便能以一种大度却不容置疑的平静提出她的见解。对于她所精通的小说或诗歌，她总是以女性的谦卑对其他更有见地的人的意见表示尊重。她相信那属于随心所欲的范畴，个人的喜好无法作为真理去评判。但对于那些由母亲传授的规矩与准则，比如怎样烹调某些菜肴，怎样演奏莫扎特的奏鸣曲，或者什么是优雅的待客之道，她确信自己知道怎样做才恰如其分，并能够判断他人做到了几分。何况，这三样事具有同样的完美标准：简洁、适度、迷人。她憎恶在菜肴中加入并非必需的调味品，矫揉造作或过多使用踏板的演奏，以及在待客时不具备完全自然态的自己。只要尝一口菜，听头几个音符，看一眼便笺，她就称自己知道面前是不是一个好厨师，一个真正的音乐家，或者一位有教养的女子。“她也许技巧比我熟练，但她演奏那段简单的行板时过于夸张，说明她毫无品位。”“她也许是个出色的女子，但在这种场合夸夸其谈可见其缺乏分寸。”“她也许是个在行的厨子，但她不会做土豆煎牛排。”正因简单所以难做的土豆煎牛排是一个理想的比赛项目，好比烹饪中的悲怆奏鸣曲，在美食方面等同于社交生活中一位夫人前来询问有关仆人的事，从这件简单的行为中便可看出她是否知分寸有修养。我祖父自尊心十足，希望每一道菜成功，但极不擅烹饪，从来不知道何处不妥。他很想承认有些菜确有不妥之处，但那十分罕见，而且完全是出于意外。而我婶祖母那永远有理有据、暗示厨子不会做菜的批评必然让祖父难以忍受。为了避免和他争论，婶祖母经常忍住不发言，只用嘴唇碰一下那道菜，但我们即刻便知道那为她所不喜。她保持着沉默，但从那双慈爱的眼睛里看得出深思熟虑、不可动摇的否认，令祖父狂怒。他会嘲讽地请她发表意见，对她的沉默很不耐烦，不断地向她提问，大发脾气，但我们能感到婶祖母宁愿忍受折磨也不愿承认祖父所相信的：点心并不是太甜。

3.午餐之后我立刻重新开始读书，特别是天气十分暖和的日子，所有人都上楼回到卧室，我也马上沿着一节窄仄的楼梯回到自己的屋子，它在很低的单独一层，从窗台上轻易就能直接跳到外面街上。我去关上窗户，但仍未能躲开对面的枪炮匠同我打招呼，他趁着放下雨篷的机会，每天午饭后在门前抽烟斗，同过路人打招呼，他们有时会停下来和他聊天。梅坡公司[47]和英国室内设计师们严格遵守的威廉·莫里斯[48]的理论规定，一间卧室是否漂亮的唯一条件是它只陈放对我们有用的物品，而任何有用的物品，哪怕是一枚钉子，都不应遮盖而应暴露在外。在这些洁净的卧室里，在完全裸露的铜条床架之上，光秃秃的墙上挂着几幅名画的复制品。以这样的审美观来看，我的卧室绝谈不上美，因为里面充满无用的物品，它们谦逊地挡住了那些还有些用处的东西，让人用起来极为困难。但对我而言，我的房间之美正源于这些不为我方便、只为其自身愉悦而存在的物品。高高的白色帷帐挡住了视线，床仿佛隐蔽在一所祭坛深处；散落的绸料压脚被、花朵图案的床罩、刺绣被套、细亚麻布枕套，我的床在白天消失在所有这一切东西的下面，好像玛丽月花彩之下的祭坛，到了晚上，为了能睡觉，我得把它们小心地放在旁边的扶手椅上，让它们在那儿过夜；床边，蓝色花纹的三件套玻璃制品，配套的糖罐和水罐（我到达的第二天姑母便嘱咐我里面不要盛水，怕我碰倒它），好像某种宗教仪式的器具——几乎同旁边小玻璃瓶中珍贵的白色香橙花液体一般神圣——它们如同圣体盒一般，我不会冒犯它们，更不会私自使用它们，但我会在脱衣之前长时间地凝视它们，担心不小心碰倒它们；那些小小的镂空钩编长巾为椅背覆盖了一层白色的玫瑰，它们一定有刺，因为每当我阅读完毕准备起身时都会发现自己被挂住了；用玻璃罩围起来以防被不慎碰到的钟对着来自远方的贝壳和一朵古老的伤感之花窃窃私语，它十分沉重，很难抬得起来，一旦停摆，除了钟表匠以外没人会鲁莽地给它上发条；白色的镂空花边布像覆盖着祭坛一样罩着五斗橱，其上装饰着两只花瓶、一幅圣像和一支圣枝，就像是圣餐桌（每天整理完卧室之后摆在那里的祈祷跪凳更让人产生如此联想），但它开松的边线总是夹进抽屉的缝隙中，让抽屉完全无法工作，即使为拿一条手帕出来我也必须将圣像、圣花瓶和圣枝全部拿下来，而且总是跌跌撞撞，不得不抓牢跪凳。最后还有薄布窗帘、沉重的细布窗帘和更沉重的花缎窗帘组成的三重窗帘，它们在阳光照耀下总是像山楂花一样明亮喜人，但每当我想要打开或关上窗户，它们就会笨重而顽固地在平行的木杆上滑动，十分恼人地互相裹挟并缠绕在窗子上，如果我成功地解开了第一层，第二层便会立即裹进连接处，将之完全堵塞，就像有一棵真正的山楂树或者真有一只异想天开的燕子在那儿筑巢，其结果就是，如果没有另一个家庭成员帮忙，我永远也别想完成开关窗子这看似简单的动作。所有这些物件非但不能满足我的任何需求，而且颇有些碍事。显然，它们放在那儿并非为任何人所用，它们让我的房间充满了某种私密沉思的气氛，带着那种自己选择所爱的生存与享受方式的神情，就像林间空地上的树，抑或路边或一段老墙上的花朵。它们使之充满了种种静默的生命，充满了让我的个体既失落其中又为之着迷的神秘。它们让这房间变为一所小教堂，阳光——在穿过我叔叔安在窗户上方的红色玻璃窗格之后——先将窗帘上的山楂花变成粉红色，又在墙壁上洒下奇异的闪烁斑点，就好像这小教堂藏身于一座彩窗的教堂大殿之中。在这里，因为离得近，响亮地回荡着乡村教堂的钟声，在盛大宗教节日，教堂的临时祭坛更通过一条花路与我们的房子相连，这钟声让我幻想它就敲响在我们的屋顶下，在窗子上面，从那里我常常问候手拿日课经的牧师、晚祷归来的姑母，或者为我们带来圣餐面包的唱诗班男孩。至于布朗所摄波提切利[49]的《春》，或者里尔博物馆的《无名女士》复制品，威廉·莫里斯对其无用之美作出了让步，让它们出现在梅坡公司室内的墙壁和壁炉架上，而我必须承认，在我的房间里，它们让位于一幅表现欧仁亲王的版画，他身着土耳其式长袍，英俊而令人生畏。一天夜里，在一个火车站餐厅入口处，在火车与冰雹的猛烈撞击声中，我震惊地看到这幅画，他为一个饼干牌子做的广告，依然英俊而令人生畏。现在我怀疑这幅画是我的祖父从前得自于一个慷慨的制造商，随后才永久地挂在我的卧室里。但当时我并不关心其似乎古老神秘的来源，也不曾想象可能存在不止一件复制品，因为在我看来他是一个活生生的人，是这房间永久的居住者，而我只不过同他共用这房间，在这里每一年我都会重新发现他，永恒不变。距离我上次看到他已经很久了，我想我再也不会见到他了。但若上天赐福我还能见到他的话，我相信他会比波提切利的《春》有更多话要对我说。让那些有品位的人用他们崇拜的名作的复制品去装饰自己的家吧，让他们把那些对他们而言珍贵的画作放进木刻相框，从而免去保存的烦恼。让那些有品位的人依其品位来安排自己的卧室，在里面放满符合其品位的物件。对于我自己，只有在每件物品都是迥异于我的生活、同我的口味截然相反的创造与表现的房间里，我才能感到自己在生活与思考，在那里没有什么与我的意识有关，我的想象力因潜入非我的深处而奔放。只有当我踏入——在俯视港口的车站大道，或在教堂广场——外省的一间旅馆时我才感到幸福，它们有着长长的寒冷的走廊，外面的寒风战胜了中央暖气，墙上唯一的装饰便是当地的详细地图，每一种声音都更烘托出寂静，房间里保留着一种腐旧的味道，新鲜空气将之清洗却无法根除，鼻孔上百次将它吸入，想象力为之着迷，将它视为样本，试图通过思想与回忆再造它所包含的一切。傍晚，当你打开房门，你感觉你侵犯了其中四处散落的那全部生命，关上门之后，当你进到房间深处，到桌子或窗户那里，你好像冒失地伸手拉住了这生命。坐在那小镇装饰工自以为的巴黎风格装饰的长椅上，你感到与那生命自由自在地亲密共处；你感到自己到处触摸到它赤裸的存在，当你欲以自己熟悉的一切来惊扰自己，当你四处堆放着自己的东西，装作是这漫溢着其他灵魂的房间的主人，而一直到薪架的形状或窗帘的图案都还保存着他们梦想的痕迹，当你赤足走在那陌生的地毯上；你感到自己仿佛将这秘密的生命锁入了自身，就在你浑身颤抖着去闩门的时候；你感到它在你前面上了床，最后和你一起躺在那一直盖到你脸上的大白被单里，就在这时，附近教堂的钟声为整个小镇敲响了对情人与垂死者而言无眠的时光。

4.我在房间里读不多久书就得去离村子1000米远的公园。把装在篮子里的点心分发给岸边的孩子们，我的书放在草地上不得拿起，但这强制的游玩活动结束后，我会在下午茶点快结束时早早离开。稍远一些，在公园茂盛而神秘的地带，河流不再是浮着天鹅、两边环以喜人的雕塑小径、时有鲤鱼跳跃的笔直的人工河道，它加快了速度，迅速越过公园围墙，变成一条地理意义上的河流——一条本应有名字的河流——并且立刻四处蔓延（它还是那条雕塑环绕天鹅漂浮的河吗？），奔流在毛茛草已被淹没的牛群睡卧的牧场和被它弄得颇为泥泞的草地中间，一边通过一些据说是中世纪遗迹的无法辨形状的塔楼同村子相连，另一边沿着蜿蜒上升的蔷薇和山楂花小径通向“自然”，将那些有过其他姓名的未知的村庄延伸至无穷。我会离开其他人，让他们继续在公园低处天鹅旁边吃完茶点，我会远远地跑到曲径深处某个树荫下，背靠修剪过的榛子丛，无人察觉地坐下，观看石刁柏苗床、草莓丛的边缘，马儿时常转着圏去汲水的水池，以及上面“公园尽头”的白色大门，还有更远处，开满罂粟花和矢车菊的草地。在我的荫蔽处笼罩着深深的寂静，几乎没有被发现的危险，从下面传来的远远的徒劳的呼唤声只让我的安全感加倍，这声音有时甚至更近些，沿着开始的斜坡向上，到处搜寻未果，又转回去，随后是一片寂静，只有从远处平原那边时时传来的金色钟声仿佛来自蓝天之外，提醒我时间已过。但惊异于那悠扬，不安于那更深沉的寂静，失落于接踵而至的最后几个音符，我从来不清楚钟鸣了几响。这不是当你重新进入村庄时听到的那雷鸣般的钟声——当你走近教堂，从近处看它恢复了那高耸僵直的外表，石板顶端栖满了乌鸦，映衬着傍晚黛色的天空——在村庄广场上那声音裂成了碎片，为了传扬“世间之善”。它们传到公园尽头的时候变得轻柔微弱，不是为我鸣响，而是朝着整个乡间，所有的村庄，那些分散在田间的乡民，丝毫无意让我抬头观望，只是从我身边经过，把时间带到遥远之地，不曾看见我、认出我或者打扰我。

5.有时，在房间里，在我的床上，晚餐早已结束，傍晚的最后时光也能用来读书，但我只将这些时光用于阅读一本书最后的章节，即将结束前的篇幅。那时，冒着一旦发现便会受到惩罚，或者读完全书后可能一夜失眠的危险，一等父母上床我便重新点燃蜡烛，就在近旁街道，在沉浸于寂静中的枪炮匠的房子和邮局之间，黑暗而湛蓝的天空繁星密布，在左边，在那蜿蜒上升的小巷之上，你能感到教堂庞大的黑色后殿在守望着，还有它一夜无眠的雕像，而这乡村教堂却自有其久远的历史，是神奇的居所，里面有慈爱的主、圣体面包、多彩的圣徒像，还有来自邻近庄园的妇人，她们在节日里“坐着马车”前来做弥撒，在穿过市场的时候让母鸡们咯咯直叫，长舌妇们眼睛发直，在回去的路上，刚刚离开门廊的阴影，信徒们从那里推开前厅大门时驱散了殿内逡巡的小鸟，她们总不忘记从广场的点心铺里买些用帘子遮挡着日晒的塔形糕点——曼格黄油蛋糕、奶油小饼、杏仁果酱小蛋糕——对我而言，它们慵懒甜美的气息仍然同大弥撒的钟声及礼拜日的欢乐掺杂在一起。

6.然后，最后一页读完了，书看完了。眼睛，和那无声地跟随着文字、停下来只为稍作喘息的嗓音，它们狂热的奔跑不得不中止于一声深深的叹息。随后，为了将我内心停留过久、无法平息的躁动引向其他方向，我会起身在床边踱步，眼睛仍然注视着不存在于房间内外任何地方的某一点，它停驻于灵魂的距离，与别的距离不同，无法用米尺或英里去衡量，你不会弄错，一旦见到那些思想在“别处”的人，“遥远”的目光就能立刻认出它来。然后呢，这本书就是这样了吗？我们对其中人物给予了比现实生活中的人还要多的关注和感情，但并不总是敢于承认自己是多么热爱他们，甚至，当父母对我读书时的激动报以微笑时，我会作出无动于衷的样子或假装无聊地合上书。我永远不会再见到这些我曾为之屏息静气或哭泣的人，永远不会再知道他们的消息。早在最后几页，作者在他残酷的“跋”里，已经用心地以一种令人难以置信的冷淡态度将他们“隔离出去”，而我们知道他曾如何一步步满怀关切地跟踪着他们。他们生活中的每一刻都被详加描述。然后，突然之间：“这些事情发生20年之后，那老人可能还会出现在富热尔的街上，仍然身材挺拔，等等。”[1]还有婚姻，我们在整整两卷书中不时瞥见那令人欢喜的可能性，为每一个障碍忧心忡忡，为每一次障碍的清除欢欣雀跃，却在“跋”中，从某个小人物不经意的一句话里听说婚礼已经举行，而我们并不确切知道是在何时，这令人吃惊的结尾好像来自上天，由一个对我们的短暂激情无动于衷的人代替作者写就。我们多么希望书中的故事继续下去，或者，如果这不可能的话，能够了解人物目前生活的一些情况，能够用我们的生活去体验一些与他们在我们心中激起的爱有关的东西[2]，而这爱的对象已不再，多希望我们并不仅仅是短暂徒劳地热爱过他们，而他们在明天就只不过是同我们的生活无关的一本书中被忘却的一页里的一个名字而已，我们一定错误地估计了这书的价值，因为现在我们看出，就像我们的父母用不屑的一句话教给我们的那样，它在此间的归宿根本不像我们想象的那样包含着全宇宙以至我们自己的命运，而只不过是在公证人的书架上，在一册册乏味的《彩图时装报》和《厄尔一卢瓦尔省地理》之间占据着一个窄窄的位置。

7.在进入《国王的宝藏》一文之前，在试图阐明我的意见之前，即阅读并不像罗斯金在这篇小文中所讲的应该占据生活中的重要位置，在此之前我必须将可爱的童年时代的阅读时光排除在外，那回忆应永远成为我们每个人的恩宠。无疑，上述文字的长度和内容只是更好地证明了我在本文一开始所说过的：阅读留给我们的是当时当地的影像。我未能逃脱它的咒语。我想谈的是阅读，但我谈到了书籍以外的一切，因为阅读对我讲述的并不是书本。但也许阅读赠予我的一个个回忆也会在我的读者心中苏醒，在他徘徊于这循环往返的花径时，慢慢引导他在心中重新创造出阅读这一独特的心理活动，并给予他足够强大的力量，让他现在能从自己内心深处聆听我即将陈述的意见。

8.我们知道《国王的宝藏》是罗斯金1864年12月6日在曼彻斯特附近拉绍尔默市政厅所作的关于阅读的讲演，目的是帮助拉绍尔默学院创立一所图书馆。12月14日他作了第二场讲演——《女王的花园》，讨论女性的作用，以帮助在安科茨建立学校。科林伍德先生在他令人钦佩的《罗斯金的生活与作品》中说：“那整整一年他都留在家中，除了……频频造访卡莱尔。他12月在曼彻斯特所作的一系列讲演后来收于《芝麻与百合》一书，成为他最广为人知的作品，从他思想最闪亮之处我们看得出当时他正处于身体与理智最健康的状态。从他所谈及的英勇、高贵、坚忍的理想观，以及他对书籍和公共图书馆价值的坚持，我们听到了他同卡莱尔交谈的回响，卡莱尔是伦敦图书馆的创办人。”

9.既然我在这里想做的只是讨论罗斯金的理论本身，不涉及其历史渊源，那么用笛卡尔的话即可相当准确地对之加以总结：“阅读好书就好像同过往时代最优秀的人物交谈。”罗斯金也许并不知道这位法国哲学家这多少有些枯燥的比喻，但这观点却贯穿了他的讲演，只不过笼罩在融合了英格兰薄雾的金色阳光中，就像那照亮了他所钟爱的英国画家笔下风景的阳光。“但是，即使我们有择友的意愿和见识，又有几人有那能力！或至少，对大多数人来说，那选择的范围多么有限！……我们无法知道我们会选择谁……幸运的话，我们可能瞥见一位伟大的诗人，聆听他的声音；或向科学家提问，得到友善的答复。我们可能占用一位内阁部长10分钟的时间同我们交谈，……或者在一生中有一两次与女王仁慈的目光相遇的殊荣。我们渴求这些短暂的运气；我们花费时光、激情与权力去追逐的不过如此。而与此同时，有一个社会圈子永远向我们开放，他们永远会与我们交谈，多久都行，无论我们的地位或职业为何……他们是如此数量众多，温文尔雅，可以一整天等待着，不是为了接见听众，而是希望被听众接见，达官贵人们耐心地徘徊在那朴素狭窄的接待室，即我们的书架上，而我们并不以之为意，也许一整天连一句他们想说的话都不听！”“你也许会告诉我，”罗斯金补充道，“你更愿意同活着的人交谈，因为你能看到他们的面孔”，等等，驳斥了这个以及下一个反对意见之后，他说明，阅读恰恰是同比我们周围可能遇见的人要聪明有趣得多的人对话。在本文的注释中我试图说明阅读并不等同于对话，哪怕是同最有智慧者的对话。一本书和一位友人的本质区别不在于其或多或少的智慧，而在于我们与之交流的方式，阅读同对话正好相反，在阅读时，我们每个人在接受他人思想交流的同时仍然保持孤独，亦即仍然享受着我们在孤独中享有的智力优势，而交谈却会顷刻间将之瓦解，同时仍然接受启迪，思想仍然富有成效地工作着。如果罗斯金对后来陈述的其他真理进行总结的话，他很有可能得出与我类似的结论。但显然他并没有去探求阅读的中心意旨。为了教导我们阅读的价值，他只是以希腊人的简洁讲述了一个动人的柏拉图式的神话，希腊人为我们揭示了几乎所有的真理，却留给现代的有心人对其进行深入探索的机会。尽管我认为阅读在本质上，就其于孤独中实现的丰硕的交流奇迹而言，有着不同于罗斯金所说的更丰富的东西，我却并不就此承认它在我们的精神生活中具有罗斯金似乎想赋予它的重要地位。

10.其地位的局限性源于其功能。我仍然要回到童年的阅读经验去发现这些功能是什么。那本书，你刚刚看到我在餐厅的炉火旁，在卧室里，蜷在罩着钩编头靠的扶手椅里，或在下午的美好时光，在公园的榛子树和山楂花下捧读的那本书，在那里，来自遥远无边原野的所有气息在我身边静静嬉戏，无声地为我心不在焉的鼻翼送来苜蓿和驴食草的香味，令我时而抬起疲倦的双眼：这本书，你靠近的眼睛无法穿过20年的时光辨认出它来，只有我的记忆，凭着它更适合此种观察的视觉，才能告诉你它的名字：《佛拉卡西上尉》，戈蒂埃[50]著。在这本书里我最爱的有两三个句子，它们在我看来是全书最优美独特之处。我无法想象别的作者写过可与之媲美的句子。但我感到这优美对应着一种现实，戈蒂埃只在每卷书的一两处让我们瞥见这现实的一角。因为我相信他一定了解其全部，我便想读他别的作品，其中所有的句子都应同这几句一样美，其内容都是有关我想知道的他的见解。“笑就其本质而言并不残酷，它将人与动物区别开来，就像希腊诗人荷马的《奥德赛》所表现的，它是幸福者和不朽神灵的特权，他们在永恒的闲散时光里像奥林匹斯诸神一般笑了个够。”[3]这句话真正令我心醉神迷。我以为透过唯有戈蒂埃才能向我揭示的中世纪，我窥见了一个奇妙的古代。但我更希望他不是像现在这样，用太多我不认识的词汇对一个我根本无法想象的城堡进行冗长描述之后一笔带过这句话，而是让书里充满这样的句子，并告诉我一些全书结束之后我还能继续了解并热爱的东西。我更希望这位掌握真理的智者能告诉我应该怎样恰如其分地看待莎士比亚、圣梯纳、索福克勒斯、欧里庇得斯、西尔维奥·佩利科[51]，我在一个非常寒冷的三月读了佩利科的书，每次合上书我便走着，跺着脚，沿着小径疾走，因为刚刚结束的阅读，因为我一动不动所积聚的能量，因为吹过村庄街道的令人振奋的风而狂喜。我还特别希望他告诉我是否更有机会接近真理，如果我重修六年级，或者以后成为外交官或高等法院的律师。但这句优美的句子刚刚结束，他便开始描绘一张“铺了一层厚厚的尘土，手指能在上面写字”的桌子，这话在我看来无甚意义，我的注意力无法为之停留。我只好想象戈蒂埃哪些其他的书能更好地满足我的渴望，让我最终了解他的全部思想。

11.确实，好书最伟大奇妙的特点之一（这让我们看到阅读在我们的精神生活中能够起到的根本而有限的作用）便在于对作者可称为“结论”，但对读者则是“激励”。我们强烈地感到我们的智慧开始于作者的智慧中止之处，我们希望他给予我们答案，而他所能做的全部便是给予我们欲望。他只有让我们注视他以艺术之全力达到的极致的美才能在我们身上唤醒这些欲望。但是从精神角度一个独特而神奇的法则来看（这法则意味着我们也许无法从任何其他人那里获得真理，而必须自己去创造真理），他们智慧的终点正是我们智慧的起点，所以就在他们说尽了所有能说的话的时候，我们却感到他们什么都没有说。而且，如果我们提出他们无法回答的问题，我们也就是在向他们要求对我们毫无用处的答案。诗人在我们心中激起的爱所产生的效果之一便是，仅对他们具有个人情感意义的事物被我们赋予了重大意义。在他们为我们呈现的每一幅图画中，我们仅能在瞬间瞥见那迥异于世界其他地方的景象，我们希望进入那奇妙的深处。“请带领我们，”我们想对梅特林克先生[52]和诺阿伊夫人[53]说，“去到那开放着古老花朵的泽兰花园，沿着充满‘苜蓿和蒿草’芳香的大路，去到世界所有那些你们在书中未曾提及但却认为同样美好的地方。”我们想去探访米勒[54]（因为画家以与诗人一样的方式给我们以教诲）在《春季》中展示的田野，想让莫奈[55]带我们去塞纳河边的吉维尼，看看他画中透过清晨的雾霭几乎难以分辨的河流弯道。而实际上，诺阿伊夫人或梅特林克或米勒或莫奈选择去描绘那条路、那座花园、那片田野、那段河流，而不是别的什么，那仅仅是因为偶然的亲戚关系使他们在那里停留。它们在我们眼中比世界其他地方更特别更美，因为它们飘忽不定地反映着天才心中的印象，这印象，同样特别，同样霸道，飘过所有他可能描绘的风景那顺从而漠然的面容。这表象迷惑我们、令我们失望，让我们想走得更远，它便是这在某种意义上不具深度的东西的本质——截留于画布的幻影——一种视象。而我们渴望的双眼想要穿越的迷雾就是艺术家的结束语。作家和画家至高无上的努力不过是为我们部分地揭开了那让我们在宇宙面前无动于衷的丑陋无聊的面纱。随后他说：

看吧，看吧，

充满苜蓿与艾蒿的芳香，

拥抱着狭窄奔腾的溪流，

是那埃纳与瓦兹之地。

“看那泽兰的房舍，粉红闪亮如一只贝壳。看啊！学着去看！”就在这时他消失了。这便是阅读的价值所在，也是它的不足之处。将它变成教条就是赋予启蒙过于重要的角色。阅读是精神生活的开始，它将我们引入精神生活：它并不构成它。

12.但在某些情形下，比如精神抑郁症的病例，这时阅读可以作为一种治疗方式加以运用，通过反复的激励，将懒惰的心灵重新不断地引入精神生活中去。那时书籍起到的作用便类似于针对某些精神衰弱症的心理疗法。

13.我们知道在某些精神系统的疾病中，虽然器官本身无恙，患者却深陷于一种失去意愿的状态而无力自拔，如果没有一只有力的援助之手向他伸出的话，最终将会衰竭。他的大脑、双腿、肺部和胃部均很健全。他并非完全失去了工作、行走、耐寒、饮食的能力。但他没有意愿去做这些完全有能力做到的动作。器官的衰竭会最终演变成他本没有的病症，造成无可挽回的后果，如果他自身无法找到的推力没有从外部出现，没有医生愿意为他作出决定，直到他慢慢恢复各种感官的意志。有一些人的情形可以同这种病患相比，他们受滞于一种惰怠[4]或无聊，无法自觉地深入到真正的精神生活开始的深层的自我中去。一旦有人将他们引入这自我深处，他们并不缺乏发现和探索那真正丰富性的能力，但是由于缺乏外界的干涉，他们便生活在表面，处于永远遗忘自我的消极状态，这使他们嬉游于各种享乐，甘心混同于周遭的熙攘，就好比一个出身高贵但从童年起便与街头盗贼厮混的人，早已不再使用因而不再记得自己的姓名，如果没有外力迫使他们重新开启恢复思考和创造力的精神生活，他们最终会丧失精神高贵性的所有感觉和回忆。但显然，惰怠的心灵必须在孤独中接受这来自外界的推动力，正如我们已看到的，没有孤独便无法产生创造活动，而创造活动恰恰是这推力所要激发的。在单纯的孤独中惰怠的心灵将一无所获，因为它不能自己进行创造性活动。但最高深的交谈和最紧迫的建议也无济于事，因为它们无法直接产生这种独特的活动。这时所需要的是来自他人但却生发于我们内心深处的影响，它确是来自另一个心智的推动，但我们在孤独之中接受它。我们已经看出，这恰恰是阅读的定义，而且只适于阅读。因此，唯一能够对这样的心灵施加有益影响的训练便是阅读：借用几何术语，证明完毕。但我重申，阅读只能作为激励，决不能代替我们的个体活动。它仅仅满足于帮助我们恢复其功能，就像我在前面比喻过的神经疾病，心理医生只能为患者恢复其意志力去运用自己仍然健康的胃、腿和脑。也许所有的心智或多或少都有些深层滞碍的惰性，尽管阅读并非必要条件，但其所带来的兴奋或许会对我们的写作产生好的影响，总之人们发现不止一位作家喜欢在写作之前先读篇好文章。爱默生很少不重读几页柏拉图就开始写作。但丁也并非唯一由维吉尔引入天堂大门的诗人。

14.因为，只要阅读对我们是激励性的，用神奇的钥匙为我们打开了内心深处我们本不懂得如何进入的所在，那么它便起到了有益的作用。反之它就是危险的，如果它不是唤醒我们心灵的个体生命，而是试图取而代之，如果真理不再表现为只有靠我们自己思想的隐秘的进步及我们自己心灵的努力才能实现的理想，而只是好像置于书页间的一件物品，就像他人酿好的蜂蜜，我们只需从书架上取下来就可以在心灵与身体的完全静止中消极地品味。有时，在一些特别的、不那么危险的情形下，始终被视作外在的真理离我们十分遥远，隐藏在难于到达的某处。比如某些机密的资料，未发表的通信或回忆录，可能出人意料地揭示某些特点，但却很难获得。对于厌倦于在内心寻找真理的理智来说，这是怎样的幸福与休憩呵，当它发现这真理就存在于外界，被小心翼翼地保存在荷兰一所隐修院的对开本书籍中，虽然我们得费些功夫才能抵达，但辛苦的只是身体，对理智而言不过是迷人的消遣。这将意味着一段漫长的旅程，你得乘坐驳船穿越风声呜咽的沼泽地，岸边的芦苇在无尽的波动中连绵起伏；你得在多德雷赫特停留，它那常青藤覆盖的教堂倒映在纵横交错沉睡的运河与金光颤动的墨兹河上，晚上，船只划过水面，搅乱了一条条红色屋顶与蓝色天空的倒影；而一直到最后到达目的地，你仍不能肯定能够借阅到这本书。为此必须想方设法运用强大的影响力，比如结交那位有一张前冉森教徒般英俊的四方脸的尊敬的乌得勒支大主教，还有阿姆斯福特[56]那位虔诚的档案保管人。在这种情形下获得真知就好像是某种外交使命的胜利，不乏艰险的旅途和充满变数的谈判。但那有什么关系？我们能否获得真知全靠乌得勒支这个古老的小教堂里所有这些可爱的成员，他们17世纪的面孔有别于我们惯常所见，与他们保持联系，至少通通信将是多么有趣的事。他们在持续与我们通信中一次次表现出的尊敬使我们颇为自诩，并把他们的信件作为证件和珍玩保存起来。对这些赠我们以……真知的人，我们不会忘记将来把我们的书题献给他们，这自然是我们所能做到的最起码的事。至于我们不得不在隐修院图书室里进行的少量研究工作则是获取真知的必要前提——谨慎起见，为了避免遗忘，我们会记笔记——抱怨这些工作所带来的麻烦简直就是不知好歹：古老隐修院的安宁清冷是如此得迷人，修女们仍然像在会客室悬挂的韦登[57]的画中一样头戴带有白色边缘的高帽；当我们工作时，一抹苍白的阳光照耀着醺醺然沉醉于17世纪温柔的排钟声里的天真的运河水，两旁从夏天结束便一直光秃秃的枝条拂过两岸悬挂在三角形房舍上的镜子。[5]

15.对思想的呼唤置若罔闻，只听从外界的影响，认为通过推荐信便能获得真知，不必了解，只要在物质上拥有，就能将之交到我们手中，并能誊录到笔记本上，这种真理观倒远不是最危险的。因为，通常历史学家甚或学者深入一本书中所寻找的，从严格意义上说并不是真理本身，而是其迹象或印证，进而为另一个它预告或证明的真理留下了空间，这至少还是他们自己思想的个别创造。文人却完全不同。他为了阅读而阅读，为了留住阅读的东西而阅读。对他，书籍并不是在他打开天堂花园大门那一瞬间便振翅飞去的天使，而是静止的偶像，他为它自身的缘故而崇拜它，并不从它激起的思想中获得一种真正的尊严，而是带给周遭一切一种虚假的尊严。文人微笑地援引它，向维尔阿杜安或薄伽丘[58]作品中的人物表示敬意[6]，或者维护维吉尔笔下的某些风俗。他的思想没有独创活动，不能从书中找出增强心智的东西，却被整部书拖累，书籍于他不是可吸收的元素，生命的原则，而只是异体，死亡的原则。自然，如果我说这种对书籍的喜爱、拜物般的崇拜是不健康的话，那是相对于完美心智的理想习惯而言，而完美的心智是不存在的，正如生理学家所描述的机体的正常工作状态在常人身上是罕见的一样。相反，在现实生活中，正如没有完全健康的身体一样，也没有完美无缺的心智，我们称为具有“伟大心灵”的人和其他人一样会染上这种“文学病”。也许比其他人更为严重。对书籍的热爱似乎同理智一起增长，略低于它但处在同一根枝干上，正如任何激情均伴随着对其对象的周围及相关事物的偏爱，并在它不在时仍然谈论它。因此最伟大的作家在未与自己的思想作直接交流的时候，喜欢与书籍为伴。它们难道不正是为了他们所写吗；它们难道不是向他们揭示那许多为大众所不知的美吗？但事实上，高尚的心智可能被称为嗜书者，但这决不证明这并非缺陷。平庸之人通常勤勉，聪明人则常常是懒惰的，但从中并不能得出结论：就心智训练而言，勤奋并不比懒惰好。尽管如此，在伟人身上看到我们自己的缺点总会使我们去想它是否在根本上是一种被误会的美德，我们不无愉快地发现雨果将昆提斯·库尔提乌斯、塔西佗和查士丁尼一世[59]的著作熟记于心，如果某个词的合理性当面受到挑战，他便可以旁征博引追述其来龙去脉。（我在别的地方说明，在他身上，学识是滋养而不是压制了他的天才，正如一捆木柴能扑灭一小簇火苗但只能让一大簇火焰燃得更旺。）在我看来，梅特林克是文人的反面，其心灵永远敞开接纳由蜂巢、花床或牧场所激起的数不清的无名情感，当他以收藏家的身份描述雅各布·凯茨[60]或桑德儒斯神父的老版著作里的版画时，我们便可大大放心于博学甚至是嗜书的危险。这种危险即使存在，它对理智构成的威胁要比对感性小得多，而思想家要比想象力丰富的诗人更具备从阅读中获益的能力。比如叔本华[61]，他生机焕发的心灵轻松地负载着大量的阅读，因为每一条新的知识都能立刻被压缩到阅读所包含的现实和生活的部分。

16.叔本华提出任何见解都会同时用数条引言来佐证，但你会感到，对他来说，他所引的文章仅为举例之用，是下意识的提前暗示，他喜欢在其中发现自己思想的一些特点，但它们绝非其灵感来源。我还记得《作为意志与表象的世界》中的一页，其中大约有连续20条引语。这段文字的主题是悲观（我自然会将这些引言加以缩写）：“伏尔泰在《老实人》中，以轻松愉快的方式同乐观作战。拜伦则在《该隐》中以其悲剧性的风格做同样的事。希罗多德记叙色雷斯人用哀叹迎接新生儿，却欢欣地对待死亡。这也是普卢塔克用以下动人的文字所表达的：这遭遇太多不幸的人儿，他为了自伤自怜而被孕育，等等。墨西哥人的祈愿习俗也必归因于此，斯威夫特亦必有同感，他从年轻时代就习惯于将生日作为苦难日来庆祝（如果相信司各特爵士的传记的话）。大家都知道柏拉图在《苏格拉底的申辩》中的段落，他在其中说死亡值得钦羡。赫拉克里特的箴言表达了同样的意思：如果说生命的名字是‘生命’，其作品却是死亡。特奥格尼斯动人的诗篇十分著名：人最伟大的命运便是不曾出生，等等。索福克勒斯在《俄狄浦斯在科洛诺斯》中简述如下：不诞生便远胜其他，等等。欧里庇得斯说：人的一生充满痛苦（《希波吕托斯》）。荷马也早已说过：无论何地，所有呼吸的生物都没有人类悲惨，等等。普林尼也这样说：没有什么好过适时的死亡。莎士比亚从年迈的亨利四世王口中说出：‘噢，如果此景可见——最幸福的青年——当合上书本，坐下死去。’最后仍是拜伦：‘死去更妙。’巴尔塔沙·葛拉西安在《批评大师》中用最黑暗的色调描绘生存，等等。”如果我不是已被叔本华带到这么远的话，我会很高兴用《智慧书》来结束这段小小的论述，在所有我所知道的书中，它也许见证了一位博览群书的作者的最独到之处，因此在这本充满引语的书的书眉，叔本华会郑重其事地写上：“编纂并非我的强项。”

17.友谊对于个体而言也许无足轻重，而阅读是友谊的一种。但至少它是真诚的，由于面对的是死者或不在场者从而带有一种无私的、几乎感人之处。而且，这种友谊摆脱了所有其他友谊所包含的丑恶。既然我们这些活着的人都是尚未赴约的死者，我们在所有那些枯燥乏味，我们称之为尊敬、感激或虔诚的门厅处的礼貌用语和问候里掺进了太多的谎言。而且——从我们最早的善意、敬仰或感激的关系开始——我们最早说出的话、最早写下的文字就开始在我们周围编织出习惯之网、真正的生活方式之网，在其后的友情中我们再无法从中解脱。还没算上这时我们饶舌的话，它始终像我们必须兑现的期票，或者我们因为听任它被拒付而终生悔恨，须以更大的代价来偿还。而在阅读中，友谊突然回归了其原初的纯粹，如同书籍不存在虚伪的友善。如果我们整个晚上与之为伴，那是因为我们真心希望如此。我们常常离开他们，但只会带着遗憾。而且离开之后不会有这些损害友谊的念头：“他们会怎么想我们？”“我们是否得体？”“他们喜欢我们吗？”，或者担心因为别的什么人而遭遗忘。所有这些关于友谊的疑惧都在阅读这纯净安详的形式面前消失了。也无须毕恭毕敬，我们对莫里哀的话大笑就只是因为它很可笑。他令我们烦闷时我们也不必害怕显得烦闷，确信读够了之后我们便突兀地把他放回去，仿佛他既非天才也非名人。这种纯粹友谊的氛围是沉默，它比话语更加纯粹。因为我们是为他人而说，自己只有沉默。所以沉默不像话语那样带着我们的错误或造作的痕迹。它是纯粹的，真正是一种氛围。在作者和我的思想之间并不夹杂着我们各自不同的自我对思想顽固的抵制。书的语言本身是纯粹的（如果它配得上被称为书的话），作者的思想更使其透明，凡不属于思想本身的均已清除，语言便是思想的忠实影像。每个句子在本质上都与其他句子相似，因为所有的语句均出自同一个拥有独特个性的语调。书中因而有一种连续性，而生活中的种种关系因掺杂了与思想无关的因素而不带有这种连续性，这使我们能很快跟上作者思想的轨迹，以及他反映在这宁静镜面中的面貌特征。我们能够愉快地观照而无需崇拜这些特征，因为对理智而言，能够辨认出这些深刻的画像，能够以无私无言的友情去爱，这真乃一大乐事。就像我们喜爱戈蒂埃，因为他是个高雅的好人（他被认为是艺术完美性的代表，这让我觉得好笑），仅此而已。我并不高估他的精神力量，在他的《西班牙游记》中，每一个句子都在无意中强调并延伸了他个性中十分优雅而欢快的特点（词语自行组合来描绘这特点，因为正是他的个性选择了它们并将其按顺序排列），但我不得不认为他的创作手法远称不上真正的艺术：他逼迫自己对每一种形式都加以详细描绘，并伴以并非源于任何愉快强烈的印象的比较，因此毫无动人之处。当他将种植着各种农作物的田野同“粘有长裤和马甲式样的裁缝的名片”相比较时，或者当他说从巴黎到昂古莱姆一路上无甚可欣赏之处时，我们不得不责怪他想象力贫乏得可怜。而这位狂热的哥特风格爱好者在夏尔特尔时连大教堂都懒得去参观，这不禁让人好笑。（“我很遗憾经过夏尔特尔时没能去看看大教堂”，《西班牙游记》。）

18.但是多好的脾气，多好的品味啊！我们多么心甘情愿地跟随这位快活的伙伴去历险，他是如此令人愉快，连他周围的一切也是如此。在他因风暴耽搁在那条“黄金般闪耀”的漂亮大船上，同勒巴尔毕耶·德·提南船长共度数日之后，我们悲哀地看到他只字不再提起这位友善的海员，让我们永远离开他，不知道他后来怎样了。[7]我们能感觉到他夸夸其谈的快乐和一阵阵的忧郁都来自记者放荡不羁的习性。但我们宽容这一切，对他唯命是从，当他满身湿透、饥累交加回来时觉得很有趣，当他像个报纸专栏作家一样追述那些与他同代的早夭的人名时又不禁随之悲伤。我说过他的句子描绘着他的面貌，而他并不知晓。因为如果词语不是我们的思想根据其本质的亲和力所选择，而是出于我们自我描绘的欲望的话，它们所表现的便是那欲望，不是我们。佛洛芒丹和缪塞[62]虽然才华横溢，但他们想将自己的肖像留传后世，于是这肖像便十分平庸。但也正因如此它们令我们极感兴趣，因为其失败之处颇具启发意义。因此，当一本书不能反映一种强有力的个性时，它倒反映了其思想中有趣的缺陷。当我们仔细阅读佛洛芒丹或缪塞的书时，我们注意到前者某种“高雅”里所包含的狭隘和幼稚，而在后者则是滔滔雄辩中的空虚。

19.如果说我们对书籍的热爱随着我们智力的成长而成长，那么其危险，像我们所看到的，则随之减弱。有独创力的精神能够使阅读服从其个体的活动。对它而言，阅读仅仅是最高贵的消遣，而且首先是最能使人高贵的，因为仅凭阅读和知识便能培养出“有教养的”心智。我们只能在内心，在我们精神生活的深处发展我们感性和智力的能力。但正是在同其他心灵的接触，即阅读活动中，我们心灵的“修养”才得以形成。无论如何，博览群书仍然同过去一样是心智超群的特征，不知道某本书或某条文学知识，哪怕对于天才也将始终是智力平庸的标志。对于精神来说也是如此，优越和高贵体现在一种习惯的默契和对传统的继承上。[8]

20.大作家们在其广泛的阅读中非常容易偏爱古人的著作。即使那些被同代人视为最“浪漫”的作家也几乎只读古典作品。谈到自己近来在读的作品时，在雨果口中最常出现的名字是莫里哀、贺拉斯、奥维德和雷尼亚尔。都德是书生气最少的作家，他的作品生机勃勃、充满现代感，好像摒弃了所有古典的传承，但他不间断地阅读、引用、评注的是帕斯卡尔、蒙田、狄德罗和塔西佗。[9]我们几乎可以走得更远，以一种当然并不完全的诠释方式，重新解释古典派与浪漫派的传统区分，说明公众（当然是聪明的公众）是浪漫派的，而大师（即使是浪漫派公众所喜爱的被称为浪漫派的大师）则是古典派的。（这一观察可推广至所有其他艺术。公众去聆听丹第的音乐，后者却在重温蒙西尼的作品。[10]公众去观看维亚尔或莫里斯·德尼[63]的作品展，他们却去参观卢浮宫。）这种现象产生的原因可能是，独具创见的作家和艺术家使公众得以接触和喜爱的一些当代思想在某种程度上早已成为他们的一部分，所以他们更容易为不同的思想所打动。为此他们须付出更大的努力去获得更多的乐趣。在阅读中我们总喜欢到身外之地去旅行。

21.最后，我更愿意把伟大心灵对古老作品的偏爱归于另一个原因。[11]这就是，同当代作品不同，对于我们，它们具有的不仅仅是其创造者置于其中的美。它们还有另一种更感人的美，来自其物质，我指它们所写就的语言，如同一面生活的镜子。就好像我们在类似博恩这样的城市中散步所感到的幸福，那里完好无损地保存着15世纪的救济院、水井、洗衣房，贴彩绘木板的天花板拱顶，高高的人字屋顶，嵌着带有薄薄的铅铂尖顶饰的老虎窗（所有一个时代消逝时仿佛被遗忘的东西，所有只属于那个时代的东西，因为从那之后所有其他的时代均未曾见过任何类似的东西产生），当我们徜徉在拉辛的悲剧或圣西门的一卷著作中时，再次感到那种幸福。因为它们包含着所有早已湮灭的美丽的语言形式，其中保存着业已不存在的习俗或感觉方式的记忆，还有那些与现在的一切毫无相像之处的过去长存的痕迹，只有时间才能为其增光添彩。

22.拉辛的一部悲剧或圣西门的一卷回忆录仿佛是不再产生的美丽物品。伟大的艺术家用来雕琢它们的语言具有一种自由之美，闪耀着柔和的光芒，突出了天生的力量，令我们感动不已，就像过去工匠所使用的，今天已不多见的大理石。无疑，这些古建筑中的石头忠实地保存着雕刻家的思想，但也多亏了雕刻家，今天已无人知晓的石头也保留了下来，带着雕刻家从中发掘、显现、调和的所有色彩。我们在拉辛的诗文中所乐于发现的正是17世纪法国的活句法——及其早已消弭的习惯和措辞方式。让我们感动的正是这句法形式本身，袒露在他如此率直而细腻的刻刀之下，其俗语的运用风格既奇特又大胆[12]，就在最为温柔圆润的段落里，突兀的构思忽如利剑般穿过，或以美妙的断句转回。我们前往拉辛作品中观赏的正是这些从过去的生活本身截取下来的古老形式，正如一座保存完好的老城。面对这些语言形式我们有着同样的感动，就像面对那些同样早已消亡的建筑形式，现在只能在由塑造它们的过去遗留下来的罕见而华美的范例中欣赏它们：比如古老的城墙、城堡和塔楼、教堂的洗礼堂。比如，回廊附近，或教堂庭院的藏骸所下那小小的墓地，它在蝴蝶和花草之下，将葬礼之泉和死亡之灯遗忘在阳光下。

23.而且，为我们描绘古老灵魂形状的并不仅仅是句子本身。在语句之间——我想到那些最早为人诵读的古籍，——在那字里行间，到今天仍然充塞着许多个世纪以来的沉寂，就像一间不可侵犯的地下墓室。常常，在“路加福音”中，当我看到遍布书中许多赞美诗般的段落之前的“冒号”时，[13]我仿佛听到祈祷者的静默，他刚刚大声朗读完毕，准备吟诵下面的诗句，[14]又似乎想到了圣经中更古老的诗篇。这寂静仍然充满在语句的停顿中，这些句子分成两行将其包围，保留了它的形状。不止一次，我在读到这些段落时闻到了微风从敞开的窗子吹进来的玫瑰的芳香，它飘散在举行聚会的上房中，两千年间仍未消散。在《神曲》或莎士比亚的剧作中，我感到过去的片断仿佛楔入了此时此刻。那种令人为之一振的印象使得某些“阅读的日子”就如同徜徉在威尼斯圣马可广场，在那里，在你面前，在近在咫尺又隔着许多个世纪之遥的物质的半真实的色彩中，你看到两根粉色和灰色的石灰岩立柱，柱头上一个是圣马可之狮，另一个是脚踩鳄鱼的圣狄奥多尔。这两个美丽修长的异乡人来自东方，穿过在他们脚下碎裂的海洋；他们听不懂四周的话语，在今天的人群中依然过着他们12世纪的日子，就在你身边的公共广场依然闪耀着他们遥远恍惚的微笑。

【注释】

[1]我必须承认，直陈式未完成过去时——这一残酷的时态，它的某些运用将生活描绘得既短暂又被动，它在追述过去的行动时使之沦为一种幻觉，并陷于过去的虚无，而不像完成时态那样留给我们行动切实存在过的安慰——这时态对我始终是一种神秘悲哀感的无尽来源。就在今天，我可以连续几小时冷静地沉浸于对死亡的思考。但只要我打开圣伯夫的《月曜日丛谈》中的一卷，例如，我刚好看到拉马丁的这段文字（关于达尔巴尼夫人）“那时在她身上没有什么还让人想得起[rappelait]……她曾经是[c'etait]一个矮小的女人，其身体因肥胖而衰弱，最终死去，等等”，我就立刻感到自己被最深沉的忧郁吞没。面对那些作者明显想让人痛苦的小说，我们更需做好防备。

[2]我们可以采用一种间接的方式，用并非完全虚构、带有深层的历史真实性的书来验证这一点。例如巴尔扎克，其著作混合着思想和基本未经改造的现实，在某种意义上来说并不纯粹，有时候尤其适合这种阅读方式。至少阿尔贝·索莱尔便是巴氏作品的读者中最令人钦佩的历史学家之一，他曾就《黑暗的勾当》和《现代史内幕》写下了无与伦比的评论文章。的确，像阅读这样既热烈又静谧的享乐看起来多么适合索莱尔先生的探索精神和平静强壮的身体。在阅读中，无数诗意朦胧的幸福感从我们安乐的身心深处欢喜地起飞，为读者的遐想营造出蜜一般金色甜美的愉悦。索莱尔先生的阅读艺术登峰造极，而这并不止于半历史性的作品。即便只是一部普通作品，他也会有独到有力的见解。我会永远记得——并衷心感谢——他为我的《亚眠的圣经》的法文翻译写下的评论——也许是他最强有力的文字。

[3]事实上在《佛拉卡西上尉》里找不到这句话，至少不是以这种形式出现。并非“就像希腊诗人荷马的《奥德赛》所表现的”，而只是“根据荷马的说法”。但书中其他地方出现过“就像荷马所表现的”和“就像《奥德赛》所表现的”这样的说法，并且这些说法我都可以愉快接受。我为了使这例子对读者更具震撼力，允许自己把这所有的美熔于一炉，而今天，说实话，我对此已不再虔诚地崇拜了。在《佛拉卡西上尉》中的其他地方，荷马也被描述为希腊诗人，无疑这也曾令我着迷。但我不再能足够准确地感受到这些早已忘却的欢乐，无法确定我在一句话中堆积了这许多的美妙的词语，是否走得太远，越过了界限！但我并不这样想。我遗憾地意识到，当我漫步在砾石小径，对着垂在河岸上方的鸢尾花和长春花反复吟诵《佛拉卡西上尉》里的这句话时，如果我能像今天一样，用自己的创造在《戈蒂埃》的一句话中聚集起这许多迷人的词语，那么我感到的欣悦之情会更加甜美，虽然今天它已不再带给我任何愉悦。

[4]我在丰丹纳身上便感到这懒惰的苗头，圣伯夫写道：“他身上有着非常强烈的享乐的一面……倘不是这些耽于物欲的习性，以丰丹纳的才华，他本能创造出更多……更持久的作品。”别忘了无能的人总是宣称自己并不无能。丰丹纳说：

照他们的话我在浪费时间，

只有他们才增添这世纪的光

并向我们保证自己的勤勉。

柯勒律治则是一个更加病态的例子。卡彭特说（转引自里博的杰作《意志的疾病》）：“在他的时代，或许在任何其他时代，没有一个人像柯勒律治那样将哲学家的逻辑能力同诗人的想象力融于一身。但也没有一个人像他那样，如此天纵英才却如此浪费自己的才华：他性格的重大缺陷便是缺乏意志力，不能将其天赋加以运用，因而纵然他脑中总是浮动着庞大的计划，他却从未真正努力去实现其中的一个。在创作生涯之初，一位慷慨的书商曾许诺为他背诵过的诗支付30个几尼，等等。而他宁愿每个星期去乞讨，也不愿写下来一行诗就能获得自由。”

[5]毋庸讳言，在乌得勒支附近寻找这家隐修院毫无意义，因为这整段文字都纯属虚构。不过，其灵感来自雷翁·塞舍就圣伯夫所写的下列文字：“他（圣伯夫）在列日的时候，有一天决定与乌得勒支的小教堂联系。天色已晚，乌得勒支距巴黎很远，我不知道是否‘沉迷’足以让阿姆斯福特档案室的大门为他敞开。我对此颇为怀疑，因为即使在《波尔罗亚尔》的前两卷之后，也有虔敬的学者主管这些档案。圣伯夫好不容易让好心的卡斯坦先生允许他瞧瞧那些纸箱子……打开《波尔罗亚尔》的第二版，你能找到圣伯夫对卡斯坦先生表示感谢的文字。”至于那旅程的细节，全仰赖当前的印象。我并不知道去乌得勒支是否要经过多德雷赫特，但我就像看到了一样加以描述。我是在去沃伦丹而不是去乌得勒支的一次旅途中乘坐过穿越沼泽的驳船。我安排在乌得勒支的运河实际上位于戴夫特。我是在博恩医院里看到了一幅韦登的画和一群修道会的修女，我相信她们是来自佛兰德斯的，她们戴着的头饰不曾出现在韦登的画中，却和我在荷兰见过的其他画家画中的一样。

[6]纯粹的附庸风雅则更加无辜。因为某人先祖参加过十字军东征，而喜欢与其为伴，这属于虚荣，与理智无关。但如果而是因为某人祖父的名字频繁出现在维尼或夏多布里昂的笔下，喜欢与其为伴，或者（我必须承认这对我是不可抵制的诱惑）是因为其家族的纹章（该女士无需此纹章便大大值得我们崇敬）出现在亚眠圣母院的大玫瑰窗上的话，那这就是理智之罪开始的地方。尽管我还有很多要说，但我在别处已经用很长的篇幅讨论过这点，在此就不必再加强调了。

[7]我听说他变成著名的德迪南海军上将，艺术家们仍然钟爱的佩舍·德迪南夫人的父亲，以及英勇的骑兵上尉的祖父。我相信他还在盖尔特之前负责弗兰西斯二世和那不勒斯女王之间的供应与联络（见皮埃尔·德拉·髙斯的《第二帝国史》）。

[8]而且，真正的髙雅好像总是只与同样髙雅的人对话，它并不去“解释”。法朗士的书暗示其丰富的才学，其中总是包含着众多易为大众忽略的典故，除了该书其他的优美之处，它们自身便具有无与伦比的髙贵。

[9]可能这就是为什么，当一位伟大的作家从事评论时，他大量谈论的常常是古代作品的现今版本，而很少提及当代作品。例如圣伯夫的《月曜日丛谈》和法朗士的《文学生活》。但如果说法朗士是当代作家的杰出评论家的话，圣伯夫便是曲解了与他同时代的所有伟大作家。请勿反对，他是被个人的敌意蒙蔽了双眼。在令人难以置信地诋毁了司汤达的写作才华之后，他对其谦逊机敏的作风大加赞赏作为补偿，就好像他再没有别的好处可言！圣伯夫对当代作家的无视同他自称的清明和预见能力形成了奇怪的对比。他在《夏多布里昂和他的文学团体》中说：“每个人都擅长就拉辛和博絮埃发表意见……但审判官的洞察力与评论家的机敏首先要在尚未被大众所知的新作品中得到验证。第一眼就去评判、预言、指导，那是批评家的天赋。极少人有这天赋。”

[10]反之亦然，古典派中并没有比“浪漫派”更好的评论家。只有浪漫派作家才真正懂得怎样阅读古典作品，因为他们将古典派作品当作浪漫派作品，因为要恰当地阅读一个诗人或散文家的作品，你自己就必须是诗人或散文家，而不是学者。对于最不“浪漫”的作品也是如此。让我们注意到布瓦洛的优美诗句的人不是修辞学教授，而是维克多·雨果：

在被她的美所沾污的四块手帕里

她的玫瑰和百合被送到洗衣工那里

或者法朗士的诗行：

无知与谬误在他新生的剧目中

身着侯爵的装束，伯爵夫人的长裙

《拉丁复兴》的最新一卷（1905年5月15日）里有一个最新的例子，让我在修改校样时把这一观察推广至美术领域。文中（作者为莫克莱尔）说罗丹是希腊雕塑的真正评论家。

[11]他们自己通常认为这种偏爱是偶然的：他们假定

最好的书籍恰巧都是古人所著；这无疑是可能的，因为我们阅读的古老书籍是从所有的“过去”中挑选出来的，而过去同当代相比是如此广泛。但在某种意义上偶然不足以解释如此普遍的思想态度。

[12]比如，我认为人们通常从《安德洛玛刻》这些诗行中发现魅力：为什么杀他？他做了什么？凭什么？谁告诉你的？其魅力恰恰来源于被刻意打断的常用句式。“凭什么”指的不是前面紧接着的“他做了什么？”，而是“为什么杀他？”“谁告诉你的”指的也是“谋杀”（根据《安德洛玛刻》的另一行文字“谁告诉你的，我的主人，说他蔑视我？”我们可以猜想“谁告诉你的”意为“谁告诉你去谋杀他？”）。表达的曲折（上文提到的反复的断句）并未使意思显得隐晦，因此我听到过一位伟大的女演员，更重视叙述的明晰而非韵律的准确，她直白地说出：“为什么杀他？凭什么？他做了什么？”拉辛最著名的诗行的确迷人，其大胆的口语形式就像一座桥梁飞架于“温和”的两岸。“Je t'aimais inconstant,qu'aurait—je fait fidele?”[我不专一，我却爱过你，我若忠诚，我又会如何？]这些表达的漂亮组合是多么令人愉快，它们的通俗简单为其意义添加了如此柔美的丰满与动人的色彩，就像曼特尼亚画笔下的面庞：

我的青春登上狂野的爱情让三颗纷争的心合于一处。

这就是为什么我们应阅读古典作家作品的全文而非节选。在这些作品的著名段落中，其语言的内在经络通常被选文几乎无所不在的美遮掩。我不认为格鲁克音乐的精髓在咏叹调的壮丽中要比在宣叙调的某些顿挫中表现得更充分。在后者，每当我们听到他的喘息时，其和音落在无意识的音调上，就像他天才的声音本身，表现出天真的肃穆和髙贵。每个见过威尼斯圣马可大教堂照片的人（我说的只是其外观而已）都可以认为他对这拱顶教堂多少有些了解，但只有当你走近并亲手触摸那些美妙多彩的圆柱，只有当你看到柱头上只从近处才辨认得出的包围着叶饰或栖息鸟儿的奇异庄严的力量，只有在广场亲自体会这低低的建筑，沿着整个正面排列的花饰立柱和喜庆的雕饰领略它“展览大厅”般的气象，你才能体会到从这些没有任何照片能够捕捉到的次要而关键的特征中爆发出的真实复杂的个性。

[13]“于是玛丽亚说：‘我的灵魂颂扬主，因主而喜悦，’等等。她的父亲萨迦利亚心中充满圣灵，预言道：‘感谢主，以色列的神，为他所赎回的，’等等。‘他拥抱她，感谢主，说道：“主啊，让你的仆人在平安中离去。”’”

[14]事实上没有直接证据证明当吟诵者阅读这一段时会唱出圣路可穿插在福音书中的赞美诗。但将勒南，特别是圣保罗、使徒列传、马可·奥勒利乌斯等不同段落进行比较之后，我认为这一点足够强烈地表现了出来。

阅读的日子（二）

1.你一定读过布瓦涅伯爵夫人[64]的《回忆录》。眼下就有“许多生病的人”，所以很少有人读书了，女性也不例外。当一个人无法出去会客时，他可能宁愿在家待客而不是读书。但“在这传染病流行的日子”，即便是在家待客也有危险。比如有位女士在你的家门口停住脚步——只是片刻而已——，好像这样就可以限制危险发生一样，并向你喊道：“你怕腮腺炎或者猩红热吗，我必须提醒我女儿和外孙们生了这病。我能进来吗？”然后不等你回答便进来了。另一位婉转些的女士，掏出表来说：“我得赶快回家，三个女儿都得了麻疹，我得轮流照顾她们，我的英国女仆从昨天起就发高烧病倒了，我很担心该轮到我了。因为起床时我就感到不适，但我排除万难，必须来看你……”

2.所以，你宁肯少去应酬。既然不能总打电话，那就读书吧，虽然这只是万不得已的选择。首先，我们打许多电话。由于我们是孩子，与那神奇的力量玩耍而不为其神秘所动，我们只是发现电话“很方便”；或者，由于我们是被宠坏的孩子，发现电话“很不方便”，于是牢骚满腹地翻阅着《费加罗报》，认为电话这魔法工具变得还不够快，有时要花好几分钟的时间才让那位我们早渴望与之交谈的女友出现。她是一种“无形的存在”，虽然她仍然在自己桌边，在她居住的遥远城市，在与我们不同的天空下，与此处不同的气候中，在我们一无所知但她即将告诉我们的情形和事务中，在一个我们随心选定的时刻。她突然从百十英里之外前来（她自己还有她沉浸其中的全部氛围），“出现”在我们耳边。我们就像童话中的人物，借助巫师的力量，通过看一本书，流几滴眼泪，或者摘几朵花，便能如心中渴盼、魔术般地清晰看到自己的未婚妻出现在身边，虽然她其实仍在远方。

3.为了让这奇迹再次发生，我们只需把嘴唇贴近那神奇的电话板上呼叫——当然，有时得花些时间——那些警觉的接线女郎，我们每天听到她们的声音却不曾见过她们的面容，她们是我们的守望天使，万般谨慎地守护着令人眩晕的黑暗之门，多亏了她们的全知全能，电话另一端的人的面容才得以浮现眼前，虽然仍无以得见；我们只需呼叫这些不可见的达纳伊得斯姐妹[65]，她们不断地倒空、盛满那些黑暗的声音之壶，相互传递。当我们对女友吐露私情，希望没有人听见的时候，她们是嫉妒的愤怒女神，讥讽地对我们呼叫：“我在线上。”这些神秘的暴躁仆人，无情的神灵，电话中的少女！就在那一刻，她们的呼叫响在黑暗中，那里充满了只有我们的双耳才能捕捉到的幻影，一个微弱的声音，抽象的声音——距离消除了——女友在对我们说话。

4.如果那一刻，一个路人的歌声，自行车的喇叭声，或者远处军乐队的声音从窗口飘入打扰了正在对我们讲话的她，这些声音也将同样清晰地响在我们耳畔（就好像要证明她，还有她周遭敲击着她的耳鼓，分散她注意力的一切，确实在我们身边）——那些真实的细节，同主题无关，自身毫无作用，但却因而更显必要，因为它们为我们揭示出那奇迹的全部真实性——就像诗人在需要使人物栩栩如生并再现其环境时所描绘的一样，从她居处所见的外省的街道和马路有着平凡而动人的地方色彩。

5.正是她，正是她的声音在对我们说话，就在那里。但那是多么遥远啊！有多少次我能够做到聆听她的声音而不深感痛苦，就好像她的声音近在耳畔，我们却面临着没有长时间的旅行便不可能相见的事实，我更加清晰地感到这仿佛最甜蜜的相依是多么令人失望，我们同所爱之人的距离是多么遥远，即使此刻我们似乎只需伸出双手就能将之挽留。真实的存在——声音近在咫尺——实际上却处于分离。但这同时也是长久分离的预兆。常常，这样地听着这声音，无法看到从那么遥远的地方对我讲话的人，她的声音好像是从无尽的深渊发出的呼喊，让我感到焦虑。而当一个声音就这样传来，孤零零的，独立于我永难再见的身体，在我的耳边呢喃着我渴望拥抱的话语，它们经过的嘴唇却已永远化为灰烬，这种焦虑，终有一天会攫住我。

6.我说过，在下决心读书之前，我们总是试着继续聊天、打电话，一个又一个地询问电话号码。但有时，那夜晚的女儿，话语的信使，无面目的女神，善变的守护神不能或不愿为我们打开那不可见之门，我们所乞求的神秘装聋作哑，印刷术可敬的发明者和热爱印象派作品同时又是汽车手的年轻亲王——古登堡和瓦格拉姆（两个巴黎电话局）！——被她们不知疲倦地呼叫着，却对她们的请求概不作答。那时，我们既不能会客，也不愿待客，电话女郎无法为我们接通，我们便任自己沉默，我们便开始读书。

7.在几个星期的时间里我们就能读完诺阿伊夫人的一本新诗《炫目》（我不知道这题目会不会保留下来），它甚至胜于她其他的天才作品，如《无数的心》和《岁月之影》，在我看来可媲美《秋叶》或《恶之花》[66]。不过我们也可以阅读由R.杜梅耶精彩翻译的巴里[67]所著纯粹精致的《玛格丽特·奥吉维》，它简单地描述了一位诗人讲述他的农妇母亲的生活。但是，一旦听任自己去阅读，我们更愿意选择像布瓦涅夫人的《回忆录》这样的书，它们让我们产生继续会客的幻觉，好像我们在拜访从前无缘得见的客人，因为在路易十六时代我们尚未出生，但他们同你认识的人并无太大区别，因为出于对你衰退记忆的感人的善意，他们的后代和你的友人，仍然保留着同样的名字，仍然叫作：奥东、吉斯兰、尼维隆、维克图尼安、约瑟兰、雷奥诺、阿尔图斯、图克杜阿、阿德奥姆或者雷努夫。这还是些优美的教名，如果对之加以嘲笑你就错了。它们来自如此久远的过去，那不同寻常的光泽中仿佛仍然散发着神秘，就像撰刻在我们教堂的彩色玻璃上那些先知和圣徒的简写名字。“日昂”这个名字，虽说像今天的名字，难道不更像用蘸着紫色、群青色或天蓝色的毛笔在一本历书中写下的哥特式字体吗？面对这样的名字，人们也许会重复那首蒙玛特尔之歌：

布拉冈斯，我们知道这人物！

他必定自傲自大

才有这么个名字！

他难道不能起个和别人一样的名字吗！

8.但诗人如果真诚的话，并不会觉得这有什么好笑，他会注视着这样的名字所揭示的过去，像魏尔兰[68]那样回答：

我看到、听到很多东西

在他加洛林王朝时代[69]的名字里

9.那也许非同寻常的过去。我愿意相信，这些极少数由于一些家族重视传统而流传至今的名字在过去都是很普通的——无论是农奴还是贵族——于是，这些名字为我们展现了幻灯机般原始的色彩，我们看到的不仅有蓝胡子的威严领主或塔楼中的安娜嬷嬷，还有躬身在草地上的农民或驱马在13世纪尘土飞扬的马路上的士兵。

10.无疑，这些名字所带来的中世纪的印象常常在不曾保有亦不解其诗意的使用者身上湮灭；但是，当最美好的东西最难与之匹配，当没有一处风景、城市或河流能够平息它们的名字在我们心头激起的梦幻的渴望时，我们能够理智地要求人类配得上他们的名字吗？明智的做法应该是用阅读欧洲王族家谱年鉴或火车时刻表来取代我们所有的社交联络和旅行……

11.18世纪末到19世纪初的回忆录，比如布瓦涅夫人的作品，其感人之处在于，它们好像是处在历史的前景，为我们当今毫无美感的生活提供了一种颇为高贵而忧郁的视角。它们使我们轻而易举地通过我们在生活中遇到的人——或我们的父母认识的人——认识到这些人的父母，他们就是这些回忆录的作者或其中的人物有关，他们也许亲历过法国大革命，看到过玛丽·安托瓦内特[70]从身旁经过。因此，我们可能见过或认识的人——我们亲眼见过的人——就像全景画的前景中那些真人大小的蜡像一样，他们踏在真正的草地上，持着从商店里买来的手杖，好像仍然是注视着他们的人群中的一员，他们将我们渐渐引向背景画布，通过设计精巧的过渡，显示出三维的生活和现实感。这位原名多斯蒙的布瓦涅夫人告诉我们，她在路易十六和玛丽·安托瓦内特的身边长大，年少时我常常在舞会上见到她的侄女，年迈的马耶公爵夫人，她亦原名多斯蒙，虽已年过80仍神采奕奕，灰色的头发从前额向上梳起，令人想起高等法院法官头戴的卷曲假发。我还记得我的父母常常同布瓦涅夫人的侄子多斯蒙先生共进晚餐，她的回忆录便是为他所写。我曾在父母的信件中见过他的照片，也见过许多他写给我父母的信件。所以我自己关于舞会的最早记忆由我父母已不甚清晰但仍真实的叙述之线牵着，通过几乎早已无形的联系与布瓦涅夫人保存下来的回忆相连，她在其中对我们讲述了自己亲身经历的最早的社交活动；所有这一切织成一张琐碎但诗意盎然的网，它像梦境般终结，如同一座纤细的桥梁飞架于现在和已然远去的过去之间，将生活与历史相连，使历史充满生机，使生活有史可循。

12.唉，我已经写到报纸第三栏的篇幅，却尚未开始我的文章。文章题目本该是“虚荣与后世”，但我不能留着这个标题，因为我已填满了为我预留的空白，却只字未提有关虚荣或后世这两位你认为一定不会再碰面的人物，这尤其是后者的福气，关于他我本想让你听听我受布瓦涅夫人回忆录的启发得出的思考。那只能等到下次了。到时，如果不断出现在我的思想和其目标之间的幻影又像在梦中一样前来干扰我的注意力，让我分心，我会将其推开，就像尤利西斯[71]用宝剑推开拥挤在身边向他乞求人形或得以埋葬的影子们那样。

13.而今天我无力抗拒这些幻象的诱惑，我看到它们漂浮于半空，在我思想的透明中。我尝试过，但未能像玻璃制作大师那样获得成功，他会在他的幻梦显现之处将其转移并固定，在两种被黑暗的粉色反光所笼罩的液体之间，在半透明的物质里，来自中心的一道道光芒会让它们以为仍然存在于活的思想当中。就像古代雕刻家从海水中攫取的仙女涅瑞伊德[72]，她们游弋于浮雕的大理石波浪中，还能够相信自己仍然浸没在大海中。我错了。这再也不会发生了。下一次我会与你讨论虚荣与后世，不再跑题。如果有什么不合时宜的想法，什么鲁莽的异想天开的念头想要掺杂进来，再次打断我们，我会立即求它放过我们：“小姐，我们正在谈话，请别打断我们！”

圣伯夫之道[73]

（节选）

……

1.因此在我看来，关于圣伯夫，我有些话自有其重要性，这在当前更多的是借其发挥而不是只论及他本人，而且，通过指出他作为作家和评论家的错误之处，我应该能够就我常常想到的事发表些意见，如批评应该是什么，艺术是什么。作为附带，关于他，就像他经常做的那样，我会以他为借口谈到一些生活的形式……

……

2.关于对圣伯夫方法的定义与褒扬，我曾参考过保罗·布尔热[74]的文章，因为他的定义简洁，褒扬具有权威性。我还能再引用其他20个评论家。为理解某人的作品及其天才的特质，他为其撰写心灵的自然史，参考其生平、其家族史及其所有的特殊之处，人们公认这是圣伯夫的独到之处，他本人也这么认为，而且确乎其然。丹纳[75]本人便梦想着一部更加系统化、规范化的人类精神的自然史，尽管圣伯夫就种族问题与他有分歧，他对圣伯夫的颂扬却并无异议：“圣伯夫的方法同他的作品一样珍贵。在这点上他是先驱，他将自然史的进程引入了精神史。”

……

3.但在艺术中并无创始者或先驱（至少在科学的意义上是如此）。一切存乎个人，每一个个体为了自己重新开始艺术或文学的求索。前人的作品并不像在科学中那样构成已知真理，可供后人获利。今天一名天才作家自有其一切要做，他并不比荷马先进许多。

4.但对于那些无法在艺术中找到真实且独立于所有科学的东西的哲学家，他们不得不认为艺术、批评等就像科学一样，前人必然不如后人先进。

5.但何必引用所有那些认为这便是圣伯夫方法论的独到出色之处的名人呢？只需让他自己说话便可。

6.“对我而言，”圣伯夫说，“文学与人及其结构的其他方面并无不同，并且无论如何不可分离……如果想去了解一个人，一个不仅仅是纯粹理智的人，那么用再多不同的方式或从再多不同的视角出发都不为过。直到你就一个作家提出了一系列的问题并找到了答案，哪怕只是悄声为自己回答，你才能确定掌握了他的整体，即使这些问题似乎与其写作的性质完全无关：他的宗教思想为何？自然界的现象是如何影响着他？他对女人、金钱的态度如何？他是富有还是贫穷？他的饮食规律、日常习惯是什么？他的缺陷或弱点是什么？所有这些问题的答案都不是无关紧要的，如果我们要对一名作者或一本书作出判断的话，只要这书不是单纯的几何论文集，如果这是一部囊括一切的文学作品的话，那就更是如此，等等。”他下意识地终生使用这种方法，并最终勾勒出某种文学植物学的框架……

7.圣伯夫的作品并无深奥之处。他著名的方法论，根据丹纳、保罗布尔热和众多他人的见解，那使他成为19世纪无与匹敌的批评大师的方法论——不将人与其作品分开，认为除非是“纯几何论文集”，我们若想判断一位作家的话就应首先回答那些似乎与其作品无关的问题（他如何为人处世……），收集关于他的所有事实，整理他的所有通信，向所有认识过他的人询问，他们若还活着就去采访他们，若已死去就去阅读所有他们写下的关于他的东西——这种方法论未能认识到任何对自身稍有深层了解便知道的：一本书是另一个自我的产物，无关我们在习惯、交往、缺陷中所展示的自我。如果我们试着在内心重新创造，我们就可能成功地尝试并理解这自我，这深藏内心的自我。这是心灵的努力，别无他途。这是一种真理，一点一滴都要我们去创造……别过于轻易地以为它会在某个晴朗的早晨以未发表的信件的形式通过邮件来到我们手里，由一位当图书馆员的友人寄来，或者能够从一个熟知作者的人的口中得知。在谈到司汤达[76]的作品在几位新一代作家当中所激起的敬仰之情时，圣伯夫说：“请允许我告诉他们，如果我们要清晰且毫无夸张地评判他那相当复杂的思想，我会抛开自己的印象和回忆，去询问在他的全盛时代和刚刚开始写作生涯的时候认识他的人们的意见，去询问梅里美、安培，还有雅克蒙[77]对他的看法，假设他还活着的话，简言之，去询问见过他并喜爱过他早期作品的人们。”

8.为什么？司汤达的友人如何能够帮助我们更好地评价他？相反，这很可能构成严重的妨碍。对这些密友来说，创造作品的自我被另一个自我所掩盖，后者可能远逊于许多其他人外在的自我。对这一点最好的验证就是，认识司汤达，收集了所有从“梅里美先生”和“安培先生”那里得来的事实，总之用所有据他所说能使批评家更准确评价一部作品的一切武装了自己之后，圣伯夫这样评价司汤达：“我刚刚读过，或者试着刚刚读过司汤达的小说，坦白地说，令人厌憎。”

……

9.他以这两条宝贵的见解作结：“尽管直率地批评贝尔的小说，我倒也不责怪他写了它们……他的小说虽然如此，但并不庸俗。它们就像他的评论，主要为撰写它们的人服务……”还有该文的结语：“说完我们的意见之后，千万不要忘记承认他在为人处事上根本的坦白和可靠。”总而言之，一个大好人。要得出这个结论也许大可不必煞费苦心地多次借晚餐之机或在学院拜会梅里美先生，或者经常“安排安培先生谈话”，而读过这一结论后我们亦不必如圣伯夫那样为晚生后代忧心忡忡了。

……

10.圣伯夫似乎从未曾把握灵感或写作活动的特殊性，以及它与其他人或作家的其他活动迥然不同之处。在孤独的写作活动中，我们赶走那些和他人共用的词语，那些让我们即便在独处时判断事物也会失去自我的词语，我们终于再次与自我面对，寻求倾听并还原我们心灵的真正声音——而他却将写作和交谈混为一谈！

11.虚假的表象让作家的作品显得模糊而外在，却让社交显得深刻而具沉思感。事实上作家向公众展示的是他独自为自己所写，在很大程度上是他自我的产品……一个人在社交中，亦即在谈话中（无论是多么高雅的谈话，而最高雅的也是最糟的，因为它关乎我们的精神生活，从而将之扭曲：福楼拜同他的侄女或钟表匠的交谈便无此危险），或者在为至交亲朋准备的作品，也就是只为吸引极少数人，充其量不过是书面谈话的作品中，所展示的都是十分外在的自我，而不是深层的自我，这深层的自我只有在不去理会他人，也不去理会与他人相识的那个自我时才能被发现，你同他人在一起时它就在一旁等待，你能清晰地感到那才是唯一真实的自我，艺术家最终只为它而活，它如神祇般令艺术家越来越难以离弃，并甘愿为之牺牲生命，那只为它带来荣耀的生命。

……

12.不曾看到将作家与名流分裂的鸿沟，不曾理解作家的自我仅仅表现在他的书里，他向社交界人物（即便是面对其他作家，他们只在独处时才重新成为作家，在社交场合便都是社交界人物）所展现的只是他作为名流的一面，不曾明了这一切，圣伯夫便抛出了那著名的，让丹纳、布尔热还有许多其他人纷纷认可的使他一举成名的方法论，其要旨是，为了理解一名诗人或作家，需热切征询那些认识过他、与他常往来的人，向他们探听诸如他与女人的相处之道等所有那些恰恰无关诗人真实自我的方方面面。

……

13.我们发现圣伯夫相信他所享受的沙龙生活对文学不可或缺，并使之穿越世纪的时光，时而到路易十四的宫廷，时而到督政府的名人圏中，因而……事实上这位全天候创造者常常在星期天亦不休息，取悦好的鉴赏家，驳斥坏的鉴赏家，在每个星期一从中领受名誉的奖赏，他将全部文学看成是一种《月曜日丛谈》，也许有人会再去读它，但它们在当时必定是根据好鉴赏家的意见写成的，为了取悦而顾不得后世如何。他将文学归于时间范畴。[……]文学于他似乎是件时事，取决于人的价值。总之，宁可扮演重要的政治角色而不写作，也不要政治上不得志而去写一部道德的书……因此他与爱默生不同，后者说我们必须胸系宇宙，而他却试图纠缠于最偶然之事：政治。

……

14.有时我会想，圣伯夫的诗是否仍可被称为他最好的东西。他的诗篇中不再有智力游戏。他不再以无穷无尽的聪明伶俐迂回曲折。神奇而可恶的循环被打破了。不再用散文体说话他便不再撒谎，就好像对他而言，他思想不间断的谎言来自精心雕琢的表达技巧。正如一名被迫用拉丁文表达的学生，不得不放弃修辞，将思想袒露，圣伯夫发现自己第一次直面现实并获得了直接的感受。[……]至于他自己，他深层的、无意识的、个体的自我，除了拙劣之外几乎别无所长。他频频如此，乃是天性使然。但他的诗虽微不足道却真诚而令人愉快，它们笔法巧妙，有时成功地表达了爱的纯洁、都市里午后的忧伤、回忆的魔力、阅读的激情、多疑老者的惆怅，这些诗——我们感到这是关于他唯一真实的事物——表明，作为批评家，他那浩如烟海、天花乱坠的作品毫无意义——因为不过如此。《月曜日丛谈》，表象而已。这几首小诗才是现实。这是一名批评家的诗，在他所有的作品中只有这些诗能令永恒的天平向他倾斜。

普鲁斯特解释《在斯万家那边》

[发表于1913年11月]

1.“我即将发表的是全称为《追忆似水年华》的小说中的一卷，《在斯万家那边》。我本想一次全部带来，但分成几卷的作品已不再发表了。就好像我有一幅对现在的寓所来说太大的挂毯，不得不将之剪开。”

2.“年轻作家们——我在其他方面倒与他们颇为投契——却与此相反，鼓吹简洁的情节，少量的人物。那并非我的小说观。怎样对你解释呢？你知道有平面几何和立体几何。那么，对于我，小说并不仅只是平面心理，而是时间中的心理。我曾试图分离出时间这不可见的物质，但为此必须进行长久的实验。我希望在我的书的结尾处，某个微不足道的社交事件，比如两个在第一卷中属于完全不同世界的人的婚姻能够表明，时间流逝了，它会呈现出如凡尔赛宫绿锈斑斑的铅制品之美，那是时间将其封存于绿宝石般的外壳之中。”

3.“那么，就像你乘着一列沿着弯曲轨道行驶的火车，外面的城市时现于左、时现于右，某个人物在另一个人的眼中会呈现出多个侧面，甚至像是不同而连续的几个人物，这会带来——但只是因此带来——时间流逝的感觉。特定的人物到后来会表现得与在当前这一卷中完全不同，也会异于人们认为他们将要成为的样子，就像生活中常常发生的那样。”

4.“这并不是同样的人物在作品进程中会以不同的面貌重新出现，像在巴尔扎克的某些系列中那样，而是，”普鲁斯特先生对我们说，“在单个人物当中某些深刻的、几乎是无意识的印象。”

5.“从这个观点来看，”普鲁斯特先生接着说，“我的书也许看起来像是‘无意识小说’的尝试。如果我相信这一点的话我会毫无愧色地称之为‘柏格森式的小说’[78]，因为在每一个时代都是如此，文学总是试图将自己——当然是后知后觉——与流行的哲学思潮联系起来。但这么说并不准确，因为主宰我作品的是无意识回忆和有意识回忆之间的区别，这一区别在柏格森先生的哲学中不但不曾出现，而且与之相抵触。”

6.“您如何验证这一区别？”

7.“对我，有意识的回忆首先是理智和视觉的回忆，它仅仅带来过去的一些方面，其中并无真相。但当我们在完全不同的场合再次与一种气息或味道邂逅，不自觉地将过去唤醒，我们便能感到这过去与我们以为还记得的过去是多么不同，后者被我们的有意识回忆用错误的色彩去描绘，就像一个拙劣的画家一样。就在这第一卷里，你会发现自称‘我’（他并不是我）的叙述者突然间，在啜饮着浸过一点儿玛德琳蛋糕的茶水时，重新找回了他久已忘却的年代、花园、人物。无疑他也能有意识地想起它们，但并无其神采。我借他之口说，就像那小小的日本游戏，你把一团团薄薄的纸浸入水碗中，它们便开始伸展、卷曲，形成花朵和人物，同样，他花园里的所有花朵，维弗纳的睡莲，村子里的好人们，他们小小的房子和教堂，还有整个贡布雷及其周遭环境，所有能够产生形状与质地的东西，城镇与花园，都在他的茶杯中浮现。”

8.“你看，我相信艺术家唯有求助于无意识回忆才能找到其作品的原材料。首先，正因为它们是无意识的，完全凭自己的心意形成，源于一些同样时刻的相似性，它们本身便带着真实性的标记。其次，它们所带来的事物仍以原来精确的记忆与遗忘的比例呈现。最后，因为它们让我们领略到的是在完全不同的场合下同样的感受，这感受便脱离了偶然性，具有了超时间的本质，而这便是优秀风格的内涵，是唯有风格之美才能揭示的普遍必然的真理。”

9.“如果我允许自己这样理性地分析我的书，”普鲁斯特先生接着说道，“那是因为它在任何程度上都不是理性的产物，它最细微的元素均由我的感性带来，我首先从内在自我的深处觉察到它们，并不理解并且很难将它们转变成某种理智的东西，就如同——我该怎么说呢——音乐动机一般与理智世界格格不入。我猜你觉得这一切太高深莫测了。但你放心，正好相反，它是现实。我们无需为自己澄清的东西，早已经明晰的东西（比如逻辑概念），并不真正属于我们，我们甚至不知道它是否真实。它是我们任意选择的‘可能性’的一部分。此外，你知道，你从风格上立刻就能辨别出来。”

10.“风格绝非某些人认为的是一种修饰，它甚至不是技术问题，它是——就像画家手中的色彩——视相的特质，是仅我们每个人自己所见、不为他人得见的隐秘宇宙的显现。艺术家为我们带来的愉悦就是引领我们进入另一个宇宙。”

John Ruskin

1. One by one, like the 'muses leaving their father Apollo to go and bring light to the world', Ruskin's ideas left the godlike head which had borne them and, embodied in living books, went to bring instruction to the nations. Ruskin had withdrawn into the solitude in which prophetic existences often end until it pleases God to call back the cenobite or ascetic whose superhuman task is done. And the mystery which was being fulfilled, the slow destruction of a perishable brain which had harboured an immortal posterity, could only be guessed at, through the veil stretched over it by pious hands.

2. Today death has put mankind in possession of the immense inheritance that Ruskin bequeathed to it. For the man of genius can only give birth to works which will not die by creating them in the image not of the mortal being that he is, but of the exemplum of mankind he bears within him. His thoughts are in some sense lent to him for his lifetime, of which they are the companions. On his death they return to mankind and instruct it. Such as that august family dwelling in the rue de la Rochefoucauld known as the home of Gustave Moreau while he yet lived and since his death as the Musée Gustave Moreau.

3. There has long been a John Ruskin Museum (in Sheffield). Its catalogue is like an epitome of all the arts and all the sciences. Photographs of paintings by the masters are found next to collections of minerals, as in Goethe's house. Like the Ruskin Museum, Ruskin's oeuvre is universal. He sought the truth, he found beauty even in chronological charts and the laws of society. But the logicians having so defined the 'Fine Arts' as to exclude mineralogy as well as political economy, it is only of that part of Ruskin's oeuvre which concerns the 'Fine Arts' as they are generally understood, of Ruskin as aesthetician and art critic, that I shall have to speak here.

4. It was said first of all that he was a realist. And indeed he often reiterated that the artist should apply himself to the pure imitation of nature, 'without rejecting, despising, choosing anything'.

5. But it has been said also that he was an intellectualist for he wrote that the best picture was the one which contained the loftiest ideas. Speaking of the group of children who are amusing themselves sailing toy boats in the foreground of Turner's 'Building of Carthage', he concludes: 'The exquisite choice of this incident, as expression of the ruling passion which was to be the source of the future greatness of the new city ... is quite as appreciable when it is told as when it is seen, it has nothing to do with the technicalities of painting; a scratch of the pen would have conveyed the idea and spoken to the intellect as much as the elaborate realizations of colour. Such a thought as this is something far above all art; it is epic poetry of the highest order.' 'In the same way,' adds Milsand, who quotes this passage, 'when he analyses a "Holy Family" by Tintoretto, the feature by which Ruskin recognizes a great master is a ruined wall and the beginnings of some masonry, by means of which the artist gives us symbolically to understand that the birth of Christ was the end of the Jewish economy and the advent of the new alliance. A composition by the same Venetian painter, a "Crucifixion", Ruskin finds to be a masterpiece of painting because the artist has been able, by a seemingly insignificant incident, by introducing a donkey grazing off some palm leaves in the background to Calvary, to state the profound idea that it was Jewish materialism, with its expectation of a purely temporal Messiah and with the disappointment of its hopes at the entry into Jerusalem, that was the source of the hatred unleashed against the Saviour and hence of his death.'

6. It has been said that he did away with the role of imagination in art by giving too large a role to science. Did he not say that: '... every class of rock, earth and cloud, must be known by the painter, with geologic and meteorologic accuracy ... Every geological formation has features peculiar to itself; definite lines of fracture, giving rise to fixed resultant forms of rock and earth; peculiar vegetable products, among which still further distinctions are wrought out by variations of climate and elevation ... [The painter] observes every character of the plant's colour and form ... he seizes on its lines of ... rigidity or repose ... observes its local habits, its love or fear of peculiar places, its nourishment or destruction by particular influences; he associates it in his mind with all the features of the situation it inhabits ... He must render the delicate fissure, and descending curve, and undulating shadow of the mouldering soil with gentle and fine finger like the touch of the rain itself ... The greatest picture is that which conveys to the mind of the spectator the greatest number of the greatest ideas.'

7. But it has been said in return that he ruined science by giving too large a place in it to the imagination. And indeed, one can but think of the simple-minded finalism of Bernardin de Saint-Pierre saying that God has divided melons into slices so as to make them easier for men to eat, when one reads passages such as this: '... God has employed colour in His creation as the unvarying accompaniment of all that is purest, most innocent, and most precious; while for things precious only in material uses, or dangerous, common colours are used ... look at a dove's neck, and compare it with the grey back of a viper ... So again, the crocodile and alligator are grey, but the innocent lizard green and beautiful.'

8. Although it has been said that he reduced art to being merely the vassal of science, since he carried his theory of the work of art seen as giving us facts about the nature of things to the point of declaring that 'a Turner discloses more about the nature of rocks than any academy will ever know,' and that 'a Tintoretto need only let his hand go to reveal a multitude of truths about the play of the muscles which will confound all of the world's anatomists,' it has been said also that he humbled science before art.

9. It has been said lastly that he was a pure aesthetician and that his one religion was that of Beauty, because he in fact loved it throughout his life.

10. But it has been said on the other hand that he was not even an artist, because into his appreciation of beauty he intruded considerations that were perhaps higher but were certainly alien to aesthetics. The first chapter of The Seven Lamps of Architecture lays down that the architect should use the most precious and durable materials, an obligation made to derive from the sacrifice ofJesus and the permanent conditions of that sacrifice agreeable to God, conditions we have no call to think have been modified, God not having let us know explicitly that they have been. And here is one of his arguments in Modern Painters, in order to settle the question of knowing who is right between the supporters of colour and the adepts of chiaroscuro: '... but take a wider view of nature, and compare generally rainbows, sunrises, roses, violets, butterflies, birds, gold-fish, rubies, opals, and corals, with alligators, hippopotami, ... sharks, slugs, bones, fungi, fogs, and corrupting, stinging, destroying things in general, and you will feel then how the question stands between the colourists and the chiaroscurists,—which of them have nature and life on their side, and which have sin and death.'

11. And because so many contrary things have been said about Ruskin, the conclusion is that he was contradictory.

12. Of all these aspects of Ruskin's physiognomy, the one we are most familiar with, because it is the one of which we possess, if I may so put it, the most painstaking and successful, the most striking and widely known portrait, is the Ruskin who throughout his life knew of only one religion: that of Beauty.

13. It may be the literal truth that the worship of Beauty was the perpetual activity of Ruskin's life; but I adjudge that the object of that life, its deep, secret and constant intention, was other, and if I say so it is not in order to go against the system of M. de la Sizeranne, but to prevent his being depreciated in readers' minds by an interpretation which is false but natural and as if inevitable.

14. Not only was Ruskin's principal religion religion as such (I shall return to this point in a moment, because it dominates and characterizes his aesthetic), but to remain for the present with his 'Religion of Beauty', our own age must be warned that, if it wishes to refer truthfully to Ruskin, it cannot utter these words without emending the sense which its aesthetic dilettantism is too inclined to lend to them. In fact, for an age of dilettantes and aesthetes, a worshipper of Beauty is a man who, practising no other form of worship but his own, and acknowledging no other god but it, must spend his life in the enjoyment afforded by the voluptuous contemplation of works of art.

15. But, for reasons the wholly metaphysical search for which would go beyond a mere essay on art, Beauty cannot be loved in a fruitful manner if one loves it simply for the pleasures it affords. And just as to seek for happiness for its own sake leads only to tedium, and to find it one must seek for something other than it, so aesthetic pleasure is given to us in addition if we love Beauty for its own sake, as something real existing outside of ourselves and infinitely more important than the joy it affords us. Very far from being a dilettante or an aesthete, Ruskin was the precise opposite, one of those Carlyle-like men warned by their genius of the vanity of all pleasure and at the same time of the presence close beside them of a timeless reality, intuitively perceived by their inspiration. Their talent is given to them as an ability to capture this omnipotent and timeless reality, to which they dedicate, enthusiastically and as if in obedience to a command from their conscience, their fleeting lifetimes, in order to endow them with value. Such men, attentive and anxious, faced by a universe needing to be deciphered, are warned as to those elements of reality on which their special gifts will shed a peculiar light for them, by a sort of demon who guides them, of a voice that they can hear, the timeless inspiration of beings of genius. Ruskin's special gift was the sense of Beauty, in nature as in art. It was in Beauty that his temperament led him to seek for reality, and hence his wholly religious life was spent wholly aesthetically. But he did not conceive of the Beauty to which he thus found himself devoting his life as an object of enjoyment designed to attract him, but as a reality infinitely more important than life itself, for which he would have given his own life. You will see Ruskin's aesthetic follow from this. You must understand first of all that the years in which he came to know a new school of architecture or of painting may have been the principal landmarks of his moral life. He can speak of the years when the Gothic made its appearance for him with the same gravity, the same recurrence of emotion, the same serenity as a Christian speaks of the day when the truth was revealed to him. The events of his life were intellectual ones and its important landmarks those when he penetrated into a new form of art, the year when he understood Abbeville, the year when he understood Rouen, the day when the painting of Titian and the shadows in Titian's painting seemed nobler to him than the painting of Rubens and the shadows in Rubens's painting.

16. You must understand next that the poet being for Ruskin, as for Carlyle, a sort of scribe writing down at nature's dictation a more or less important part of her secret, the artist's first duty is to add nothing of his own pressing to this message from God. From which height the complaints of realism as well as of intellectualism directed at Ruskin can be seen to evaporate, like clouds that hug the ground. If such objections are wide of the mark, it is because they do not aim high enough. Such criticisms mistake the right altitude. The reality which the artist must record is at once material and intellectual. Matter is real because it is an expression of the mind. As for mere appearances, no one was more sardonic than Ruskin about those who see the object of art as being their imitation. 'The simple pleasure in the imitation,' he says, 'would be precisely of the same degree (if the accuracy could be equal), whether the subject of it were the hero or his horse ... we may consider tears as a result of agony or of art, whichever we please, but not of both at the same moment. If we are surprised by them as an attainment of the one, it is impossible we can be moved by them as a sign of the other.' If he attaches such importance to the way things look, this is because it alone reveals their underlying nature. M. de la Sizer-anne has given us an admirable translation of a passage where Ruskin shows that the 'leading' lines of a tree can reveal to us which troublesome trees have pushed it to one side, which winds have tormented it, etc. The configuration of something is not simply the image of its nature, it is the clue to its destiny and the transcript of its history.

17. Another consequence of which conception of art is this: if reality is one and the man of genius he who sees it, what importance does the substance in which he represents it have, be it pictures, statues, symphonies, laws, actions? In his Heroes and Hero-Worship Carlyle makes no distinction between Shakespeare and Cromwell, Mohammed and Burns. Emerson numbers Swedenborg as well as Montaigne among his Representative Men. Where the system goes too far is, because the reality being translated is one, in not distinguishing profoundly enough between the different modes of translation. Carlyle says that it was inevitable that Boccaccio and Petrarch should have been good diplomats because they were good poets. Ruskin commits the same error when he says that 'a painting is beautiful to the extent that the ideas it translates into images are independent of the language of images.' If Ruskin's system errs in any direction, it is in this one, it seems to me. Because painting cannot attain to the unitary reality of things and hence compete with literature, except on condition that it not be literary.

18. If Ruskin promulgated the artist's duty as being scrupulously to obey these 'voices' of his genius which tell him what is real and to be transcribed, it was because he himself had had experience of what was genuine in inspiration, infallible in enthusiasm and fruitful in reverence. Only, although what excites enthusiasm, commands reverence and prompts inspiration be different for each one of us, we each end by attributing to it a more particularly sacred character. It can be said that for Ruskin this revelation, this guide was the Bible.

19. Here let us pause as at a fixed point, at the centre of gravity of Ruskin's aesthetic. Thus it was that his religious sense directed his aesthetic sense. And first, to those who may think that it adulterated it, that into the artistic appreciation of monuments, statues and pictures it introduced religious considerations which had no place there, I shall answer that it was quite the reverse. That something divine which Ruskin sensed deep inside the feeling inspired in him by works of art was precisely what was profound and original about that feeling, which imposed itself on his taste without being susceptible to modification. And the religious reverence that he brought to the expression of this feeling, his fear of subjecting it to the least distortion in translating it, prevented him, contrary to what has often been supposed, from ever introducing into his impressions of works of art any artifice of reasoning that was foreign to them. So that those who see in him a moralist or an apostle loving in art what is not art, are equally as mistaken as those who, ignoring the profound essence of his aesthetic feeling, confuse it with a sensual dilettantism. So that, finally, his religious fervour, which had been the token of his aesthetic sincerity, further reinforced it and shielded it against all interference from without. It is as I see it of no importance that this or that notion of his supernatural aesthetic should be false. All those who have some idea of the laws by which genius develops know that its strength is measured more by the strength of its beliefs than by whatever satisfaction the object of those beliefs may offer to common sense. But since Ruskin's Christianity was of the very essence of his intellectual nature, his artistic preferences, equally profound, had to have some kinship with it. And so, just as his love of Turner's landscapes corresponded in Ruskin to that love of nature which afforded him his greatest joys, so to the fundamentally Christian nature of his thought there corresponded his permanent predilection, which dominated the whole of his life, the whole of his work, for what may be called Christian art: the architecture and sculpture of the French Middle Ages, the architecture, sculpture and painting of the Italian Middle Ages. There is no need to search in his life for evidence of the disinterested passion with which he loved their works, you will find the proof of it in his books. So vast was his experience that very often the most thorough knowledge displayed in one work is neither used nor mentioned, even by way of allusion, in those other of his books where it would be appropriate. Such are his resources that he does not lend us his words; he gives them to us and does not take them back. You know, for example, that he wrote a book on Amiens cathedral. From which you might conclude that that was the cathedral he loved the most and knew the best. Yet in The Seven Lamps of Architecture, where Rouen cathedral is named forty times as an example, and that of Bayeux nine times, Amiens is not named once. In Val d'Arno, he confesses that the church that made him the most profoundly drunk on Gothic was Saint-Urbain in Troyes. Yet, not once in The Seven Lamps nor in The Bible of Amiens is mention made of Saint-Urbain. So far as the lack of references to Amiens in The Seven Lamps is concerned, perhaps you imagine that he only came to know Amiens at the end of his life? Far from it. In 1859, in a lecture given in Kensington, he compares the Vierge Dorée of Amiens at length with the statues, less skilful as art but more profound in feeling, which appear to be holding up the west porch of Chartres. Yet in The Bible of Amiens, where one might suppose that he had brought together all his thoughts about Amiens, not once, in the pages where he speaks of the Vierge Dorée, does he make reference to the statues of Chartres. Such is the infinite wealth of his love and of his knowledge. Usually, with a writer, the harking back to certain favourite examples, or even the repetition of certain developments, reminds us that we have to deal with a man who had a certain life, particular knowledge which took the place of some other knowledge, and a limited experience from which he drew all the advantage he could. Merely by consulting the index to Ruskin's various books, the constant novelty of the works cited there, and even more the spurning or, very often, abandoning for good of an item of knowledge used only once, give one a sense of something more than human, or rather the impression that each book is by someone new, who has other knowledge, not the same experience, another life.

20. The delightful game he played with his inexhaustible riches was forever to be drawing new treasures out from the wonderful jewel-cases of his memory: one day the precious rose window of Amiens, another day the golden lacework of the porch at Abbeville, and to wed these to the dazzling gems of Italy.

21. He was able indeed to pass from one country to another in this way because the same soul that he had worshipped in the stones of Pisa was that which had also given their immortal form to the stones of Chartres. No one has had his sense of the oneness of the Christian art of the Middle Ages, from the banks of the Somme to the banks of the Arno, and he has realized in our hearts the dream of the great medieval popes for a 'Christian Europe'. If, as has been said, his name has to remain tied to Pre-Raphaelitism, we should understand by that not the one following Turner but that from before Raphael. Today we can forget the services he rendered to Hunt, to Rossetti, to Millais; but we cannot forget what he did for Giotto, for Carpaccio, for Bellini. His godlike task was not to arouse the living but to resurrect the dead.

22. Is this oneness of the Christian art of the Middle Ages not everywhere to be seen in the perspective of those passages in which his imagination here and there illuminates the stones of France with a magical reflection from Italy? A moment ago we saw him in Pleasures of England comparing the Amiens Charity with that of Giotto. In The Nature of Gothic see how he compares the way in which flames are treated in Italian Gothic and in French, where he takes the porch of Saint-Maclou in Rouen for his example. And in The Seven Lamps of Architecture, in connection with this same porch, see how something of the colours of Italy plays over its grey stones.

23. 'The subject of the tympanum bas-relief is the Last Judgement, and the sculpture of the Inferno side is carried out with a degree of power whose fearful grotesqueness I can only describe as a mingling of the minds of Orcagna and Hogarth. The demons are perhaps even more awful than Orcagna's; and, in some of the expressions of debased humanity in its utmost despair, the English painter is at least equalled. Not less wild is the imagination which gives fury and fear even to the placing of the figures. An evil angel, poised on the wing, drives the condemned troops from before the Judgement seat ... but they are urged by him so furiously, that they are driven not merely to the extreme limit of that scene, which the sculptor confined elsewhere within the tympanum, but out of the tympanum and into the niches of the arch; while the flames that follow them, bent by the blast, as it seems, of the angel's wings, rush into the niches also, and burst up through their tracery, the three lowermost niches being represented as all on fire, while, instead of their usual vaulted and ribbed ceiling, there is a demon in the roof of each, with his wings folded over it, grinning down out of the black shadow.'

24. Nor was this parallelism between the different kinds of art and different countries the most profound one he was to insist on. He was to be struck by the identity of certain religious ideas in pagan and Christian symbols. M. Ary Renan has remarked, very profoundly, how much of Christ there is in Gustave Moreau's Prometheus. Ruskin, whose devotion to Christian art never made him contemptuous of paganism, compared in an aesthetic and religious sense the lion of St Jerome with the Nemean lion, Virgil with Dante, Samson with Hercules, Theseus with the Black Prince, the prophecies of Isaiah with the prophecies of the Cumean sibyl. There is no call, certainly, to liken Ruskin to Gustave Moreau, but it can be said that a natural tendency, fostered by their acquaintance with the Primitives, led both to proscribe in art the expression of violent feelings and, in so far as it was applied to the study of symbols, to a certain fetishism in the worship of the symbols themselves, a fetishism that carried few dangers however for minds so fundamentally attached to the feeling symbolized that they could pass from one symbol to another without being detained by mere differences of surface. As for the systematic prohibition of the expression of violent emotion in art, the principle which M. Ary Renan has called the principle of Beautiful Inertia, where can we find it better defined than in the passages on 'The relation of Michaelangelo to Tintoretto'?[【1】] Was it not inevitable that his study of medieval French and Italian art should lead to his somewhat exclusive worship of symbols? And because he was searching, beneath the work of art, for the soul of an age, the resemblance between the symbols of the portal at Chartres and the frescoes of Pisa was bound to affect him as a proof of the originality typical of the spirit by which artists were then inspired, and their differences as evidence of its variety. With anyone else the aesthetic response might have risked being chilled by reasoning. But in him all was love, and iconography, as he understood it, might better have been called iconolatry. At this point, moreover, art criticism gives way to something greater perhaps; its procedures are those almost of science, it is a contribution to history. The appearance in the porches of cathedrals of some new quality informs us of changes no less profound in the history, not only of art but of civilization, as those announced to geologists by the appearance on earth of a new species. The stone sculpted by nature is no more instructive than the stone sculpted by the artist, and we derive no greater profit from that which preserves for us some ancient monster than that which exhibits a new god to us.

25. From this point of view the drawings which accompany Ruskin's writings are highly significant. In the one plate you may find a single architectural motif as treated at Lisieux, Bayeux, Verona and Padua, as if we had to do with the varieties of a single species of butterfly in different climes. But the stones which he so loved never become abstract examples for him. On each stone you can see the nuance of the passing moment joined with the colour of the centuries. '... Rushing down the street to see St Wulfran again,' he tells us, 'before the sun was off the towers, are things to cherish the past for, — to the end.' He went further even; he made no separation between the cathedrals and that background of rivers and valleys against which they appear to the traveller as he approaches, like in a primitive painting. One of his most instructive drawings in this respect is that reproduced in the second engraving of 'Our Fathers have told us' entitled 'Amiens, Jour des Trépassés'. In the towns of Amiens, Abbeville, Beauvais and Rouen, consecrated by Ruskin's stay in them, he spent his time sketching, either in the churches ('without being disturbed by the sacristan') or else in the open air. And what delightful, transient colonies they must have formed in these towns, the troupe of sketchers and engravers whom he took with him, just as Plato shows us the Sophists following Protagoras from town to town, and similar also to the swallows, in imitation of which they would pause for choice on the old roofs and ancient towers of the cathedrals. Perhaps some of these disciples of Ruskin's are still to be met with who accompanied him to the banks of this re-evangelized Somme, as if the days of St Firmin and St Salve had returned, and who, while the new apostle was talking and explicating Amiens like a Bible, made instead of notes drawings, graceful notes the folder of which is doubtless to be found in some English museum room and in which I imagine reality will have been slightly rearranged, in the style of Viollet-le-Duc. The engraving 'Amiens, Jour des Trépassés' seems a little too beautiful to be true. Is it the perspective alone which, from the banks of a widened Somme, brings the cathedral and the church of St Leu so close together? Ruskin it is true might answer us back by repeating on his own account the words of Turner which he quotes in The Eagle's Nest and which M. de la Sizeranne has translated: '... Turner, in his early life, was sometimes good- natured, and would show people what he was about. He was one day making a drawing of Plymouth harbour, with some ships at the distance of a mile or two, seen against the light. Having shown this drawing to a naval officer, the naval officer observed with surprise, and objected with very justifiable indignation, that the ships of the line had no port-holes. "No," said Turner, "certainly not. If you will walk up to Mount Edgecumbe, and look at the ships against the sunset, you will find you can't see the port-holes." "Well, but," said the naval officer, still indignant, "you know the port-holes are there." "Yes," said Turner, "I know that well enough; but my business is to draw what I see, and not what I know is there."'

26. If, when in Amiens, you take the direction of the slaughter-house, you will get a prospect no different from that in the engraving. You will see the distance arrange, in the deceptive but happy manner of an artist, monuments which, if you then draw closer, will resume their earlier, quite different positions; you will see it, for example, inscribe the shape of one of the town's water installations on the façade of the cathedral, and create a plane out of a three-dimensional geometry. But if you nevertheless find this landscape, tastefully composed by your perspective, somewhat different from that recounted by Ruskin's drawing, you may lay the blame above all on the changes brought about in the appearance of the town by the almost twenty years which have elapsed since Ruskin stayed there, and as he himself said of another location which he loved: 'Since I last composed, or meditated there, various improvements have taken place.'

27. But at least this engraving in The Bible of Amiens will have associated the banks of the Somme and the cathedral more closely together in your memory than your eyes no doubt could have done, no matter at what point in the town you had been placed. It will prove to you better than anything I could have said that Ruskin made no separation between the beauty of the cathedrals and the charm of the country out of which they arose, and which everyone who visits them can savour still in the particular poetry of the country and the misty or golden recollection of the afternoon he spent there. Not only is the first chapter of The Bible of Amiens called 'By the Rivers of Waters', but the book that Ruskin planned to write on Chartres cathedral was to be entitled. 'The Springs of Eure'. So it was not only in his drawings that he set churches on the edge of rivers and associated the grandeur of the Gothic cathedrals to the gracefulness of their French settings.[【2】] We would be more keenly alive to the individual charm of a landscape if we did not have at our disposal those seven-league boots which are the great expresses and were obliged, as in the old days, in order to get to some remote spot, to pass through countrysides more and more like that we are making for, like zones of graduated harmony which, by making it less easily penetrable by what is different from itself, and protecting it gently and mysteriously against brotherly resemblances, not only envelop it in nature but also prepare it in our minds.

28. These studies of Ruskin's of Christian art were for him like the verification and counter-proof of his ideas on Christianity and of other ideas I have been unable to indicate here but the most celebrated of which I shall allow Ruskin himself to define in a moment: his horror of machinism and of industrial art. 'All beautiful things were made when the men of the Middle Ages believed in the pure, joyous and beautiful lesson of Christianity.' After that he saw art as having declined along with faith, and dexterity as having taken the place of feeling. When he saw the power to realize beauty that was the privilege of the ages of faith, his belief in the goodness of faith could only grow stronger. Each volume of his last book, Our Fathers Have Told Us (only the first was written), was to have comprised four chapters, the last of them devoted to the masterpiece that was the fruition of the faith whose study had been the aim of the first three chapters. Thus did the Christianity that had been the cradle of Ruskin's aesthetic feeling receive its supreme consecration. And having mocked at his Protestant reader, at the moment when he led her before the statue of the Madonna, 'who must understand that neither Madonna-worship, nor Lady-worship of any sort ... ever did any human creature any harm', or before the statue of St Honoré, after lamenting that this saint was 'little talked of now in his Parisian faubourg', he might have said as at the end of Val d'Arno: 'And if you will fix your minds only on the conditions of human life which the Giver of it demands, "He hath showed thee, O man, what is good; and what doth the Lord require of thee, but to do justly, and to love mercy, and to walk humbly with thy God?" you will find that such obedience is always acknowledged by temporal blessing. If, turning from the manifest miseries of cruel ambition, and manifest wanderings of insolent belief, you summon to your thoughts rather the state of unrecorded multitudes, who laboured in silence, and adored in humility, as the snows of Christendom brought memory of the Birth of Christ, or her spring sunshine, of His Resurrection, you may know that the promise of the Bethlehem angels has been literally fulfilled; and will pray that your English fields, joyfully as the banks of Arno, may still dedicate their pure lilies to St Mary of the Flowers.'

29. Finally, Ruskin's medieval studies confirmed, together with his belief in the goodness of faith, his belief in the need for work to be free, joyous and personal, without interference from machinism. This you will best understand if I transcribe here a passage highly characteristic of Ruskin. He is talking of a small figure, a few centimetres high, lost amidst hundreds of minuscule figures, in the portal of the Booksellers in Rouen cathedral.

30. '... the fellow is vexed and puzzled in his malice; and his hand is pressed hard on his cheekbone, and the flesh of the cheek is wrinkled under the eye by the pressure. The whole, indeed, looks wretchedly coarse, when it is seen on a scale in which it is naturally compared with delicate figure etchings; but considering it as a mere filling of an interstice on the outside of a cathedral gate, and as one of more than three hundred (for in my estimate I did not include the outer pedestals), it proves very noble vitality in the art of the time ...

31. 'We have certain work to do for our bread, and that is to be done strenuously; other work to do for our delight, and that is to be done heartily: neither is to be done by halves and shifts, but with a will; and what is not worth this effort is not to be done at all. Perhaps all that we have to do is meant for nothing more than an exercise of the heart and of the will, and is useless in itself; but, at all events, the little use it has may well be spared if it is not worth putting our hands and our strength to. It does not become our immortality to take an ease inconsistent with its authority, nor to suffer any instruments with which it can dispense, to come between it and the things it rules: and he who would form the creations of his own mind by any other instrument than his own hand, would also, if he might, give grinding organs to Heaven's angels, to make their music easier. There is dreaming enough, and earthiness enough, and sensuality enough in human existence, without our turning the few glowing moments of it into mechanism; and since our life must at the best be but a vapour that appears for a little time and then vanishes away, let it at least appear as a cloud in the height of Heaven, not as the thick darkness that broods over the blast of the Furnace, and rolling of the Wheel.'

32. I will confess that rereading this passage at the time of Ruskin's death I was seized with a desire to see the little man he speaks of. And I went to Rouen as if in obedience to some testamentary thought, as if in dying Ruskin had somehow entrusted to his readers that poor creature whose life he had restored by speaking of him and who had, without knowing it, just lost for ever someone who had done as much for him as his original sculptor. But when I came close to the immense cathedral, before the door where the saints were warming themselves in the sun, higher up, from the galleries of radiant kings up to the very topmost heights of stone that I supposed to be uninhabited but where, in one place, a sculpted hermit led his isolated life, allowing the birds to dwell on his forehead, while in another a coterie of apostles was listening to the message of an angel who had settled beside them, wings folded, beneath a flock of pigeons that were opening theirs, and not far from a personage who had received a child on his back and was turning his head with a sudden, age-old gesture; when I saw, in rows before its porches or leaning from the balconies of its towers, all these stone guests of the mystical city breathing in the sunshine or the early morning shadows, I realized it would be impossible to find a figure a few centimetres high amidst this superhuman population. I went to the portal of the Booksellers none the less. But how to recognize the little figure among the hundreds of others? Suddenly a young sculptress of talent and of promise, Mme L. Yeatman, said to me: 'Here's one that looks like it.' We looked a little lower down, and ... there it was. It wasn't ten centimetres high. It has been worn away yet its gaze is there still, the stone still has the hole picking out the pupil and lending it the expression by which I recognized it. There, amidst thousands of others, an artist dead centuries before has left this little person who dies a little each day, and who had been dead for a very long time, lost in the midst of that host of others, for ever. But he had set it there. And one day a man for whom there is no death, no infinity of matter, no oblivion, a man who, casting far away from him that annihilation which weighs us down, to pursue ends that dominated his life, so many that he was unable to achieve them all whereas we seem to lack them, this man came, and seeing, in those waves of stone where one jagged crest seemed just like another, all the laws of life, all the soul's thoughts, named them by their names, and said: 'Look, it is this, it is that.' As at the Day of judgement, which is represented not far away, the trumpet of the archangel is to be heard in his words as he says: 'Those who have lived shall live, matter is nothing.' And indeed, like the dead represented not far away in the tympanum, who have been awoken by the archangel's trumpet and have arisen, have resumed their form, are recognizable and alive, so the little figure has come alive again and has recovered its gaze, and the Judge has said: 'Thou hast lived, thou shalt live.' He himself is not an immortal judge and his body will die; but what matter! He carries out his immortal task as if he were not going to die, unconcerned by the size of the object that occupies his time and, though having but one human life to live, he spends several days in front of one of the ten thousand figures on a church. He drew it. For him it corresponded to the ideas stirring in his brain, heedless of approaching old age. He drew it, he spoke of it. And the monstrous, inoffensive little figure was to be resurrected, against all hope, from that death which seems more absolute than others, that disappearance into the midst of an infinite number made anonymous by their resemblance, but out of which genius can quickly draw us also. Rediscovering it there, one could not but be moved. It seems to live and to be gazing, or rather to have been taken by death in the very act of gazing, like those Pompeians whose movements remain suspended. In fact it is the sculptor's idea that has been seized here in its movement by the immobility of the stone. I was touched to rediscover it there; nothing then dies of what has once lived, the sculptor's thought any more than that of Ruskin.

33. Coming upon it there, necessary to Ruskin, who devoted one of the very few engravings illustrating his book to it (The Seven Lamps of Architecture) because for him it was an actual and enduring part of his thought, and pleasing to me because his thought is necessary to me, a guide to my own which met with his along the way, I felt myself to be in a state of mind closer to that of the artists who carved the Last Judgement in the tympanum and who believed that the individual, that which is most particular in a person, in an intention, does not die but remains in the memory of God and will be resurrected. Who is right out of Hamlet and the gravedigger, when the one sees only a skull and the other recalls a fancy? Science may say: the gravedigger; but it reckons without Shakespeare, who will cause the memory of that fancy to endure beyond the dust of the skull. At the angel's summons, each one of the dead is found to be still there, in his place, when we had thought him long since turned to dust. At Ruskin's summons, we find the smallest figure, framing a tiny quatrefoil, resurrected in its form, gazing at us with the same gaze which seems to fit inside no more than a millimetre of stone. No doubt, poor little monster, I would not have been clever enough to find you, amongst the thousands of stones in our towns, to pick out your figure, to rediscover your personality, to summon you, to make you live again. Infinity, numbers, annihilation weigh us down, but it is not that they are so strong; it is that my mind is not very strong. True, there was nothing really beautiful about you. Your poor face, that I would never have noticed, does not have a very interesting expression, although obviously it has, as everyone does, an expression that no one else has ever had. But since you were sufficiently alive to continue to gaze with that same sideways gaze, for Ruskin to notice you and, after he had spoken your name, for his reader to be able to recognize you, are you sufficiently alive now, are you sufficiently loved? One can but think on you with tenderness, unkind though your look be, because you are a living creature, because, through long centuries, you were dead without hope of resurrection and because you have been resurrected. And one of these days perhaps some other person will go to seek you out in your portal, looking fondly on your oblique and spiteful face, now resurrected, because what has come from a human mind can alone one day arrest another mind which, in its turn, has fascinated our own. You were right to remain there, unregarded, crumbling away. You could hope for nothing from matter, in which you were mere nothingness. But the little ones have nothing to fear, nor do the dead. For sometimes the Spirit visits the earth; and as it passes the dead arise, and little forgotten faces recover their gaze to engage that of the living who, for their sake, abandon the living who are not alive and go to seek for life only where the Spirit has shown it to them, in stones which are already dust yet still contain human thought.

34. The man who enveloped the old cathedrals in more love and more joy than is bestowed on them by the sun when it adds its fugitive smile to their centuries-old beauty, cannot, if we understand him aright, have been mistaken. In the world of the spirit it is as in the universe of physics, where the height of a fountain can not exceed the height of the place from which the water has originally descended. The great beauties of literature correspond to something, and in art it is enthusiasm perhaps which is the criterion of truth. If we suppose Ruskin to have sometimes been mistaken, as a critic, in the exact assessment of a work's value, the beauty of his wrong judgement is often of greater interest than that of the work being judged and corresponds to something which may be other than it but no less precious. I do not believe that Ruskin was wrong to say of the 'Beau Dieu of Amiens' that 'no sculpture would satisfy, or ought to satisfy, the hope of any loving soul that has learned to trust in Him; but at the time, it was beyond what till then had been reached in sculptured tenderness,' and M. Huysmans right to call this same Amiens God 'a fop with a sheep's face', but it hardly matters that we should know. Whether or not the 'Beau Dieu of Amiens' is what Ruskin thought it was is of no importance for us. Just as Buffon said that 'all the intellectual beauties to be found (in a beautiful style), all the relations of which it is made up, are so many truths as useful and perhaps more precious for the public mind than those which may constitute the subject-matter,' so the truths making up the beauty of the passages in the Bible about the Beau Dieu of Amiens have value independently of the beauty of the statue, but Ruskin would not have found them had he spoken of it disdainfully, for enthusiasm alone could give him the power to discover them.

35. What it will never be given to us to know perhaps, and what in any case we cannot search for here, is just how faithfully that marvellous soul reflected the universe, and in what tempting and pathetic forms falsehood may, for all that, have insinuated itself into the very heart of his intellectual sincerity. Whatever the answer, he was one of those 'geniuses' of whom even those amongst us who were endowed at birth by the fairies have need if we are to be initiated into the knowledge and love of a new part of Beauty. Much of what is said by our contemporaries in their intellectual exchanges bears his imprint, just as on coins one sees the effigy of the reigning sovereign. In death he continues to enlighten us, like those extinguished stars whose light still reaches us, and it can be said of him what he said when Turner died: 'It is through those eyes, closed for ever in the depths of the grave, that generations yet unborn will see nature.'

36. 'In what tempting and magnificent forms falsehood may have insinuated itself into the very heart of his intellectual sincerity ...' This is what I meant to say: there is a sort of idolatry which no one has defined better than Ruskin himself, in a passage from the Lectures on Art: 'Such I conceive generally, though indeed with good arising out of it, for every great evil brings some good in its backward eddies — such I conceive to have been the deadly function of art in its ministry to what, whether in heathen or Christian lands, and whether in the pageantry of words, or colours, or fair forms, is truly, and in the deep sense, to be called idolatry — the serving with the best of our hearts and minds, some dear or sad fantasy which we have made for ourselves, while we disobey the present call of the Master, who is not dead, and who is not now fainting under His cross, but requiring us to take up ours.'

37. Now it certainly seems that at the basis of Ruskin's work, at the root of his talent, one finds this very idolatry. No doubt he never allowed it completely to overlay — even as an embellishment, — to immobilize, paralyse and finally to kill his intellectual and moral sincerity. In every line he wrote, as at each moment of his life, one senses this need for sincerity struggling against idolatry, proclaiming its vanity and humbling beauty before duty, be it an unaesthetic duty. I shall not take examples of this from his life (which was not like the lives of Racine, or Tolstoy, or Maeterlinck, aesthetic at first and later moral, but one in which morality established its rights from the outset and in the very heart of his aesthetic — without perhaps ever liberating itself as completely as in the lives of the other Masters I have just named). I have no need to recall its stages, for they are quite well known, from the early scruples which he felt at drinking tea while looking at Titians, up until the time when, having swallowed up the five millions left him by his father on his social and philanthropic work, he decided to sell his Turners. But there is a more inward form of dilettantism than the active form (which he had overcome) and the real duel between his idolatry and his sincerity was fought out not at certain moments of his life, or in certain passages in his books, but the whole time, in those deep and secret places, unknown almost to ourselves, where our personality receives images from the imagination, ideas from the intellect and words from the memory, and affirms itself in the ceaseless choices it makes from them and ceaselessly wagers in a sense the destiny of our moral and spiritual lives. I have the impression that in those places the sin of idolatry never ceased to be committed by Ruskin. And at the very moment when he was preaching sincerity he lacked it himself, not in what he said but in the manner in which he said it. The doctrines he was professing were moral and not aesthetic doctrines, yet he chose them for their beauty. And as he did not want to present them as beautiful but as true, he was obliged to lie to himself concerning the nature of the reasons which had led him to adopt them. Hence a compromising with his conscience so unceasing that immoral doctrines sincerely professed might have been less dangerous for the integrity of his mind than these moral doctrines whose affirmation is not wholly sincere, having been dictated by an unacknowledged aesthetic preference. This sin was being committed constantly, in the actual choice of each explanation he gave of a fact, of each judgement he passed on a work, in his actual choice of the words he used — and it finally lent a mendacious attitude to the mind that was constantly giving way to it. So that the reader may be better able to judge the sort of trompe l'oeil which a passage from Ruskin is for anyone, including for Ruskin himself, I shall quote one of those which I find most beautiful yet where this defect is at its most flagrant. You will see that if in theory (in appearance, that is, the content of a writer's ideas being always the appearance, and their form the reality) beauty has been subordinated to the moral sense and to truth, in actual fact truth and the moral sense have been subordinated to the aesthetic sense, and to an aesthetic sense somewhat distorted by these perpetual compromises. The subject is 'The Causes of Venice's Decline'.

38. 'Not in the wantonness of wealth, not in vain ministry to the desire of the eye or the pride of life, were those marbles hewn into transparent strength, and those arches arrayed in the colours of the iris. There is a message written in the dyes of them, that once was written in blood; and a sound in the echoes of their vaults, that one day shall fill the vault of heaven, — "He shall return to do judgement and justice." The strength of Venice was given her, so long as she remembered this: her destruction found her when she had forgotten this; and it found her irrevocably, because she forgot it without excuse. Never had a city a more glorious Bible. Among the nations of the North, a rude and shadowy sculpture filled their temples with confused and hardly legible imagery; but, for her, the skill and the treasures of the East had gilded every letter, and illumined every page, till the Book-Temple shone from afar off like the star of the Magi. In other cities, the meetings of the people were often in places withdrawn from religious association, subject to violence and to change; and on the grass of the dangerous rampart, and in the dust of the troubled street, there were deeds done and counsels taken, which, if we cannot justify, we may sometimes forgive. But the sins of Venice, whether in her palace or in her piazza, were done with the Bible at her right hand. The walls on which its testimony was written were separated but by a few inches of marble from those which guarded the secrets of her councils, or confined the victims of her policy. And when in her last hours she threw off all shame and all restraint, and the great square of the city became filled with the madness of the whole earth, be it remembered how much her sin was greater, because it was done in the face of the House of God, burning with the letters of His Law. Mountebank and masquer laughed their laugh and went their way; and a silence has followed them, not unforetold; for amidst them all, through century after century of gathering vanity and festering guilt, that white dome of St Mark's had uttered in the dead ear of Venice: "Know thou, that for all these things God will bring thee into judgement."

39. Now if Ruskin had been entirely sincere with himself he would not have thought that the crimes of the Venetians had been more inexcusable and more severely punished than those of other men because they possessed a church of multicoloured marble instead of a limestone cathedral, because the Doge's palace was next to St Mark's instead of at the other end of the town, and because in Byzantine churches, instead of being simply represented as in the sculpture of northern churches, the biblical texts of the mosaics are accompanied by lettering forming a quotation from the Gospel or the prophecies. It is none the less true that this passage from The Stones of Venice is of great beauty, even though it is quite difficult to account for the reasons for that beauty. It seems to me to rest on something false and I feel some scruples about yielding to it.

40. Yet there must be some truth in it. There is no altogether false beauty properly speaking, for aesthetic pleasure is that very pleasure which goes with the discovery of a truth. What is quite hard to say is to what order of truth the very keen aesthetic pleasure one gets from reading such a passage can correspond. It is itself mysterious, full at once of images of beauty and of religion like that same church of St Mark's, where all the figures from the Old and New Testaments appear against a background of a sort of splendid darkness and fitful brilliancy. I remember having read it for the first time in St Mark's itself, during an hour of storm and darkness when the mosaics shone with their own material light alone, with an inner, earthly and ancient gold, to which the Venetian sun, which sets even the angels of the campaniles on fire, no longer added anything of itself; the emotion which I felt on reading this passage, amidst all these angels bright against the surrounding gloom, was very strong and yet not perhaps very pure. Just as my joy grew at seeing these beautiful and mysterious figures, yet was tainted by the pleasures of erudition as it were, which I felt as I took in the texts appearing in Byzantine script beside their haloed brows, so the beauty of Ruskin's images was quickened and corrupted by the presumption of his allusions to the sacred texts. A sort of egotistical return into the self is inevitable in these joys, in which erudition mixes with art and where the aesthetic pleasures may become keener but not remain so pure. So perhaps this passage from The Stones of Venice was beautiful above all for affording me precisely those mixed joys I had felt in St Mark's, for it too, like the Byzantine church, had its biblical quotations inscribed beside the images in the mosaic of its style, dazzling amidst the shadows. Did the same not hold for it, moreover, as for the mosaics in St Mark's, whose purpose was to instruct and which laid no great store by their artistic beauty? Today they no longer give us anything except pleasure. Yet the pleasure their didacticism gives the scholar is a selfish one, and the most disinterested pleasure is still that given to the artist by a beauty despised by, or even unknown to those whose one purpose was to educate the people and who gave it to them as something extra.

41. On the last page of The Bible of Amiens, the 'if ... you would care for the promise to you' is an example of the same kind. When, again in The Bible of Amiens, Ruskin ends the section on Egypt by saying: 'She was the Tutress of Moses and the Hostess of Christ,' we can allow the tutress of Moses: certain virtues are required in order to educate. But the fact of having been the 'hostess' of Christ may add beauty to the sentence but can it really come into the reckoning in a reasoned appreciation of the virtues of the Egyptian genius?

42. I have been trying to wrestle here with my most cherished aesthetic impressions, attempting to carry intellectual sincerity to its ultimate and cruellest limits. Do I need to add that if I enter this general caveat, in some sense in the absolute, less about Ruskin's works than about their essential inspiration and the quality of their beauty, he nevertheless remains for me one of the greatest writers of all times and all countries. Rather than seeking to decry a defect peculiar to Ruskin, I have been trying to lay hold in him, as in a 'subject' particularly favourable to such observation, of an infirmity essential to the human mind. Once the reader has understood fully in what this 'idolatry' consists, he will be able to explain to himself the excessive importance that Ruskin attaches in his essays to lettering in works of art (an importance another reason for which I indicated, far too summarily, in my preface), as well as his misuse of the words 'irreverent' or 'insolent': 'mystery which we are not required to unravel, or difficulties which we should be insolent in desiring to solve,' 'let the artist distrust the spirit of choice, it is an insolent spirit,' 'where it is just possible for an irreverent person rather to think the nave narrow than the apse high,' etc., etc. — and the state of mind which they reveal. I was thinking of this idolatry (I was thinking also of the pleasure Ruskin takes in balancing his phrases in an equilibrium which seems rather to impose a symmetrical arrangement on his thought than to receive one from it)[【3】] when I said: 'I do not have to look for the tempting and pathetic forms in which falsehood may have insinuated itself into the very heart of his intellectual sincerity.' But I should, on the contrary, have looked for them and I should be committing that same sin of idolatry were I to continue to shelter behind this essentially Ruskinian formula of reverence. It is not that I fail to recognize the virtues of reverence, it is the very condition of love. But where love ceases, it must never be substituted for it, so enabling us to believe without examination and to admire on trust. Ruskin moreover would have been the first to approve my not according to his writings an infallible authority, since he even refused it to the Holy Scriptures: '... and there is no possibility of attaching the idea of infallible truth to any form of human language ...' But he liked the attitude of 'reverence' which believes it 'insolent to throw light on a mystery'. In order to have done with idolatry and to make yet more certain that no misunderstanding remains concerning it between myself and my reader, I would like to bring on here one of our most justly celebrated contemporaries (as unlike Ruskin in other ways as could be!) who allows this fault to show in his conversation, though not in his books, carried to such an excess that it is easier to recognize and to demonstrate it in his case, with no need any more to strive so hard to magnify it. When he talks he is afflicted — delightfully — with idolatry. Those who have once heard him will find an 'imitation' very crude in which nothing survives of his attractions, but they will know however of whom I wish to speak, whom I am taking here as my example, when I tell them that in the material in which a tragic actress is draped he recognizes admiringly the same stuff as is worn by Death in Gustave Moreau's 'The Young Man and Death', or in the costume of one of his lady friends: 'the very dress and hairstyle worn by the Princesse de Cadignan the day she saw d'Arthez for the first time.' And as he looks at the actress's drapery or at the society woman's dress he is moved by such noble associations and exclaims: 'Quite lovely!' not because the material is lovely, but because it is the material painted by Moreau or described by Balzac and hence forever sacred ... to idolaters. In his bedroom you will find dielytras, either real ones in a vase or painted ones in a mural done by artist friends, because this is the very flower one sees represented in the Madeleine at Vézélay. As for some object that has belonged to Baudelaire, or to Michelet, or to Hugo, that he hedges about with a religious reverence. I savour too profoundly, am even carried away by, the witty improvisations into which our idolater is led and inspired by the particular kind of pleasure he finds in such veneration to wish in the very least to wrangle with him over it.

43. But at the very height of my enjoyment I ask myself whether this incomparable talker — and the listener who lets him go on talking — are not equally guilty of insincerity; whether because a flower (the passion flower) bears on it the instruments of the passion, it is a sacrilege to offer it to someone of another religion, or whether the fact of a house's having been lived in by Balzac (if nothing remains there anyway which might tell us something about him) makes it more beautiful. Ought we really, other than to pay her an aesthetic compliment, to prefer someone because her name is Bathilde, like the heroine of Lucien Leuwen?

44. Mme de Cadignan's costume is a ravishing invention of Balzac's because it gives us an idea of Mme de Cadignan's artistry, and informs us of the impression she wishes to make on d'Arthez and of some of her 'secrets'. But once deprived of the idea it contains, it is no more than a sign deprived of its meaning, that is to say, nothing; and to continue to worship it, to the point of going into ecstasies when one finds it again in real life on the body of a woman, that is true idolatry. This is the favourite intellectual sin of artists, to which very few of them have failed to succumb. Felix culpa! one is tempted to say when one sees how fruitful it has been for them in terms of charming inventions. But they should at least not succumb without a struggle. There is in nature no particular form, however beautiful, which has value except for that portion of the infinite beauty that has been able to embody itself there: not even the apple blossom, not even the blossom of the pink hawthorn. My love for these is infinite and the affliction (hay fever) which proximity to them brings on enables me each spring to give them a proof of that love not within reach of everyone. But even towards them, which are far from literary, far from being linked to any aesthetic tradition, which are not 'the actual flower to be seen in such and such a picture by Tintoret' as Ruskin would say, or such and such a drawing by Leonardo as our contemporary would say (who has revealed to us, among many other things, which everyone now speaks of yet to which no one had paid any regard before him — the drawings in the Accademia in Venice), I shall always beware of an exclusive cult that might attach itself to anything in them other than the delight they afford me, a cult in whose name, by an egotistical return into the self, I might make of them 'my' flowers and take care to honour them by decorating my bedroom with the works of art in which they appear. No, I shall not find a picture more beautiful because the artist has painted a hawthorn in the foreground, although I know of nothing more beautiful than the hawthorn, because I want to remain sincere and I know that a picture's beauty does not depend on the things portrayed in it. I shall not collect images of the hawthorn. I do not venerate the hawthorn, I go to see it and to breathe it in. I have allowed myself this brief incursion — which is not in any way an offensive — on to the ground of contemporary literature because it seemed to me that the features of idolatry there in germ in Ruskin would stand out clearly to the reader when thus magnified, all the more for being so strongly differentiated. I beg our contemporary in any case, should he have recognized himself in this very clumsy pencil sketch, to believe that it was done without malice and that, as I have said, I needed to go to the furthermost limits of sincerity with myself to make this complaint against Ruskin and discover this fragile element in my absolute admiration for him. Now not only is there 'nothing at all dishonourable in sharing with Ruskin', but also I could never find any greater compliment to pay this contemporary than to have addressed the same criticism to his as to Ruskin. I can almost regret having been so discreet as not to name him. For when one is admitted into the presence of Ruskin, be it in the attitude of a donor, solely in order to hold up his book and to help it to be read more attentively, that is not a punishment but an honour.

45. I come back to Ruskin. So 'used' am I to him today that to grasp the evidences, and study the nature of this idolatry, and the slight factitiousness it sometimes adds to the keenest literary pleasures that he affords us, I need to descend deep into my own self. But it must often have shocked me when I was starting to love his books, before gradually closing my eyes to their defects, as happens in any love-affair. Love-affairs with living people may sometimes have a sordid origin which is later purified. A man makes the acquaintance of a woman because she can help him to achieve an end unconnected with herself. Then, once he knows her, he loves her for herself, and unhesitatingly sacrifices to her that end she was merely to have helped him to attain. Thus originally there was something self-interested mixed in with my love for Ruskin's books, a delight in the intellectual profit I was to derive from them. The fact is that, sensing the power and attraction of the very first pages I read, I made an effort not to resist them, not to argue too much with myself, because I felt that if one day the attraction of Ruskin's thought should extend for me over everything he had touched, in short if I became completely enamoured of his thought, the world would be enriched by everything of which I had hitherto been ignorant, by Gothic cathedrals and by any number of pictures in England and in Italy which had not yet awoken in me that desire without which there is never true knowledge. For Ruskin's thought is not like the thought of an Emerson, for example, which is contained in its entirety in a book, something abstract that is, a pure sign of itself. The object to which a thought like Ruskin's is applied and from which it is inseparable, is not immaterial, it is scattered across the surface of the earth. One must go to seek it wherever it is to be found, to Pisa, to Florence, to Venice, to the National Gallery, to Rouen, to Amiens, into the mountains of Switzerland. Such a thought, which has an object other than itself, which has realized itself in space, which is thought no longer infinite and free but limited and subjugated, which is incarnate in bodies of sculpted marble, in snow-covered mountains, in painted faces, is perhaps less godlike than pure thought. But it makes the universe more beautiful for us, or at least certain parts of it, certain named parts, because it has touched them and initiated us into them by forcing us, if we would understand them, to love them.

46. And so indeed it was; the universe suddenly took on for me again an infinite value. And my admiration for Ruskin lent to the things which he had brought me to love so great an importance that they seemed to me charged with a value higher than that of life itself. This was literally so on an occasion when I believed that my days were numbered; I set off for Venice in order, before I died, to approach, to touch, to see embodied, in palaces that were decaying yet still upright, still pink, Ruskin's ideas on the domestic architecture of the Middle Ages. What importance, what reality can a town so special, so localized in time and so particularized in space as Venice have in the eyes of someone about to take leave of the earth, and how could the theories of domestic architecture that I might study there and verify from living examples, be amongst those 'truths which dominate death, which keep us from fearing it and cause us almost to love it' (Renan)? The power of genius is to make us love a beauty we feel to be more real than ourselves, in those things which in the eyes of others are as particular and as perishable as ourselves.

47. The poet's 'I shall say they are beautiful once your eyes have said so' is not very true, if the eyes in question are those of the beloved. In a certain sense and whatever splendid compensations, on this same ground of poetry, it may be preparing for us, love depoeticizes nature. To the man in love the earth is nothing more than 'the carpet for the lovely child's feet' of his mistress, nature nothing more than 'her temple'. That love which uncovers so many profound psychological truths for us, excludes us on the other hand from the poetic feeling for nature, because it puts us into selfish frames of mind (love is at the highest point along the scale of selfishness, but it is still selfish) in which the poetic feeling occurs only with difficulty. Admiration for someone's thought, on the contrary, causes beauty to arise at every step because it is constantly awakening the desire for it. The mediocre usually imagine that to let ourselves be guided by the books we admire robs our faculty of judgement of part of its independence. 'What can it matter to you what Ruskin feels: feel for yourself.' Such a view rests on a psychological error which will be discounted by all those who have thus accepted a spiritual discipline and feel thereby that their power of understanding and of feeling is infinitely enhanced, and their critical sense never paralysed. Then we are simply in a state of grace in which all our faculties, our critical sense as much as the others, are enhanced. And so this voluntary servitude is the beginning of freedom. There is no better way of coming to be aware of what feels oneself than by trying to recreate in oneself what a master has felt. In this profound effort it is our thought itself that we bring out into the light, together with his. We are free in life but only if we have an aim: the sophism of an indifferent freedom was exposed long ago. Those writers who are forever emptying their minds, thinking to rid them of all outside influence so as to be quite sure of remaining personal, are obeying, unknowingly, a sophism equally as naive. In point of fact, the only occasions when we can truly call on the full power of our minds are those when we do not believe we are acting independently, when we do not choose an arbitrary objective for our endeavours. The theme of the novelist, the vision of the poet, the truth of the philosopher, impose themselves on them in an almost necessary way, externally to their minds so to speak. And it is by submitting his mind to the conveying of that vision, to the approximation to that truth, that the artist becomes truly himself.

48. But in speaking of the passion, somewhat artificial to start with but later so very profound, which I had for Ruskin's thought, I speak by the light of memory and of a memory which recalls only the facts 'but can repossess nothing of the deep past'. It is only when certain periods of our lives are forever closed, when, even at those times when we seem to have been granted the power and the freedom, we are forbidden to reopen the doors to them by stealth, when we are incapable of reverting even for an instant to the state in which we were for so long, only then do we refuse to accept that such things should have been entirely abolished. We can no longer sing of them, having failed to heed Goethe's wise admonition, that there is no poetry but in the things one can still feel. But if we are unable to relight the fires of the past, we would like at least to gather up their ashes. For want of a resurrection of which we are no longer capable, we would like at least, with the frozen memory we have preserved of these things — the memory of the facts which tells us: 'you were this or that' without enabling us to become it again, which affirms the reality of a paradise lost instead of restoring it to us in memory, — to describe it and to constitute the knowledge of it. It is when Ruskin is far away from us that we translate his books and try to capture the characteristics of his thought in a close likeness. And so it is not the accents of our faith or of our love that you will come to know, but our piety alone that you will perceive here and there, stealthy and impassive, busied, like the Theban virgin, on the restoration of a tomb.

Notes

【1】1. Similarly in Val d'Arno, the lion of St Mark is the direct descendant of the lion of Nemea, and its plumed crest is the one to be seen on the head of the Hercules of Camarina, with the difference pointed out elsewhere in the same book 'that Herakles kills the beast and makes a helmet and cloak of its skin; the Greek St Mark converts the beast and makes an evangelist of him.' [Val d'Arno, 8, cciii.]

It is not in order to find another sacred lineage for the lion of Nemea that I have quoted this passage, but to emphasize the whole idea of the end of this chapter in The Bible of Amiens, 'that there is a Sacred classical art'. Ruskin did not want (Val d'Arno) Greek to be contrasted with Christian but with the Gothic, 'because St Mark is Greek like Herakles'. We touch here on one of Ruskin's most important ideas, or more accurately on one of the most original sentiments he brought to the contemplation and study of Greek and Christian works of art, to convey which fully it is necessary to quote a passage from St Mark's Rest which is, in my opinion, one of those where there emerges the most clearly anywhere in Ruskin, where that particular attitude of mind can most easily be seen at work which led him to pay no heed to the advent of Christianity, to recognize a Christian beauty already in the works of paganism and to trace the persistence of a Hellenic ideal into the works of the Middle Ages. It is quite certain that this attitude of mind, wholly aesthetic in my view, at least logically in its essence if not chronologically in its origins, became systematized in Ruskin's mind and that he extended it into his historical and religious criticism. But even when Ruskin is comparing Greek royalty with Frankish (Val d'Arno, chapter on 'Franchise'), or when he is declaring in The Bible of Amiens that 'Christianity brought no great alteration to the ideal of virtue and of human happiness,' or when he speaks as we have seen on the preceding page of the religion of Horace, all he is doing is to draw theoretical conclusions from the aesthetic pleasures he had felt on rediscovering a canephoros in a Herodias, a Harpy in a cherub, a Greek vase in a Byzantine dome. Here is the passage in St Mark's Rest: 'And this is true, not of Byzantine art only, but of all Greek art ... Let us leave, today ... the word "Byzantine". There is but one Greek school, from Homer's day down to the Doge Selvo's; and these St Mark's mosaics are as truly wrought in the power of Daedalus, with the Greek constructive instinct ... as ever chest of Cypselus or shaft of Erectheum.'

Then Ruskin enters the baptistery of St Mark's and says: 'Over the door is Herod's feast. Herodias's daughter dances with John the Baptist's head in the charger, on her head, — simply the translation of any Greek maid on a Greek vase, bearing a pitcher of water on her head ... Pass on now into the further chapel under the darker dome. Darker, and very dark; — to my old eyes scarcely decipherable, to yours, if young and bright, it should be beautiful, for it is indeed the origin of all those golden-domed backgrounds of Bellini, and Cima, and Carpaccio; itself a Greek vase, but with new Gods. That ten-winged cherub in the recess of it, behind the altar, has written on the circle on its breast, "Fulness of Wisdom". It is the type of the Breath of the Spirit. But it was once a Greek Harpy, and its wasted limbs remain scarcely yet clothed with flesh from the claws of birds that they were ... Above, Christ himself ascends, home in a whirlwind of angels; and, as the vaults of Bellini and Carpaccio are only the amplification of the Harpy vault, so the Paradise of Tintoret is only the final fulfilment of the thought in this narrow cupola ... there is no question but that these mosaics are not earlier than the thirteenth century. And yet they are still absolutely Greek in all modes of thought and forms of tradition. The Fountains of fire and water are merely forms of the Chimera and the Peirene; and the maid dancing, though a princess of the thirteenth century in sleeves of ermine, is yet the phantom of some sweet water-carrier from an Arcadian spring.' [St Mark's Rest, 92, et seq. The quotations are not continuous.] Cf., when Ruskin says: 'I am alone, as I believe, in thinking still with Herodotus.' Anyone of a mind sufficiently discerning to be struck by the features characteristic of a writer's physiognomy, and who does not hold where Ruskin is concerned to everything he may have been told, that he was a prophet, a seer, a Protestant and other things which mean very little, will feel that such features, though certainly secondary, are yet very 'Ruskinian'. Ruskin lives in a sort of brotherhood with all the great minds of every age, and since he is interested in them only to the extent that they are able to answer the eternal questions, for him there are no ancients or modems and he can talk of Herodotus as he would of a contemporary. As the ancients have no value for him except in so far as they are 'of the present day', and can serve as illustrations for our daily meditations, he does not treat them at all as ancients. And so all those of their words which have not been rejected as obsolete and are no longer seen as relating to a given epoch, have a greater importance for him, and preserve in some sense the scientific value they may once have had but of which time had deprived them. From the manner in which Horace speaks of the spring of Bandusia, Ruskin deduces that he was pious, 'in Milton's fashion'. And even at the age of eleven, learning the odes of Anacreon for pleasure, he learnt from them 'with certainty, what in later study of Greek art it proved extremely advantageous to me to know, that the Greeks liked doves, swallows, and roses just as well as I did.' [Praeterita, lxxxi.] Obviously for an Emerson 'culture' has the same value. But without even pausing over the differences, which are profound, let us note first of all, to stress those features peculiar to the physiognomy of Ruskin, that because he saw no distinction between science and art he speaks of the ancients as scientists with the same reverence as of the ancients as artists. When it comes to discoveries in natural history he invokes the 104th psalm, falls in with the view of Herodotus (readily opposing it to the opinion of a contemporary scientist) on a question of religious history, and admires one of Carpaccio's paintings as an important contribution to the descriptive history of parrots (St Mark's Rest: 'The Shrine of the Slaves'). Obviously we should soon join up again here with the idea of a classical sacred art, 'there is only one Greek art, St Jerome and Herakles, etc.', each one of these ideas leading to the rest. But for the time being we still only have a Ruskin deeply attached to his library, making no distinction between science and art, believing in consequence that a scientific theory may remain true just as a work of art may remain beautiful (this idea he never expresses explicitly, but secretly it governs all the others and alone can have made them possible), and going to an ode from antiquity or a medieval bas-relief for facts of natural history or of critical philosophy, convinced that all the sages from every age and every country are better worth consulting than the fools, be they contemporary. This inclination is of course held in check by a critical sense so right that we can have full confidence in him, and he exaggerates it only for the pleasure of making little jokes about 'thirteenth-century entomology' etc., etc.

【2】2. What an interesting collection might be made of French landscapes as seen through English eyes: the rivers of France by Turner; Bonington's 'Versailles'; Walter Pater's 'Auxerre' or 'Valenciennes', 'Vézélay' or 'Amiens'; Stevenson's 'Fontainebleau'; and how many more!

【3】3. I do not have the time today to make myself clear concerning this failing, but I fancy that through my translation, however flat it may be, the reader may be able to see, as through the thick but abruptly illuminated glass of a fish-tank, the rapid but perceptible snatching away of the thought by the phrase, and the instant wasting which the thought suffers.

Days of Reading (Ⅱ)

1. You have no doubt read the Memoirs of the Countess de Boigne. There are 'so many people ill' at the moment, that books are finding readers, even female ones. When one is unable to go out and pay calls, one would rather receive them no doubt than read. But 'in these days of epidemics' even the calls one receives are not without danger. There is the lady who pauses for a moment — just for a moment — in the doorway, where she puts a frame round her threat, to call to you: 'You're not afraid of mumps or scarlet fever? I must warn you that my daughter and my grandchildren have got them. Can I come in?'; and comes in without waiting for a reply. There is another lady, less candid, who pulls out her watch: 'I must be off home; my three daughters have got measles; I go from one to the other; my English girl has been in bed since yesterday with a high fever, and I'm very much afraid it may be my turn to be caught, because I felt off colour when I got up. But I had to make the big effort to come and see you ...'

2. So one prefers not to entertain too much and since one cannot be always telephoning, one reads. One reads only as an absolutely last resort. First, we do a lot of telephoning. And, since we are children who play with the sacred powers unawed by their mystery, we find merely with the telephone that 'it is convenient', or rather, since we are spoilt children, that 'it is not convenient' and fill Le Figaro with our complaints, finding this wonderful fairy-land still not fast enough in its transformations, when several minutes may sometimes elapse indeed before there appears beside us, invisible yet present, the friend to whom we had desired to speak and who, though still at her table, in the far-off town where she lives, beneath skies different from ours, in weather not as it is here, in the midst of circumstances and pre-occupations of which we know nothing but of which she is about to tell us, finds herself suddenly transported a hundred miles away (herself, and the whole ambience in which she remains immersed), against our ear, at a moment ordained by our own whim. And we are like the character in the fairy-tale who, this being what he has wished for, is shown his betrothed by a wizard, with a magical clarity, in the act of looking through a book, or shedding tears, or picking flowers, right beside him, yet in the place where she then is, far away.

3. For this miracle to be renewed for us, we have only to put our lips to the magic planchette-board and summon — for quite some time on occasions, I will agree — the vigilant Virgins whose voices we hear every day without ever knowing their faces and who are our guardian angels in that vertiginous darkness whose gates they watch over jealously, the Omnipotent ones thanks to whom the faces of the absent loom up beside us without our being allowed to see them; we have only to summon these Danaids of the Invisible who empty, recharge and hand on to one another unceasingly the dark urns of sounds, the jealous Furies who, as we murmur a confidence to a woman friend, call out to us ironically: 'I'm on the line,' at a moment when we were hoping no one could hear us, the irate servants of the Mystery, the implacable Divinities, the Damsels of the telephone! And the instant their summons has sounded in the night full of apparitions to which our ears alone are opened, a faint sound, an abstract sound — of distance being suppressed — and the voice of our friend is addressing us.

4. If at that moment the singing of a passer-by, the horn of a bicyclist or a distant regimental band should enter by the window to importune her as she is speaking to us, they ring out just as distinctly for us (as if to prove that it is indeed she who is beside us, with everything that surrounds her at that moment, that is striking her ear and distracting her attention) — truthful details, nothing to do with the subject, useless in themselves, but all the more necessary as revealing to us the full evidence of the miracle — prosaic and charming elements of local colour, descriptive of the provincial street and roadway to be seen from her house, such as a poet chooses when he wants to bring a character alive and evokes his milieu.

5. It is she, it is her voice which is speaking to us, which is there. But how far away it is! How many times have I been able to listen to it without anguish, as if, faced by the impossibility of seeing, without long hours of travelling, the person whose voice was so close to my ear, I sensed more clearly how disappointing this semblance of the sweetest proximity is and how far distant we may be from the things we love at the moment when it seems we need only stretch out our hand to detain them. A real presence — this voice so close — in an effective separation. But an anticipation also of an everlasting separation. Very often, listening to it in this fashion, unable to see the person who was speaking to me from so far away, her voice seemed to be crying out from the depths from which one does not reascend, and I experienced the anxiety that would one day seize hold of me, when a voice returned to me thus, alone no longer dependent on a body I should never set eyes on again, to murmur in my ear words I would like to have been able to embrace as they passed on lips that are forever dust.

6. I was saying that before making up our minds to read, we try to keep on conversing, to telephone, we ask for number after number. But sometimes the Daughters of the Night, the Messengers of the Word, the faceless Goddesses, the capricious Guardians cannot or will not open the gates of the Invisible to us, the Mystery we solicit remains deaf, the venerable inventor of printing and the young prince who was both a lover of Impressionist painting and a motorist — Gutenberg and Wagram! [two Parisian telephone exchanges] — upon whom they call tirelessly, leave their supplications unanswered; then, since we cannot pay calls, since we do not wish to receive them, since the damsels of the telephone cannot connect us, we resign ourselves to being silent, we read.

7. In only a few weeks' time we shall be able to read the new volume of poetry by Mme de Noailles, Les Eblouissements (I do not know whether it will keep that title), superior even to those books of genius, Le Coeur innombrable and L'Ombre des jours, the equal in fact, it seems to me, of the Feuilles d'automne or the Fleurs du mal. Meanwhile, we might read the pure and exquisite Margaret Ogilvy de Barrie, wonderfully well translated by R. d'Humières, which is simply the life of a peasant woman told by a poet, her son. But no; the moment we resign ourselves to reading, we choose for preference books like the Memoirs of Mme de Boigne, books which give us the illusion of continuing to pay calls, calls on people we had not been able to visit before because we were not yet born under Louis XVI, but who are not so very different as it happens from the people whom you know because almost all of them bear the same names as they do, their descendants and your friends who, by a touching courtesy towards your ailing memory, have kept the same first names and are still called: Odon, Ghislain, Nivelon, Victurnien, Josselin, Léonor, Artus, Tucdual, Adhéaume or Raynulphe. Fine baptismal names moreover, which one would do wrong to smile at; they come from a past so profound that in their unwonted lustre they seem to sparkle mysteriously, like those names of prophets and saints inscribed in brief in the stained-glass of our cathedrals. Does Jehan itself, although more like one of today's names, not appear inevitably as if traced in Gothic characters in a Book of Hours by a brush dipped in purple, ultramarine or azure? Faced with such names, the common people would perhaps repeat the Montmartre song:

　　Bragance, on le connaît ct'oiseau-là;

　　Faut-il que son orgueil soye profonde

　　Pour s'être f... u un nom comme ça!

　　Peut donc pas s'appeler comme tout le monde!

　　Bragance, we know that character;

　　He must be really big-headed

　　To have got himself a f ... ing name like that!

　　Couldn't he have a name like everyone else!

8. But the poet, if he is sincere, does not share in such merriment but, with his eyes fixed on the past that such names disclose to him, will reply with Verlaine:

　　Je vois, j'entends beaucoup de choses

　　Dans son nom Carlovingien.

　　I see, I hear many things

　　In his Carolingian name.

9. An enormous past perhaps. I should like to think that these names, so few examples of which have come down to us, thanks to the attachment to tradition of certain families, were in the old days very common names — the names of villeins as well as noblemen — so that, through the naive colours of the magic-lantern slides that such names offer us, it is not only the mighty lord with the blue beard or Sister Anne in her tower that we can see, but also the peasant bent over the ripening meadow or the men-at-arms riding along dusty thirteenth-century roads.

10. Very often no doubt the medieval impression their names give off does not survive an acquaintance with those who bear them and who have neither preserved nor understood their poetry; but can we reasonably ask of human beings that they should show themselves worthy of their names when the most beautiful things have so much difficulty in living up to theirs, when there is no landscape, no city, no river the sight of which can assuage the dreamlike desire its name had given birth to in us? The sensible thing would be to replace all our society connections and many journeys by a reading of the Almanach de Gotha or the railway timetable ...

11. What is moving about Memoirs from the end of the eighteenth century and the beginning of the nineteenth, like those of the Countess de Boigne, is that they lend to the contemporary age, to our own days that are lived without beauty, a rather noble, rather melancholy perspective, by making them as it were into the foreground of History. They enable us to pass easily from the persons whom we have met with in life — or whom our parents have known — to the parents of those persons, who themselves, as authors or as characters in these Memoirs, may have witnessed the Revolution and seen Marie-Antoinette go by. So that the people whom we may have been able to glimpse or to know — the people we have seen with our own eyes — are like those life-size wax models in the foreground of panoramas, treading on real grass and holding up a cane bought from a shop, who seem still to be part of the crowd that is gazing at them and lead us gradually to the painted backcloth, to which, thanks to skilfully contrived transitions, they lend the three-dimensional appearance of life and reality. This Mme de Boigne then, born a d'Osmond and brought up, so she tells us, on the laps of Louis XVI and Marie-Antoinette, as an adolescent I very often saw her niece at balls, the old Duchess de Maillé, née d'Osmond, over eighty yet still splendid beneath the grey hair brushed upwards from her forehead which put one in mind of the bob-wigs worn by presidents in the High Court. And I recall that my parents very often dined with Mme de Boigne's nephew, M. d'Osmond, for whom she wrote these Memoirs and whose photograph I found among their papers, together with many letters he had addressed to them. So that my own earliest memories of balls, which hang by a thread from the for me somewhat less distinct yet still very real accounts of my parents, are connected by an already almost immaterial link to the memories which Mme de Boigne had preserved and which she recounts to us of the earliest entertainments at which she was present; all of which weaves a tissue of frivolities, yet a poetic one, for it ends as the stuff of dreams, a slender bridge thrown between the present and an already distant past, and which joins life to history, making history more alive and life almost historical.

12. Here I am, alas, at the third column of the newspaper and I have not yet begun my article even. It was to have been called. 'Snobbery and Posterity', but I am not going to be able to leave it with that title since I have filled the entire space reserved for me without saying a single word to you as yet about either Snobbery or Posterity, two persons whom you no doubt thought would never be called upon to meet, for the greater good fortune of the second, and on the topic of whom I was intending to subject you to a few reflections inspired by reading the Memoirs of Mme de Boigne. That must wait until next time. And if then one of those phantoms that interpose themselves ceaselessly between my mind and its object, as happens in dreams, should again come to solicit my attention and distract it from what I have to say to you, I shall thrust it aside just as Ulysses thrust aside with his sword the shades that crowded round him imploring him for a human form or for burial.

13. Today I have been unable to resist the appeal of these visions that I could see floating halfway down, in the transparency of my mind. And I have attempted without success what the master glassmaker so often achieved when he transported and fixed his dreams, at the very distance at which they had appeared to him, between two waters clouded by dark, pink reflections, in a translucid substance in which at times a fitful ray of light, coming from its heart, might have made them think that they were still at play inside a living mind. Like the Nereids which the sculptor of antiquity had snatched from the sea but who could still believe themselves to be immersed in it as they swam between the marble waves of the bas-relief that figured it. I was wrong. It will not happen again. Next time I shall talk to you of snobbery and posterity, without digressing. And should some untoward idea, some indiscreet fancy seek to meddle in what is none of its business and threaten once more to interrupt us, I shall at once beg it to let us be: 'We are talking, do not cut us off, mademoiselle!'

From The Method of Sainte-Beuve
(extracts)

[...]

1. Thus it seems to me that I would have things that have their importance perhaps to say about Sainte-Beuve, and presently much more in connection with him than about him, that by showing where he sinned, in my view, both as writer and as critic, I should perhaps come to say some things about which I have often thought as to what criticism should be and what art is. In passing, and in his connection, as he does so often, I shall use him as the excuse for talking about certain forms of life ...

[...]

2. For the definition and eulogizing of Sainte-Beuve's method I have looked to the article by M. Paul Bourget, because the definition was short and the eulogy authoritative. I could have cited twenty other critics. To have written the natural history of minds, to have looked to the biography of the man, to the history of his family, to all his peculiarities, for an understanding of his work and the nature of his genius, that is what everyone recognizes to have been his originality, and what he recognized himself, in which moreover he was right. Taine himself, who dreamt of a more systematic and better codified natural history of men's minds and with whom as it happens Sainte-Beuve did not agree over questions of race, says no differently in his eulogy of Sainte-Beuve: 'M. Sainte-Beuve's method is no less valuable than his work. In this he was a pioneer. He imported into moral history the procedures of natural history.'

[...]

3. Now, in art there are no initiators or precursors (at least in the scientific sense). Everything is in the individual, each individual starts the artistic or literary endeavour over again, on his own account; the works of his predecessors do not constitute, unlike in science, an acquired truth from which he who follows after may profit. A writer of genius today has it all to do. He is not much further advanced than Homer.

4. But those philosophers who have been unable to find what is real and independent of all science in art have been forced to imagine art, criticism, etc., to themselves as sciences in which the predecessor is necessarily less far advanced than whoever follows after him.

5. But why trouble anyway to name all those who see in this the originality and excellence of Sainte-Beuve's method? One need only let him speak for himself.

6. 'For me,' said Sainte-Beuve, 'literature is not distinct or at any rate separable from the rest of the man and of his organization ... We cannot go about it in too many different ways or from too many different angles if we are to get to know a man, something more than a pure intelligence, that is. Until such time as one has put to oneself a certain number of questions about an author, and has answered them, be it only to oneself alone and under one's breath, one cannot be sure of having grasped him entire, even though the questions may seem quite foreign to the nature of his writings: What were his religious ideas? How did the spectacle of nature affect him? How did he behave in the matter of women, of money? Was he rich, poor; what was his diet, his daily routine? What was his vice or his weakness? None of the answers to these questions is irrelevant if we are to judge the author of a book or the book itself, provided that book is not a treatise on pure geometry, if it is a work of literature above all, one, that is, which brings in everything, etc.' This method which he applied instinctively all his life and in which towards the end he saw the first outlines of a sort of literary botany ...

7. Sainte-Beuve's is not a profound oeuvre. The famous method which in fact, according to Taine, to M. Paul Bourget and to so many others, made him the peerless master of nineteenth-century criticism — that method which consists of not separating the man from the work, of considering that it is not irrelevant if we are to judge the author of a book, unless the book is 'a treatise on pure geometry', to have first answered questions which seem quite foreign to his work (how did he behave ...), to surround oneself with all the possible facts about a writer, to collate his correspondence, to question the people who knew him, talking with them if they are still alive, reading what they may have written about him if they are dead — such a method fails to recognize what any more than merely superficial acquaintance with ourselves teaches us: that a book is the product of a self other than that which we display in our habits, in company, in our vices. If we want to try and understand this self, it is deep inside us, by trying to recreate it within us, that we may succeed. This is an effort of the heart from which nothing can absolve us. It is a truth every bit of which we have to create and... It is too easy to suppose that it will arrive one fine morning among our mail, in the form of an unpublished letter imparted to us by a librarian friend, or that we shall gather it from the lips of someone who knew the author well. Speaking of the great admiration aroused in several writers of the new generation by the work of Stendhal [Henri Beyle], Sainte-Beuve says: 'May they permit me to tell them, that if we are clearly to judge that rather complicated mind and not exaggerate at all in any direction, I shall always come back for preference, independently of my own impressions and memories, to what those who knew him in his prime and when he was starting out have to say about him, to M. Mérimée, to M. Ampère, to what Jacquemont would have to tell me about him were he still alive, to those, in short, who saw and savoured much of him in his earlier version.'

8. Why so? How does the fact of having been a friend of Stendhal make us better able to judge him? On the contrary, it would probably be a serious hindrance. For such intimates the self which produces the works is obscured by the other self, which may be very inferior to the outward self of many other men. The best proof of which moreover is that, having known Stendhal, and having collected up all the facts he could from 'M. Mérimée' and 'M. Ampère', having equipped himself, in short, with everything which, according to him, enables a critic to judge a book more accurately, Sainte-Beuve judged Stendhal in the following manner: 'I have just reread, or tried to, the novels of Stendhal; they are frankly detestable.'

[...]

9. He ends with these two gems: 'Criticize Beyle's novels with some candour though I may, I am far from censuring him for having written them ... His novels are what they may be, but they are not vulgar. They are like his criticism, for the use chiefly of those who write them ...' And the concluding words of the article: 'Beyle had a fundamental straightforwardness and reliability in his personal dealings which we must never forget to acknowledge once we have said our piece about him.' A good fellow, Beyle, all things considered. To reach which conclusion it was perhaps scarcely worth the trouble of meeting M. Mérimée so often at dinner or at the Academy, or 'setting M. Ampère talking' so much, and once having read it one is less anxious than Sainte-Beuve was at the thought of the new generations to come.

[...]

10. At no time does Sainte-Beuve seem to have grasped what is peculiar to inspiration or the activity of writing, and what marks it off totally from the occupations of other men and the other occupations of the writer. He drew no dividing line between the occupation of writing, in which, in solitude and suppressing those words which belong as much to others as to ourselves, and with which, even when alone, we judge things without being ourselves, we come face to face once more with our selves, and seek to hear and to render the true sound of our hearts — and conversation!

11. It is only the deceptive appearance of the image here which lends something vaguer and more external to the writer's craft and something deeper and more contemplative to sociability. In actual fact what one gives to the public is what one has written when alone, for oneself, it is very much the work of one's self... What one gives to sociability, that is to conversation (however refined it may be, and the most refined is the worst of all, because it falsifies our spiritual life by associating itself to it: Flaubert's conversations with his niece or with the clockmaker are without risk) or to those productions intended for one's intimates, that is to say reduced so as to appeal to a few and which are barely more than written conversation, is the work of a far more external self, not of the deep self which is only to be found by disregarding other people and the self that knows other people, the self that has been waiting while one was with others, which one feels clearly to be the only real self, for which alone artists end by living, like a god whom they leave less and less and to whom they have sacrificed a life that serves only to do him honour.

[...]

12. And not having seen the gulf that separates the writer from the society man, not having understood that the writer's self shows itself only in his books, that he only shows society men (even those society men that other writers are, when in society, who only become writers again once on their own) a society man like themselves, he was to launch that famous method which, according to Taine, Bourget and so many others, is his claim to fame, and which consists, in order to understand a poet or writer, in questioning avidly those who knew him, who frequented him, who may be able to tell us how he behaved in the matter of women, etc., that is, on all those very points where the poet's true self is not involved.

[...]

13. Just as we find Sainte-Beuve believing that the salon life which he enjoyed was indispensable to literature, and projecting it across the centuries, here to the court of Louis XIV, there to the select circle of the Directory, so ... In point of fact this seven-days-a-week creator, who often did not rest even on Sundays and who received his wages of fame on Mondays from the pleasure he gave to good judges and the knocks he inflicted on the unkind ones, saw all of literature as a sort of Lundis which may perhaps be reread but which have had to be written in their own time heedful of the opinion of the good judges, in order to please and not relying too much on posterity. He sees literature under the category of time. [...] Literature seems to him to be of its period, to be worth what the person was worth. In sum, it is better to play a major role in politics and not to write than to be a political malcontent and write a book on morality ... etc. He was not like Emerson, therefore, who said that we must hitch our wagon to a star. He tries to hitch his to the most contingent thing of all, to politics.

[...]

14. I wonder at times whether what is still best in Sainte-Beuve is not his poetry. There the intellectual games have ceased. He no longer comes at things obliquely, with endless clevernesses and trickery. The magic and infernal circle has been broken. In ceasing to speak in prose he ceases to tell lies, as if the constant mendacity of his thought stemmed in his case from his contrived skill in expression. Just as a student, forced to translate his thoughts into Latin, is forced to lay them bare, so Sainte-Beuve finds himself for the first time in the presence of reality and receives a direct sense of it. [...] of him, of the deep, unconscious, personal self there is hardly anything bar the clumsiness. That recurs frequently, as nature will. But the trifling thing, the trifling yet also delightful and sincere thing that is his poetry, that skilful and at times successful attempt to express the purity of love, the sadness of late afternoons in large towns, the magic of memory, the emotion of reading, the melancholy of an unbelieving old age, demonstrates — because one feels that it is the only real thing about him — the lack of significance in his vast, marvellous, ebullient oeuvre as a critic — for all these marvels come down to this. Mere appearance, the Lundis. The reality, this handful of poems. The poems of a critic, they it is out of all his writings that tip eternity's scales.

Swann Explained by Proust

[Published November 1913]

1. 'I am publishing only one volume, Du côté de chez Swann, of a novel whose general title will be A la recherche du temps perdu. I would like to have brought the whole of it out at once; but works in several volumes are no longer being published. I am like someone who has a tapestry too large for present-day apartments, and who has been obliged to cut it up.

2. 'Young writers, with whom I am otherwise in sympathy, advocate on the contrary a succinct plot with few characters. That is not my conception of the novel. How to put it to you? You know that there is plane geometry and solid geometry. Well, for me, the novel is not only plane psychology, but psychology in time. I have attempted to isolate the invisible substance of time, but to do that the experiment had to be able to be long-lasting. I hope that at the end of my book, some minor social event of no importance, some marriage between two persons who in the first volume belong to very different worlds, will indicate that time has passed and will take on the beauty of certain patinated leadwork at Versailles, which time has encased in an emerald sheath.

3. 'Then, like a town which, as the train follows a curve in the track, appears now on our right hand and now on our left, the various aspects that a single character has taken on in someone else's eyes, to the extent of being like different and successive characters, will convey — but only by this — the sensation of time having elapsed. Particular characters will later reveal themselves as different from what they are in the present volume, and different from what they will be believed to be, as very often happens in life for that matter.

4. 'It is not only the same characters who will reappear in the course of the work under different aspects, as in certain cycles by Balzac, but,' M. Proust tells us, 'certain profound, almost unconscious impressions within a single character.

5. 'From this point of view,' M. Proust goes on, 'my book would perhaps be like an attempt at a sequence of "Novels of the Unconscious"; I would not be at all ashamed to say "Bergsonian novels" if I believed that, for it happens in every age that literature attempts to attach itself — post hoc, of course — to the prevailing philosophy. But that would not be accurate, for my work is dominated by the distinction between involuntary and voluntary memory, a distinction which not only does not appear in M. Bergson's philosophy but is even contradicted by it.'

6. 'How do you substantiate this distinction?'

7. 'For me, voluntary memory, which is above all a memory of the intellect and of the eyes, gives us only facets of the past that have no truth; but should a smell or a taste, met with again in quite different circumstances, reawaken the past in us, in spite of ourselves, we sense how different that past was from what we thought we had remembered, our voluntary memory having painted it, like a bad painter, in false colours. Already, in this first volume, you will find the character who tells the story and who says "I" (who is not me) suddenly recovering years, gardens, people he has forgotten, in the taste of a mouthful of tea in which he has soaked a bit of madeleine; he could have remembered them no doubt, but without their colour or their charm; I have been able to make him say that, as in that little Japanese game where you soak flimsy bits of paper which, the moment you immerse them in the bowl, spread out and writhe and turn into flowers and characters, all the flowers in his garden, and the water-lilies of the Vivonne, and the good people of the village and their little houses and the church, and the whole of Combray and its surroundings, whatever can take on shape and solidity, has emerged, town and gardens, out of his cup of tea.

8. 'You see, I believe that it is really only to involuntary memories that the artist should go for the raw material of his work. First, precisely because they are involuntary and take shape of their own accord, drawn by the resemblance of some identical moment, they alone bear the hallmark of authenticity. Then, they bring things back to us in exact proportions of memory and oblivion. And finally, since they give us to enjoy the same sensation in quite other circumstances, they release it from all contingency, they give us its extratemporal essence, which is the very content of good style, that general and necessary truth that the beauty of a style alone can reveal.

9. 'If I permit myself to rationalize about my book like this,' M. Proust continues, 'that is because it is not in any degree a product of the reason, for its least elements were supplied to me by my sensibility, I perceived them first deep inside myself, without understanding them and had as much difficulty converting them into something intelligible as if they had been as alien to the world of the intellect — as what shall I say — a musical motif. You are thinking I imagine that this is over-subtle. But I assure you, on the contrary, that it is a reality. What we have not had to elucidate for ourselves, what was clear already (the ideas of logic for example), is not truly ours, we do not even know whether it is the real. It is a part of the "possible" that we select arbitrarily. Besides, you can tell that right away, you know, by the style.

10. 'Style is not at all an embellishment as certain people think, it is not even a matter of technique, it is — like colour with painters — a quality of vision, the revelation of the private universe that each one of us can see and which others cannot see. The pleasure an artist affords us is to introduce us to one universe the more.'

译者导读

乔治·艾略特（George Eliot，原名Mary Ann Evans，玛丽·安·伊万斯，1819—1880），英国小说家，与狄更斯和萨克雷齐名。她出生于英国华威郡一个中产阶级商人家庭（父亲曾是木匠，后暴发成为房地产商人）。三十几岁时，她因翻译工作而开始文学生涯，之后还担任《威斯敏斯特评论》杂志的编辑；由于曾在两所宗教气息浓厚的学校就读，艾略特受宗教影响颇深；平日最喜研究语言，拉丁文、法文、德文、意大利文、希伯来文、希腊文皆能通晓。艾略特年近四十岁才开始写作，并发表文章于杂志上；1859年发表了她的第一部长篇小说《亚当·比德》；之后，她发表了两部极为成功的著名之作《织工马南传》与《弗洛斯河上的磨坊》，奠定了在英国文坛的地位。

乔治·艾略特是英国文学发展史上，同时也是女性文学发展史上一位重要的作家。肖尔瓦特曾指出，在英国小说的版图里，女性的领土通常被描绘成四周被山峦包围的荒漠，这些山峦即“奥斯汀巅峰、勃朗特峭壁、艾略特山脉、伍尔夫丘陵”，这足以证明艾略特在英国文坛的重要性。

除了小说，艾略特的论文和书评也饱含了杰出的思辨能力和极高的写作水平。本书收录了六篇艾略特极具代表性的论文以及书评，第一篇就是她非常著名的文章《女作家写的蠢故事》，她在文中颠覆了世人以往对女性作家的看法，提出不能因为作者是女性就在批评时手软。她以俏皮诙谐的口吻讽刺了同时代女性作家互相模仿、不思进取的写作陋习，并且戏谑地将女作家写的愚蠢故事分成了女帽类、白色圣领体、神谕体以及现代仿古类小说。艾略特着重介绍了女帽类小说，借由英国女士们都十分喜爱的帽子来暗讽她们的作品虚有其表，没有实际的用处，并且选取了几本时下流行的女性作品进行分析，文笔活泼犀利，向读者展示了十九世纪英国女性作家的通病；她还在文章结尾处奉劝没有真材实料的女性不要踏入写作这个圈子。

第二篇是《法国女作家：萨布莱夫人》，艾略特首先介绍了女性在法国文学中的重大影响，并且分析了其原因，接着详细描述了低调而谦逊的法国女作家萨布莱夫人，其间穿插着法国女性文学发展史，包括沙龙文学、肖像文学、箴言文学等。艾略特以丰富的背景知识和精练的语言向读者展示了萨布莱夫人独特的人格魅力以及她一些可笑的小缺点。萨布莱夫人一生影响了很多著名的政治家、哲学家、作家和诗人，是众多女性作家中熠熠生辉的一位。

第三篇是《评杰拉尔丁·朱伊斯伯里的〈康斯坦斯·赫伯特〉》，艾略特用短小精悍的篇幅抨击了杰拉尔丁的新小说《康斯坦斯·赫伯特》，她认为作者花费大量篇幅诉说自己的道德观是极不明智的。

在第四篇《玛格丽特·富勒和玛丽·沃斯通克拉夫特》中，艾略特对比了美国和英国这两位著名的女权主义作家。这两位作家虽然在时间上相差六十多年，空间上隔着大西洋，但是她们在很多女性观点上都是一致的。艾略特引用了两位作家的一系列观点，例如男性纵容女性的愚昧、男性控制女性的受教育权利、社会上对女性职业的偏见等，呼吁女性应当获得与男性平等的受教育和择业权利。

第五篇是艾略特的另一篇书评，她在该文中评论了当时三位来自不同国家的著名作家的新书：美国作家哈丽雅特·比彻·斯托的《德雷德》，英国小说家查尔斯·里德的《改过不嫌晚》，以及瑞典女权主义者弗雷德里卡·布雷默的《赫莎》。艾略特认为斯托夫人的《德雷德》并没有走出《汤姆叔叔的小屋》的套路，但是书中对希伯来基督教的细致描写是一大看点；里德的《改过不嫌晚》具有夸张的戏剧效果，虽然书中有各种小缺陷，但仍然值得一读；布雷默的《赫莎》则是一本目的很明确的小说，因为作者布雷默把妇女解放看作是一生的追求。

最后一篇是短文《翻译和译者》，艾略特列举了一些著名的翻译者在翻译时犯的错误，以此说明翻译不仅需要天赋，还需要知识的积累，并不是一件易事。

该书是乔治·艾略特个人观点的集中展现，无论是杂文还是书评，都体现了她的机智和幽默。她一方面呼吁女性的觉醒，另一方面又批判当时文学女性的局限性；她希望女性获得和男性平等的权利，也希望文学女性能真正充实自己，避免写出更多的蠢故事。乔治·艾略特具有同时期女作家所没有的批判精神和幽默感，她视野广阔，极具开拓精神，该书是研究乔治·艾略特的宝贵文献，是研究女性文学史及女权主义思潮的参考书籍，也是窥探同时期法国、美国、瑞典等其他国家女性文学作品的重要资料。

女作家写的蠢故事[1]

女作家写的蠢故事内容丰富，风格多样；按照愚蠢的不同特质，它包含了浅薄空洞型、单调涣散型、一片虔诚型、迂腐卖弄型等多种文风。然而，所有这些展示女性愚昧的作品中，有一个分支流派数量最为庞大，我们暂且管它叫女帽类小说[2]。此类蠢故事往往是这样开始的，女主角是一位继承人或者颇有家产的贵族夫人，书中前半部分都在详细描述她的几位情人：一位桀骜不驯的准男爵，一位和善亲切的公爵，以及一位魅力四射的年轻侯爵；中途一定还会有个牧师或诗人追求她；当然，她身后还跟着一群各式各样的追求者，书里只是轻描淡写地一笔带过。通常来说，这位女主角的眼睛闪耀着美丽的光泽，头脑机智非凡；她的鼻子挺拔，就像她的品性那样端庄；她的声音甜美，思维敏捷；她穿戴讲究，笃信宗教。跳舞时，她宛如曼妙的西尔芙精灵；读起书来更是了不得，能读懂原版[3]的《圣经》。另外一种女主角拥有所有这些美好品质，只不过她不是继承人，也没有万贯家财，然而她总是有跻身上流社会的机缘，为了觅得如意郎君而拒绝很多绅士的追求，最终成为了大家眼中正直不阿、极具传统家庭观念的贤良淑女。男人面对她机智的言语常常无力还击，只好保持沉默；或者，在某些适当的场合，她原本表示责难的话，在男士听来也意味深长，反而因此被打动；诚然，这些女主角都有长篇大论滔滔不绝的潜质，甚至连她自己一个人就寝时也能高谈阔论一番。人们能从她文章的字里行间看出她的伶牙俐齿，而从她的谈吐感受到她的诙谐和巧思。她懂得如何通过学习粗浅的哲学道理增加自己的见解和洞察力，她敏锐的直觉就像精确的钟表一样，男人只需跟随她的节奏，一切都能进展顺利。事实上，男人在她身边只是扮演了跑龙套的角色。然而时不时的，你又能从书中某些暗示里感受到男女主人公之间的暧昧关系，让你又开始坚信男女之间亘古不变的自然爱情法则，心里有了些许欣慰。但显然，在该女主角领衔主演的这部漫长人生影片中，男人存在的最终目的也只不过是扮演了女主角的护送者而已。他们的相遇总是很俗套：男人们在一次舞会上对她一见钟情，在某次花展上被她迷住，在短途旅行中被她精湛的骑术所征服，或是在教堂瞥见了她庄重又甜美的姿态。总之，她在感觉、精神甚至穿着上全方位地符合了男性心中理想的女神形象。尽管如此，女主角有时也会嫁给一个桀骜不驯的准男爵，让她饱受情感折磨。但是这个男爵为了她而浪子回头，渐渐完全钟情于咱们的女主角，并愿意为她献出生命。邪恶的男爵最终一定会在决斗中丧生，躺在床上奄奄一息，他请求妻子一定要再嫁给她最爱的人，并且已经自作主张给她的情人派送了信件，就当作是对将死的自己的一种恩赐。当情节发展到此，我们也跟随高贵、可爱、有才的女主角一起体验了她之前诸多的倒霉遭遇，但是无论她经历了多少变迁和苦难，就算曾经哭湿了刺绣镶边的精致手绢，晕倒在价值连城的高档坐垫上，她依旧能在走出马车的那一瞬间保持容光焕发，或是在心血来潮剪了个短发之后愈发显得明艳动人。这些，都无不让各位读者内心宽慰。

我们可能会这样评价，正是因为淑女小说家写出了这些愚蠢的小说，把我们引入了一个高贵时尚又充满爱的世界，才让我们释怀。我们会因此推断，那些穷困潦倒的女人之所以选择当小说家或是家庭教师，是因为她们实在找不到别的“女性化”生存之道了。基于这样的假设，我们即使发现小说中有语病、有错误，也会像看到盲人卖针垫和睡帽那样，虽然觉得他卖的东西毫无用处且样式丑陋，却会因为心中的同情而原谅这些瑕疵。我们会告诉自己，这些物品虽然有缺陷，但是我们所付的钱却能解救那些穷苦女性。我们的脑海里播放着这样的画面：那些寂寞的单身女性为了生存而苦苦写作，妻子们为了偿还丈夫的债务、女儿们为了给生病的父亲买件礼物而孜孜不倦地辛勤“炮制”着所谓的纯粹英雄主义的小说。在这样的印象下，我们对于淑女小说的评价就比较含蓄了：她的小说有语病，但她的写作动机却无可指责；她的想象力毫无创意，但她坚持不懈的精神令人感动。似乎，我们因作者的困境而原谅了她们写的白痴故事，因为眼泪而相信了那些废话。但事实并不是这样！我们的这种想法以及类似的冠冕堂皇的观点都可以丢弃了！女作家的这些小说是在完全不同于我们想象的状态下写出来的。这些女作家们出行都坐马车，只透过车窗和卖东西的小贩交谈；她们除了和自己的仆人打交道以外和工人阶级毫无交集；她们觉得五百英镑的年薪简直少得可怜；贝尔格莱维亚区[4]和“豪华大别墅”才是她们的最终目标；而男性若不是一位有身份地位的政治家，或者至少是个富有的资本家，那她们甚至连看都不愿看一眼。很显然，她们是坐在优雅的闺房里，用紫罗兰颜色的墨水和红宝石笔尖的钢笔写作的人群；她们对出版商的出价完全不在乎，她们一点都不穷困潦倒，拮据的是她们的脑容量。她们所描绘的上流社会的确惟妙惟肖，令人羡慕；但同时，她们的文字却流露出对其他阶层的陌生。这足以证明，她们生活圈子里的同胞都很富有，否则她们所描写的文人雅士、车马商人就不会如此栩栩如生；以她们的智商，在对自己的所见所闻进行再创作时能保持还原现实的态度，但是对那些没有见过也闻所未闻的事物就只好虚构与想象了。

我们认为，有些女士根本就没有见过五岁以下的孩子，但是最近一部自称“源自真人真事”的女帽类小说《补偿》（Compensation）中，却有一个才四岁半的小女孩在以奥西恩式[5]的口吻说话：

“我太开心了，亲爱的外婆！我遇到了一个如此令人心旷神怡的人：他就像所有美好的事物——像芬芳的花朵，像从本洛蒙德山上看到的景致那般——噢！不！比那还要美——当我一想到他、见到他时就非常非常幸福；他唱歌时就像妈妈那样温柔，他的前额如同远方的大海一般，”小女孩手指向蔚蓝色的地中海继续说道，“没有边际；又像温暖的夏夜里，我抬头仰望天空时最爱的那一群星星……不要这样看着我啊，你现在的额头就像是被阳光照射、被风吹皱了的罗蒙湖面，我最喜欢平静湖面上的阳光了……就像现在，天上飘着些深色云朵，当太阳冲破云层，阳光瞬间就给旁边的丛林和紫色的岩石镀上了金色，倒映在湖面上，显得那么美丽。”

文中的神童小女孩完全展现了一个成人在醉酒后才有的滔滔不绝，这并不奇怪，我们就当是她再现了她母亲的特质，所谓有其母必有其女嘛。于是，我们一遍一遍地告诉自己，文中的小女孩就是这样一个对自己的创造力有“自觉意识”的神童，而且她足够幸运，遇上了一个同样“最具独创性”的令她倾心的天才爱人。

按照书中所写，这位神童的爱人虽然与她“在家境和能力”上都惊人地相似，但“在宗教信仰和未来发展上”却更胜一筹。她把他当作自己的“挚爱”（Agape）——这个词多么少见——她在读希腊文的圣经新约时学到这个词并且一直憧憬，这完全得益于她平常习得语言的超常能力以及阅读原版经文的习惯。当然，希腊语和希伯来语对于女主角来说只不过是小菜一碟，要她讲梵语更是易如反掌；事实上，除了英语之外，她还能准确无误地用其他任何语言交流。她不仅会跳波尔卡舞，还通晓数国语言，她简直就是一位穿着裙子的外交家。可怜的男人们！你们有几个看得懂希伯来语，你们唯一可以夸耀的恐怕只是知道博林布鲁克[6]怎么拼写吧；你们可能正在迷恋那些偶尔挂念你们的女人，自己讲的闪族语却还磕磕巴巴呢。然而，我们都知道这样一个道理，女主角常常有一颗“爱美之心”，她的聪明才智因为对服饰搭配和行为举止的关注而过早地被激发出来，因此，对她们而言，选择说东方语言而不讲自己的母语就像是蝴蝶采蜜的本能那样简单。另外，读者根本不用费心去研究女主角的学识到底有多深，因为作者已经写得很明白了。

在另外一本女帽类小说《劳拉·盖伊》（Laura Gay）中，女主角并不精通希腊语和希伯来语，但她对拉丁古典文学的熟稔弥补了这一缺点——她熟读“亲爱的老维吉尔[7]”、“优雅的贺拉斯[8]、仁慈的西塞罗[9]，以及令人愉悦的李维[10]”，各种经典烂熟于心。正如《劳拉·盖伊》中写的那样，当和一群贵妇人以及绅士外出聚会野餐时，女主角能旁征博引拉丁名著是一件多么重要的事情！“那些所谓的高人一等的男性根本不会对这些话题产生嫉妒，是的，一定不会。”书中继续写道，“若在场的多数人是理智且高贵的绅士，他们必定不会对女士的卖弄产生嫉妒感；但在场的若都是温德姆小姐和雷德福先生这种普通之流，那么就必须得作出牺牲证明一下自己了”。我们认为，他们这种引经据典的自我牺牲并不是出于对拉丁经典的狂热兴趣，对于理智且高贵的少数男性来说，他们更愿意主动避免和愚蠢且无知的大多数人产生正面冲突。在男女混合的聚会场所，有教养的男性和女性都很少谈论拉丁名著，他们即使熟读“仁慈的西塞罗”，即便是“令人愉悦的李维”几欲脱口而出，也能在平常的谈话交流中不卖弄自己的学识。然而，对于书中的盖伊小姐来说，拉丁经典西塞罗之类只是她最基础的谈资。一次在帕拉丁山上，她对一众观光客作出了如下脉络清晰、内容全面而丰富的评论：

“真理是完全客观的，甚至那些被分门别类的主观性教义，每一种都多多少少沾染了些许迷信的色彩；例如罗马天主教中的无知、爱好、古老的偶像崇拜、宗教权威等，都在纯正的真理基础之上逐渐积淀，并最终转化成有众多跟随者的大型宗教，这样的转变是多么难得啊！要探索这种积淀就像是发掘出这堆垃圾下价值连城的珍珠一样，需要热忱、勇气与智慧。”

如果仔细想想，我们或许见过很多比劳拉·盖伊更加清新脱俗、思想深刻的女性，但是肯定没遇见过如此啰唆的。有一位刚刚爱上盖伊小姐的贵族牧师正是因为听了以上那一段深沉的评论，于是开始有些怀疑她是个独立思考的女性，担心不好把控。但是他想错了！当他有一次深陷痛苦，想请求“唤起她的回忆，唤醒那种我们很容易忘却、只有在经历过生活的磨难之后才明白的力量和安慰”之时，她却对这种文绉绉的话完全听不懂。所以，虽然《劳拉·盖伊》中所描写的各种奢华财富和高雅生活都散发着正统气息，然而只要我们用“理智的头脑来分析”，或者亲自研读过“仁慈的西塞罗”，就会发现这种正统也不过虚有其表罢了。

相比之下，《补偿》一书更具教条主义风格，但是其中堆砌了更多势利世俗以及荒诞的插曲，夹杂着虔诚与轻浮的矛盾感。书中的女主角琳达比劳拉·盖伊更精明、更聪敏，她被呈现得很全面，她的爱人更多；书中还介绍了各种邪恶但令人着迷的女人——甚至包括一个法国悍妇；此书不遗余力地讲述了你所能想象到的恶俗小说中各种令人兴奋的故事。事实上，这本书就是一个大杂烩：有苏格兰人的预言、罗杰斯先生的早餐、意大利强盗、临终剧情大反转、优越感十足的女作家、意大利女教师、毒杀老妇人、有关信仰与宗教的探讨，以及“最具原创性的思想”。书中的女作家苏珊·巴顿小姐是个天才，她提起笔“写小说时一挥而就”，但她拒绝了一桩好婚姻（她拒绝了琳达父亲的求婚）；虽然她的年纪大到已经足够当琳达的母亲，但她最终选择了一位年轻的伯爵，情定这位曾被女主角拒绝过的情人。当然，天赋和道德若不是有合适的支持者，就会显得乏味；同样，虔诚也必须融入到“社会”最好的圈子里才能合乎礼仪。

《阶级与美女》（Rank and Beauty）是一本更加浅薄、宗教色彩相对较弱的女帽类小说。书中是这样写我们的女主角的：“即使她出身卑微，但如果她继承了父亲的风骨、母亲的美貌，加上具有符合她年龄的奔放与热情，这些特质将最终升华成敢爱敢恨的勇气，她的后代会觉得这些是他们能够得到的最好的财富。”这位青春热血的年轻女士在读父亲的报纸时爱上了首相先生。这个住在乡下的灰姑娘温德姆小姐，通过阅读头条新闻以及国会辩论中的个人简介，觉得首相先生就是她在这世间独一无二的真爱，像一颗闪亮的星星照耀着自己。但是她很快就选择做了乌姆弗拉维尔男爵的夫人，当她搬进春日公园的豪宅时，她的美貌和成就惊艳了周围的人，正如你所想的，她不久就将会碰到那位素未谋面的首相先生了。可能“首相”一词总让你想起满脸皱纹、一身赘肉的六十多岁的老头儿，但是现在赶紧把这些印象都抹干净吧，鲁伯特·康威首相“被称为是这个宇宙中青春永驻的男性”，头条新闻和国会辩论的个人简介对他的描述没有丝毫是胡乱编造的，全都符合事实。

“门又打开了，鲁伯特·康威走了进来。伊夫琳[11]小姐抬头看了一眼，这一眼就足够了！他完全没让她失望。这一眼似乎就像是她之前一直盯着一幅画看，而现在画中人竟然走了出来的感觉。他的个头、他非凡的气质，就像是范戴克——他的一位骑士祖先再世。她幻想着他的这位骑士祖先曾经率领乌姆弗拉维尔征战异教徒，将他们赶到了海的另一边。这些都是真实的吗？”

当然不是。

故事的进展很明确，渐渐地，首相先生对她动心了，这发生在乌姆弗拉维尔夫人在温莎堡觐见女王的时候——

这是她（温德姆小姐）在王宫的最后一晚了，骑马回来后，温德姆先生带着她和一群伙伴到围墙顶上看风景。她倚在城墙边，站在最高处俯瞰脚下的城池，不禁感叹：“这风景真是无与伦比的美丽啊！”而这时，鲁伯特正在她身边。

“是很美！但是也只有站在这样的高度才看得到如此美景啊！这次旅行觉得高兴吗？”

“简直令人陶醉！为女王而生，为女王而死，为女王尽忠！”

“哈！”他叫出声来，脸上露出找到知音般的欣喜。

这种“找到知音般的表情”为第三卷中他们最终结婚埋下了伏笔，但是在那美满的结局之前，女主角和一位名叫勒特雷尔·威彻利的先生经历了一段充满误解的复杂感情。这位威彻利先生是一位天才诗人，在各方面都是个非凡的角色。他不仅是浪漫的诗人，潇洒的浪子，还是个愤世嫉俗的才子。他对乌姆弗拉维尔女士的极端爱慕使他的讽刺才能变得如此匮乏，以至于在交谈中他的形象是那么可怜。她拒绝他时，这位先生竟然冲进灌木林在泥里打滚，并且开始了最为邪恶和煞费苦心的报复历程。他伪装成一位从事全科诊疗的江湖医生，并且假装预言伊夫琳生了重病必须由他来医治。最终，他的计划泡汤，他写了一封长信跟她道别，信中洋溢着他的满腹才华：

“噢，亲爱的小姐，当你沉浸在美好和喜悦中时，你能否想起，给你写信的我，这痛苦的灵魂？当你的镀金豪华轮船驶入平静的大海，当你的心境被令人陶醉的乐声抚平时，你能否听到来自远方的，我的叹息？”

总之，虽然故事浅薄空洞，但是和其他两部小说比较起来，大家还是更喜欢这本《阶级与美女》。书中当然也有令人觉得愚蠢无语的时候，但是作者写的对话贴近生活且生机勃勃，没有丁点矫揉造作和卖弄学问的痕迹。读者不需要去研究作者所写的怀疑论者与哲学家的相互驳斥，也不用分析和探寻宇宙的奥秘问题，就能自然地相信女主角依旧是个智慧十足的女孩儿。

女帽类小说的作者们在写作措辞上都十分雷同。在她们的小说中，总有一位女士或者绅士像见血封喉树一般阴险毒辣，扮演着大反派：他男子气概十足，精神世界丰富多彩，内心却空虚寂寞；他算计朋友，做任何事都追求利益；他性格的形成可以追溯到幼年时期；他的住房简陋，天晴时太阳照耀着他的沙发，下雨时雨滴则掉在他身上，生活对于他来说充满忧伤；阿尔比恩和斯科舍仅仅是他对话中使用的绰号和诨名。这些人物的道德评价也惊人地相似，例如“所有人，无论贫富，都会被不好的榜样所影响，这是个令人忧伤的事实”“读者在任何一本不起眼的书中都能获取有用的信息”“邪恶总是能打着美德的幌子横行”“小说写得再喧嚣浮夸，也没那么容易欺骗熟读何为人性的读者，所以美德和高尚是必不可少的元素”以及“我们只有被伤害过，才能学会原谅”等等。毫无疑问，这些评论对有一部分读者可以说是一针见血、辛辣刺激。我们常常看到一些读者手握铅笔一遍又一遍地在书上作标注，因为他们的生活与书中描写相差甚远，所以被这些新奇却生硬的创作所打动，那些充满赞叹的标注就是证据。这些小说的语言特点在于使用很多具有独创性的倒装句，并且刻意避免日常生活中的普通用语。愤怒的年轻人这样惊呼“就是这样，我认为”；再听听晚餐前半小时，一位年轻女士和她的邻居谈论她第一次读莎士比亚的经历：“我偷偷溜进公园里，坐在绿色的树冠下，兴高采烈地阅读着这位如同魔术大师般的人所写的带给人无限惊喜的书页。”但是此类女帽类小说家最显著的贡献在于她们的哲学思考。例如《劳拉·盖伊》的女作家让女主角和男主角最终结婚，证明了“如果那些怀疑论者的眼睛只是长期盯着物质看，那么他们就看不到这个人身上别的特点了；当他们的目光移开物质，全心全意投入到精神的福祉当中，就会发现一个人的灵魂和肉体有着不同的起源，其本质也是不一样的。”淑女小说家似乎能看到除却物质层面的其他内容，她们不局限于观察到现象，而是能透过现象洞察更深；自然，她们就比其他任何人更能抗衡那些虽负盛名，但是我们并不熟知的怀疑主义者，并说服他们：一个人的灵魂和肉体在本质上是不一样的。

在淑女作家所写的愚蠢小说中，还有一种“神谕体”（oracular species）最令人惋惜叹气，这类小说致力于阐释作者自己的宗教哲学和道德观。在女性中似乎广泛存在着这样一个概念，她们相信只有通过最简单的言论和行为，才能增长人类的知识，才是启发人类智慧最合适的方式。通过她们的写作来判断，总有那么一些女作家认为，对科学和生活的完全无知，是对复杂的道德及推理问题形成自身观点的最好途径。显然，她们解决类似难题的秘诀都像这样：用一颗女性特有的头脑，加上对哲学和文学零零碎碎的一知半解，对社会固执己见的错误认识，用自己有限的英语水平，每天现学现卖地在书桌前写上好几个小时。你很少能碰见一个“神谕体”的淑女小说家会质疑她自己对神学问题的判断能力，她从不怀疑自己，自认为在任何宗教聚会中都能精确地区分出善与恶；她们能准确地发现男人们迄今为止出了哪些毛病，并且对没有机会向她请教的哲学家们表示遗憾。然而，真正伟大的作家总是谦逊地将自己的经历写进小说，用以展示人和物最本真的样子；与此不同，神谕体女作家认为这种写作能力实在是不敢恭维：“他们并没有解决什么重大问题啊”——于是乎她时刻准备着，通过讲述一个爱情故事来弥补所谓的伟大作家们的缺陷，给读者补习人生道理，普及神学指南；这样的爱情故事中，来自富裕家庭的女士和先生们总是会经历上层社会特有的种种磨难。另外，她还会讲解自然神论者、皮由兹[12]以及极端新教徒（ultra-Protestants）理论，虽然她自己都搞不太清楚；接着，她时而采用浓缩的语句总结，时而通过三百三十多页的长篇大论阐释有关基督教的特殊观点。你会觉得，无论这些先生和女士们在小说中拥有好运或是遭遇不幸，都与你曾经碰到过的人完全不一样。因为，在通常情况下，一个女作家描写她同胞真实生活的能力，与她谈论上帝的能力成反比；而她想要凭借自己的经验来描写从未见过的事物是完全行不通的。

《一个谜团：来自乌尔克里庄园档案中的一页》（The Enigma：A Leaf from the Chronicles of Wolchor-ley House，后简称《谜团》）是我们能见到的最典型的“神谕体”小说。书中，破解该“谜团”所需要的能力不会超过一个女作家的能力，不多不少，刚刚符合了作者的智力水平。作者已经在小说的第一页提出了难题，答案也欲隐欲现。留着乌黑头发、生机勃勃的年轻女士说，“一切生命都是难以解开的谜团”；而顶着褐色头发的另一位温柔女士，对着自己临摹的圣母像说，“曾几何时，有解开这些谜团的方法”。这种小说的风格同它的目的一样崇高，即使书中有斜体字和小写字母的详细注释，但有些段落我们可能花了很长时间研究却仍然不懂；或许，我们必须等到智力进一步开发才能理解书中的内容。那就让我们来开开眼吧。书中写了一位年轻的模范牧师欧内斯特，无论在什么情况下，他都能把每个人校正到最佳状态，他认为“婚姻是不可交易的，那是对神灵的亵渎”。在某个晚上，“他辗转难眠，悲痛与欢快的情感充斥着他挣扎的内心”，“他不能容忍任何形式的买卖婚姻，即使这种行为自有其价值，不管是出于尊敬抑或是阶级需要，他正直的灵魂都对之深恶痛绝，自欺欺人者的最后结论对于他来说只是一个神圣的谎言，因为他们‘生活在一出虚无的演出中，欺骗别人并且被人欺骗’，而他觉得自己的护经匣以及衣服夸张的下摆并不只是一种社交摆设”。（我们多么希望原文中的斜体字和小写字母有助于读者理解文意啊。）文中另一位莱昂内尔先生是个模范老绅士，“除了不散漫不颓废，人们对中世纪人物的典型印象似乎在他身上都得到了体现，将人们团结在一起的正是一种英雄主义纽带。原始信仰和真理的色彩镌刻在普通人的内心，随着法律准则的出现和积累，融入到更加广泛的兄弟情谊中，并且互相依赖，越来越臻于完美”。是的，看了这句话，你是否能明白这些色彩是如何铭刻在心中，又是怎样融合成一道情谊之桥——显然这是一条彩虹——准则的出现和积累又是如何使得这座情谊之桥越来越完美？看到这里，你肯定还需要更多的提示才知道莱昂内尔先生到底是干什么的。我们接着来告诉你，他的灵魂深处，“相比较于原始脉搏周围晃动的空气，他的逻辑思想更能够显示出善与真的最佳和谐状态！”当他在封信时，“瞧！这位好人胸膛中跳动着一颗充满真与善的心，如同他装满爱意的双眼，充盈着对祖先的崇敬和自豪，似乎在凝视着家族那清晰的箴言——忠诚”。

小说的作者总是想寻找到高尚的方式来代替庸俗。普通人可能会说休息室的桌上摆着一本莎士比亚手抄本，可是《谜团》的女作家决心迂回地表现自己的文采，会这样描述桌上的书：“《莎士比亚》，那是人类思想和感情的结晶，时刻教化着人们的内心世界。”又比如，一位夜巡人看到某间窗户里的灯比平常亮得久了一些，他就会感慨这些熬夜的人为何傻到有机会早睡却不珍惜；但是，作者唯恐这些事实对于我们来说太过平淡无奇，于是采用了如下这种引人注目且形而上学的方式为我们描述：“他惊叹——因为人们通常会以一种完全独立的人格考虑其他人，于是容易处在错误的精神前提下思考问题（尽管有人不接受这种观点）——自己要如何拥有独树一帜的表现，要如何夸奖一部分人才能让屋内所有的人都欢欣鼓舞呢。”一位叫詹姆斯的普通侍从，他小腿粗壮，发元音总带着气音，现在正开门去迎客，作者立即抓住了这样一个机会开始描写：他是“众多养尊处优的奴仆中的一员，就像是中了该隐[13]一样的诅咒——成为世间的‘流浪者’，通过客人的财富和出价来给他们分级别……噢！英格兰！所有的这些都是你病态子民的浮光而已！”是的，我们曾经听过很多人讲“浮光”，从卡明博士到罗伯特·欧文[14]，从皮由兹到灵魂导师，但是之前我们还从未听过一介女流所谈论的“浮光”。

同样，在《谜团》的作者看来，人们十分普通的生活情节都可能隐藏着最为糟糕的危机；例如那些身着宽下摆长裙和中国水袖的女士，看似贤淑，她们的一言一行却像残暴音乐剧中的女主角。《谜团》中的珀西太太是一位肤浅且虚荣的妇人，她希望自己的儿子贺勒斯能娶一位富有的女继承人：褐色头发的格蕾斯；而贺勒斯却有自己的主张，他爱的是女继承人的表妹：黑头发的凯特，即便凯特没有任何财产；此外，格蕾斯对贺勒斯本来也没有任何好感。在这种情景设定下，儿子一般要么阴沉忧郁，要么脾气暴躁，母亲则强势主动且尖刻易怒，而那位没有财产的灰姑娘只得在夜深人静时躺在床上默默哭泣。我们已经很熟悉这些套路了，就像我们已经了解了天狗吃月的道理，再也犯不着在看到月食的时候敲锣打鼓地把天狗吓跑了。然而，书中的珀西太太在这种状况下的表现真是太出其不意了，读者倒是真没见过。有一天，珀西太太碰巧看到自己的儿子贺勒斯和格蕾斯在窗前谈话，距离远到根本听不见他们在谈什么，而且众所周知，高贵的庄园继承人格蕾斯小姐根本没有任何理由会接受贺勒斯，但是珀西太太就直冲冲地奔了过去，紧紧抱住他们俩，她的脸色因为激动和兴奋而泛红，说道：“幸福的一幕终于上演了啊！那我现在是不是不能叫你格蕾斯了？我的格蕾斯，贺勒斯的格蕾斯！我亲爱的孩子们！”贺勒斯连忙解释，指出这只是一个误会，自己已经和凯特订了婚，于是，我们就看到了以下场景和画面。

她（珀西太太）听到这个消息后，眼睛充满怒火，声音提到了前所未有的高度，她用嘶哑和愤怒的语气吼道：“你这个不孝子！”她双拳紧握继续说：“你不知道这个糟糕的决定会带来什么后果！低下你悲惨的头颅，让妈妈——”

“不要诅咒他了！”此刻，从珀西太太身后传来一句低低的反驳声。这一声就像是上天派来的天使，打断了珀西太太恶毒的语言；反正她是被吓住了，停止了讲话。

而与此同时，贺勒斯正双手捂脸，悲伤地跪在母亲的脚下。

母亲的那些可怕语言很过分，已深深刺伤了他，就像是挥之不去的魔咒，将一直留存在他的心间。那一声反驳是谁说的？是他真正的守护神发话了！

站在珀西太太身后的人正是凯特，她脸色苍白，站得笔直，全身笼罩着死寂一般的镇定——她是当下唯一一个冷静的人了，她抑扬顿挫地缓慢地讲着，语气中充满悲愤和哀伤，一字一句都像是敲在人心上。

“他是作了他的决定，但是我并没有接受！所以，你不能，也没有权力诅咒他！我现在，”此时，凯特又大又黑的双眼闪烁着庄严和痛苦的光泽，她伸出一只手向天起誓，“在这里对天发誓，无论福祸甘苦，如果没有贺勒斯母亲的同意和祝福，我绝不答应贺勒斯·乌尔克里先生的求婚！”

看到了吧，女作家所写的蠢故事就是这样的出乎意料，让我们继续来见识一下。《谜团》本来是一个描写现代社会的故事——在这个社会中，人们跳波尔卡，谈论皮由兹主义，而作者写的人物和事件仅仅是捡了这些丰富多彩故事的零头碎末。书中写了一个爱尔兰竖琴家，他是“很久很久以前一位特立独行的吟游诗人的后裔”，他来到这个普通的英国小村庄，在教堂主日学校举办的茶点庆祝会上惊艳出场。另外，有一个疯狂的吉普赛人，她披着鲜红的斗篷，爱唱浪漫的歌曲，在她临终的时候还揭露了一个秘密：年轻的模范牧师欧内斯特是凯特的哥哥。这一秘密是有证人的，是一个矮小、吝啬的商人，他爱诅咒陌生人并且对着他们发出邪恶的笑声。作者还写了一位极其正直的爱尔兰人巴尼，他通过比对一份文件的落款日期和签名日期证实了它是一份假文件，虽然这份文件已经通过了法庭的审核并且已经生效。谈到莱昂内尔先生的住所，那是他古老家族留下来的珍贵房产，而女作家的想象力就此开始跳跃到城堡和城墙，“听啊，守卫吹响了号角”，据普利斯曼·X回忆，居民夜里都住在内屋卧室；一开始，外面的风很微弱，接着渐渐变大，把香柏的枝杈吹到了草地上，于是女作家开始了中世纪式的描述（黑体是我们加的）：“守夜人挥舞着旗帜，旗面随着声音而展开，猫头鹰受到惊吓后突地窜进了常春藤丛；而苍天正透过它的‘天眼’俯瞰着这个世界——天眼是百眼巨人，掌管无声旋律的神。噢，听吧！守卫塔的钟敲了两声，楼下回荡着报时人‘凌晨两点’的回音。”

《谜团》中的故事就是如此混搭，就像我们在观赏一幅完全源自小朋友想象力的画：右边画着一处时髦的别墅，中间却是两个穿着盔甲的骑士在搏斗，而左边竟然画着一只咧着嘴的老虎在丛林中趴着，这些没有联系的事物被混在了一起，仅仅是因为作者觉得它们各自很有特色，或者真正的原因是她在其他的画中见过这些场景，所以全部拿来为己所用。

然而，比起女作家写“神谕体”小说谈论“本我”、“主观”、“客观”，并且将基督教真理划分得一清二楚，一旦人们偏离了这条分界线就得接受她恩赐般的教诲，我们更喜欢她的中世纪写作风格。书中一位名叫茵西奎林的小姐通过醒目的黑体字告诉我们：“作为内心不可或缺的对外表达方式，在这样一个唱诗的年纪，宗教渐渐地吸引了她，这是一种功能，而不是形式。”另一位福音派的美嘉女士，她十分擅长探访病危的女人并且谈论她们的心理状态；她告诉我们，那位模范牧师“并不反对人们顶着巨大的压力，主观上想着善良，而客观上却追求真实的利益”。当她说到句中的黑体字时，我们可以想象着她加重了音调，并且略微点了点下巴。我们在这里就不引用她别的神学教条式段落，因为相对于我们的语言来说，她所讲述的内容实在是太严肃了。

对于《谜团》这本受众很广并且饱含作者心血的小说，我们说它“愚蠢”似乎不太合适。不过，“愚蠢”这个评论的确是经过我们深思熟虑才给出的。如果大家很早之前就公认，大量词语的堆积并不能成就一个智慧的男人，那么以此类推，一半数量的词语堆积也不能成就一个智慧的女人。女性最顽皮的愚蠢形式表现在文学作品上，因为人们往往对妇女的教育背景存有偏见。当男人看到淑女们耗费光阴谈论礼帽和舞会礼服时，看到姑娘们为了爱情时而傻笑时而神伤时，或是看到中年妇女热衷于说长道短而管不好自家孩子时，他们禁不住感叹：“上帝啊！让女孩们多读些书吧！让她们的头脑里多些有价值的东西好吗？”但是，当他们与一位神谕体女作家谈论几个小时，或者读了她的书之后，男人们又会这样说：“算了吧，当女人有了学识，看看她们是怎么利用这些学识的！她的知识仅仅停留在习得时候的样子，并没有融入到文化中去；她并没有结合谦逊和朴素、通过思考或者学以致用的方式将知识吸收，而是急于表现自己的造诣；她脑袋里装了一面精神镜子，并且时不时地沉浸在自己的‘才华’里；她会用形而上学式的问题去嘲讽别人做的小松饼；她会在晚餐桌上利用自己通过旁门左道得来的知识‘战胜’男人；或者是在晚宴上抓住机会与我们讨论终极哲学问题：物质与意识的关系。然后，再看看她写的东西！她错把模糊当作深邃，将夸张的言辞看作文采，把矫揉造作等同于创造力；她在自己作品的第一页还在炫耀自己的学识，眼睛却瞟向下一页，对着第三页做鬼脸，却又在第四页里歇斯底里。她肯定是读过很多伟大的男性作家的作品，以及少许伟大的女性作家的作品，但是她根本就不能分辨他们的风格和自己的风格，就像一个约克郡人分不清自己的口音和伦敦音的区别，大言不惭正是她天生的风格。天呐！所以，一般来说，女人的资质还是像贫瘠且脆弱的土壤，经受不起太多的耕种，只适合最轻的农作物罢了。”

诚然，男人们仅根据表面观察和片面推断而得出这样的结论并不明智；但我们在此不是要反驳他们的观点——而只是指出，有很大一部分自认为很有才华的女作家恰恰印证了他们的观点。如果一个男人和一位真正有修养的女人交谈过，真正有修养是指那种真正吸收了学识、而不是被学识所淹没的女人，那么他就不会得出以上观点了。一个真正有修养的女人，正如一个真正有修养的男人，她能公正地看待自己以及自己的观点，她越有知识只会越加朴素，越不事张扬。她不会拿知识当垫脚的高台，洋洋自得地以为站在这里便可以对底下所有的人和事一览无余；而会把知识当作一个观察点，由此可对自己形成正确的评价。她不会动不动就口喷诗句或引证西塞罗，这种沉默并不意味着她输给了男人，反而，她觉得脸红脖子粗地和别人比拼记忆力和争论拉丁名著简直是有损自己的优雅气质。她写书不是为了让哲学家困惑，或许正因为她能写出让哲学家感到愉悦的书，在谈话中，她是最不难缠的对象，因为她了解你，而又不想让你知道其实你根本不了解她。她不是在教化你，而是在给你赞同——这才是有教养的最高境界。

比起小众的神谕体小说（被少数高教会派[15]和超验基督徒推崇），数量相对比较庞大的愚蠢小说我们叫作“白色圣领体”[16]，之所以叫这个名字，是因为牧师脖子上佩戴的白色硬领能展示出福音派[17]的思想氛围和虔诚基调。这类小说描绘的大多是上流社会的有教养人士，可谓是低教会派[18]年轻女士的最爱；人们热衷于寻求新鲜感，于是用福音派小说替代流行小说，把参加五月集会当成是看话剧；就连贵格会[19]的小朋友玩的洋娃娃也与众不同，它不能身着俗气的亮片薄纱裙，必须身穿单色礼服，头戴黑色软帽。而且，这类小说中的年轻女士都有着一段爱情故事，这很正常，她们又不是联合兄弟会教堂的，那里的人们都过着没有任何性生活的婚姻。因此，福音派的年轻女士们拥有福音派爱情故事，这样的爱情经过各种磨难之后，因为重生和赎罪而变得神圣起来。这种小说不同于神谕体小说，就像低教会派女教徒不同于高教会派女教徒一样：她们不那么傲慢，却更加无知，她们的句法使用水平提高了一点，却更加粗俗。

福音派文学的主角一般都是年轻的牧师，从中产阶级的观点来看，牧师衣服上的亚麻带对年轻女士的吸引力就如同军服肩章对非福音派女士的吸引力。这类福音派小说的男主角无一例外都是一个忧国忧民的年轻牧师，市井的老妇们对他可能不屑一顾，但是她们年轻的女儿们“却再也不能忘怀他的布道”，轻易就被他俘获芳心；人们只能在讲道坛的阶梯上看到他温柔的一瞥，而不是在话剧包厢里；他的言谈时常引用圣经，而不是文学类诗集；他对女主角感情状态的关心还会深入到对她灵魂的担心。这位牧师的背景总是很好，要么出生在上流社会，要么家庭富裕、衣着得体——其实，福音派小说也具备其他类别小说的愚蠢之处，作者在前一页还在跟你讲赎罪，下一页又开始描写贵族的礼仪和他们的高谈阔论。作者所描绘的上流社会只不过是她的福音派想象力的奇怪彰显罢了；但是在众多白色圣领体小说类别中有一点是异常真实的——万年不变的男主角：传福音的年轻牧师，通常这也是最无聊的一点。

最近刚巧有一本这种类型的小说面世——《古老的灰教堂》（The Old Grey Church）。这本书完全平淡无味，本书的作者对小说的受众没有明确定位。我们完全不知所措，揣测她把自己生命经验中的哪个阶段写进了小说，但能确定的是，她粗鲁低俗的用语风格已足以让人明白，虽然她有这种优势，但她并没有发挥好，将那些男男女女的习惯和特征混为一谈，当然这些男女并不像他们的前辈那样被已经完善过的传统主义所蹂躏。她无端地在权威阶层和劳动阶层间做文章，这在福音派小说家来说是比较少见的。可是真正的福音派故事就应当存在于中低产阶级，这个阶层中存在着很多优质的素材，前提是你得有一双善于发现的眼睛，并且能用文字重现这些剧情。难道我们的福音派观点就只能被有权势的人所理解，而不能被弱势群体所接受吗？为什么我们的福音派女作家就不能向大多数普通人展现她们的宗教观点呢？这些“大多数”普通人没钱买马车，“更别说是镶黄铜的轻便型双轮马车了”，甚至在家吃饭的时候连银制的刀叉都用不起，而且女作家们蹩脚的英语在他们看来却是极其通顺的。我们为什么不能描绘一下英国工人阶层的宗教生活，就像斯托夫人[20]描绘黑人宗教生活那样，一定也会很有意思。然而事实上，这些虔敬的女作家却写些令人恶心的老段子，譬如一个世俗的妇女如何被感化而信教：虽然她还是那么喜欢晚宴，但是她不再宴请花花公子而是邀请牧师；她虽仍旧沉迷于服饰，但她挑选颜色和图案的品味却变得严肃和清醒；她的言语依旧琐碎，但琐碎的言论中却充斥着福音而不是小道传闻。在《古老的灰教堂》一书中，我们同样能看到与流行小说一致的滑稽片段，而且总会有各种品行不端却魅力无边的准男爵。有必要引用小说中的一段话来证明，这种出身高贵的人与斯桂尔斯小姐是相配的。这类谈话中充斥着大量的黑体字和显而易见的暗讽。在一个夜晚，年轻的尤斯塔斯牧师为了和勒欣顿小姐能单独谈话，在聚会时带着她去参观罗马斗兽场遗址。准男爵对此很嫉妒，于是就有了以下这段对勒欣顿的气话：

“毫无疑问，勒欣顿和他在一起是十分安全的，因为他有尤斯塔斯教皇一世般的神圣指引。他会给勒欣顿小姐说教，告诉她很多年前，就在这里，在罗马斗兽场，邪恶的异教徒放出凶猛的野兽袭击我们的门徒保罗——噢，不！顺便说一句，我觉得我错了，那并不是门徒保罗，也并不是在罗马斗兽场。但是内容的真假没关系，他依旧可以布道，从这些离谱的故事讲到那些堕落的异教徒，描述他们不恰当的行为，并且以这样的训词结尾：‘醒来吧！不要和他们同流合污！’——而且我确定，勒欣顿小姐，你十分虔诚地遵守了当晚的禁令，因为我们自从到达聚会就没有看见你。可是，大家都公认今晚是个快乐且迷人的聚会，而且我们都十分感激格雷先生提议举办这个聚会，他是如此慷慨的一位向导，我希望他也能觉得愉快。”

这种喋喋不休的对话以及喋喋不休的叙述就像一幅糟糕的画，什么都没表达出来，或者仅勉强表现了全书有意想要表现的一部分。但是毫无疑问的是，我们和蔼可亲的女作家认为这是一本极具教育意义的小说，虔诚的基督徒妈妈肯定会把这本书塞到她们女儿的手中。我们可能会遇到这样的美国素食者，他们平常只吃干粮，当没有胃口时，会吃些流食改善一下。所以，我们可以把《古老的灰教堂》看作是福音派小说圈子里口味独特的一味菜品，或许有的人读起来还是会觉得很有力量很有趣呢。

然而，可能最不具有可读性的女作家写的蠢故事要数“现代仿古类”[21]小说了。这类小说给读者讲述雅尼和佯庇[22]的家庭生活、亚述王西拿基立[23]的个人感情经历、或是银匠迪米特里厄斯的内心挣扎和最终皈依。其实别的大多数蠢故事至少能够博得读者一笑，而现代仿古类简直就是给人完全呆板和沉重的感觉，其愚昧程度让人禁不住想要咆哮。比起文学女性时常假定某个任务只能由她们和凤毛麟角的天才合作才能完成，还有什么比这类小说更能证明她们根本就没有正确衡量自己的能力呢？重现过去最好的办法只能是模仿——她们通常会在古老的故事脚本中多多少少注入些时代的精神——

“时代精神是什么？

那就是做自我精神的主宰，

由此映射出的时代精神。”[24]

我们承认有些天才对过去任何一个时期都了如指掌，他们可以通过丰富的想象力修复“人类历史之声”里缺失的音符，并且将这些碎片重构成一个整体，从而把久远的过去呈现在我们面前。这种天才的想象力十分稀有，因为它不仅要求有准确和详细的知识，而且需要极其鲜活的创造力。然而，现代仿古类女性作家总用一些适得其反的写作技巧来暴露她们平庸的资质：她们借用古人的名字，把多愁善感用在罗马修女和埃及公主身上，并且引用大量犹太主教和希腊哲学家的修辞论证。这种极度愚昧的小说最近有《亚多尼雅：犹太人驱逐史》（Adonijah, a Tale of the Jewish Dispersion，后简称《亚多尼雅》），这一系列的故事“结合了品味、幽默和合理的原则”。我们能在《亚多尼雅》一书中读到合理的原则，而在其他几本中读到品味和幽默。小说的封面上说，“此书将带你体会与众不同的阅读乐趣”，而且前言这样写道：“如果你对被驱逐的以色列人和朱迪亚人感兴趣，本书会向你提供相关重大历史事件的信息并带来别样的阅读体验。”因为书中所谓的“重大历史事件”并未详细说明，所以有很多深奥的意义我们根本读不懂；然而要说被驱逐的以色列人和朱迪亚人这段历史，任何一个爱读书的女学生知道的都比这本小说中提供的信息要多。至于《亚多尼雅》中的爱情故事可以算是最无力的了，而我们假定它尚且具有一定的教育意义，一是因为小说的男主角是个犹太俘虏，女主角是个罗马修女，他俩以及他们的朋友在经过“促进犹太人改变信仰协会”最简单、最快速的感化之后都皈依了基督教；二是因为作者为了让小说看起来比较复古，并不用平实的语言来写，而是采用了夸张的书面语言，例如“尼禄大帝毋庸置疑拥有天下最杰出的头脑”、“这一贵族气数将尽”、“他忠贞不渝的床笫伴侣”、“啊！对维斯塔灶神起誓！”“罗马人，尔等听着！”等等。本册书的封面上有众多名人推荐和介绍，有一句来自辛克莱小姐：“理性、智慧、虔诚的人都会坦坦荡荡地选择读这本充满想象力的小说”，据此读者可以愉快地推理，无论是多贝尼医生、米勒先生还是莫里斯先生，都是公开地阅读《亚多尼雅》，而不是将其偷偷藏在沙发垫子底下或者在桌子下断断续续地阅读。

俗语说：“若是黄油做的脑袋，就别去当面包师。”变通一下也可以说，如果没有准备好接受后果，女士们就不要投身于写作事业。我们意识到，我们的评论与别的评论者的语气完全不同。评论者的情感常年循环，完全相似，就像护士对待产妇的重复性工作那样，向每一位女性作家的作品“欣然致敬”。我们同样也意识到，我们所批评的那些女作家已经习惯了别人对她们的夸奖：小说的措辞十分考究，描写的生活十分生动，人物性格刻画突出，风格令人着迷，而且人物的精神高尚等等。但是如果她们怨恨我们正直的言论，我们则建议这些女作家应该好好审视一下那些虚有其表的赞词和无关痛痒的批评，给出这些赞词的评论家认为她们的作品在不久的将来就会成为经典。一位女性一旦展现出她的天赋或是影响力，那么她就应当接受适度的赞扬和严厉的批评。若是用一支温度计来度量女性的才华，那么，如果这位女作家的才华本身为零，媒体夸奖她作品的热度则可能达到沸点；若是她的才华算得上平庸，外界的称赞则能达到酷暑的温度；倘若她才华横溢，外界的评论热情却会降到冰点。哈丽雅特·马蒂诺、柯勒·贝尔以及加斯克尔夫人若是男人，那么她们定会得到骑士般的待遇。如果哪个评论家对女作家的评论很高，那么从原则上来说，他一定得是个中立者，并且不对文学女性的作品有特殊偏好。因为评论女性文学很难做到公平公正，评论者面临的最大问题在于往往忽略了书中所缺乏的智力因素，例如看到女作家的耐心勤奋和对作品的责任心，并且欣赏作者的写作技艺时，就会因主观原因提升了对作品的评价。在女性大部分的著作中，由于缺乏高标准的约束而存在着大量愚昧的拼接或是拙劣的模仿，其实一丁点的自我批评就能使其原形毕露；但是，就好像听歌的人若不能正确给出评价，唱歌的人就会跑调一样；倘若听歌的人有那么一些音乐细胞，就会让唱歌的人闭上嘴。单纯地想让文字变成出版物的虚荣心似乎鼓舞了很多女性，她们错误地认为只要会写作就好像高人一等了，可是写出来的作品却充满智力和道德的退化，毫无用处，她们就是没有这一点自知之明。在这样的前提下，我们认为女性的平均智力被大部分女性文学作品所代表了，而且这种代表有失公平；极少数写作水平很高的女作家则远远超出普通水平，当然，还有多数女作家的写作能力远远低于平均水平。因此，严厉的书评肩负着一项十分具有骑士精神的任务，即剥夺女性作者的虚假威望，制止她们具有迷惑性的吸引力，并且劝阻那些资质平庸的女性就不要写小说了——这是她们作为女性对文坛能做的唯一贡献。

女性不经任何特殊资格证明就成为作家，其根源在于社会上的其他职业长期将女性拒之门外。看来，社会真是个十恶不赦的存在，小到有毒的咸菜，大到糟糕的文学，社会都应当对这些有害身体的物品负责。然而，社会，就像“物质”、女王陛下的政府或者其他崇高的抽象概念一样褒贬参半。如果有一个女性是为了生计而写作，那么必定有三个女性是为了名利而写作；是否为生计工作这一事实很好辨认，然而那些最没用、最蹩脚的女性文学明显不是迫于生计而产生的。虽然俗语说“一切劳动必有收益”，但是我们认为女性作家的这些蠢故事只能算作是瞎忙活。

幸运的是，我们并不需要去论证、去证明在小说这个领域，女性就不如男性。我们可以列出一长串的女性小说家名字，无论是已故的还是健在的，她们的小说不仅仅写得还行，有的还写得非常好，比起男性小说的阳刚之气，这些女性小说有着宝贵的特性。即使没有受到完整的教育，女性仍然不会被挡在写小说的门外，而其他艺术形式则没有如此简单的入门原则。就好像水晶石可以在任何形态下呈现美丽，而我们只需要在写小说时加入诚恳的观察、幽默以及热情，就能成就好小说。可是，正是因为写小说的门槛太低，才使得很多能力不够的女性也加入了写作的队伍。正如女性的琴技很难骗人，在弹琴的技巧上，只要战胜几处实际的难点，弹奏中的缺点是必然可以克服的。在一定程度上，任何一种讲求绝对技巧的艺术，都会自动抵制能力不足引发的愚蠢行为。然而，在小说写作中，即使你能力不够，也没有什么外在的条件来约束你，也不会阻碍你把愚昧的能力当作写作天赋。于是我们一次又一次地见证了拉封丹的故事：他将鼻孔对准长笛，发现竟然奏出了声音，于是他激动地大叫：“我！我能吹笛子了！”最后，我们把这个寓言故事谨献给那些想加入“写蠢故事的女作家”行列的女性读者，还是好自为之吧。

法国女作家：萨布莱夫人[25]

1847年，一位名叫康特·利奥波德·菲力的人在帕多瓦[26]去世，留下了一间私人图书馆，其藏书涵盖了世界各国女性作家的作品，多达三万二千多册。我们并不需要像《唐·吉诃德》（Don Quixote）中的牧师那样，在判断这些书籍孰轻孰重时将它们扔到火中检验，我们很清晰地认为，最需要解救和关注的应当数法国女作家的作品。女性文学中品质上乘的小说可谓凤毛麟角，而品质一般的作品如果由男性作者来写则会更优秀；当模仿还不太拙劣时，她们只不过是夸大了男性写作风格，像一个身着男性服装的差劲女演员，大摇大摆地踱着步。女作家的这些作品勉强还算得上是文学，就好像学术获奖诗作也算作诗一样。很少有英语类女性作家能像理查德森·C.女士那样写作。科学没有性别之分：不论男女，只要他们有认知和推理能力，并且进行正确的探索，那么最终都会经历相同的过程，达到相同的结果。而现在我们可以确定，说文学作品没有性别之分是极大的错误。艺术和文学蕴含着整个生命活动，关系着自然界中的每个细节，任何个体进行的独特修正都会对其产生影响，而女性对于文学与艺术作出的贡献是无与伦比的。对于任何一种可能存在的社会场景，女性必然会有其自身的感受和情绪——这种母性的情感，男性是无从得知的；另外，女性相对来说体力较弱，这一事实很难被改变，女性的这种独特体质必然会产生不同于男性的奇妙感情和情愫，继而引发与众不同的想法与灵感。男女之间的心理差异源自不同的性别，这种差异并不会随着女性智力和道德本性的完全发展而消失。事实上，不论是晨曦的微光还是露水的清香，不管是正午阳光的强度还是亮度，只要它们带给男女不同的感受，那么这种差异就是产生多样性和美好作品的永恒源泉。从17世纪初到18世纪末，那些令人身心愉悦的法国女人为法国的政治和文学史书写了最精彩的几笔，这些女性角色往往富有开拓精神，丝毫不畏惧犯错和付出。她们并没有想过为自己创造一番事业，也根本没想过要成为公众人物；她们只不过是给情人、朋友写信，写日记记录自己每天的生活，描写自己认识的人的爱情故事，描述发生在自己眼前的各种悲喜剧。她们精致有涵养，优雅且诙谐，她们审慎明智，兢兢业业地记录所见所闻、所感所想；她们写作的目的并不是要证明女性和男性一样能够写作，她们也并不想去影响男性的观点或者说解放女性。有人说，至少对于17世纪的女性来说，写作就是她们在记录多彩生活过程中的美丽意外，就像玫瑰花的花瓣随风摇摆，自然而然地散发出了淡淡的芬芳。所以，也只有在法国，女性对文学进步的影响是至关重要的；只有在法国，女性的思想和语言如同电流般清晰确切，不像在其他国家那样沉重且模糊不清；只有在法国，如果没有了女性的文学作品，那么法国的历史将出现断层。

爱国主义者可能又要开始叫嚣了，他们认为英国女作家如果愿意，也能把小说写得像法国女性那样好。但这个问题我们还是留给文学评论者去评说吧。毋庸置疑的是，在女性文学作品的各种类别中，法国女性取得的成就是最高的。我们承认，意大利的女性作家大多被冠以教授权威，她们熟识民法和教会法，但她们的作品令人望而生畏，我们并不熟悉；当然还有很多其他地下女性文学根本没有纳入探讨范围，可是我们确信它们根本不能和市面上的作品匹敌，因此，我们认为有关女性文学之间的较量只存在于英国和法国之间。直到今天，塞维涅夫人依旧是在充满男性成功典范的文学世界中至高无上的女性代表；达钦夫人（Madame Dacier）[27]仍旧是学者界的女王，虽然她不听劝告地学了那么多希腊语；当我们要列举出一位机智非凡的女性时，斯塔尔夫人必定是最先被想到的一位；罗兰夫人深受爱戴，她那充满智慧和严肃的史诗也无人能敌；乔治·桑更是一位无可媲美的女作家，就像让·雅克的评语那样，她对外界的感知十分深刻，能够将人物性格的刻画和悲剧式的浓烈激情融合得恰到好处；这些伟大的名字是法国各个时代的里程碑，她们像高高的松树一样耸立在并不那么引人注目却依旧风采不减的女性作家之林中。另外，在这片树林里，还分布着大量的山楂树、野蔷薇和忍冬，这些女性为人所知的缘由并非她们自己创作的作品，而是她们激发男性创作出的作品。她们发挥自己的聪明才智和个人魅力开辟了文化沙龙这一全新形式；在那里，文学、哲学还有科学得以从陈旧迂腐的束缚中解放出来，进入到一个更加明媚通透的发展阶段。

那么，是什么原因促使了法国文学的早期发展以及女性才华的充分展现呢？最基本的原因可能要追溯到法国种族的生理特征上——他们脑子小，秉性活泼、有生气，这就让本性脆弱的女性具备了创造性才思的最高级原料；而英国人和德国人的大脑相对较大，性情缓慢，女性常常爱空想并且态度消极。后者的情感可能更广泛复杂，所以需要更多的条件才能产生出一个完美的标准。纵观动物世界，机能越高的群体，越容易背离标准；我们不常看到进化并不完美的昆虫，但很少看到完美匀称的人类。因此，如果一个女性具有一颗优秀的法国头脑，那么她就不会同时达到日耳曼人的标准。我的这一理论可以由我们自己国家的女性来证实，英国的文学女性通常热情奔放但不复杂，倾向于法国人的特征，而不是日耳曼人类型。另外，那些脑容量大的女性会不停地吸收更多的知识，她的自身条件已经决定了她缺乏对突发情况的应对能力；就好像压力不够集中就不能形成钻石一样，她的脑海中虽然漂浮着各种伟大的思想和念头，却不善于将这些思想固化，即捕捉到这些想法并用语言表述出来。我们认为，比起外部环境等种种因素，这才是造成女性很少在艺术领域开拓创新、在科学领域有所发现、在哲学领域作出深度探索的原因。她们不具备哲学思考所必需的自身条件。然而在充满光明的未来，我们相信这些条条框框将会随着妇女机能的完善得以打破，上述原因也将被推翻。但是就目前来看，我们的这一理论的确为法国女性智力较高提供了生理学基础。

第二个原因则是人们在观念上和实践上对婚姻的散漫态度。但愿我们不要去为法国人的道德观辩论，这一辩论大部分都会是关于婚姻的！但是不可否认，婚姻是随着双方思想和情感的成熟而产生，最后因内心的契合和相互吸引而定下来的，这种联合使得女性给男性带来了更多智力上的支持，并且增加了女性在政治事件中的参与度。对于文化程度高的人来说，他们毫无疑问偏爱稳定且安全的婚姻关系，因为这是他们生活最高品质的表现，但他们缺乏激情。激情是一种神奇的东西，它能唤醒人内心的动力——将懒惰转化为行动，将漠不关心转变成热血沸腾，将模棱两可变得清晰简单，并帮助人们得到最心爱的东西。殷勤和私情虽然本身可鄙，但是相对于刺绣和家务事，却足以激起女性还在沉睡的才华，尤其是在17世纪法国的上流社会，女性受到西班牙骑士精神的熏陶，同时又受到意大利刻薄习俗的约束，这些爱异想天开的少女们在为人妻为人母之后被现实惊醒，她们抛弃了自己幻想出来的幻象，学会爱那个在政治舞台的仇恨和竞争中挣扎着的真真切切的男人；她要拥护他的言论，将自己的财富和影响力都化作他野心的垫脚石；她曾经认定自己就是一支“即将凋谢的玫瑰”，而此刻她决定要改变，这一次，她想成为女主角。女性对于婚姻的鲜明兴趣必定会明显提高她们的智力水平，并督促她们付诸实践；但是与爱情相伴的产物——心痛和悔恨——也同样加深和丰富了她们的本性，她们鼓励自己要克服这些困难，并且继续活下去。我们可以想象，没有哪个明智的人想要回到17世纪的法国社会，除非他认为女性的理想人生应该是十五岁结婚，从二十岁到三十八岁接受男性的殷勤，然后在忏悔和虔诚中度过余生。话虽如此，但这种曾经存在过的社会状态也有其好的结果，就像十字军东征也有积极的影响一样。

当然，法国女性文学发展最无可争议的来源应当是沙龙的影响。全世界都知道，沙龙是一个允许女性与男性智力激荡的地方。在那里，人们谈论的话题从社会现象到笛卡尔的哲学，可谓包罗万象。黎塞留[28]在沙龙里树立了一种将文学品味与社会的文雅习惯和对野心的追求融为一体的风尚。在17世纪前期，巴黎已经出现了大大小小的旅馆，这些旅馆分散在巴黎的大街小巷，或与法院毗邻，或紧挨着贵族和资产阶级矛盾频发的地点；在当时，这种旅馆是各行各业的人交流思想、展示才华的固定场所。在众多旅馆中，洪布耶府邸是最出名的一间，它在1630年达到鼎盛，直到1648年法国兴起投石党运动[29]才逐渐没落，因为出入洪布耶府邸的常客被怀疑有政治目的而遭到迫害。这间沙龙的首席领袖是洪布耶侯爵夫人[30]，她是一个能把各种不协调元素融合在一起的典范；她美貌，却不卖弄风骚；她才华横溢，极其崇尚有才华的人，自己却从不炫耀学问；她谈吐举止精致优雅，而且待人温和，慷慨大方；她不会拿自己的作品愉悦客人，也不会用自己的广博知识让客人叹服。她曾打算学习拉丁语，后来因为一场大病停止了。在一个缺少本国文学经典的时代，或许只读意大利和西班牙作品更好，因为这些作品是不懂拉丁语的文化人最好的精神食粮。洪布耶夫人温和可人的性格正是融合了西班牙高尚的骑士精神和意大利尖刻的智慧以及精妙的讽刺，并且由此诞生了一种新的艺术风格——极端热烈的感情和极其简练的语言。女性十分适合这种风格，原因如下：首先，她们时常把爱情、感情、想象力混合在一起，并且细化成情绪；其次，她们担心简单困苦或者单调的生活会使得智力负荷过重，于是对轻松空灵的表达产生本能的偏爱，这让她们抛弃冗长啰唆的叙事方式，并且抵制各种长篇大论。在谈话交流中，独具女子气概的特征和装点着黎塞留、高乃依、康德、巴尔扎克和鲍修埃的观点相碰撞时，所产生的结果毋庸置疑是辛辣活泼并且令人着迷的。然而，来光顾洪布耶府邸的著名人士，他们的第一要务并不是和女士们闲聊调情，继而转战酒店角落里讨论自己真正感兴趣的话题，他们更愿意在聪明伶俐有修养的女士面前侃侃而谈，展现自己成熟的观点。当然，他们的谈话不仅限于文学，还包括散发着文雅和睿智的所有话题——战争、政治、宗教，以及日常生活的点滴。另外，洪布耶夫人的府邸并不光是文学者的聚集地，除了作家，还有企业家和军人。在这样一个圈子里，女性自然不会沦为卖弄学问的学者或是不切实际的说教者，她们对世界和人性并不无知，对人对事有着独特的洞察力和深刻的见解。如此，也并不难理解这样一种现象：在巴黎以及其他省份，出现了大批模仿沙龙聚会却并不成功的人，他们将简洁扭曲成矫揉造作，把高贵的情感夸张地理解成超越自然，因此这种高雅派（Précieux）遭到了大量批评和嘲讽，尤其是《可笑的女才子》（Précieuses ridicules）和《女学究》（Les Femmes savantes）[31]这两本书的出版，把该讽刺风潮推到了顶点。这两本书分别出版于1660年和1673年，书中的马德隆和卡多丝作为斯卡莉小姐的直系后裔，就像洪布耶府邸的女主人一样举办沙龙。每周六，聚集在她们沙龙上的团体都是精通文学的学者，偶尔会有几个贵族来拜访，他们满口资产阶级的典雅，醉心于各种情歌、十四行诗，咬文嚼字、玩弄尾韵；他们把装腔作势渗透进优雅的谈吐中，而这种矫揉造作是违背高雅派的初衷的。其实，看到比自己高的阶级但又不甘心屈居其下时才会产生这种可笑的东施效颦。

另外一处影响较大的女性文学出现在卢森堡宫，多奥里昂小姐因为参与了投石党活动而在宫廷里不受待见，于是她自己举办聚会，让自己沉浸在生机勃勃的精神和文学世界中。在一个明媚的早晨，这位公主又邀请来了她聚会的常客，包括塞维涅夫人、拉斐特夫人以及拉罗什福科[32]，她提议让这些朋友们来个自我描述，带头要求大家能坦白地说出自己的缺点和优点。多亏了公主的这个点子，让平常没有机会或者是不够勇敢为自己写点儿什么的作家找到了契机。

“这就是多奥里昂小姐和她的朋友们在1657年和1658年的娱乐消遣方式，”库辛先生说，“这种消遣却渐渐演变成了一种文学形式。1659年，赛格雷改进了这种自述，增加了大篇幅的散文体甚至是诗歌体描述，并集结成册，取名叫《名人群像》（Divers Portraits），并且以漂亮的四开本出版，印刷极其精美，流传至今的已经十分稀有。多奥里昂小姐当时只印刷了三十本，并不用于出售，而只是当作礼物送给她们。这一作品取得了意想不到的成功，并且满足了斯卡莉小姐窥探别人生活的私欲——她不仅很高兴看到自己的自传被写得如此完美，也满足了对别人传记的好奇。中产阶级总是十分关注并且想要了解贵族圈子都发生了些什么（在那个年代，了解他人生活的途径是很有限的），而那些平常如雷贯耳的名人们也第一次如此详尽地被描述并且全方位地展现在人们面前，这些贵妇人转瞬变成了作家，并且在不知不觉中创造了一种新的写作方式，不需要其他任何书籍的说教，而是对贵族生活最自然的讲述。这种无法给出名字的写作方式融合了自然、朴素、宜人和卓越等特色，一经面世就吸引了整个宫廷和整座小城的眼球；早在1659年，就有书商请求多奥里昂小姐出版这本书的大众版。”

这种人物描写的风潮席卷了整个法国，直到1688年拉布吕耶尔的《品格论》（Characters）出版，他在人物描写中加入了对人物性格的刻画，使之上升到了一个新的高度。现在看来，拉布吕耶尔的作品固然伟大，但仍旧是受到一个女人的启发（多奥里昂小姐的《名人群像》）才写出来的；可见，多奥里昂小姐的沙龙虽然比不上洪布耶夫人的府邸，其影响力也不容小觑。

随着一个国家的文学日渐丰富、文化逐渐分散，相应的，个人力量在创造新的文学形式以及在社会进步中的影响就会变小。不再是圈内人影响文学的发展趋势，而变成文学来影响圈内人；代表“大众”的圈子在前所未有地扩大，取得更大成就的野心在膨胀，沙龙也渐渐退出了历史舞台。曾经长篇大论的谈话都变成写作素材或“文章”，目的不是为了交流，而是保持原创性。随着老式的公路被铁路所代替，新闻界开始将传播的方式从对话转变为报刊，就算读者的范围会因此受到限制，也比“大众”这种根本不明确的抽象概念好。人们开始通过写作来表述自己的观点，而不只是靠谈话。我们（女性）开始在茶几上偷偷翻看《阿西娜神庙》（Athenaeum），在社交晚会上看《哲学日报》（Philosophical Journal）并且做笔记，我们邀请朋友，赠送给他们书籍；我们十分期盼看到“女士”表达她们自己观点的独家报道，相信有一天轻轻松松就能“挺进”《泰晤士报》（Times）。实际上，现在人们的交流方式越来越有限，这一趋势让人们开始担忧面对面的对话将越来越少，唯恐电报的进一步发展会让我们陷入一个无声的世界，或者担心会在昆虫的启示下，开始使用自己发明出来的天线进行沟通。在上个世纪，科技还远远没有达到这个程度；即便文学和社会已经超出了旧圈子的发展，即便那时有很多模仿洪布耶夫人府邸的沙龙，它们也仅仅局限于娱乐消遣，并不构成一种影响力。但毫无疑问的是，那时候的夜晚美好得令人嫉妒，如果时光能够倒流到那个时代，我们会很难抉择，到底是和达兰贝尔、德斯皮纳斯小姐、格林姆一起奔赴乔佛弘夫人的晚宴，还是去三十年后的严肃社团与孔多赛和他年轻美丽的妻子相见。沙龙仍然有它的吸引力，但是它的鼎盛时期已经一去不返：历史的河流越来越宽，越来越深，不是这条小溪所能撼动的。

17世纪和18世纪的法国女人各有千秋，不分伯仲，不过在这一问题上很容易出现不同的派别。前者大多对自己高尚的情操自视甚高，却对自己的才情少有自知之明，甚至比卢梭的噩梦——作家德毕内夫人还不自知。18世纪法国女人的观点更加丰富多彩——并非因为她们有多少独创性，而是指她们比17世纪的女性多了整整一个世纪的素材用来学习和加工。17世纪的女性，当她们的爱情逝去，她们只是温和地默默奉献，而英国女性则拿起笔杆开始写作，绝不妥协；18世纪的女性，当鲍修埃[33]和马西隆让位于伏尔泰和卢梭时，当她们的年轻和美貌都逐渐消逝时，只好将筹码放在自己的道德力量上。

库辛尤其迷恋17世纪的法国女作家。他甚至挤出自己研究哲学的宝贵时间来研读描写她们生活的原始文献。去年，库辛用一卷书的内容向我们展示了他对德·隆格维尔公爵夫人[34]青年时期的研究成果，接下来，他将继续用一卷的篇幅，通过描写公爵夫人与其好朋友萨布莱夫人的关系，来详述公爵夫人的职业生涯。他将要用到的手稿和文献主要来自两位名人：一位是来自法兰西学院的第一秘书康尔特，他是被同辈人视为奇葩却被后辈奉为珍宝的人；另外的手稿则来自瓦兰特，他曾经是一名内科医生，也是萨布莱夫人的秘书兼管家，他在萨布莱夫人晚年时，经允许私藏了大量别人写给萨布莱夫人的信件，以及萨布莱夫人回复给他们的谈论个人或者文学的信件。从这些手稿中，库辛挑选了许多之前并未经过编辑的文件。虽然他的作品经常给读者留下欲言又止、留有悬念的感觉，但是这次他写的介绍萨布莱夫人的新书却很吸引我们，即便书中的故事相当分散，而且包含很多以小号字体标注的解释附录；不过萨布莱夫人的事迹足以让我们连续看完三百多页还保持兴趣。库辛恰如其分地这样描述萨布莱夫人的性格，“（她是）一个充满幸福的混合体，理智、机敏、愉悦且善良”，而且，很少有女性像她那样对所有事物都怀有同情心；她是以整个人格而不是某一特殊品质在影响着我们；她的人格并不耀眼夺目，却像是多种颜色和谐地混合在一起，令人赏心悦目，即便是每天都能看见，也不觉得疲累，就像让眼睛得到了休息。萨布莱夫人是对法国文学有着重大影响的杰出人物之一，因此，她本来就值得被研究。如果读者跟我们想法相同，那么库辛可能会像我们一样，倾向于继续研究萨布莱夫人的生活和性格。

玛德琳·德·苏威尔的父亲古登瓦侯爵是著名的贵族，被路易十三选中为官员。玛德琳生于1599年，在17世纪中期算是一位杰出的天才。她的才华不仅体现在她的头脑，也体现在她的人生经历上。1635年，苏威尔的一位更加出名的朋友波旁小姐，即隆格维尔公爵夫人，第一次出现在洪布耶夫人的府邸，而那时的萨布莱夫人已经经历了女人年轻貌美的时期而进入熟女阶段。萨布莱夫人于1614年嫁给了博伊斯—杜芬的庄园主，萨布莱侯爵菲利普·伊曼纽尔·德·拉瓦尔—蒙莫朗西，除了他在1640年去世，人们对他一无所知，给她留下了四个孩子，同时留下的财富根本不够家用。我们有很多证据可以证明萨布莱夫人不仅有聪明的头脑，还有美丽的外貌和极高的地位，因此我们有十足的理由相信她年轻时期是非常风光的。关于她的美貌，向来严肃冷静的莫特维尔夫人都不惜言辞这样描述她：“光彩照人且真实自然，毫无矫揉造作之感”，并且在以下段落中活灵活现地展现了萨布莱夫人的性格特征：

萨布莱侯爵夫人的美貌甚至可以媲美英国的女王。但是如果她和蔼可亲，那就更好了；这位年轻女士的自恋使得她对男士的眼光十分敏感。那时在法国还保留着凯瑟琳·德·梅第奇从意大利引进的礼节，从马德里引进的新式戏剧、散文和诗歌，所有这些无一不精致且高雅，她（萨布莱夫人）对西班牙人从摩尔人处学到的殷勤十分赞赏。

别人告诉她，男人对女人展现柔情的时候从来不会犯错——为了取悦女性，男性一般都会表现出最好的一面——例如唤醒自己的才华，激发出文采，展现各种美德；但是，另一方面，女性作为世界上不可或缺的装饰品，生来就是被服侍和宠爱的，她们其实只是在乎男性对她们的尊重和关心。我们这位女士以她的智慧和美貌证明了这一点，她在她的时代塑造了权威，而关注她的人越来越多，并且延续到现在，西班牙人管这叫“微妙之处”（finezas）。

这就是最初版本的高雅派淑女的基础元素，莫特维尔夫人曾详细描绘了萨布莱夫人的一位狂热爱慕者——极其有学问的蒙莫朗西公爵。一开始，萨布莱夫人对他的殷勤也有所回应，但是当她发现（具体时间不详）蒙莫朗西公爵对女王暗送秋波之后，她就立刻和公爵分手了。莫特维尔夫人说：“我听她说，她对蒙莫朗西公爵十分高傲，自从蒙莫朗西公爵第一次表现出对她的变心之后，她就决定再也不和他见面，因为她不能忍受和最伟大的公主殿下分享他的爱慕。”塔利门特·德卢克斯的证言虽然不是百分之百可信，但仍旧能证明萨布莱夫人除此之外没有别的风流韵事，当然这一假设也有可能被轻易打破，因为萨布莱夫人有那么多特殊的友谊。和萨布莱夫人关系最好的是她早年间的朋友多娜·德阿蒂琪，然后是摩尔女伯爵，这些友谊陪伴着她度过了无忧无虑的青年时期和充满浪漫爱情的中年时期，直到她1663年离开人世。她友谊中的超验主义思想颇具特色，有个小插曲使得她所有感情都带有超验色彩，这一点值得用大量篇幅详细阐述。一次，德阿蒂琪小姐不满黎塞留对待她亲友的态度，于是怀着悲痛和忧伤离开了巴黎，准备去投奔她的好友萨布莱，而就在此时她偶然发现萨布莱夫人在给洪布耶夫人的信中说自己最大的幸福就是和洪布耶一起相处，其次是和蒙托西耶。她这才意识到，原来她在萨布莱夫人心中并不是最好的朋友，这对于德阿蒂琪来说简直就是塞纳河友谊（lèse-amitié）之罪，再多的解释都不能安抚她。萨布莱的那些文字对她来说是一种冒犯，她不能接受，甚至不能自欺欺人说这种沙龙式语言只不过是萨布莱一时的“胡言乱语”而已。德阿蒂琪放弃了这次行程，并且给萨布莱写了封信。当萨布莱夫人决定销毁自己年轻时期的文献时，唯一选择保留了德阿蒂琪的这一封信，信的内容如下：

“虽然你说那封信都是胡言乱语，但我还是看了信的内容，而且并不觉得你在胡言乱语。相反，你的表达再清晰不过了，你想对洪布耶夫人说的话一清二楚，你说，‘如果我自己想要一段完美且幸福的生活，那么我只想和你洪布耶在一起’。你知道，我是最能信服她才华的人，但是这次，我不得不说你为了讨好她深深地伤害了我们俩之间的友谊。姑且相信你只是为了给她一个令人愉快的赞美，所以才那样写；我不敢相信你的殷勤会背叛你真实的内心，尤其是在这件事情上；我想你更应该掩藏你对洪布耶夫人的这些感情，因为我对你的感情众所周知，尤其是洪布耶。所以我怀疑你如此给她写信，她看到的可能并不是你有多么迷恋她，而是你如何地伤害了我。你的那封信阴差阳错地被我看见，真是应了贝尔托的这句话：

‘无知是一件不幸的事情，

而更加不幸的则是无知还被人知道。’

因为那封信，我对自己的生活支柱丧失了信任，我根本不用再考虑去投奔你。我觉得自己在这样的季节颠簸六十多英里来找你实在是太不合时宜了，因为我是那么地不配你，这么多年来我的真情没有得到你应有的回应，你此生最大的快乐竟然是不要和我在一起。所以我独自一人离开了，我要好好反省，并且消化那些给我带来如此多不愉快的缺点，如若我还没有改正好这些缺点，我见到你只会更困惑，而不会高兴。”

能和如此多愁善感的德阿蒂琪小姐成为朋友，足以证明萨布莱夫人的魅力所在。不过，萨布莱夫人还有很多热情的朋友，例如隆格维尔夫人等等。当然，她有时也会怀疑别人对她的情感，所以只会被动地等待感情的积累，而不会去积极经营。我们能从隆格维尔夫人的言论中找到很多蛛丝马迹，萨布莱夫人一会儿和朋友们隔离，一会儿又在纠结自己的信写得是否完美。下面引用一段能够反映出萨布莱夫人矛盾特质的文字，爱人或朋友都能从中获取些实用经验：

“如果我关心你、在乎你，那么我非常害怕自己知道什么时候能见到你之后，将很长时间不再有那种相见时的快乐，那种快乐是你我做什么都买不到的，因为我发现，每次我们的友谊出现问题，在你没有彻底恢复之时，我的解释只会徒增烦恼，所以我害怕解释。就算解释本身是好的，是出于给人们带来安慰，是为了缓和气氛，但遗憾的是，不得不承认，解释的起因都是不好的，而且若是解释得不合时宜，有时会让两人更加生气，让双方的交流更加不畅。我是从你的举止行为了解这些道理的，所以我觉得，我应该写信问你，今天是否想跟我和好。”

圣佩韦[35]曾描述内克尔夫人有一个缺点，那就是太完美了，显然，萨布莱夫人远远没有这一缺陷，我们能够看到她外表及内心的优美之处恰好是她的不完美，她有对缺点的感知力。隆格维尔夫人在信中谈到这一点，让我们见识了萨布莱在四十不惑的年龄时魅力依旧，她这样写道：“我确信，你是我在这世界上最想要见到的人，我们之间的沟通那样真实可靠，没有人可以替代你。岁月变迁，时光流逝，我对你的喜欢依旧没变；我要感谢上帝赐予我的欢乐，虽然他让我很多的朋友都流失了，但我还是会全心全意地感谢上帝让你一直在我身边。”

既然我们谈到了萨布莱夫人的缺点，那就不得不听听她的朋友们对她的评价——她极端关注自己的健康，特别害怕传染病，甚至怕那种并不会传染的病。或许她的这种忧虑不仅是身体上的，也是美学上的；她对疾病深恶痛绝，不愿让自己的身心受到折磨。她觉得若是感染风寒抑或是肠胃绞痛，那么必定会影响她谈论文艺，势必会影响到她成为“世间的装饰品”，并且不再“受人爱戴”。即便是坚固的友谊也没能让她克服对传染病的恐惧。当波旁小姐成为隆格维尔公爵夫人后染上了天花，洪布耶夫人常常去照看她，萨布莱夫人不仅不敢去探望病人，而且连洪布耶也不敢见了。洪布耶知道这件事后给她写了封信，那个年代的才女们对于处理类似的情况十分熟练，信中都是饱含技术含量的揶揄调侃，我们在此略引用一段：

洪布耶小姐致萨布莱侯爵夫人

要是让沙莱小姐（萨布莱夫人的女性伴侣）来朗读这封信，她一定感同身受。

夫人：

我认为最近来见你是不太可能的事，因为我听说你在见我之前和之后，要花很长的时间斟酌，还要咨询很多医生，需要克服极大的心理恐惧，这些时间足够我出去散散步了。所以，我会选择在离开康德旅馆（隆格维尔公爵夫人生病下榻的地方）三天之后再来拜访你，而且会选择寒冷的一天，我保证会与你隔一个座位坐，并且保持至少四步的距离。你可以在你的卧室里生火取暖，在房间四角燃放杜松，在你身边摆放芸香和苦艾，并且用皇室的熏醋消毒，只要你不要让我剪掉我的头发。如果上述这些条件让你觉得有安全感，我发誓我会立即去执行；如果你对这些条件还有所顾虑，那么我告诉你吧，肖德伯尼先生在探访过德·波旁夫人之后，女王还同意接见他呢；德艾吉永夫人在传染病这些问题上也很讲究，但是她并没有因为我而对此心怀顾虑，她甚至放话，如果我不去见她，她就会主动来找我。

萨布莱夫人面对这样的揶揄显然有些退缩，这在她的回复中有所体现；基于隆格维尔夫人已经康复的事实，她起草了一份十分严肃但礼貌的回复，并且激起了她克服恐惧心理去拜访隆格维尔的勇气。洪布耶夫人后来通过她俩的共同朋友伏尔蒂得知，她的讽刺力度过猛以致于自找麻烦，还得绞尽脑汁给萨布莱一个极具安抚性却又彰显自己尊严的道歉。萨布莱夫人害怕疾病的这种怪癖随着年龄的增长而愈发强烈，因此在十五年之后，我们看到德奥里昂夫人在她的《帕夫拉戈尼亚公主》（Princesse de Paphlagonia）中描绘了如下有趣的场面——该书描写了发生在宫殿中的喧嚣的爱情故事——或者在一定程度上说是一出讽刺剧，讽刺了萨布莱夫人严重的恐病症以及同样具有这个怪癖的她的朋友摩尔伯爵夫人（也就是影射德阿蒂琪小姐）。在这本书中，萨布莱和德阿蒂琪分别化身帕尔泰尼公主和蕾娜·德·米奥尼，出现在读者面前。

“一天中的每时每刻她俩都在一起讨论如何避免死亡、如何长生不老这件事。她们谈话的地点不同于常人，她们总是担心所呼吸的空气太冷或者太热，担心风太干燥或是太湿润——总之，她们总是夸大天气的因素，认为那不利于自己保持健康，于是便待在各自房间里飞信传书。如果这些手稿有幸能被找到，那么都足够出版成一本文集了。我得知她们会为如何养生制定规则，并且适时地服用些预防药剂，但是，这些药剂是用希波克拉底[36]和伽林都没听过的医术炼制而成的。这本文集若要问世，定会惠及大众，给巴黎和蒙彼利埃的相关医疗机构带来暴利；若这些信件曝光，将会因此产生很多优势，因为即便是公主殿下也知道没有什么是永垂不朽的，她们知道自己终有一死。读她们的书信，我们能感受到严谨文雅的风格，以及谈论各种话题时显露出来的优雅气质。她们用各种技巧从自己的伙伴那里了解世界各国发生的事情，几乎无所不知；她们在谈论勇气或者其他事情时，总能给出重要的意见；她们有时还帮忙调停争执和纠纷，有时给朋友们带来惊喜，她们的朋友们总能因她们而获益——总之，她们是那种知道世界上所有秘密的人。帕尔泰尼公主（也就是萨布莱夫人的化身）的味觉如同她的思想般敏锐，她的手艺很少有人能够匹敌，她的每道菜都精致美味；另外，她的洁癖也达到了超乎想象的程度。在她们那个年代，人们才开始写作，在那之前，除了结婚契约是手写的外，书信这种东西连听也没听说过；所以我们真应该感谢她们推动了人类书信交流的进程。”

之后，在1669年，最顽固的波尔罗亚尔信徒[37]开始低调地向萨布莱夫人征税，原因是萨布莱夫人没有在香榭丽舍的波尔罗亚尔女修道院加入他们。我们看到萨布莱夫人给德·赛维尼先生这样写道：“除了放手离开，我没有其他更好的选择了。没有可以为我治疗的医生和医疗技术，这让我非常害怕。”

另外，我们可以看到，萨布莱夫人还十分热爱美食，这也是朋友们对她众多缺点中诟病最多的一个，尤其是当她结束了自己的宗教事业之后。她做甜点十分有一套，知道如何将甜品做得既精致又美味。她神经质的特征还表现在其他方面：她经常给朋友送可口的食物，并且和他们谈论餐桌文化，交流自己的心得和品味。隆格维尔夫人完全没有像萨布莱夫人那样的奢华味觉，她这样写道：“连上帝都知道，你做出来的东西完全没有什么滋味，更谈不上丰盛了。上帝呀，难道就没有什么可以吃的了吗，你知道的，这些都不合我胃口，这让我真的很不安。”但其他朋友则很感激萨布莱的好意。伏尔蒂感谢她送的甜瓜，并且赞扬它们比自己以前吃过的都好；乔伊喜夫人则希望约翰逊主义[38]的思想不要成为萨布莱继续给自己送沙拉的阻碍；拉·罗什富科写信给她：“如果你能给送信人尝尝你的橘子酱和美味的蜜饯那就太好了，我真心乞求你能给他这个机会。如果我能尝到你的两道新菜，我的一生都将感激涕零。”对于我们来说，那些崇尚精神生活的人喜欢将一种缺点转变成一种原则，并且对自己迟钝的味觉引以为荣，我们尽可能要和他们保持亲善，并且不把萨布莱夫人的甜点看作是一种缺点。库辛曾经这样说以表达歉意：

“人们对美味佳肴的过度迷恋以及对故作高雅的些许崇拜还比较容易理解。萨布莱夫人不可能像常人一样吃饭，因为对于高雅的淑女来说那是多么独树一帜的事。我们从莫特维尔夫人那里节选了一段有关萨布莱夫人年轻时在洪布耶夫人府邸的文字，她那时还是主张女性生来就是世界的装饰品，理应得到男性的爱慕和敬仰的。而值得爱慕的那些女性常常不在意物质追求，甚至在最质朴和原始的生活方式中依然坚持着卓越和纯粹的精神世界。民以食为天，但总是被忽略。萨布莱夫人依旧在饮食上坚持着她的洁癖。据她说，并不是每个女人都能在吃饭时泰然自若地面对自己的爱侣，仅仅是吃东西时的面部表情，就足以毁掉所有浪漫的气氛。大鱼大肉这种饭菜还是留给资本家去享受吧，讲究的女人们只用吃一点营养品维持体力就行，她们甚至还很享受吃少许点心、饮料里加冰块的饮食方式。财富并不能满足她们的生活，她们需要的是独特的才智和习惯。萨布莱夫人正是深谙这门艺术的女能人，她成功地将贵族气质、尊贵高雅、文学修养和美味都融入了自己的烹饪技术中。她的晚餐虽不奢华，却被众人追捧并且模仿。”

据此，我们认为萨布莱夫人十分享受味觉的满足，事实上也的确如此。她在波尔罗亚尔修道院的时候，已经年迈到丧失了敏锐味觉的程度，于是她写信给梅尔·艾格尼丝寻求安慰。艾格尼丝在早年就丧失了味觉，她用一种十分神圣和坚定的口吻回复了萨布莱：“我亲爱的姐妹，你已经尝遍美食，如果你把这种损失当作是向上帝的赎罪，那么损失也未尝不是一种收获。”斯卡龙[39]这样描述她：

“与木头或海豚不同，

女士们对自己的要求总是很多。”

这些语句似乎在说，萨布莱做的珍馐美味不仅源自她的个人习惯，还源自她的情感和智慧。

我们知道，一直以来，萨布莱夫人的生活都相当平静，直到1640年她的丈夫过世，留给她一笔财产需要打理。后来，她在勒内—德隆格伊找到了一位朋友，即麦松庄园主热内·德·隆盖帮助自己管理财务。而这位朋友却偷偷地出售她家的房地产，这导致后来1649年巴黎大封锁时，萨布莱不得不住到麦松家。其实，她对麦松的行为早就不满，在和他对簿公堂时，她凭借自己的信誉最终赢得了皇室的审判。除去这些金钱的纷争，最令萨布莱夫人痛心的是她失去了自己最疼爱的儿子——勇敢并且英俊的盖·德拉瓦尔。德拉瓦尔在孔代的竞选时表现突出，但在1646年的敦刻尔克围剿中被杀害，年仅二十四岁。他的人格魅力让他在军中赢得了很多赞誉，尤其是孔代亲王十分重用他，并且给他介绍了瑟桂尔大臣的女儿认识，为他开启了美好的未来。德拉瓦尔的离世可以算是萨布莱夫人生命当中最痛心疾首的事件。接踵而至的则是法国投石党暴乱，导致社会动乱，众叛亲离。一直倚仗古维尔权威的勒内特说，萨布莱夫人因为接受了两千克朗[40]的抚恤金，因此对皇室仍肩负着极大的义务；无论如何，她都始终坚持忠于女王和马萨林，尽可能和其他激烈的党派保持距离；她同时听从两方的部署和裁决，并且维系着两个阵营的朋友，扮演着调停者的角色。德摩尔伯爵虽然是最为顽固的投石党派，但德摩尔伯爵夫人和萨布莱却是一生相惜的朋友；另外，萨布莱夫人与投石党派中可爱且勇敢的女英雄隆格维尔夫人也保持着长久的书信联络。她通过让蒙特鸠家族和投石党的贾布列家族联姻而消减双方的仇恨，她极力撮合孔代亲王以及他的兄弟和马萨林的侄女联姻，并且让马萨林的三个侄女和投石党三位杰出贵族领袖联姻。虽然她的计划没有全部实现，但是她的中间人地位却让她保全了自己的友谊。当这场政治风暴完结之后，萨布莱夫人还是能在她的府邸、在波尔罗亚尔修道院像以前一样集结自己的朋友圈。虽然这时的萨布莱已经步入六十岁，但是她的思想和人格魅力却让她的追随者数量丝毫不逊色于年轻女性，正如她当时所宣扬的宗教理念那样，社会上对“拯救”的关注度变得紧迫起来，这一点都不令人惊讶。她虽然退休不研习宗教了，这意味着她的年龄见长、薪水变少，但是她的个人生活依旧很舒适，并没有影响到她继续接待文人墨客。约翰逊主义开始在当时的天主教中流行，就像皮由兹运动在当今的英格兰本土宗教中流行一样——那是一种极其讲究形式和内容的信仰模式，普通老百姓不信那个，明眼人一看便知道这必定受到附庸风雅的高雅派的追捧。萨布莱夫人退休后去了波尔罗亚尔女修道院，并不是因为她已经相信约翰逊主义，而是想要去了解；她想和来自世界各地的朋友们交谈，她享受这种乐趣，于是她为自己在修道院旁边盖了一套公寓。这里的一切都令人舒心，公寓里住着她的管家兼秘书瓦兰特医生、她之前的女性伴侣以及现在的好友沙莱小姐、一位出色的厨师、几位随从，大部分时间里还有一辆四轮马车和一位车夫。正如库辛所写，萨布莱夫人平常和几位好友不用离家太远，就能远离尘世喧嚣，一方面保鲜着自己的友谊，一方面享受眼前的美好风景——“自由自在地忙于她的永福和健康”。

至此，我们只是单一地了解了萨布莱夫人在文学方面的特征和影响。但她远远不止我们了解的这样：她是贵族女性和杰出男性们值得信赖的珍贵朋友，她是法国社会中令人鼓舞的精神领袖，一种新的文学形式因她而产生；她不仅才华横溢，而且胸怀宽广，连帕斯卡[41]也愿意取悦她，阿尔诺在《论逻辑》（Logic）的前言中感谢她的意见，而对拉罗什福科说：“您知道我认为您对一些章节是不确信的，尤其是这些内心深处的。”瓦兰特秘书所收藏的那些手稿则说明了萨布莱夫人和大量不同阶层形形色色的人都保持着书信联络，萨布莱为了和他们联系一直笔耕不辍。男人把她当作寄托思想的港湾，女人则把她看作倾诉痛苦的知音；一旦她销声匿迹几天，她的朋友们一定会抓狂，就像是在追求心上人时那样心急如焚。隆格维尔夫人在她的耳边诉说自己的烦心事以及遭遇的困难，拉斐特夫人则向她倾诉自己的担忧，她生怕年轻的德圣保罗伯爵发现自己和拉罗什福科之间的亲密关系。[42]少数幸存下来的萨布莱夫人的书信显示了她极其擅长的洪布耶式书信体，其中一封是应帕斯卡的姐夫斐瑞尔先生所托，写给蒙托西耶夫人的，这封信展示了她独特的品味和才华。但是我们更愿意引用她的另一封信，是写给拉特里穆耶公爵夫人的，这封信风格活泼轻快，含义深远，却又不像肥皂泡般一戳就破：

“我认为只有我自己可以面对跟自己如此对立的事，因为尽管您可能会不相信，但您确实是我最尊敬的人了。我深知这并不足以说服您，我不配拥有您的体谅和问候，我已经拖延了太长时间没有给您回信了，而且还必须要再等上十五天才能给您回信表示敬意。事实上，女士，我除此之外对于其他的事都更负有责任。我确实特别喜欢做这样一个人：着手干一件非常艰难但可以证明自我的事。但是，从骨子里，我又觉得自己是如此地无辜，就好像您在千里之外能够感觉到我是如此地尊敬您、崇拜您、爱您一样似的，尽管我没有对您说过一句这样的话。这就给了我直到那时才给您回信的勇气，但是这不会妨碍我很长时间了。我开始被迫食言，犯了很多错误，我为我所做的事感到羞耻，我向您承诺，到了那个时间，如果我还没有得到使我安心的信任——这种从我对您的特殊的爱里提炼出来的品质的话，我就再也不敢让您记起我来了。但是我确信您会忘了这所有的一切，因为我保证：我不会再对我的错误无动于衷了，而且这个保证是永远不可违反的。女士，您真挚的……”

写这封信的女主人将从容惬意和优雅得当结合得恰到好处，她的智慧让人们愿意跟她讨论理性和哲学问题，她的感情真挚动人，她时刻不忘关心他人，作为一个大作家却毫无野心，对做果酱和蔬菜炖肉情有独钟，这样一个人难道不是汇集了各种特质的奇异混合体吗？难怪，她在波尔罗亚尔女隐修院的沙龙是拉菲耶特夫人、蒙托西耶夫人、隆格维尔夫人、奥特福尔夫人以及帕斯卡、拉罗什福科、尼克尔、多玛等人最乐意去拜访的场所。瓦兰特的手稿收藏还展示了他们在沙龙中最常谈起的话题。神学当然是最主要的议题，其次是谈论很广泛的道德问题，有时会讨论到物理和玄学。瓦兰特还保留了一张“论加尔文主义”的会议摘要手稿。当罗奥在帕斯卡的气压试验启发下发明了玻璃管时，索迪斯侯爵随即在纸上写了一篇《水为什么能在玻璃管中上升》的文章向大众普及知识。那时，笛卡尔哲学也是令人兴奋的谈论主题，甚至整个法国都在谈论笛卡尔，有人为其摇旗呐喊，也有人反对质疑，随便拿起一份报纸，上面写的都是《论笛卡尔的思想》。这些高深的主义在不同的讨论中时刻被提及，例如在谈论爱情、友谊、戏剧，以及天地之间所有令人做白日梦的哲学问题时。另外，道德作为对人类感情、情绪，以及行为的概括，也是他们十分钟爱的谈资；探讨的目的是为了锻炼口才，将这些话题缩减为简练的警句模式以便记忆，这就是萨布莱夫人沙龙圈子的特点，当然也是受到沙龙主人的影响。正如洪布耶府邸孕育出了优美的书信体，卢森堡宫廷诞生了“肖像体”和“品格论”，萨布莱夫人的沙龙则培养出了格言体，最出色的当数帕斯卡的《思想录》（Pensées），以及拉罗什福科的《箴言集》（Maximes）。萨布莱夫人自己也在朋友圈子里写些格言，在她去世之后，艾比·德艾丽将这些格言结集出版。我们可以从中感受到萨布莱夫人的丰富情感和高贵情操，但她的格言因缺乏个性而谈不上是天才之作；比起拉罗什福科的《箴言集》，萨布莱夫人的格言用词较为乏味，就像是用粘土制作的花瓶，而拉罗什福科的格言却像是被火焰烧制过的花瓶，晶莹透亮。她写过一篇有关教育的杂文，虽然都是些简短的格言，却得到了拉罗什福科和德艾丽的赞扬，可惜原文早已遗失，或许是因为论教育没有像《论友谊》那样写得精致而用心。显然，萨布莱夫人的长处并不在于自己写作，而在于激发他人写作，她对别人的赞同和欣赏就像早晨的阳光般令人舒适且振奋。她用理解的方式鼓励着他人展现才华，这是女性对文化进步能作出的最好贡献了；另外，独创性的缺失反而让她被更多具有创造力的人所接受。

帕斯卡的《思想录》手稿显示，这不是一部仅仅为宗教作品提供原材料的普通书籍，帕斯卡一遍遍地修改和雕琢它，目的是想达到最大限度的简练和完美，而并非只让别的更伟大的作品去援引它。如果思想只是被当作搜罗来的材料，那就像是盖房子时堆放的石头那样，就不会经过打磨而变成紫水晶或者绿宝石。帕斯卡和他的姐姐斐瑞尔夫人（萨布莱夫人最亲密的朋友之一）是第一批在波尔罗亚尔女隐修院拜访萨布莱夫人沙龙的客人，我们可以想象他们必定需要在大大小小的格言圈里先展示一下自己打磨的珠宝（作品），就像交登记费一样先亮个相。他们出口就是经典的格言，为的就是吸引活力四射、博学多才的女性，他们仿佛是哲圣拉罗什福科附身，甚至达到了一个新的级别。但不可否认的是，萨布莱夫人对帕斯卡的《思想录》起了极大的催化作用，如果没有她，拉罗什福科也写不出《箴言集》。就像在其他沙龙圈子里，有些致力于创造最棒的双关语，有些则致力于创造出最好的字谜，萨布莱夫人的波尔罗亚尔沙龙的消遣方式则是打造最出色的箴言。拉罗什福科说：“树立行为准则的愿望像感冒一样传播着。”但是，他非但没有宣称自己开创了这种写作方式，还指出是雅克·埃斯普利特——另一位萨布莱夫人沙龙的常客——激起了自己写箴言的兴致。埃斯普利特是一位学者，他之前经常出入洪布耶府邸，已经出版了一本名为《韵文箴言集》（Maximes en vers）的书，之后又创作了一本《虚假的人类美德》（La Fausseté des vertus humaines），数落了单调的拉罗什福科主义以及变质的加尔文主义[43]。虽然如此，拉罗什福科还是赞扬了埃斯普利特，请求他给自己评价，邀请他一起创作箴言，并且听从他的意见将作品交给萨布莱夫人征求意见。他还曾将自己写的一些箴言单独给萨布莱，想让她用一种食物来比喻自己的作品：“这是我写的格言，你觉得是像胡萝卜汤还是像炖羊肉呢？”拉罗什福科和埃斯普利特的品味才华互相辉映，但是直到最后，拉罗什福科才意识到自己在格言圈子的杰出性，并且发现自己拥有更加广泛的读者，由此才诞生了家喻户晓、毋庸赘言的《箴言集》。现在，几乎每个人都深信，《箴言集》在形式上十分完美，在内容上包含了毋庸置疑的真实性，却又不全都正确；真实是在于它的内容刚好和社会上依旧流行的人的自私本性相契合，不完全正确则在于它把自私片面当作人性所有的可能性，以偏概全。我们认为拉罗什福科在人性的广泛性上有所摇摆，这种摇摆体现在某些箴言内容上，且时不时地提醒着他，在美德之下还存在着相对应的一面，但是他从未抓住过那一面——这一点甚至从未在他的意识中出现过。

拉罗什福科对以作家的身份出现在公众面前这件事十分担忧和紧张，这尤其令人惊奇。在书稿付梓之时，他还偷偷潜入印刷厂，征询读后感来试探读者的回馈。据萨布莱夫人说，他还将多份手稿送给品味不等、才华各异的男男女女，征求他们的意见和评论，很多收到的回复至今还保存完整。大多数女性读者对箴言不感冒，但是男性则十分赞许。因为这些男性读者大多是神职人员，他们的职责就是拷问人的本性并且启迪思想，渴望达到一种高尚且神圣的思想境界。当时奥古斯丁主义[44]和加尔文主义正主导着宗教思想，其人性堕落的教义和箴言所表现出的愤世嫉俗正好在拉罗什福科的一些观点里找到共鸣，并且以一种辛辣的方式体现，因此得到不少赞许。有个作家写到：“为了使人们信仰上帝，相信他的思想和意愿，我说不出一句比教理者的箴言更准确的话。当圣灵和福音书存在于世界时，我将成为基督教徒，一方面可以教我认识自己的不幸，另一方面则教我恳求救星的到来。”在拉罗什福科的书出版之后，曼特农夫人更赞扬说《箴言集》和《约伯记》（Book of Job）是她唯一愿意读的书。

萨布莱夫人对于拉罗什福科的为人和他的《箴言集》都抱着一种宽容且公正的态度，这种态度一方面体现在他俩一致的写作风格上，他们的箴言都饱含了对美好人性的信心，虽然她的箴言比拉罗什福科的略逊一筹；另一方面还体现在她回复绍姆贝格夫人的批评之中。萨布莱夫人这样说：“作者是通过反省自己的懒散而写出的那些箴言，他有别人无可比拟的闲暇时间来反省，我认为他的内心和他的意志一样闲散懒惰。他从来没有为别人做些什么，在他伟大的欲望和期盼中，我甚至觉得他对自己也是放任不管的。”但是，她对《箴言集》还是非常感兴趣的，在一定程度上她的养女对作者也十分推崇，却并不苛求从作者那里获得任何回报。另外，值得一提的是她的养女深得爱尔维修[45]信徒的喜爱。我们可以看到，萨布莱夫人给了拉罗什福科全方位的支持，不仅为《箴言集》提供批评建议，还提出改进办法，当该书最终出版后，她还为当时唯一的报纸《学者报》（Journal des savants）写了推荐公告。这份公告本来是对作品特点的概述，汇集了对作品支持或反对的两方观点，萨布莱夫人最后用温和的语气赞扬了该作品的机智、才华，以及对人性的深刻洞察力。但是当她把这份公告交给拉罗什福科时，拉罗什福科却并不接受里面的负面意见，且执意让她修改。但是，萨布莱夫人固执地不愿意做任何改动，并且把公告退还给拉罗什福科，还附上了以下便条：

“我给您寄的这篇公告是我精心写出来要发表在《学者报》上的，我选取了您最容易感知的章节，是要让您克服羞愧，使您觉得前言没有什么可以删改的；我不担心选取这一章节，因为我确信您会出版的，尽管您非常喜欢余下的内容。我也向您保证，如果您想按照您自己的意愿对此公告进行修改，我还不如把它烧了，那样我会更加感激您的。像我们这样拥有丰富作品的作者，一点也不害怕失去一篇文章，请来信告诉我您对此有什么看法。”

拉罗什福科利用这份授权，自己“编辑”了萨布莱夫人的公告，他将用词打磨润色，还删掉了其中对作品的反面意见。《学者报》最终刊登了修改后的公告，我们可以看到，当时新闻界的年轻人还是很有远见的。

萨布莱夫人就这样扮演着拉罗什福科的文学知音，同时也是法国“纯文学”（belles lettres）的灵魂人物，引起了社会的极大关注，另外，她同样活跃在雕塑领域。萨布莱夫人仍然同波尔罗亚尔女隐修院的女性们保持着连续不断的交谈或是书信交流，附近的加尔默罗会[46]女修道院的女性们也常常找她攀谈，她们很多都曾是受到追捧和尊敬的“人世间的装饰品”。有证据证明萨布莱夫人也意识到自己得到她们的敬重。当加尔默罗会女隐修院的玛丽·玛德琳公主重病不能亲自拜访萨布莱夫人时，萨布莱夫人派人在她的病房挂了一幅自己年轻时的画像，同时收到了梅尔·艾格尼丝的俏皮留言。没错，我们在上文引用过这位艾格尼丝的警世恒言，这次她的留言描写了这幅画像如何在“我们梅尔女佣”的医院里发挥了它的作用。此外，萨布莱夫人还对圣经《新约》的翻译有浓厚的兴趣。《新约》的翻译是沙西、阿尔诺、尼科尔、勒梅特以及吕纳公爵的共同作品，沙西是主要译者。前文我们提到阿尔诺向萨布莱夫人征求自己《论逻辑》一书前言的意见，由此可见，阿尔诺在其他很多事情上也得到过她的宝贵建议。此外，对波尔罗亚尔信徒的迫害开始时，萨布莱夫人联合隆格维尔夫人一同援助和保护她虔诚的朋友们。鉴于她对约翰逊主义的中庸态度，就像她对其他任何事物的态度一样，不会走极端，萨布莱夫人进行了一次十分著名的谴责奥古斯丁主义的演说，她指出奥古斯丁的教义最初都源自约翰逊；像往常一样，她相信可以通过非暴力的调解方式解决问题，当然她的中庸并不代表没有行动。她曾一度因受到威胁而想离开波尔罗亚尔女隐修院，也曾想过退休，搬到巴黎附近的小村庄奥特伊，住进当地的宗教家庭。事实上，她的确在那里度过了几个夏天。偶尔，她也在自己的兄弟索夫勒司令家避难，或者在蒙托西耶夫人或隆格维尔夫人家。在这些人中，隆格维尔夫人最为勇敢，而且她丰厚的财富以及崇高的地位能给予波尔罗亚尔信徒更加高效的帮助。阿尔诺和尼科尔在隆格维尔夫人的府邸住了五年，正是在她的保全之下才完成了《新约》的翻译；而且，正是因为隆格维尔夫人的不懈努力，在1669年，对波尔罗亚尔隐修院的迫害最终被解除。同样，萨布莱夫人也在竭尽自己的人脉和机智帮助他们，当然，就像她在其他事件里发挥的作用那样，她的价值只是起到联络和催化的作用，激发他人做某事，而不是自己亲力亲为。正是因为她，隆格维尔夫人才得以在波尔罗亚尔事件中获得胜利，而且我们会发现，虽然萨布莱相对来说更加羞怯内向，内心却真挚诚恳，富有真知灼见，勇敢热心的隆格维尔夫人也不时地向她寻求意见和建议。

1669年，当萨布莱夫人最终不再担心受迫害时，她已经七十岁高龄了，而且我们知道，她在接下来的九年里专注于自己的精神修炼。在她风风火火的年轻时代，她对死亡是恐惧的，而现在这种循序渐进、平静沉着的衰老方式抚平了她对死亡的恐惧，最终，她在平静和信任中离开了人世。在她生命的最终时刻，她不希望人们把她和家人葬在一起，甚至不愿意和自己神圣且高尚的同伴们葬在波尔罗亚尔女隐修院——她选择了自己教区的公墓，就像普通人一样被埋在那里，没有浮华的墓碑，也没有盛大的告别仪式，这是一种多么高尚的美德啊。

有一点值得我们注意，在那个封建制度逐渐解体的时代，萨布莱夫人和其他卓越非凡的法国女性一样，她生活中最为人感兴趣并且成果最丰硕的时候是女性同胞们满怀忧伤地期待着她。当萨布莱夫人五六十岁的时候，她仍被各路哲学家、智者、美人、思想才俊所包围，当然，大家最想知道的是她持久保持这份吸引力的法宝。我们认为她经久不衰的吸引力很大程度上来自于她卓越的智商和情商；她聪慧的智力带给自己深刻的感悟能力，而她宽容的性格则让她能够接纳各种性格迥异的人，这对于当时的女性来说是一件很难得的事。下面我们来谈谈她和隆格维尔夫人的一点区别，以下引用的是圣佩韦发掘出来的由艾比·圣·皮埃尔执笔的有趣段子，放心，我们并没有跑题，这些文字完美地从侧面凸显了我们萨布莱夫人伟大的人格魅力。

“有一天，我让尼科尔先生给我讲讲隆格维尔夫人的智力特点。他说，隆格维尔夫人的洞察力非常敏锐且精细，但是她对科学和推理的理解则十分有限，甚至对于所有不涉及感情的事务都力不从心。他举了一个例子，有一次，他跟夫人打赌说他能证明在巴黎至少有两个人的头发数目是一模一样的，虽然不可能具体指出是哪两个人。但是隆格维尔夫人坚决不同意，她认为除非真正数清了头发的数目，否则是不能够证明的。但是尼科尔已经开始证明了：‘我假定一颗头上最多有二十万根头发，而最少的也得有一根；那么，如果你假设二十万个人的头发数量都不一样，但是每个人的头发数量都在一到二十万根之间，若是这二十万个数字中刚好有两个是相等的，那么我的打赌就赢了。继续假设，这二十万人的头发数量都不相同，但是现在又多了一个人，他的头发数量也不超过二十万根，那么他的头发数量一定在一到二十万根之间，于是就必定和之前的二十万人中的一个人拥有相同的头发数了。现实是，别说比二十万人多了，巴黎的居民都快超过八十万人了，显而易见，他们之中一定至少有两人的头发数量是相等的，而我根本不用去数头发的数量。’隆格维尔夫人始终不能理解这种证明方式，她还是相信唯一的证明是亲自去数清楚。”

当然，大多数对女性文学感兴趣的热情爱慕者都会被隆格维尔夫人这种死脑筋所激怒，转而去崇拜更加智慧的萨布莱夫人。论优雅、精致和女性气质，萨布莱夫人并不逊于隆格维尔夫人，况且，萨布莱夫人还有层次清晰的推理能力，并且对科学感兴趣，这种感性与理性的结合让她拥有了独具一格的魅力：她不是天才，也不是女英雄，男性对她远不止爱——她是他们的挚友、知音和顾问，她不仅能为他们分担欢乐和痛苦，还懂得他们的思想和抱负。

这就是萨布莱夫人，因为她在文学和历史中总是那么谦逊和低调，所以对于很多读者来说她的名字还比较陌生。我们也看到，萨布莱夫人可以算是众多女性作家的苍穹中熠熠生辉的一颗，当历史传记的望远镜对准这一领域时，她的人生经历和人格魅力丝毫不逊色于其他星星。现在，如果读者好好回想一下萨布莱夫人同时期的英国，即在詹姆斯一世和两位查尔斯统治时期，英国上流社会中女性的地位和平均智力水平，那么我们不得不承认，英国女性的地位只能达到法国早期的女性水平，这一事实以及它的原因不仅仅是一个历史问题：直到现在，它仍旧极大地影响着当代英国的女性文学。女性在法国拥有崇高地位，是因为她们被公平对待，她们被认为和男性一样有着相同的思想和目标，这就是法国女性文学得以繁荣发展以及社会和谐的真正根源所在。我们并不奢望女士们都能在女性学术座谈会上滔滔不绝地谈论阿波罗和战神；但是我们却希望学校的机构或学术集会能做出实际行动，将更多的妇女从织布绣花和打扫房间中解救出来。我们希望所有领域的大门都向妇女敞开，我们希望女性特有的细腻情感能填补人类生命中真善美的缺失，而不是像现在的社会这样充满性别歧视和不和谐；只有这种思想的交汇，才会迸发出足够精彩的思想色彩，才能描绘出希望之虹，才能让人类收获真正的幸福。

评杰拉尔丁·朱伊斯伯里的《康斯坦斯·赫伯特》

本季度的英国小说中，除了查尔斯·金斯利[47]的《向西去！》（Westward Ho！）能吸引人眼球之外，就数《康斯坦斯·赫伯特》（Constance Herbert）这本书还比较有趣了。朱伊斯伯里小姐自己创立的那套评论体系，恐怕只会招来更多的批评。我们若是用她自己的标准来衡量她的小说，只能给个差评；但若是以女性作家的一般水平来衡量，这倒是一篇十分优秀的小说。在这篇小说中我们理所当然地见到了作者在《两姐妹》（Half Sisters）中塑造的美丽淑女形象，让我们忽略了她新创造出来的其他角色；这对于她来说并不公平，如果我们仅仅把眼光放在她作品的不足上，而忽略令我们满意的地方，对于自我要求极高甚至是苛刻的她来说，这更像是一种称赞。这本书叙事简单却让人读着很愉悦，它用一种安详且低调的方式讲述了一些高尚的情感，描写人物的性格和优点时又呈现出难得的真实和坦率，这种沉稳风格给人的感觉是，书的内容均来自深深的信念和历练之泉，而不是人云亦云如暴风雨似的一时热忱；这些优点已经足以让此书凌驾于图书馆中的普通小说之上，可是，它还算不上是一部优秀的小说，或者说并没有达到朱伊斯伯里小姐应有的水平。《康斯坦斯·赫伯特》可以算是一部训导型小说[48]；其中人物和事件的选择都考虑到不能违背某些原则。要实现的大原则是坚定不移地为责任和义务奉献自我，而具体到小说中的小原则是：有精神病遗传史则不能结婚。到目前为止，我们的观点都和朱伊斯伯里小姐一致。但是我们认为她想要树立的模式，不管是通过《使节》（Envoi）中的理论，还是通过小说中的叙述，都是错误的人生观点，而且事实上，她的这种观点正好和她之前的主张相悖。她在《使节》中说：“如果我们成功地在这本书中植入某个原则，那就是恳请我们的读者，鼓起勇气去实践这些既定的最严厉的要求。虽然有时候这好像是在强迫读者，但最终，这些原则被证明是正确的。为了一个更高原则而自我克制，这是值得的。”黑体字是我们用来证明朱伊斯伯里小姐的道德观有问题的证据。她的道德观体现在小说中三位女性的故事上。这三位女士要么抛弃了自己的爱人，要么被爱人所抛弃，她们安慰自己说那些爱人只不过是“无用之人”，达到了一种十分释然的安稳状态。我们并没有在其中看到真正的“自我克制”原则，也没有看到真实的生活；而朱伊斯伯里竟然要花掉三大卷书来说教这样的道德观，这让我们对她的洞察力和真诚深感抱歉。问题不在于我们有义务进行自我克制，或者说这种坚持是否值得；而在于，如果我们有义务这样做，那么自我克制就不再是一种道德英雄主义，而只是一种经过思考的谨慎行为而已了。让我们再看看朱伊斯伯里小姐在小说中描写的这种特殊情况，若是一位女性遇到类似情况，也会像康斯坦斯·赫伯特一样放弃婚姻，因为她不想将精神病带给另一个家庭；她对自己的感情很坚定，不是对菲利普·马奇蒙特那样自私浅薄的世俗之人，而是对一个能带给她幸福生活的人；她曾拒绝他，她会觉得这种因爱而生的牺牲会让他之后的人生越发依恋和感激她。只有在这一点上，我们认为自我克制还算得上是难能可贵，那是一种不需要任何补偿的大义凛然，是凄美与英雄主义的统一。康斯坦斯·赫伯特的高尚之举只有一种动机，那就是对人性的痛苦与不幸的真切同情，女性宁愿牺牲自己，也不会将不幸传递给别人；但是，当人们发现曾经所珍视的一切在现实中竟然毫无价值时，这种动机也是站不住脚的。对于女性来说，任务虽然艰巨，但她自始至终都手捧蜜饯，并且告诉我们总有一天能得到奖赏，这是乐天派最爱采用的伪善之言，她们以为在坎坷的荒野中探寻人生之路就好像找到荷兰园林中的小径那样简单；可是，将外在因素由动机永久地替换为行动，这的的确确破坏了真正的道德发展；相反，一时兴起的激情或正义却足以保证一个人的行为品德端正。我们似乎该讲讲小说这个严肃的话题了，但是朱伊斯伯里小姐花了大量篇幅强调她的道德观，这不得不让我们认为她的书是一本训导书，而不是小说，以致让我们一直在驳斥她的观点，而忽略了她所讲的故事。换一个角度，我们之所以不得不反驳她一下，是因为我们承认她的影响力，所以必须时刻关注她的观点是否把我们领往正确的方向。书中除了哈罗普先生一直在忠心等待着一位妻子给自己的生命增添意义之外，其他男性角色要么懦弱无能，要么背信弃义、卑鄙无赖；而书中所有女性都是宽宏大量、忠贞不二的典型代表；这回狮子们，即女性同胞们，手中有了可以复仇的笔，就可以对从亚当之后所有中伤过自己的男性们进行报复了。或许，我们允许她们写得夸张些，这样会显得比较公平。但是我们仍旧要低调地表示一下我们并不能接受片面的观点，即使是人生楷模玛格丽特姑妈的话。玛格丽特姑妈告诉我们，她在青春貌美时已经具备了高尚的美德和文学造诣，却由于自己一方全心全意的付出而使丈夫疏远了自己。她说：“没有一个男人能忍受完全意义上的付出。”这让我联想到一个酒徒在某个晚上喝了几杯白兰地和白水混合的饮料，隔天的早上抱怨白水让自己身体不适。我们倾向于认为，通常并非是女性的付出使男性疏远了她们，而是掺杂在付出中的东西，比如愚蠢、怒气或紧张，这些情感只要加入些许剂量，就会引起激烈的后果。事实上，男性处在一个很艰难的位置上：一方面，格蕾斯·李小姐或某个像她一样意志坚定的女性，怒斥男性想得到女性的爱戴和敬仰，而憎恨具有自我独立意识的女性；另一方面，一位具有忧郁气质的维尔拉，抱怨男性从来不感激女性的付出，而只关注那些对他们态度漠然的女性。这对于所有男女来说，是个多么令人沮丧的观点啊！严肃地说，我们对于如何理解女性的真实地位关注本来就多，所以当看到朱伊斯伯里小姐这样的女作家在这一问题上又增添了她自己的观点，让我们的认识更加混乱时，我们不能不感到遗憾。

玛格丽特·富勒和玛丽·沃斯通克拉夫特

最近新书不多，正好有机会去重新翻阅那些迄今为止被我们忽略的书。在此，我们选了玛格丽特·富勒[49]最新版本的《十九世纪的女性》（Woman in the Nineteenth Century），因为和当时同类别的书比起来，该书的内容更加充实和公正，算得上是同类别书中的翘楚。虽然这本书中也具有和美国其他伟大作品相似的缺点，例如混杂着模棱两可的唯心论以及不切实际的豪言壮语，但是它仍旧十分难得：书中散发着高贵和谐的热忱，全书基调中庸、涉及面广，为读者提供了大量充满活力和修养的内容。书中并没有夸大女性的道德品质抑或智力水平，也没有盲目地去强调女性适合做哪些迄今为止被男性所垄断的事情；作者只是冷静地呼吁废除针对女性的不公正法律以及人为的约束，创造一个能让她们全面发挥资质的空间：

帮助她们摆脱一种寄生状态，这种状态看似在助她们进步，实则在拖她们的后腿；

带领她们来到充满希望和新生的田野，看繁花遍地，帮助她们认识真实的自己；

让全社会都关注并且学习，如何保护和支持与众不同的女性权利。

玛格丽特·富勒的这本书最早在1843年出版，如果把它和六七十年前玛丽·沃斯通克拉夫特[50]的《女权辩护》（Rights of Woman）作个对比，那将是一件十分有趣的事。《女权辩护》仅有一卷，但是它所涵盖的内容与富勒的书相比，至少在道德意识上绝对让上世纪的女性受益匪浅。某些评论者对《女权辩护》一书颇有微词，认为它在某些方面应受到谴责，但是读者若是抱着这样的印象翻开此书，只会惊讶地发现这本书实际上十分严肃，而且道德感厚重——或许是因为这本书到1796年已经绝版，而现存的也很稀有了。两本书的观点有时候非常相似，有时候却又大相径庭。两本书都表现出了作者充分的理解力。玛格丽特·富勒的观点似乎总是局限在美国大陆的范围之内，让人常常在刚刚经历了明媚的“透彻”之后又立马进入到神秘纠结的迷雾森林——她经常在前一段还逻辑严密地推理，之后却又如梦呓般含糊其辞；而她所处的独特的文化背景也让她拥有了超强的描写能力。另一方面，玛丽·沃斯通克拉夫特则极其理性，她的书中没有炫耀性的渊博学识，也没有展示灵动的想象力。我们可以透过这两个作家看到，在她们坚硬或是真挚的秉性之下，都跳动着一颗充满爱的女性之心，这让她们不会低估任何一个具有细小关爱和善心的人或机构。玛格丽特·富勒是个激情澎湃的女性，她多愁善感，习惯了以笔抒情、以文明志；而我们认为玛丽·沃斯通克拉夫特并不是为了写作而写作，她的写作动机更加复杂。虽然两人生活在不同的时代，但是她们在思想轨迹上却有着惊人的相似之处。《女权辩护》中说，对于男孩和女孩的教育应当将家庭教育和普通的学校教育相结合，除了这一观点，书中其他重要的思想都在玛格丽特·富勒的文章中有所重现。

两位作家都写到过的一个观点是，男性害怕另外一个性别群体的能力和修养也达到自己的水平，所以一直处在一种满足于女性无知、愚昧的状态。玛格丽特·富勒说：

“只要男性的成长环境没有任何贫困和愚昧，充分享受到了家中壁炉的温暖以及生活中的美好，那么此时，女性更具影响力，如果她选择使用这些权力，也经常倾向于这么做，这与她们的无知、幼稚和虚荣心的程度成一定比例。她们根本没考虑过生命的重要性和意义，从小被教导如何卖弄风骚、贪图小便宜，目光仅仅局限于自己某个时刻的享乐，而政府的动荡不安以及市场的萧条竟然能抚慰她们的内心。尽管英国商铺老板的妻子们没有选举权，但是她们却对政治家们奉承般的游说感兴趣。”

她接着说：

“当病人们（容许我们把这样的男性叫作病人）不再戒备时，所有的妻子们，无论品德好坏，无论爱与不爱，都不可避免地会使用到她们所拥有的权力，并且掺杂着自己的情感影响她们的丈夫。”

对于相同的话题，玛丽·沃斯通克拉夫特这样说：

“女性被囿于自身的愚昧和奴性依赖已经很多很多年了，但是她们依旧怡然自得，喜欢浪子和军人，醉心于玩具，她们的虚荣心让她们更注重成就而忽略美德。历史已经给我们展示了一部令人心寒的女性犯罪记录，这些罪行都是她们试图超越她们的主人、运用自己的智慧犯下的……我把女性说成奴隶是有原因的，这是政治和公民上的含义；她们间接地拥有很多权力，可惜被她们争取不法权力的行为所削弱……成功男士的自由玩乐以及他们的美德，一直是鼓动女人超越男人的强大推力；而这些弱小的女人们，在孩子气和自私的虚荣心的驱使下，将会对男人们所认定的事物产生合理怀疑；而实际上，她们应该采纳他们的判断。对于爱幻想以及对生活乐观的大部分男人，他们都能一方面把自己的人生事务管理得井井有条，另一方面在女性社会中放松自己；当然，我不需要从历史上搬出大量的反例，也不用详述由于好心的愚蠢干涉所引起的悲剧，因为这些反对是由于女性的独断专行造成的。在业务处理中，宁愿和无赖打交道，也不要和傻瓜打交道，因为无赖尚且知道依照计划办事，可以提前认清采取计划的动机，而不是像愚者那样不知何时才能顿悟。有些无耻愚蠢的女人爱管教睿智的男人，她们通常都是臭名昭著的。”

在男性中似乎广泛流传着这样一种观点，那就是一个受过良好教育、具有自己独立观点的女士，更容易变成一个爱唱反调的个性女子：当她的丈夫想要往西时，她却要往东，说话时满口深奥的道理，还喜欢枕边训导。当然，只要你意识到这一点，你就会知道，在不能使用暴力、鞭子、缰绳和脚镣的情况下，你家那位毫不讲理的妻子便是世上最难对付的生物了。但在女性自己看来，通过在体罚的旧俗和现代教育之间找到一种合适的中间状态，以此让男性能够理智地对待他们的妻子是不可能的。当弱小不受控制时它就会泛滥成灾；就好像一位强壮的男人手牵着一个调皮的小孩，你可以看到那小孩是如何为了挣脱大人的束缚而左右拉扯，最后挣扎累了便只好乖乖地跟着大人继续前行。一个真正有教养的女人应当和一个真正有教养的男人一样，都得做好最终被生活琐事所征服的准备。由此可见，松散的逻辑和薄弱的意志之间并没有什么牢固的联系，一位对哲学一窍不通的女士，她对厨房的热情也不会那么不屈不挠。真正有文化的女性不会因为有了学问就自以为高人一等，只有对真知一知半解的女性才会有至高无上的优越感，就像马勒普太太[51]所说，这种优越感源自“女性身上徒劳无益的品质”——她那些知识只是随处搜刮来的，并没被完全吸收，没有真正融入到自己的品格中去。

回到玛格丽特·富勒，她谈及社会上对女性最大的偏见在于对女性性格的绝对定义以及对女性使命的绝对划分。她说：“女人们的性格反映在很多侧面，就好像她们不受规则约束一样，我们必须承认女性性格的多样性。”她接着说：“如果她们的天性不被束缚，她们的言论不被扼杀，这就够了。当她们需要抒发自己的情感时，能够自由地书写或倾诉，那将是多么令人欣慰的一件事。当然，若她们依旧保持一贯的沉默，并不是因为男权的压迫，而是因为神的召唤，那么这种沉默还算不上是灾难。”玛格丽特说了下面这一段话，其中第一句的引用频率颇高：

“如果你问我，女性适合什么职业，我将毫不犹豫地回答：任何职业。我不在乎你假设的情景，如果可以，她们还能当女船长呢，我从不怀疑她们的能力，如果要选择女船长，我将非常荣幸地推荐萨拉戈萨、密淑伦其的少女们，苏列特的女英雄或者艾米丽·普莱特。我认为在这样一个时期，女性尤其需要一个广阔的就业面和众多的职业选择，激发她们潜在的力量……我们会发现，有些小女孩在家里被木工活所吸引，或者自己爱研究木工的器具，如果她们的这种兴趣能被接受并被正确引导，她们将身心愉悦，而且培养出木工的技艺；但是，如果家长们认为木工活不适合女孩子干，那么小女孩们的这种兴致就被扼杀了，她们可能会因此变得易怒且淘气。傅立叶[52]曾经研究过女性的这些兴趣，他认为大人都能看出小女孩的渴望，也很容易看出成年女性的空虚无聊，当然那些具有一技之长或是保有自己兴趣爱好的女性除外。所以，他主张制造业和看护动植物等行业至少要向三分之一的女性开放，让她们具有和男性一样的追求，当然女性职业也应当向三分之一的男性开放。但是，我敢肯定，即便是有这样的呼吁，大部分女性还是会和现在一样选择职业，因为她们迫于很多因素很难改变。母亲们自然而然地会把家庭营造得温暖舒适，这就是天性，就好像想要高飞、想要鸣叫的鸟儿，不需要帮它拍打翅膀，它也能一飞冲天，或者说人们很难发现一只翅膀没有力量的小鸟。唯一需要说明的是，不能因为某些职业不适合女性就认为所有职业都不适合女性。”

针对这一问题，玛丽·沃斯通克拉夫特提出了这样的建议，该建议已经在美国妇女中开始实施，她说：

“所有的女性，都想成为淑女。当她们接触到一些自己曾经很少关心的领域，总是无精打采、无所事事，那是因为她们不知道该谈论些什么。那么女性在社会中应该干些什么呢？有人可能会这样回答：‘迈着优美的步伐闲逛吗？或者就放任她们哺育小孩子，或是记载些无足轻重的琐事。’不！女性应该学习医术，成为医师或者护士……她们能进军各行各业，前提是她们得到正规的受教育的机会……女性不应当迫于生计而结婚，这样会使男性被动接受婚姻而忽略应尽的义务。”

事实上，男性不愿意鼓励女性自助和独立的同时，也让自己尝尽了苦头。许多青年才俊宝贵的时间在日复一日的辛勤工作中流逝，他们设立的“原则”是不让女性们明白自己的小心思，只需要她们安静地待在休息室，就像圣母端坐在神祠里一样。这都没问题。但是，想要改变人们对女性建立起来的陈旧观念，或者放弃偏见，仰视一下自己的妻子，这却显得那么困难。罗马神话中的富豪罗米拉斯说：“就把男人当作神灵吧，就好像他已经死去了一样”；而男人们也这样说女人：“就把她们看作是木偶吧，身穿漂亮的衣物却毫无用处，即便我们不承认她们是严格意义上的人类，我们仍旧得到她们的尊重”。

社会上有一方的观点认为，只有女性的素质提高了，她们的地位才会提高；另一方观点则认为，如果女性的地位没有改变，她们就很难变得更好——这就需要更加公平公正的法律以及针对女性的更广阔的择业机会。然而，与此同时，我们也时常能听到解决人权问题的种种难处。在个体和社会机构之间总是存在着一种作用力和反作用力，难以调和；我们必须尽力去修补双方的关系，哪怕这样的尝试步履维艰，任重道远，但也只有这样才是唯一能改善人权的方式。不幸之处在于，许多过度热心的极端妇女认定自己和男人们是完全平等的——噢！还不止，她们认为女性的道德水平甚至超越了男性——基于此，她们极力倡导将女性从令人窒息的法律法规和社会惯例中解放出来。可是，她们因为错误的定位而大大削弱了自己的力量。如果她们提出的根据是真实的，那么奴隶制度和愚昧无知岂不是成了培养美德的摇篮，人们岂不是就得支持奴役制的延续了？但我们想为女性争取更多自由和文化，因为长久以来，她们习惯了顺从和愚昧，这使得她们的地位下降，可是——

如果她们弱小、脾气傲慢、生活痛苦，

那么男人们又怎么成长？

玛格丽特·富勒和玛丽·沃斯通克拉夫特两人有足够的智慧来证明这句多愁善感的夸大之词，她们热切地希望女性能改变现状。当谈到男人和女人的道德水平时，玛丽·沃斯通克拉夫特坚定地说：

“比起男性，女性的情感更加敏锐，可以说更加人性化，因为她们感情专一，并且随时怀揣着怜悯之情；但是她们对愚昧的执着却易发展成为自私或极端的情绪，例如对孩子的溺爱或对野兽的憎恨。我认识很多意志力薄弱的女人，她们原本丰富的情感被丈夫所钝化，甚至连基本的人性情感都所剩无几，只有偶尔会窜出一丝的同情心。一位著名的演说家说过，人性并不是从‘神经质的耳朵里听来的，它应当来自心灵和头脑’。虽然女性这种独特的情感可能让个体变得软弱，但它却不能被当作证明某种性别不如另一性别的证据，因为这种情感是基于各种束缚和压迫后自然产生的。就算是情感十分丰富的女性，如果她们不关注工作和个人规划，很少在意道德品质，那么她们的英雄主义般热烈的情感，抑或是精神，也只会在被爱情驱使的情况下一生只出现一次。我因此倒也同意有些伦理学家主张的‘女人不如男人般慷慨大方’；女性的情感领域时常因为保全正义和仁慈而变得狭窄，这使得在和男性作比较时处于劣势；但是我想说，若是女性不想再被男性的观点所束缚，那么就请打开心房，学会包容和接纳，让心充满力量吧。”

我们还找到了玛格丽特·富勒的一些观点，但是我们的主题只需要点到为止，并不需要长篇大论地赘述，所以此处就略去不引用了；我觉得，上文所列的各种断断续续的内容已经足够向读者说明我的观点了。

哈丽雅特·比彻·斯托的《德雷德》[53]、查尔斯·里德的《改过不嫌晚》，以及弗雷德里卡·布雷默的《赫莎》

我们终于等来了斯托夫人的新小说，在过去三周里，男女老少都在全神贯注地读着这本小说——书中描绘的美景、幽默或温暖的场景，以及粗鲁的英雄主义让他们时而欢笑，时而哭泣——当然，他们也会对书中所写的粗野行径义愤填膺。这样的一本书是一股很难操纵的力量，评论更是各执一词，有反对也有支持——有人抱怨斯托夫人酷爱重复叙事，导致情节不够完美，全书充斥着赞美诗和宗教对话，拖沓啰唆，由此还产生了不公平的偏见——但这些抱怨的人就像是手拿喷壶去浇灭草原火灾的救火人，力量单薄。在此期间，《德雷德》（Dred）已经被数以百万计的人所阅读，他们大多数认为这是一部天才之作，并且没有那么多苛刻的评论。我承认，我们很多人都在这数以万计之列，只是不习惯与法德拉蒂圣人之流相提并论。我们被德雷德深深感动，并且精确地评估着它与汤姆叔叔[54]的差距；我们也对斯托夫人的套路留下了深刻印象，以至于完全知道她将要写些什么。我们对她小说的钦佩已经超越了废奴制度等大问题，并不只是停留在所谓的“纯文学”上了。即使我们并不完全赞同斯托夫人的观点，认为她夸大了她所塑造的人物形象，但《德雷德》仍旧算是一部少见的优秀小说，因为作者不仅功底深厚，而且所写的故事情节张弛有度。

如果从艺术的角度看，我们没有理由因斯托夫人的新小说还是在继续上一本书里的黑人和殖民者生活的故事而感到遗憾，像司各特[55]刚写完《威弗利》（Waverley），本该将苏格兰高地的生活重复写进《罗布·罗伊》（Rob Roy）以及《珀斯的美丽姑娘》（The Fair Maid of Perth）那样。斯托夫人创造了黑人文学小说，此类小说不仅具有新颖的内容、独特的手法，而且包含了奥古斯特·蒂尔里[56]指出的极具罗曼蒂克情节的种族冲突——司各特的《艾凡赫》（Ivanhoe）[57]也是一例。文学作品中的创造力并不像制造男女外套或是防水公寓那样无穷无尽，对于读者来说，读文学作品的乐趣可能就在于看书中各式各样的重复和模仿，所以，我们对斯托夫人又写了一部黑人小说应当持宽容的态度；或许，她只会写这类小说呢，因为她的写作才能的确比较特殊。她写的《晴天记忆》（Sunny Memories）简直搬不上台面，但是不管她还写过什么，或者是以后还会继续写什么，我们都不可否认，《汤姆叔叔的小屋》以及《德雷德》已经让她跻身于一流小说家之列，她以最高的水平给读者描绘了国民生计各个阶段的情形——大众的、贵族的、幽默的、悲伤的、政治的、宗教的——生动而全面。

当然，斯托夫人的小说里并不是只有种族冲突那类宏大的主题，和司各特一样，她的作品中还有另一个重要的内容，从某种程度上讲，她对这一主题的描写成就甚至超过了司各特。这个主题就是对希伯来基督教的细节重现。在当时，希伯来基督教还十分鼎盛，圣经《旧约》的教义渗透在人们日常生活的方方面面。司各特塑造了贝尔福的伯利，生动描写了杜门罗格和博斯维尔布里格战役以及以法莲·麦克布瑞尔的审判，还有谁能超越他的这些成果呢？而斯托夫人所写的德雷德沼泽地的阴暗景色、长老会教徒和循道宗信徒的野营集会则可以与之匹敌，前提是我们忽略掉司各特在《清教徒》（Old Mortality）中描写的精彩打斗。斯托夫人自己的宗教情感是她自身的一种艺术优势，她绝不会让你觉得她在无情地算计后果，你看到的只是她一时之间疯狂的热情、未加思量的信念以及德雷德、缇夫和迪克森神父的烈士精神。不仅如此，敏锐的幽默感也让她的语言远离浮夸和单调；虽然她总是从好的方面描绘虔诚的黑人们，但他们还是黑人，斯托夫人从来不会对自己塑造的人物失去掌控，也不会让本该妙趣横生的对话变成毫无生气的演说。当然了，这就是斯托夫人的特点：她的戏剧本能随时开启着，无论是风格怪异的老缇夫、爱做白日梦的妮娜、直率的智者伯尼姆神父，还是极其绅士的弗兰克·罗素，她都能把这些角色塑造得栩栩如生，使得她在竞争激烈的优秀小说家之林中占据一席之地。

若是从争论角度看待斯托夫人的小说，人们对她的反对意见也是其众多艺术瑕疵中的一个。大家认为她在成名前的小说中没有描写一定比例的黑奴真是太可惜了。从她的观点来看，黑人种族大大优于白人，甚至是在某些非奴隶制国家——这一点足以击败斯托夫人对某些将奴隶制度称作“基督化制度”[58]之人的暗讽和挖苦。如果说奴化的黑人真的如此优良，那么奴隶制度就算得上是道德准则了。但是除了这种自杀式的论点之外，斯托夫人却因触动了种族之间最悲剧的元素而唤醒了被压迫在恶习中的涅墨西斯复仇女神。她暗指奴隶中也有败坏的道德，但并未给予详细的描述，可是，她为什么花了那么长的篇幅来写勒格雷和汤姆·戈登，却在黑奴的道德堕落问题上如此惜字如金呢？

我相信，用不了多久，斯托夫人的这本小说大家就会人手一本，所以我根本就不用提及该书的内容，要做的只是称赞它是一本伟大的小说，衡量政治意义这件事就留给别人去做吧。

合上《德雷德》，我们现在翻开的是查尔斯·里德[59]的《改过不嫌晚》（It is Never Too Late to Mend），这又是一本值得一读的好书，能深深地拨动我们的心弦。这本书在叙事风格和本质特征上与《德雷德》形成鲜明的对比。里德先生的小说再现了一些英国人真实的悲惨生活：正直的青年农夫乔治·菲尔丁赶上了这个“不景气”的时代，在家里农场颗粒无收的情况下，为了和自己心爱的女人苏珊·默顿结婚，他只好到澳大利亚去寻求财富。还有一位聪明的盗贼罗宾逊，他本是菲尔丁在乡下时的房客，作者通过他描写了阴森的监狱生活和无知残暴的监狱长，这些平常很难看到的情节令人不寒而栗。读者跟随英勇的牧师一起在书中抗争这种愚蠢且不公正的迫害，最终导致了伯明翰监狱的悲剧；比起真人真事，人们的同情心似乎更容易被小说激发。接着，我们来到澳大利亚，目睹了菲尔丁的幸运和不幸——首先经历了澳大利亚大牧羊场的考验，然后是极具戏剧性的淘金之旅，这让他收获了四千磅的财富并且及时赶回家，避免了心爱的苏珊被自己的头号情敌娶走。

可以说，这部小说有三个亮点：引人入胜的场景，真挚感人的情感，还有极具说服力的写作水平。在监狱中遇到的那个最佳伙伴可能很令人讨厌，但是当他决定要退场时又让读者舍不得。菲尔丁对苦难生活的抗争在澳大利亚再次上演，但这次，朋友们的友谊点亮了他的惨淡生活，包括那位改过自新的盗贼罗宾逊以及他的小狗卡洛，还有澳大利亚土著人——令人鼓舞的“杰克”，这群鲜活的朋友是吸引你看完整本书的动力。“杰克”是一个全新的人物，他举止优雅并且风趣幽默，完全不像其他野蛮人。而读过这本小说的农夫都会对书中的一些英国生活场景产生共鸣：例如乔治·菲尔丁和兄弟威廉的小口角，女主人苏珊·默顿的保守思想以及其他众多的优点。总之，《改过不嫌晚》是一本非常优秀的小说，不仅适合无所事事和文化程度不高的人读，也适合成天忙碌、博古通今的人阅读。

然而，里德先生的小说还没有超越“机智”这个水平：我们的确能在全书中感受到他高效利用各种素材的天资，因为读者只会赞叹将素材进行重组归纳和再创造的“天才”作者，却常常忽略制造精巧素材的原创人。当然，市面上探讨天才和灵感的废话比比皆是，就好像天才不需要动脑一样；但是，有些作家的作品能让你瞬间着迷，而有些作家只能唤醒你的好奇心，这二者之间还是有很大差别的，差别的根源可能是跟作家的“天赋”有关吧。事实上，这种差别的真正原因可能在于此——第一种作家完全将自己投入了所写的作品，本人的情感与角色融为一体；第二种作家将自己置身于故事之外，只是一个劲儿地装扮着角色。斯托夫人算得上是第一种作家，她对自己的作品充满了激情，并且被自己塑造的每个角色所鼓励着；她丰富的内心，而非下意识的雕琢，最终让她的作品取得了最佳戏剧效果。相反，里德先生似乎总是存在于一种自觉状态中，他时刻经营着自己的角色，一遍一遍地润色修饰；他塑造的人物可能此时是一种状态，而彼时又随着情节的发展和之前的性格相差甚远。这种跳跃式的描写习惯导致他乐于在写作中追寻对比强烈的冲突和夸张的戏剧效果，然而这种快节奏的情节更适合观看舞台剧的观众，并不适合一部小说的读者，因为小说的时间线和容量都比剧本要大，小说应当通过均匀的描写，着重赋予人物更多现实主义色彩，而非仅仅追求情节的起落。看里德的小说，我们仿佛看到了一个被“打造”得非常完美的剧场绅士，注视着舞台下的观众，用抑扬顿挫的语调述说着书中的对话，此处引用一例：当伊登先生做完关于盗窃的晨训之后，监狱长霍斯听了十分赞同，跟狱吏弗赖伊吩咐，应该让大家都听听这样的讲解。于是当天下午弗赖伊又请人举办了一场关于残暴行为的训诫，霍斯问弗赖伊：“我不是让他在神坛上给其他人讲课吗？”弗赖伊答道：“是的，长官，我就是这样说的，可是你有说过想让他在其他人面前说教吗？”“我说过，”霍斯生气地回答，“但不是让他对着我讲！你个笨蛋！”这场景若是在舞台上必然会引起一阵小轰动，同时还展现了些许人物性格；但是出现在小说中时，人们有足够多的时间思考和怀疑这种极端的朴素，还不如自己创造一两句可以感知的诗句呢。

里德先生似乎从来不相信节制和简单。他描写的监狱生活夸张到漏洞百出，前后的重复也让读者产生了审美疲劳；他的男女主角都设定在伯克郡家园，这可以算是一个创举；可是接下来他将浪漫和邪气相结合的努力却显得幼稚且格格不入：伊萨克·利瓦伊是一个拼接式的多重性格的犹太人，极具远见的马基雅维利主义者[60]梅多斯先生竟然穿长筒靴，甚至是他自言自语时也在怒斥人性的弱点，并且召唤上帝和他人见证自己的愤怒，这完全就是混淆了原因和结果的重要性。但是像里德先生这样的大作家，他真正的缺点可能要算过于信赖排版的效果。我们通常认为，在大量理念和大量样式之间很难建立联系，因为这种联系总是会被文字的样式所限制；但是我们的里德先生总能不遗余力地通过现代事物、运用大写字母给读者留下深刻印象，例如突然在书页中出现几个夸张的大字“这个不可思议的时代”。也许，我们如此鸡蛋里挑骨头是件不道德的事，毕竟《改过不嫌晚》带给我们那么多快乐；但不可否认，正是我们对里德先生智慧的钦佩使得他书中的瑕疵变得那么令人伤脑筋，让我们在介绍他的作品时不得不提及。

布雷默[61]小姐的新书让我们回想起十年前，小说界的人们曾热烈讨论《友邻》（The Neighbours）、《总统的女儿》（The President's Daughters）、《H家族》（The H-Family）等瑞典小说的情景。那次大讨论引发了文学界和图书销售界的“瑞典小说”热潮，但是热潮如同昙花一现般很快退去。可能很少有一种类型的小说像布雷默女士的小说那样在英国轰动一时，却在之后的文学史上销声匿迹。没有人再引用它们，也没有人再谈及它们：当人们迈入四十多岁的年纪时，思想成熟，回想起当年对瑞典小说的狂热，不禁会对那时的“年轻不羁”报以一笑。那么为什么会这样？布雷默小姐独特的写作才华不仅给英国读者带来了新鲜感，同时还给写作带来了非同寻常的影响——活泼生动的想象力、诗意的情感、丰富的语言、对细节的感知以及能给日常生活点滴增添色彩的轻快而朴素的幽默感。那么回到之前的问题，为什么布雷默小姐的小说在读者中的评价并不高呢？当我们精读一下《赫莎》（Hertha）就会发现第一个原因，她所有的优点都被过度的多愁善感给毁了，就好像在美洲的森林里看到一只嗅觉并不灵敏的爬行动物，却让人觉得周围弥漫的都是危险气息。她总是在小说中做些怪异的拼接，例如把模糊虚构的空想主义和不同寻常的类荷兰现实主义结合；她在前一页还在写丰盛的香肠三明治、啤酒、牛奶甜酒，而接下来描写的历险记却根本不像是吃三明治喝甜酒的人能干出来的，更像是精灵或是火蜥蜴种族。布雷默小姐的小说经不起时间考验的另一个原因，在于贯穿小说始终的过于绝对的宗教哲学口气。当一个小说家夸口她要表达的理论能解决世人所有的困难时，那么显然，她的小说只不过是自说自话而已。

在《赫莎》中，布雷默的多愁善感和教条式自信这两点表现得十分明显，但是对比她前期的小说，缺少了对细节的描述以及现实主义幽默感。《赫莎》并不是一本单纯出于艺术灵感而写成的小说，它的目标很明确，就是要把女性从有碍她们发展的法律和教育限制中解救出来，把她们从没有工作机会而只能致力于婚姻生活的无聊人生中解救出来。我们认为，所有具有判断能力的人都会佩服布雷默，因为她在很多年前就已经为自己赢得了名声和独立的人格，并且将自己的余生都奉献给了妇女解放事业，她这种慷慨激昂的能量是当时妇女所严重缺乏的。看着她在《赫莎》中阐述的那些智慧且高尚的事，我们不由得惋惜，她提出的所谓解决困难和实际问题的观点，并没有考虑到当时的时代局限性，而只不过像粉色烟雾般浪漫和不切实际罢了。《赫莎》的故事简介如下：

赫莎自幼丧母，她的父亲是个典型的思想狭隘、贪得无厌的传统男人，要求儿女百分之百的顺从。在她二十七岁时，赫莎对父亲的束缚越来越不满，同时，父亲还专横地阻止了赫莎的姐姐阿尔玛同她心爱的人结婚，阿尔玛因此陷入悲痛之中。我们的女主角第一次亮相是在一次化装舞会的预演中，她脸上写满了忧郁和痛苦，舞会将于几天后在孔斯雪平镇举行。她在舞会上认识了不少朋友，其中一位年轻人叫英韦·诺丁，赫莎十分赞同他关于女性地位的论断。接着，我们跟随女主角回到她了无生趣的家，在那里住着她的“独裁者”父亲，父亲会因为她们没有在规定的八点之前回家而狠狠训斥她们；在那里还有她的精神依靠，她的姐姐阿尔玛，她总是向阿尔玛倾吐内心的痛苦以及在父亲的压迫下而滋生的仇恨和叛逆。虽然赫莎和阿尔玛从母亲那里继承了部分财产，但是依据瑞典法律，她们还是未成年人，因此没有实际的财产支配权。就在当晚，镇上发生火灾，破坏范围极大，“独裁父亲”的家也被烧毁，他自己还是被我们的女主角赫莎救出火海的。当时，赫莎冲进父亲的房间，背起瘦弱的父亲冲出了大火。这一孝顺的举动，加上阿尔玛的遗言，为赫莎从父亲那里争取到了自由的许诺，当然，这一自由也是有限制的。父亲仍旧掌管着她的财产权，直到她成年；但是赫莎在家里已经有了地位，并且有更多出门活动的自由。为了帮助火灾中的伤员和病员，妇女们组建了一个“妇女救助社”，赫莎也是其中一员。碰巧的是，她接待的伤员正好是英韦·诺丁，英韦受了重伤，现在寄住在救助社社长——一位好心的牧师家。赫莎照顾英韦的这段日子是他们培养友谊的绝好时机，赫莎发现，诺丁宽大的内心和渊博的学识一方面抚慰了自己的伤痛，一方面激发了自己的思想；后来，这种友谊渐渐发酵，最终变成了爱情。在经历了种种猜忌和怀疑之后，独裁父亲终于勉强答应了英韦对赫莎提出的求婚，前提是英韦必须找到一份稳定的工作。英韦于是出国寻求财富，赫莎为了等他一直延后婚期，一直到七年后，英韦重病奄奄一息的时候，赫莎才放下顾虑嫁给他。在与英韦分离的那七年里，赫莎做了很多有意义的事，她创办并且管理着两所学校——一所是专门给女孩提供基础教学的学校，另一所学校则更像是导师制的护士学院，在那里，学生通过听赫莎的朗读、与她直接交谈，以及受她人格魅力的影响，而提升自己的思想境界和人生追求。她的学校非常成功，但是英韦的去世令她悲痛不已，她随后不久也离开了人世。

这个简要的故事梗概只能展示而不能完全解释我们对《赫莎》一书的批评。我们的批评在于：书中提出的问题大多只能通过十分绝对的观点和特别详细的事实来解决，当然还得用到空洞的口才以及轻浮的爱情故事。试举一例，书中提到是否应该让女性学医并且从事医疗职业。而作家采用女性成功从事医学事业的例子来证明了这一点，我们杰出的女作家认为，只要女性足够认真，学习了足够多的课程，那么根据“生动的观察和坚定的意志必定带来思想顿悟”这一理论，她们仅仅通过在病床旁边观摩病人，再演绎一段爱情故事，而不经过长期的临床试验，就能成为一名好医生、好护士。当然，女性们不用证明自己很情绪化、偶尔狂热和唯心主义，因为这些都是大家所公认的。她们需要证明是：自己也有精确的思维能力、严谨的学习态度和持续的自控力，虽然这几点我们都很难心甘情愿地同意，因为从布雷默小姐的笔下，我们更容易被女主角的满口正义和她精妙的观察能力所吸引。在此，我们实在是没有足够的空间来引用赫莎抱怨其他女性不懂自然科学的长篇大论了，仅仅摘出一小段来：“在我很小的时候，就对自然界中的一切抱着浓厚的兴趣，我爱观察山川河流、一草一木，期望能了解它们的性格，它们的生命，以及它们存在的意义。但是因为自己有限的知识和机会，大自然于我就像是一个高深莫测的谜团，直到现在，我还是会为它迷人的景致和神秘所倾倒，它就像是赋予我生命活力的甘泉，让我源源不断地从它那里汲取灵感。噢！感谢伟大的造物主！”

翻译和译者

一位像查尔斯·霍尼曼那样的牧师曾告诉我们，他不到周六晚上是不会着手准备他的布道辞的，因为他“听从天意的安排”。我想，类似“听从天意”的安排也存在于译者当中，他们大多数相信有这样一种超能力：

可以赋予任何人翻译的能力

即使人们对那种语言一窍不通——

这让我们对早期译者的神奇往事——耶稣的七十个弟子将圣经《旧约》翻译成希腊语的故事——产生了共鸣。传说托勒密将他们分别关在不同的单间里进行翻译，最终比对他们的翻译成果时，竟然发现翻译的结果惊人地吻合！当然，我们认为，七十子译本的译者们肯定还是有一定的语言天赋，否则也不会得到上帝赋予他们的超级翻译能力，因为至少在翻译这件事上，我们相信“天助自助者”；这句话我要献给所有年轻的女士和中年绅士们，尤其是那些对自己母语掌握得不够好的人，以及那些以外语作为基础必备技能的译者们。

虽然天才大多从事翻译事业，但是翻译这件事并不需要多少天赋，这是一个事实。翻译所需要的能力会因原始作品难易程度的不同而不同：译者若具有一般的资质，则足以翻译一本普通游记或是轻小说；但是要翻译推理或是科学的作品，则需要能力非凡和知识渊博的译者来完成。后者例如康德的《纯粹理性批判》（Critique of Pure Reason），对于译者来说就是一部很有难度的翻译作品——就像一颗难以敲开的坚果，要将其中要义有条理地铺陈开来不是件容易的事，但是我们很开心地看到，已经有能力很强的译者翻译过这本书了。以前有很多德国形而上学作品的译本都不太对劲，给人的感觉是译者还没学会游泳就一头扎进了深水里，仅仅依靠字典和听从“上帝的指示”进行翻译。而看看我们面前的这个译本，它简直太与众不同了。不得不说，米克尔约翰先生的翻译棒极了，完全还原了原作者应有的大师风范，这也让英国读者第一次有机会读到康德的《纯粹理性批判》。

我们在此提到一部思想如此深刻的书似乎有点奇怪，用博特小姐（或夫人）所编的德国抒情诗集译本中的话来说，这本书就像是装着九十门大炮的大船，一点也不令人轻松愉快。当然，我们在此只谈翻译，不会牵扯到康德的哲学或者德国抒情诗的内容；巧的是，这二者刚好在最近的翻译领域频频出现。若是翻译散文，我们可以用到戈德史密斯的秘诀，他说，译者经历的痛苦越多，就越能理解作者的心，翻译得也就越好；若是翻译诗歌，我们就不能保证这个“痛苦”秘诀能产生令人满意的成果了。这就不得不谈谈博特小姐的《德国诗歌选集》（Specimens of the German Poets）。博特小姐具有其他译者都羡慕的知识和能力，但是她翻译的诗歌缺乏一种诗意，会让那些读过原著的人觉得还不够完美。但是对于那些没有读过原著的读者来说，博特小姐的译本已经足够好了，读者的热情让诗集出了第二版。博特小姐野心颇大，她大胆地尝试着翻译了歌德著名的《奉献》（Zueignung），下面引用一段。歌德伴着神圣的感情和音乐这样唱着——

Für andre wächst in mir das edle Gut，

Ich kann und will das Pfund nicht mehr vergraben，

Warum sucht'ich den Weg so sehnsuchtsvoll，

Wenn ich ihn nicht den Brüdern zeigen soll?

而博特小姐的翻译则像是用单簧口琴去演奏钢琴曲般风格迥异——

我的才华渐渐逝去，

但是谁还曾拥有像我这样的智慧？

噢！为什么如此热情地要找到出路

若是我没有带领同胞们一同上路？

这样的版本就好像是著名绅士的脸庞和报纸上的画像对不上号一样。鉴于我们对外国诗人的了解大多间接地来源于一些译作，因此评论家肩上的担子就重了，他们需要对诗歌翻译一遍又一遍地进行批评，才能迫使译者在翻译时力求精益求精。

德国人翻译我们诗作的水平大大超过了我们翻译德文诗作的水平，这是因为他们的语言风格多变，在散文中如同一匹缓慢笨拙的驿马，但在诗歌中则像一匹优雅矫健的阿拉伯战马；而且从事诗歌翻译的德国人大多数都是才华横溢的男性。例如，我们记得弗莱里格拉特的翻译，若是我们首先读到的是英文版，那一定会被诗歌中精妙的语言迷住。诚然，德国人对自己的翻译水平自视甚高，尤其是被一些愚蠢的英国读者追捧后更甚，有些英国人认为施莱格尔翻译的莎士比亚甚至比原著更出彩——不仅仅是指对于德国人来说更容易理解，而且翻译本身就算得上是诗。施莱格尔的翻译的确是精准和典雅的结合，如果比对原著研读他的翻译，那将是一件令人无比快乐的事情，就好像在检阅一座基于最爱的画而创作出的精美木雕。他所使用的德语和英语一样能传达正确的意思——就好像是用另一种优秀的乐器奏响音乐一样。然而他也有翻译得不好的时候，这时他的翻译更像是无力的回音，在通篇华丽的语言里显得毫无吸引力。例如洛兰佐对杰西卡说的这段话。莎士比亚这样写道——

寂静的幽夜，

是最适宜于谐和的乐声。[62]

施莱格尔将其翻译成德语——

Sanfte Still und Nacht

Sie werden Tasten süsser Harmonie

意思是：“寂静的幽夜弹奏出了谐和的乐声。”另外，蒂克（他与施莱格尔的翻译水平不相上下）在《麦克白》（Macbeth）独白的翻译中犯了一个更大的错误。原文的台词如下——

如果这一击能够让事情在这里大功告成，

并毕其功于一役，那么在这里，

在这人世的涯岸与沙滩上，

我们就顾不得来世了。[63]

蒂克将Upon this bank and shoal of time译成Auf dieser Schülerbank der Gegenwart，意思从“在这人世的涯岸与沙滩上”变成了“在这学校里的长凳边”，这个极大的错误就是因为蒂克根本没有完全理解原著。再举一例小错误，科里奥兰纳斯[64]说——

就像是雄鹰在鸽棚上方展翅，

在科里奥利统治着沃尔西人。[65]

施莱格尔在翻译“展翅”时却用了德语里类似“盘旋”一词。这种小瑕疵在翻译中可谓屡见不鲜。

像施莱格尔和蒂克这样聪明杰出的人都会在翻译中出错，更别说那些学问不精的人了，他们更难去理解那些伟大的诗歌作品，这一事实已经被各种有难度的翻译任务所证实。虽然一个极好的译者比不上创作出经典作品的原作家，但是他绝对比那些写出三流作品的作家出色万分。我们想要强调的是，一个译者应当具有以下道德品质——耐心、对原文的忠诚度，以及解读另一种思想时的责任感。当然，我们对这一话题的讨论也不是一天两天了。

[1]《女作家写的蠢故事》是艾略特1856年写给《威斯敏斯特评论》（Westminster Review）的一篇论文。——译者注

[2]女帽类小说（mind-and-millinery species），作者借由英国女士们都十分喜爱的帽子来暗讽女作家的作品虽然样式纷繁、精巧别致，但基本上都虚有其表，华而不实。——译者注

[3]用希伯来语和希腊文写的《圣经》。——译者注

[4]贝尔格莱维亚区（Belgravia），伦敦的上流住宅区。——译者注

[5]奥西恩风格（Ossianic fashion）是指十分夸张的口吻，类似现在的琼瑶体。——译者注

[6]博林布鲁克（Bolingbroke），英格兰国王亨利四世的姓。——译者注

[7]维吉尔（Virgil，前70—前19），古罗马诗人。——译者注

[8]贺拉斯（Horace，前85—前8），古罗马诗人，批评家。

[9]西塞罗（Cicero，前106—前43），古罗马哲学家。——译者注

[10]李维（Livy，前59—17），古罗马历史学家。——译者注

[11]伊夫琳·温德姆（Evelyn Wyndham），文中的乌姆弗拉维尔夫人、伊夫琳都是温德姆小姐。——译者注

[12]皮由兹运动（Puseyism），又称牛津运动，或书册派运动，19世纪中期由英国牛津大学部分教授发动的宗教复兴运动。该运动主张恢复教会昔日的权威和早期的传统，保留罗马天主教的礼仪。运动领导者纽曼、凯布勒、皮由兹等人发表了一系列书册或论文，为这些主张作了理论说明或论证。——译者注

[13]该隐（Cain），亚当与妻子夏娃所生的两个儿子之一，后来因为嫉妒弟弟亚伯，而将其杀害，受到上帝惩罚。根据《圣经·创世记》4:1-12，耶和华对该隐说：‘你做了什么事呢？你兄弟的血的声音通过地向我哀告。地开了口，从你手里接受你兄弟的血。现在你必从这地受咒诅。你种地，地不再给你效力，你必流离飘荡在地上。’——译者注

[14]罗伯特·欧文（Robert Owen，1771—1858），英国的空想社会主义者、企业家、慈善家。代表作品有《新社会观》和《新道德世界书》。——译者注

[15]高教会派（High Churchmen），基督教新教圣公会派别之一。专指英格兰教会和英国国教会中的信徒，追随皮由兹运动。与“低教会派”对立。——译者注

[16]白色圣领体（white neck-cloth）源自牧师的穿着，牧师一般穿黑色长袍，脖子上戴着白色硬领，习惯上被称作罗马领，牧师在不穿长衫的时候也会把罗马领戴在普通的衬衫上，白色的罗马领成了他们身份的标签。——译者注

[17]福音派（Evangelical）：这个词始于16世纪，当时的宗教改教者以此称呼表明反对罗马天主教的立场。凡接受基督教新教信仰的人都被称为福音派，福音派重视圣经权威和学术研究，因其较罗马天主教更注重直接与上帝建立信约而不通过耶稣以外的任何人作中保，更加恪守传统教义。——译者注

[18]低教会派（Low Church）观点较倾向于清教徒而反对倾向于天主教，不赞成高教会派恢复旧制的倡导，认为主教制度、神职圣品与圣事礼仪相对而言并不重要，强调福音派及新教的做法。——译者注

[19]贵格会（Quaker）是基督教新教的一个教派，又称教友派或者公谊会。该派成立于17世纪，创始人为乔治·福克斯，因一名早期领袖的号诫“听到上帝的话而发抖”而得名Quaker，音译贵格会。该派反对任何形式的战争和暴力，不尊敬任何人也不要求别人尊敬自己，不起誓，主张任何人之间要像兄弟一样，主张和平主义和宗教自由。——译者注

[20]哈丽雅特·比彻·斯托夫人（Harriet Beecher Stowe，1811—1896），美国小说家，代表作是《汤姆叔叔的小屋》。——译者注

[21]现代仿古类（Modern-antique）小说的作者一般是胡乱设定某个历史场景作为故事背景，然后完全不考据，便将自己想写的东西套进该时代。——译者注

[22]雅尼和佯庇（Jannes and Jambres），埃及法老所御用的与摩西斗法的术士。——译者注

[23]西拿基立（Sennacherib），古亚述国的国王，公元前704至前681在位。——译者注

[24]出自歌德的《浮士德》。——译者注

[25]本文最早发表于1854年10月的《威斯敏斯特评论》（Westminster Re-view）。——译者注

[26]帕多瓦（Padua）：意大利北部城市。——译者注

[27]达钦夫人（也就是后来的勒费夫尔小姐Mademoiselle Le Fèvre）给克里斯汀娜女王（Queen Christina）寄过自己的卡里马科斯手抄本。女王这样给她回信：“大家都说你是一位漂亮讨喜的姑娘，但是你如此博学，你不知道女子无才便是德吗？你不为此感到羞愧吗？”

[28]黎塞留（Richelieu，1585—1642），法国宰相，法国历史上最伟大、最具谋略，也最无情的政治家。——译者注

[29]投石党运动（Fronde，音译为“福隆德”运动），Fronde是一种投石器，故又称投石党运动，是17世纪中叶在法国发生的反对专制王权的政治运动。运动可分两个时期：前期为1648—1649年高等法院福隆德运动；后期为1650—1653年亲王福隆德运动。——译者注

[30]洪布耶夫人（Madame Rambouillet，1588—1665），第一座文学沙龙是在1618年成立的，位于洪布耶夫人的府邸。洪布耶夫人原名凯瑟琳（Catherine de Vivonne），十二岁时嫁给洪布耶伯爵，来到法国亨利四世的宫廷之后，对于当时宫廷的粗俗生活感到惊讶和失望，于是决定在自己的家里主持沙龙。——译者注

[31]法国作家莫里哀（Molière）的两部喜剧作品。Précieuses原本的意思是有价值的女人或珍贵的女人，该词是用来嘲弄她们赋予许多没有价值的东西不该有的价值，首先是她们自己。——译者注

[32]拉罗什福科（La Rochefoucauld，1613—1680），17世纪法国古典作家，代表作有《箴言集》。——译者注

[33]鲍修埃（Bossuet，1629—1704），17世纪时主张君权神授的法国神学家、政治理论家。——译者注

[34]隆格维尔公爵夫人（Duchese de Longueville），原名安妮·德·波旁（Anne Geneviève de Bourbon，1619—1679），法国女王族，以貌美风流和在投石党内战中的影响而闻名。——译者注

[35]圣佩韦（Sainte-Beuve，1804—1869），法国19世纪文艺批评家。——译者注

[36]希波克拉底（Hippocrates），希腊名医，被称为医药之父。——译者注

[37]波尔罗亚尔信徒（Port-Royalists）：17世纪法国天主教约翰逊派教徒，活动中心在巴黎附近的波尔罗亚尔女隐修院。——译者注

[38]约翰逊主义（Jansenism）是罗马天主教在17世纪的运动，由康内留斯·奥图·约翰逊（Cornelius Otto Jansen，1585—1638）创立，其理论强调原罪、人类的全然败坏、恩典的必要和宿命论。——译者注

[39]保罗·斯卡龙（Paul Scarron，1610—1660），法国诗人、小说家、剧作家。——译者注

[40]克朗（crown），英国25便士的货币。——译者注

[41]布莱士·帕斯卡（Blaise Pascal，1623—1662），法国数学家、物理学家、思想家。——译者注

[42]我们所提到的这封信中有这样很妙的描写：“我对这个年龄的人恨得要命，他们认为我有追求女人的本事和手段，就好像我们比他们老一百岁似的，他们还处于对人类的问题特别惊讶的状态。”

[43]加尔文主义主张人类不能通过正义的行为获得救赎，恢复逐渐被天主教所遗弃的奥古斯丁学说“救恩独作说”。——译者注

[44]奥古斯丁主义涵盖宇宙论、恩宠论、圣事论、教会论、历史观等神学和哲学的领域，认为上帝是宇宙中唯一真实的存在，人类由于始祖犯罪，本性已经败坏，无力行善避恶，只有依靠上帝的恩宠才能得救。——译者注

[45]克洛德·阿德里安·爱尔维修（Claude Adrien Helvétius，1715—1771），18世纪法国哲学家、功利主义与唯物主义者。他的主要著作包括《论精神》和《论人的理智能力和教育》。——译者注

[46]加尔默罗会（Carmelites），又称圣衣会，会规要求会士安贫、守贞、服从、静默、斋戒。——译者注

[47]查尔斯·金斯利（Charles Kingsley，1819—1875），英国作家，代表作《向西去！》写于1855年，内容是伊丽莎白时代反对天主教和击败西班牙舰队的故事。——译者注

[48]训导型小说（Tendenz-Roman），指通过一定的故事或者说教而让读者接受某种观点，德国人将这种作品称为训导型小说。——译者注

[49]玛格丽特·富勒（Margaret Fuller，1810—1850），美国作家、评论家、社会改革家、早期女权运动领袖。她是新英格兰先验论派的著名成员。——译者注

[50]玛丽·沃斯通克拉夫特（Mary Wollstonecraft，1759—1797），18世纪的英国作家、哲学家和女权主义者。——译者注

[51]马勒普太太（Mrs.Malaprop），爱尔兰喜剧《情敌》中的人物，喜欢搬弄漂亮的词句，却不懂其含义，因此经常闹出笑话。人们普遍把用词不当称作马勒普风格。——译者注

[52]夏尔·傅立叶（Charles Fourier，1772—1837），法国空想社会主义者，代表作为《新的工业世界和社会事业》。——译者注

[53]《德雷德》（Dred：a tale of the great Dismal Swamp），全名《德雷德：阴暗的大沼地的故事》，出版于1865年。——译者注

[54]斯托夫人的另一部作品《汤姆叔叔的小屋》（Uncle Tom's Cabin）中的主角，发表于1863年。——译者注

[55]沃尔特·司各特（Sir Walter Scott，1771—1832），苏格兰历史小说家、诗人。——译者注

[56]奥古斯特·蒂尔里（Augustin Thierry，1795—1856），法国历史学家。——译者注

[57]又译《撒克逊劫后英雄传》。——译者注

[58]指奴隶从小被灌输敬畏上帝、逆来顺受、忠顺于主人这类的基督教说教。——译者注

[59]查尔斯·里德（Charles Reade，1814—1884），英国小说家、剧作家，代表作为《患难与忠诚》（The Cloister and the Hearth）。——译者注

[60]马基雅维利主义（Machiavelianism），又叫权术主义，主张为达目的可以不择手段。——译者注

[61]弗雷德里卡·布雷默（Fredrika Bremer，1801—1865），瑞典小说家，女权主义者。——译者注

[62]出自《威尼斯商人》第五幕第一景。——译者注

[63]出自《麦克白》第一幕第七景。——译者注

[64]科里奥兰纳斯（Coriolanus）是莎士比亚晚年创作的一出可与四大悲剧相媲美的古罗马历史悲剧《科里奥兰纳斯》中的人物。——译者注

[65]出自《科里奥兰纳斯》第五幕第六景。——译者注

译者导读

雅各布·布克哈特（Jacob Burckhardt，1818—1897），19世纪杰出的文化历史学家，出生于瑞士巴塞尔一个古老的名门望族家庭。1839年至1843年留学德国，获哲学博士学位。回国后，在巴塞尔大学执教，长期担任历史学与艺术史教席教授。1897年8月8日，在巴塞尔的寓所去世。布克哈特终生未婚，并一直定居巴塞尔。重点研究欧洲艺术史及人文主义。

布克哈特最重要的著作有《君士坦丁大帝时代》（Die Zeit Konstantin des Großen）（1853年）、《向导：意大利艺术品鉴赏导论》（Der Cicerone.EineAnleitung zum Genuß der Kunstwerke Italiens）（1855年）、《意大利文艺复兴时期的文化》（Die Kultur der Renaissance in Italien）（1860年），还有作者去世后由他人整理和出版的两部重要作品《世界历史沉思录》（Weltgeschichtliche Betrachtungen）和三卷本的《希腊文化史》（Griechische Kulturgeschichte）。其中最具代表性的是《意大利文艺复兴时期的文化》一书。文艺复兴是欧洲历史上具有重大意义的新文化运动。恩格斯评价为：“这是一次人类从未经历过的最伟大的、进步的变革。”[1]

布克哈特最突出的贡献是关于意大利文艺复兴运动的研究。欧洲的传统历史学家，一直到19世纪，都认为历史学的研究范围在于政治和军事；而文艺复兴属于思想、文学和艺术领域，在传统的历史学中没有地位。布克哈特在古典主义学派温克尔曼（Johann Joachim Winckelmanns）和歌德（Johann Wolfgang Goethe）等人的影响下，形成了以美学、人类学作为观察人类历史和思想的出发点的研究方式，这与前人过分重视政治和军事不同。德国埃森文化科学研究所所长、当代著名历史理论家耶尔恩·吕森在为《世界历史沉思录》中译本撰写的一篇长篇序言中，如此评价布克哈特：“他尝试把人类学当作历史思维的基础，并以此来代替历史哲学，从而发展了考察历史的新方法。”[2]

布克哈特的代表作《意大利文艺复兴时期的文化》是自伏尔泰以来，欧洲学术界第一部关于文艺复兴运动综合研究的专著，它奠定了近代西方历史学在此领域的正统理论，具有划时代意义。英国著名历史学家阿克顿勋爵评价此书是“现有著作中关于文化史的一部最深刻、最精确的研究著作”。

《意大利文艺复兴时期的文化》全书共有六篇，记述了从13世纪下半叶到16世纪中叶这300年间意大利文化的发展情况，依次阐述了政治、思想、学术、社交生活和道德宗教等方面的内容。本书收录的是《意大利文艺复兴时期的文化》的第一篇也是最长的一篇——“论作为艺术品的国家”，约占全书四分之一左右，下分10章，从不同侧面叙述了文艺复兴时期意大利的政治制度和政治形势。书中，布克哈特重视的不是具体的政治事件，而是影响社会变化的政治背景。这种以论述政治形势开始，接着介绍文化状况的撰史方法，为欧洲后来的文化史著述树立了一个范例。

《意大利文艺复兴时期的文化》自出版以来，各种译本风行不衰，以其经典的地位一直吸引着每一代读者。

引言

本书的题目从最严谨的字面意义来说是一篇论文的题目。作者比任何人都清楚他自己是以何等有限的方法和力量来进行如此艰巨的工作的。即使他能更自信地看待自己的研究，也很难由此就对获得有识之士的认可多一分把握。也许任何一种文化在每个人的眼中都会呈现出不同的画面；在探讨一种孕育了我们自身的、现在仍然在影响着我们的文化时，必然会随时显示出作者和读者个人的判断和感觉。正如我们在一望无际的大海上冒险航行时可能面临许多路线和方向，本书采用的研究材料在别人手中也很可能因处理方式和应用方式迥异，而得出截然不同的结论。的确，本课题非常重要，仍需进一步的探索，也许从不同的视角研究起来更具优势。如果有人耐心倾听，并对本书加以整体的评判，我们就很满足了。撰写文化史的最大困难在于，为了各方面易于理解，一个伟大的智识进程必须被分成一个个阶段，并且常常近乎武断地予以分门别类。我们原打算写一本专门论文艺复兴时期艺术的著作来弥补一些本书未及论述的内容——然而，此想法只得到部分的实现。教皇们与霍亨斯陶芬王朝之间的斗争使意大利处于一种与西方其他国家完全不同的政治环境中。在法国、西班牙和英格兰，封建制度组织极其严密，以至于当它解体时很自然地成为统一的君主制国家。在德国，封建制度至少有助于维持帝国表面上的统一；而意大利几乎已完全摆脱了封建制度。14世纪的历代皇帝，即使在最顺利的情况下，也不再是作为封建领主而是作为已存各势力可能的领袖和支柱，受到人们的承认和尊敬。而罗马教皇政权及其傀儡和同盟，有力量阻止未来的国家统一，本身却无力完成统一。在皇帝和教皇政权之间，有许多政治组织——共和国和专制君主国——一些历史较久，一些刚刚兴起，这些政治组织只是依靠维持自己生存的实力才得以存在。从它们身上，我们第一次觉察到欧洲的现代政治精神，即随心所欲以及经常呈现出的极端自私的最恶劣特征，侵害每一种权利，扼杀健康文化的每一个萌芽。但是无论在什么地方，只要阻止了或以任何方式补偿了这种邪恶的趋势，历史上就会出现一个新的事实——经过深思和谋算所产生的国家，作为一种艺术品的国家。这种新生活以千百种形式，在共和国家和专制国家中表现出来，也决定了他们的内部政治制度，还有国家的外交政策。我们的探讨范围仅限于由专制国家所表现出来的这种更完整、更明确的国家类型。

南意大利和西西里的诺曼帝国，在弗里德里克二世改革之后，为暴君统治下的国家的内部情况提供了一个令人难忘的近似写照。弗里德里克，这位首位登上王位宝座的现代型的统治者，由于成长于邻邦撒拉森人的叛乱和危险中，因此很早就习惯于非常客观地处理各种事务。他对撒拉森国家的内部局势和管理情况的熟悉以及与教皇的殊死斗争，迫使他及其对手倾尽全力应付此事。弗里德里克所采取的措施（尤其是在1231年之后），目的是完全摧毁封建政体，把人民变成无意志、无反抗手段却最能为国库带来收入的广大群众。他用一种在此之前整个西方国家无人知晓的方式，把整个司法权和行政权集于一身。任何职位的任用都不需要人民的选举，如有提出异议的地区，则摧毁其城池，把其居民变为奴隶，以示惩罚。各种赋税，根据综合评估以及伊斯兰教国家的做法，以残酷而严苛的方式来征收。的确，如果不以此方式，要想从东方人那儿收到钱是不可能的。简言之，在这里，我们看到的不是人民，而仅仅是一群唯命是从的臣民。比如，不经特别许可，不准与外国人结婚并且绝不允许在国外求学。那不勒斯大学是我们所知道的第一所限制学习自由的大学，而东方各国，在这些方面不管怎样是不限制他们的年轻人的。弗里德里克按照伊斯兰教国家统治者的做法，为了自己个人的利益，在地中海各地进行贸易，把许多商品垄断在自己手中，并以各种方式限制臣民的商业活动。法蒂玛王朝的哈里发们尽管不信仰秘教，但至少在初期，他们容忍人民的各种宗教信仰。而弗里德里克却通过设立审判异端的宗教法庭来建立他的政府体制。当我们记起他以异教徒之名迫害自治城市的自由民代表时，这种宗教法庭似乎更应予以谴责。最后，国内警察，还有对外作战的军队的核心，是由从西西里带到诺切拉和卢切拉的撒拉森人组成的——这些人对人民痛苦的呼声置若罔闻，并且也不在乎教堂的禁令。后期，人民因为久已不习武备，只好坐视曼弗雷的灭亡和安茹的查理攫取政权，后者发现这一体制行之有效，便继续使用。

这个实行中央集权政治的皇帝身边还出现了一个最令人感到奇怪的篡位者，即他的代理主教及女婿埃兹利诺·达·罗曼诺。他不是任何政府或组织的代表，因为他所有的活动都浪费在了北意大利东部地区的最高权力的争夺上。但是作为一种政治典型人物，他对于未来的重要性并不亚于他的保护人弗里德里克皇帝。在此之前发生在中世纪的征服和篡权，不是以真正或虚假的继承权为理由，就是以反对不信教者和开除教籍的人为借口。在这里，第一次公开通过大屠杀和无休止的暴行努力建立政权，总之，采用一切手段，只为达到最终目的。埃兹利诺的后继者们，甚至凯撒·波几亚，也比不上埃兹利诺所犯下的滔天大罪。但是先行者的榜样是不会被人忘记的，他的灭亡在各国并没带来正义的回归，也没有起到对后来篡位者的警示作用。

在这样一个时期，生为弗里德里克臣民的圣托马斯·阿奎那徒劳地创立了君主立宪的理论，提出君主应得到由自己命名的上议院的支持，并且君主是由人民选举产生的代表。这些理论在讲堂外得不到任何反响，并且弗里德里克和埃兹利诺过去是、现在仍然是意大利13世纪伟大的政治形象。他们那带有半传奇色彩的人物性格构成了《古代故事百篇》中最重要的主题，这本书无疑是在本世纪[3]创作的。在讲述埃兹利诺的故事中，由于他给人以威力无边的印象而让人心生敬畏。从亲历者的编年史到后来诗人们半神话式的悲剧作品，埃兹利诺的形象已成为整个文学的中心。

第一章　十四世纪的暴君

14世纪大大小小施行暴政的国家证明像这样的事例一直在持续。他们的恶行昭著，并且历史学家在其著作中不断详细描述。作为只能依靠自己而生存，并为此目的科学构建内部组织的国家，它们比历史故事更能引起我们的兴趣。

由于有目的地采用了当时意大利之外的君主未想到的手段，并把此手段与国内实行的几乎绝对的权力相结合，所以在暴君中产生了奇怪的人和奇怪的生活方式。一个精明的统治者治理国家的要诀是：尽可能在他所发现的或者在他起初安排的项目上征税。主要的收入来源包括：根据估定价值所征收的土地税、有明确数额的消费品税、进出口货物关税，还有统治家族的私有财产。税收增加的唯一可能性在于商业的发展和国家整体上的更加昌盛。像我们在自由城市里所见到的贷款，在这里是没有的。只要公信力不动摇，经过周密计划实行的没收所获得的钱财被认为是一种可取的筹款方式——例如，由迫使财政官下台并抢夺其财产这一真正东方人的方式来达到的一种目的。

从此收入中支出小朝廷、卫兵、雇佣军和公共建筑的费用，以及服侍君主个人的滑稽演员和其他有特长人员的费用。暴君统治的不合法使他陷于孤立，并不断被危险包围。他所结成的最值得尊敬的联盟就是有知识的人，而不管其出身。13世纪北方君主只限于对骑士和歌功颂德的贵族豪爽大方，而意大利的暴君做法不同。他渴望声名，热衷不朽的作品，因此他所需要的是才能，而不是出身。与诗人、学者为伍，他感觉自己处于一个新的位置，确实，他觉得自己几乎拥有了新的合法性。

在这方面，没有其他君主比维罗纳的统治者坎·格兰德·戴拉·斯卡拉更出名，此人在宫廷中招待著名的流亡者，在整个意大利的代表中是数一数二的。文人并非不感激。彼特拉克因拜谒这些人的宫廷一直受到的指责，描述了一幅14世纪君主的理想图画。他虽然向他的保护人帕多瓦君主提出很高的要求，但是他提出的方式却表明，他认为是君主是有能力实现的。

您一定不要做臣民的主人，而要做他们的父亲，像爱您自己的孩子、爱您自己的身体一样爱他们。武器、卫兵和军队，您可用来抵御敌人；而对于您的臣民，善意足矣。提到人民，当然，我指的是那些热爱现存秩序的人；至于那些每天渴望变革的人，他们是谋反者和叛徒，对他们要通过严苛的法律加以惩治。

接着，文章对国家的无限权力进行了详细、完全现代式的描述。君主应该掌管一切事务，维护和修建教堂和公共建筑，维持城市秩序，排净沼泽的水，监督酒类和粮食的供应；摊派捐税时，使人民认识到税收的必要性；他还要帮助病人和无助者，并保护和招待优秀学者，这些人影响到他后世声名的流传。

但是，这种制度不管有什么闪光点和个别统治者的优点，14世纪的人们仍然多多少少明显意识到这种大多数君主国家的短暂性和不确定性。由于像这样的政治组织机构的安全与其疆域的大小成正比，这样就驱使着较大的王国不断吞并较小的国家。当时，上百个小君主牺牲在了维斯康提这一个家族手中。这种外部的危险直接导致内部无休止的骚乱。这种局势对统治者的性格一般造成了最坏的影响。握有绝对的权力、沉溺于奢华、放纵自私，还有敌人及谋反者所带来的危险，所有这些不可避免地使他变成最坏的暴君。要是他能信任最近的亲戚就好了！但是在一切都不合法的情况下，无论是王位的继承，还是统治者财产的分配，都不可能有规范的继承法；因此，如果继承者无能或未成年，为了家族本身的利益，他就可能被更果敢坚定的叔伯或堂兄弟所取代。对私生子的承认或排除是争斗的根源，因此这些家庭大多数都被一群心存不满和伺机报复的族人所困扰。这种情况引起一次次叛乱和家族杀戮的可怕场面。有时，觊觎王位者流亡在国外，像维斯康提家族，当时在加达湖上捕鱼为生，却冷漠而又耐心地关注着国内的局势。当对手的使者询问他们中的一位，他考虑什么时候、以什么方式回米兰时，他回答道：“和当年驱逐我的那些人一样的方式，但要等到他的罪恶超过我当年罪恶的时候。”有时，暴君十分恶劣地违背了公众的道德，基于拯救家族的考虑，他被其亲属所杀，以平息他所引起的公愤。有几个这样的情况，政府掌握在整个家族手中或至少统治者必须要听从他们的意见，在这里，对财产和权势的分配也常常引起激烈的争夺。

这整个制度激起了当时佛罗伦萨的作家们深切而持久的仇恨。即使暴君用以给民众留下印象而不是满足自己虚荣心所举办的庆典排场，也引起了作家们最辛辣的嘲讽。有人胆敢冒险，如果落入作家手中，那就倒霉了。像比萨的崛起者阿盖罗总督（1364年），常常手持金杖，骑马出行，有时出现在王宫的窗口，让民众观看。“像遗物被展览”，他斜倚在绣花织物和软垫上，被跪着的侍从像服侍教皇或皇帝一样服侍着。然而，佛罗伦萨的老作家们常常以一种高傲的严肃语气来谈论这个话题。但丁清楚地看出新君主的野心勃勃与粗俗平庸。他们的喇叭和钟铃，他们的号角和长笛，有何意义？不过是警示“刽子手来了，抢劫者来了”。暴君的城堡像大家所想象的，是一座高耸孤零的建筑，里面布满了地牢和偷听管道，是残忍和痛苦之源。对于所有那些为暴君服务的人，已经预先被告知要遭到不幸，即使暴君自己也最终变成了让人可怜的对象，他们必然成为所有善良正直的人们的敌人，他不可能相信任何人，并且从他臣民的脸上能够读出期待他下台的信息。随着暴君专制国家的崛起、发展和巩固，在其中也暗暗滋长着注定使它们瓦解和灭亡的因素。但是还没谈到这种憎恨的最深层根源，佛罗伦萨当时是人类个性得到最丰富发展的地方，而对于暴君们，除了他们自己的以及最亲近依附者的个性外，不容忍其他人个性的存在和发展。严格实施对个人的控制，甚至建立了护照的制度。

许多暴君迷信占星术、不信仰宗教，在同时代人心中，这种被上帝舍弃的可怕的存在被涂上了一层怪异的色彩。当卡拉拉家族的最后一位君主不能再保卫遭受瘟疫袭击的帕多瓦的城墙和城门，四面又被威尼斯人所包围时（1405年），卫兵听到他对魔鬼喊道：“杀死我吧。”

从乔万尼大主教去世后（1354年），在米兰的维斯康提家族中无疑能发现14世纪最完整的、最具启示性的暴君专制的类型。贝尔那博和罗马最坏的皇帝家族是多么相像啊。当时人们生活的重中之重就是君主的野猪狩猎活动，不管是谁，只要妨碍狩猎，就施以极刑。满心恐惧的人们被迫喂养5000头猎犬，并要严格保证它们的健康和安全。君主想尽一切办法强征各种捐税；他的7个女儿每人得到一笔10万金弗罗林的嫁妆；他还搜刮了大量的金银珠宝。他妻子去世时（1384年），他向臣民发布一个告示，要他们分担他的哀伤（就像他们曾经分享他的快乐一样），并且要穿丧服一年。他的侄子吉安加利佐使他就范于自己权力之下的“突袭事件”（1385年）——至今仍使后世的历史学家惊心动魄的著名阴谋之一——清楚刻画出吉安加利佐的性格特征。

在吉安加利佐身上最大程度地表现出大部分暴君所具有的对修建巨大工程的狂热。他以30万金弗罗林为代价，承担了巨大堤坝的建造工程。必要时，把明乔河水从曼图亚改道，把布莱塔河水从帕多瓦改道，结果，致使这两个城市全无防御能力。事实上，他很可能考虑要排干威尼斯的湖水。他在帕维亚修建了女修道院中最好的切尔托莎修道院；并修建了雄伟壮丽超越基督教界所有教堂的米兰大教堂。帕维亚王宫由其父加利佐初建，他在位时竣工，很可能是欧洲王宫中最宏伟的。他把他著名的图书室和他所收集的大批圣贤遗物（对此他有一种奇怪的信仰）转移至此处。要是这种性格的君主对政治没有最高野心的话，那真让人感到奇怪。温切斯劳斯国王封他为大公（1395年），当他病逝时（1402年），他所渴望的只是意大利王国或帝国的王冠。据说，单单一年，他整个领地付给他除了120万金弗罗林的常规贡赋外，还有不少于80万金弗罗林的特别补贴。在他死后，他用各种武力统一起来的领地四分五裂了；并有一段时期，他的继任者连维持原来的核心王国都有困难。他的儿子乔万尼·马利亚（死于1412年）和菲利波·马利亚（死于1417年），若是生活在不同国家，或身处其他传统中，不好说会变成什么样的人；但是，作为这个家族的后嗣，他们继承了一代代积累的残忍和怯懦的可怕资产。

乔万尼·马利亚也以他的狗著称，然而这些狗不再用来打猎，而是专为撕扯人肉。它们的名字像皇帝瓦伦廷尼安一世的熊一样一一流传下来。1409年5月，当战事正酣，饥饿的人们在街上向他喊着“和平！和平！”时，他派雇佣军扑向他们，200人被夺取了生命；他禁止人们说“和平”和“战争”这两个词语，违者处以绞刑，加以严惩，并且命令牧师“赐给我们安宁”来取代“赐给我们和平”。最后，一群谋反者利用这个丧心病狂的统治者的雇佣兵大队长法西诺·凯内在帕维亚生病的时机，在米兰的圣哥达多教堂杀死了乔万尼·马利亚。同一天，奄奄一息的法西诺让其部下宣誓效忠继任者菲利波·马利亚，他自己要求他的妻子在他死后嫁给菲利波·马利亚，他妻子比阿特丽丝·第·丹达听从了他的劝告。在文章的后面我们要讲到菲利波·马利亚。

在这样的时期，柯拉·第·利恩奇梦想在腐朽的罗马居民摇摇晃晃的热情上建设一个即将危及整个意大利的新国家。他和我们已描述过的那些统治者相比，好像不过是个可怜的自欺欺人的傻瓜而已。

第二章　十五世纪的暴君专制

15世纪暴君专制国家的特点已有所改变。许多不太重要的暴君和一些较大的暴君，像斯卡拉和卡拉拉，都已灭亡；而靠征服别国变得更加强大的暴君们已使他们的制度得到各具特色的发展。例如，那不勒斯从新的阿拉戈纳王朝获得了一种新的更强大的推动力。这一新时代的显著特征是许多雇佣兵队长企图建立他们自己的独立王朝。人们不再考虑传统的评价，而只注重事实和事情之间的真实关系；才能和冒险是人人追求的目标。小国的暴君们，为了得到可信赖的靠山，开始服务于较大的国家，他们自己成了雇佣兵队长，作为效劳的回报，他们从这些大国领取金钱并且如果他们有不端行为，只要不是扩张本国领土，可以免受惩罚。所有暴君，无论大小，必须更加努力，其行为必须更加谨慎和深思，必须学会抑制住实施大规模暴行的冲动；舆论只容许为了实现大家期待的目标而必然会犯的错误，公正的旁观者当然不挑剔这种错误。在这里，看不到任何支持西方合法君主的那种半宗教式的忠诚的痕迹；我们所能发现的最接近这种忠诚的，是个人声望。才能和算计是前进道路上唯一的手段。像大胆查理那样，在狂热追求不切实际的目标中耗尽心力的性格，意大利人难于理解。“瑞士人只是些农民，如果全部被杀死，对有可能阵亡的勃艮第贵族们也不能补偿。如果勃艮第大公不战而拥有整个瑞士，他的收入也不会多加5000金币。查理性格中的中世纪特点、他身上所具有的骑士精神的抱负和理想，长期以来让意大利人难以理解。当南方的外交官们看到他殴打军官后，却还让他们继续服役；当他因军队打败仗而施以惩罚，以此虐待他们，而又在这些军人面前责备他的顾问官时，他们认为这个人已无任何希望。而路易十一，尽管其政策胜过意大利各君主按自己的方式所制定的政策，并且公开宣称自己是弗兰切斯科·斯福查的崇拜者，但在文化和优雅诸方面，人们认为他与这些统治者还相差甚远。

15世纪的意大利诸国中，美德与邪恶令人奇怪地并存。统治者的个性发展很充分，其个性往往又具有非常深刻的意义，并且极具那一时代社会状况和需求的特点，因此要对它作一恰当的道德判断并不是一件容易的事情。

这种暴君专制制度的基础过去是，现在也仍然是不合法的，并且没有什么能消除它身上的魔咒。皇帝的批准或者授权对此并无任何改变，因为暴君从国外某处或从过境的陌生人手中购买羊皮纸授权书这件事，人民对此并不以为然。要是皇帝对于任何事情都处理得当的话——依毫无判断力的常识的逻辑这样推论——他就根本不会让暴君兴起。自查理四世的罗马远征起，皇帝们在意大利除了批准那些不依靠他们帮助而兴起的暴君政权外，没有做任何事情；他们给予暴君专制的实际权威，除来自皇帝诏书之外，无其他任何方式。查理在意大利的整个行为是一场充满丑闻的政治喜剧。马提奥·维兰尼讲到维斯康提家族怎样陪查理游览他们的领地并且最后护送他出境，途中查理怎样为了得到钱，像小贩一样叫卖他的货物（特权等）；他在罗马的形象是多么庸俗小气，以及怎样在最后，甚至剑都没出鞘，就带着金银宝箱越过阿尔卑斯山满载而归。西吉斯蒙多来了，至少在第一次（1414年），怀着劝说教皇约翰二十三世参加他的议会的美好愿望。就在旅途中，当教皇和皇帝从克雷莫纳的高塔上眺望伦巴第的景色时，他们的东道主，暴君加比诺·丰多洛满心想的是把两人推下高塔。第二次，西吉斯蒙多只是作为一个冒险家来到意大利，半年多的时间里，他都像不敢出门的欠债者一样在锡耶纳闭门不出；克服重重困难，后来才在罗马成功加冕。那么想一想弗里德里克三世，又是什么情况呢？正是那些想让他确认其特权或者为了满足其招待过皇帝的虚荣心的那些人，使他的意大利之行充满了假期旅行或短途游乐的气氛。后者就像那不勒斯的阿尔方索，他为了皇帝访问的荣耀而付出15万弗罗林。在费拉拉，当弗里德里克第二次从罗马归来时（1469年），一整天没离开他的房间，颁发了不少于80个头衔，他授封了骑士、伯爵、博士、公证人——伯爵，实际上分有不同等级，例如，有宫廷伯爵，还有有权授封至多五个博士的伯爵，以及有权予以私生子合法地位和任命公证人的伯爵，等等。作为回报，这位颁发头衔的人期望从这些封赠中得到获取报酬的特权，而这在费拉拉被认为是过多了。当博尔索的皇室庇护人给所有小朝廷颁发头衔和委任状时，他也被册封为摩德纳和勒佐公爵；作为回报，他每年需缴纳4000金弗罗林，博尔索对此事的想法，并未提及。人文主义者，也就是那个时代的主要发言人，根据个人的利益，对于此事的看法有所分歧，而其中几人以罗马皇室的诗人们常用的歌颂向皇帝表示致敬。波吉奥坦承，他不再知道加冕典礼有什么意义；在古时候，只有凯旋的大将军才被加冕，那时他被用桂冠加冕。

马克西米利安一世即位后，不仅开始了对外国的普遍干涉，而且开始实施针对意大利的新的帝国政策。第一步——授封洛多维科·摩罗为米兰大公和除掉他那不幸的侄子——就不是一个有好结果的措施。按照现代的干涉理论，当两方正在争斗瓜分一个国家时，就可能有第三方插手进来并获取自己的那份利益。罗马帝国就是按照这个原则来采取行动的，但人们却不再诉诸公理和正义。当人们期待路易十二到热那亚时（1502年），帝国之鹰从公爵宫殿的大殿上被除掉而代之以彩绘的百合花。历史学家塞纳雷加问及侥幸逃过那么多变乱而留下来的鹰究竟有什么意义、帝国对于热那亚提出什么要求时，除了“热那亚是帝国的账房”这句老生常谈外，没人有更多的了解。最后，当查理五世把西班牙和帝国合并起来时，他能够凭借西班牙的军事力量提出帝国的要求，但臭名昭著的是他由此所得并非给帝国，而是给西班牙君主国带来了利益。

与15世纪各个朝代政治上的非婚生身份有密切关系的是民众对于合法婚生身份的不在乎态度，这一点对于外国人来说——例如，科米斯——似乎非常不寻常。这二者自然并行不悖。在北方国家，像在勃艮第，私生子的后代依靠独特的附属封地为生，如主教管区之类；在葡萄牙，非婚生世系只能通过不断的努力在王位上延续下去；在意大利，情况相反，已没有即使在直系后代中也不容许私生子存在的王室家族。那不勒斯的阿拉戈纳世系的君主们属于非婚生世系，阿拉戈纳王国本身传给了阿尔方索一世的兄弟。也许乌尔比诺的伟大的弗里德里克根本就不是蒙特费尔特罗家族的后裔。当教皇庇护二世在去曼图亚会议（1459年）的路上时，伊斯特王室家族的八个私生子在费拉拉骑马去迎接他，其中有在位的博尔索大公本人和他的非婚生兄弟、前任大公利奥纳洛的两个私生子。利奥纳洛也曾经有一个妻子，是那不勒斯的阿尔方索一世和一个非洲女人的私生女。当婚生子女年幼而同时国内局势处于生死存亡之际，私生子往往被允许继承王位；年长者的统治开始被承认，而不再考虑其出身的纯正与否。个人的健康、价值和能力比在西方其他地方盛行的所有法律和惯例都更重要。确实，那正是教皇的儿子们正在建立王朝的时代。16世纪，由于国外的思想和当时开始的反宗教改革运动的影响，整个问题才得以更严格地判断。瓦尔奇发现：婚生子对于王位的继承是“理智所赋予的，并且是上帝的旨意”。红衣主教伊波利托·得·美第奇基于他也许是一个合法婚姻所生的后代，并且无论如何是一个淑女的儿子，而不像阿利桑德罗大公是一个女佣的儿子这个事实，提出佛罗伦萨君主权要求。这时开始了在15世纪，无论在政治的或道德的基础上都是毫无意义的上层社会男子与下层社会女子的恋爱婚姻。

但是15世纪最高的和最受人仰慕的非婚生形式是雇佣兵队长，他无论是什么出身，自己已升到了独立的统治者的地位。说到底，诺曼人在11世纪占领南意大利就属于这一性质。那时这种企图开始使这个半岛处于不断的动荡中。

一个雇佣兵队长在他的雇主由于缺乏金钱或者军队而以此方式为他提供生计时，即使不经过夺权，也有可能获得一个地方的君主身份。雇佣兵队长，无论在何种情况下，即使暂时解散了他的大部分军队，也需要一个能够建立冬营并储藏军需物品的安全地方，第一个获得这样的君主身份的队长是约翰·霍克伍德，他被教皇格雷戈里十一世封为巴尼亚那卡瓦洛和科蒂尼约拉地方的君主。当意大利的军队和统治者们与阿伯利哥·达·巴比亚诺的共同势力开始强大时，就有了更多建立一个公国或者扩张一个已建立公国的机会。第一次血腥的重大军事暴乱发生在吉安加利佐死后（1402年）的米兰公国。他的两个儿子所施行政策的目的，主要是消灭雇佣兵队长们所建立的新暴君专制政权；从这些雇佣兵队长中最大的法西诺那里，维斯康提家族继承了很多城市和40万金弗罗林，以及法西诺的寡妇，不用说还有比阿特丽丝·第·丹达所带来的她前夫的士兵。从那时起，15世纪所特有的、政府和它们的雇佣兵队长之间的完全不道德的关系变得越来越普遍。一个虚虚实实、影影绰绰的老故事对此有如下描述：某城市（好像指的是锡耶纳）的人们曾有一个为他们服务的军官，这名军官曾从外来侵略中解放了他们，每天这些人都在商议怎样回报他，商议的结果是，他们的力量太微弱，即使选他做那个城市的君主，也不足以酬报他的恩德。最后，其中一人站起来说：“让我们杀了他，然后把他当作我们的庇护圣徒来崇拜吧！”然后他们这样做了，仿照罗马元老院处置罗慕路斯的先例。事实上，雇佣兵队长们有理由最畏惧他们的主人。如果他们打了胜仗，他们就成了危险人物，就像罗伯托·马拉泰斯达，为教皇西克塔斯四世打了胜仗后就被处死（1482年）；如果他们打了败仗，威尼斯人对卡马尼约拉的报复给他们显示了他们会有什么样的危险（1432年）。这种处境道德上的特点是，雇佣兵队长常常不得不把他们的妻子儿女当人质，尽管如此，他们不仅自己不放心，别人对他们也不放心。他们必须一直是克制私欲的英雄，本性像贝利撒留将军那样，不为仇恨和怨毒所腐蚀；只有最完美的优秀品质才能拯救他们免于罪大恶极。那么我们如果发现他们对一切神圣的事物充满蔑视，对他们的同胞——那些不关心自己是否会死于教会禁令的人——残忍而奸诈，就不会感到奇怪了。与此同时，迫于这种形势，他们中许多人的天才和能力获得了能想象到的最高度发展，并为他们赢得了部下的景仰和献身。他们的军队是现代历史上第一支以统帅的人格魅力为唯一动力的军队。弗兰切斯科·斯福查的一生就是一个光辉的典范；对他出身的任何偏见都不能阻止他必要时从他所打交道的每一个人那里赢得无限忠诚并加以利用；不止一次，他的敌人一看到他，就放下了武器，恭敬地脱帽向他致意，每人都尊敬他为“所有军人共同的父亲”。斯福查家族有这种特别的，从它家族历史一开始，我们似乎就能追溯到的努力追求王冠的兴趣。这个家族的幸运基于家庭中惊人的人丁兴旺。弗兰切斯科的父亲亚科波本人就是一个名人，他有20个兄弟姊妹，都在法恩扎附近的科蒂尼约拉没经过多少管教地长大，在他们成长过程中，一直处于自己家族和帕索利尼家族之间在罗马尼约尔的无尽的族间仇杀的危险之中。全家人的住处只不过是一个军火库和堡垒，母亲和女儿们都像家中男子一样地尚武好战。亚科波13岁时，离家逃到班尼加尔的教皇雇佣兵队长博尔德利诺那里——此人甚至死后还在继续领导他的军队，命令从停放着涂有香膏的遗体的营帐中发出，直至最后找到了合适的统帅来接替他。当亚科波在为不同的雇佣兵队长服务中最终使自己变得实力强大时，他派人把他的亲属找到一起，并从他们那里获得了如同一个君主从人口众多的王国那里所得到的同样的好处。当他被俘在那不勒斯的乌奥沃城堡里做阶下囚时，是他的亲属保住了军队免于解散。他妹妹亲手拘捕王室使者，并把他们关进监狱，以这种报复手段拯救了他的生命。亚科波在金钱问题上绝对值得信赖这件事，表明他做事深谋远虑；甚至在他打了败仗的时候，他都能从银行家那里得到钱。他经常保护农民免遭军队的骚扰，并且情非得已才摧毁或破坏一个被占领的城市。他为了免除与王室姻亲联盟关系的束缚，让他众所周知的情妇，即弗兰切斯科的母亲露西亚嫁给了别人。即使他亲属的婚姻也都是按照一定的计划来安排的。他远离同时代人的邪恶放纵的生活，并抚养儿子弗兰切斯科，遵从三条诫律：“不要染指别人的妻子；不要殴打你的追随者，或者如果你打了他，就把受伤的人发配远方；不要骑难咬马嚼子的马或脱落了蹄铁的马。”但他的影响力主要源自他即使不是一个伟大的将军，至少他也拥有一个伟大的军人所具有的品质。他的体格孔武有力，并且通过各种锻炼得到增强；他那一张农民的面孔和坦率直白的性格赢得大众的欢迎；他的记忆力惊人，经过多年之后仍能记起部下的姓名、他们马匹的数目和他们薪俸的数目。他所受的教育纯粹是意大利式的：他利用闲暇时间研读历史，并命人翻译了许多希腊语和拉丁语作品以供参考。弗兰切斯科，他那比他还著名的儿子，从一开始就决心建立一个强大的国家，并且通过其卓越的统率才能和对任何事都毫不犹豫的奸诈作风，拥有了米兰这座伟大的城市（1447—1450）。

他的榜样具有感染力量。伊尼亚斯·希尔维优斯对于这一时期曾写道：“在我们这热爱变革的意大利，在这个没有任何事情是一成不变的地方，在这个古代的王朝已不存在的地方，一个佣人轻易地就能变成国王。”有一个特别的标榜自己是“幸运之人”的人，让全国人们充满了想象：他是尼科洛的儿子亚科波·皮奇尼诺。他是否也能成功建立一个王室，这是一个当时激起激烈争论的问题。较大的国家明显要阻止它，甚至弗兰切斯科·斯福查也认为那张自我封君的名单最好不要再扩大了。但是在当时，例如，亚科波·皮奇尼诺想要做锡耶纳的君主时，那些被派去攻打他的兵士和队长们却意识到拥护他对他们自己有利：“要是他完蛋了，我们就不得不回家去种地。”甚至把他围困在奥贝泰罗期间，他们还给他给养；并且他体面地脱离了困境。但是最终命运突袭了他。在他（1465年）访问了米兰的斯福查之后，去那不勒斯的费兰特国王那里的时候，全意大利都在就他此行的结果打赌。尽管他得到过保证，尽管他和权贵有联系，他还是在乌奥沃城堡里被人谋杀了。连通过继承而获得领地的雇佣兵队长也从来没有感到他们自己是安全的。当罗伯托·马拉泰斯达和乌尔比诺的菲德利哥，一个在罗马，另一个在波洛尼亚，在同一天去世的时候（1482年），人们发现他们曾建议把自己的国家交给对方来治理。为反对胆大妄为之人所做的任何事都被认为是允许的。弗兰切斯科·斯福查年轻时娶了一个富有的卡拉布里亚女继承人波丽森娜·露莎，即蒙达多女伯爵，生下一个女儿；而她的姑母却毒死了母女二人，从而攫取了继承权。

自皮奇尼诺死后，由雇佣兵队长建立新国家的所作所为成了一件令人不能容忍的丑事。四个伟大的政权，那不勒斯、米兰、教皇政权和威尼斯，在它们之间形成了一种不容许有任何干扰的政治均衡。在教皇的属邦里，蜂拥着许多小暴君。其中部分是，或者曾经是雇佣兵队长，自教皇西克塔斯四世的时代以来，历任教皇的侄子们独占了所有这些暴君所承担事务的权利。但是一有政治危机的苗头，这些做过雇佣兵队长的军人们就又出现在现场。在教皇英诺森八世的邪恶治理下，有一个从前曾在勃艮第军队中服役的叫博卡利诺的人，几乎要把自己及其统治下的奥西莫镇献给了土耳其军队；幸运的是，由于庄严之人洛伦佐的干涉，他愿意拿到一笔钱后离去。在1495年，当查理八世的战争把意大利搞得天翻地覆时，布雷西亚的雇佣兵队长维多韦罗试了试自己的实力：他已经夺取了切泽纳市镇并屠杀了很多贵族和自由民；但却没攻下城堡而被迫撤退。然后他率领着另外一个恶棍——已经谈到过的罗伯托的儿子、威尼斯的雇佣兵队长、里米尼的潘多福·马拉泰斯达——借给他的一队人马，从拉文纳的大主教那里强夺了乌奥沃城堡。威尼斯人，恐怕情况变得更糟糕，也是受教皇的催促，命令潘多福，“怀有最善良的意愿”利用一个机会逮捕了他的好朋友维多韦罗：尽管逮捕是“怀着深深的遗憾”进行的，但接着传来了把他送到绞刑架上的命令。潘多福体贴地在监狱里先勒死了他，然后把尸体给人们看。这种篡位者的最后一个引人注目的例子是著名的慕索城堡总管，他在帕维亚之战（1525年）后的米兰领地的混乱中，在科莫湖畔临时拥有了统治权。

第三章　小专制国家

关于15世纪的暴君专制，一般可以说，最大的罪恶常常发生在最小的国家。在这些家族人口众多、并且所有成员都希望以适合他们身份的方式生活的小国家里，有关继承权的争端不可避免。加米里诺的伯尔那多·瓦拉诺处死了他的两个弟兄（1434年），想要把他们的财产分给他自己的儿子们。如果某一个城镇的统治者以英明、温和和仁慈的政治以及对知识文化的热情而著称，一般情况下，他要么是某个大家族的一员，要么在政治上依靠那个大家族。例如，阿利桑德罗·斯福查（死于1473年）就是这样的情况。他是佩扎罗的君主，伟大的弗兰切斯科的兄弟，乌尔比诺的菲德利哥的继父。由于管理上谨慎、治理措施公正仁慈，所以经过数年战乱以后，他享有安定的统治，建立了宏伟的图书馆，并在知识或宗教问题的对话中消磨闲暇时光。属于同样情况的另一个人是乔万尼二世，波洛尼亚的本蒂伏利奥（1462—1506），他的政策取决于伊斯特和斯福查两个家族的政策。另一方面，在加米里诺的瓦拉诺家族、里米尼的马拉泰斯达家族、法恩扎的曼弗雷家族中间，尤其是在佩鲁贾的巴利奥家族中间，却让人看到了多么残忍和血腥的暴行。我们在格拉齐亚尼和马达拉佐令人赞美的历史记载中，看到上述最后一个家族在15世纪末所做事件的惊人写照。

巴利奥家族是那些从未采取公开宣称的暴君专制形式的家族之一。它倒是通过其巨大财富和对挑选官员的实际影响来行使领导权。在家族内部，有一个人被承认为首领，但在不同族系的成员中间却深藏着嫉妒。在巴利奥家族的对立面，是由奥地家族领导的另一个贵族党派。1487年，佩鲁贾城变成了军营，豪门望族的家里挤满了亡命之徒，暴乱事件每天都在发生。在一个死于暗杀的德意志学生的葬礼上，两所大学的学生拿起武器兵戎相见；有时住在不同家里的亡命之徒甚至在广场上打起来。商人和工人抱怨也没用；罗马教皇派来的治理者和“亲族”或保持缄默，或一遇到机会就离去。最终奥地家族被迫放弃了佩鲁贾，而这个城市在巴利奥家族——他们甚至把大教堂当兵营——的绝对专制统治下变成了一个被围困的要塞。密谋和偷袭遭到灭绝人性的报复；1491年，在处死了130名冲入城内的叛乱者并陈尸于市政厅前之后，他们在广场上建起了35个祭坛，一连三天举行弥撒和宗教游行，以消除施于此地的魔咒。教皇英诺森八世的一个侄子于光天化日之下在街上被刺杀；被派来此地平息事端的亚历山大六世的一个侄子，由于民众的公然蔑视而被斥退。在这一时期，这个统治家族的两个首领，圭多和利都弗，正在和一个拥有圣徒之名和超自然能力的多密尼克会修女里埃蒂的科伦芭频繁会晤。她命令他们和解，否则会遭到大灾祸的惩罚——这自然是徒劳的。尽管如此，在编年史中却也给在这个恐怖的统治时期佩鲁贾城中一些较好人士的奉献精神和虔诚行为留下一席之地。当1494年查理八世兵临城下时，佩鲁贾的巴利奥家族和在阿西西城内及其附近宿营的流亡者进行了非常残酷的战争，以致山谷中的的每一间房子都被夷为平地。田地无人耕种，农民变成杀人越货的野人，新长起来的灌木丛中都是牡鹿和狼群，这些野兽靠吃死去的战士尸体——所谓“基督徒肉”而膘肥体壮。当教皇亚历山大六世在查理八世面前撤退（1495年）到翁布里亚的时候，后者当时刚从那不勒斯归来，在佩鲁贾，他发现现在他可以一劳永逸地把巴利奥家族除掉。他向圭多提议举行一个庆典或一个比赛，或者其他类似的集会，这样可以把整个家族聚在一起。然而，圭多却持有这一观点，即“最感人的壮观场面将是看到集合到一起的佩鲁贾的全部武装力量”，因此教皇放弃了他的计划。不久，流亡者们进行了第二次袭击，并且只靠巴利奥家族的个人英勇行为就打败了他们，取得了胜利。就在当时，西蒙那多·巴利奥，一个刚满18岁的小伙子，带着几个部下在广场上和数百敌人作战：最后他身上带着20多处伤倒下了；但当阿斯多利·巴利奥来增援时，他再次站起，身穿镀金盔甲，头戴饰有猎鹰的头盔，跨上战马，“忍耐力和行为俨如战神，投身于战斗中”。

此时，拉斐尔，一个12岁的孩子，正在彼埃特罗·佩路基诺门下求学。这些日子的印象也许通过他早期的圣米凯尔和圣乔治这些小画而永留人世；可能是这些印象中的某些东西永远留存在他的圣米凯尔的大型画幅中；如果说阿斯多利·巴利奥在某处被尊封为神的形象，那就是在拉斐尔的壁画——赫利奥多路斯——里边的天廷骑马勇士的形象。

巴利奥家族敌对者的一部分在恐怖时期被消灭，一部分逃散，因此没有能力再进行这种冒险行为。过了一段时间，达成了部分和解，一些流亡者被准许回来。但佩鲁贾并未变得更安全或更稳定：统治家族的内部倾轧以可怕的暴行形式爆发。两个圭多和利都弗的侄孙，也就是格里丰和卡洛·巴奇格利亚——后者是加米里诺君主瓦拉诺的侄子并且也是以前的一个流亡者耶罗尼莫·德拉·潘那的姐夫——组成反对派，对抗圭多和利都弗以及他们的儿子们吉安保罗、西蒙那多、阿斯多利、吉斯蒙多、贞提尔、马堪托尼奥，等等。西蒙那多为预感到一种不祥，跪请他的叔父准许他把潘那杀死，但他此举徒劳：圭多拒绝了。阴谋突然在1500年仲夏，趁阿斯多利和拉维尼亚·柯伦纳结婚这个时机得逞了。结婚庆典开始并且在阴郁的预示中持续了几天，马达拉佐极好地描写了这些预示的越来越深的影响。瓦拉诺用恶魔般的机智酝酿并促进了阴谋的形成：他以独掌大权的前景和捏造格里丰的妻子珍诺比娅与吉安保罗私通的故事来做格里丰的工作。最后，两个叛乱者每人都选定了自己的袭击目标。（巴利奥家族所有人都各自住在自己的房子里，大部分都在现在的城堡旧址上。）他俩每人带领15名刺客，其余的人则被派去放哨。在7月15日夜间，他们破门而入，谋杀了圭多、阿斯多利、西蒙那多和吉斯蒙多，其余的人逃掉了。

当阿斯多利的尸体在街市上被陈列在西蒙那多的尸体旁边时，围观者们，“尤其是外国学生”，把他比作古代的罗马人——他看起来是如此高大、仪表堂堂。在西蒙那多的面容上仍能看出就是死神也不能驯服的冒险和挑战的精神。胜利者们到处去走访这个家族的朋友们，并竭尽全力把自己推荐给他们；但他们发现所有的人都在流泪并且准备搬往乡间去。同时，逃跑的巴利奥家族聚集起失去城市的兵力，第二天由吉安保罗率领攻入城内，并迅速在巴奇格利亚以死相威胁的人中找到了追随者。当格里丰在圣艾科罗诺教堂附近落入他们手中的时候，吉安保罗把他交给了他的部下去处死。巴奇格利亚和潘那逃去投奔在加米里诺的瓦拉诺，他是这场悲剧的主要作者；顷刻之间，几乎没有遭受任何损失，吉安保罗成了这座城市的主人。

阿塔兰达，格里丰的依然年轻貌美的母亲，前一天刚刚和格里丰的妻子珍诺比娅还有吉安保罗的两个孩子撤退到乡下的住宅，她曾不止一次以母亲的身份咒骂斥责儿子，现在她和儿媳回到城里来找寻那奄奄一息的人。当这两个女人走近的时候，所有的人躲在一边，每个人都不敢向前，害怕被认出是杀害格里丰的凶手，受到这位母亲的诅咒。但是他们想错了：她自己恳求儿子宽恕那个致他于死地的人，然后儿子带着母亲的祝福死去。人们恭敬地目送这两个穿着有血污的衣裙的女人走过广场。拉斐尔后来画的闻名世界的《耶稣圣尸降架》就是为阿塔兰达所作的，画中她把自己母亲的悲痛敬献在一个更崇高、更神圣的苦难的脚下。

与悲剧发生地相毗邻的大教堂，被酒冲洗过，重新变成圣地。为婚礼而建的凯旋门依然矗立着，上面绘有阿斯多利的事迹和诗人马达拉佐对其颂扬的诗句。

讲述这些暴行的一种传说从巴利奥家族的早期就开始出现。据说，这个家族的所有成员从一开始就不祥地死去——一次就死了27人；有人说他们的房子从前曾被夷为平地，并且佩鲁贾的街道就是用这些砖铺筑的——还有更多这一类的说法。在教皇保罗三世统治下，他们的宫殿真的毁灭了。

曾有一个时期，他们似乎已形成好的决议，似乎已整顿好自己的党派，并已经保护官吏们不受贵族阶层的专横行为的欺压。但过去的诅咒像郁积的怒火一样再次显示了威力。1520年，吉安保罗被诱惑去了教皇列奥十世统治下的罗马，在那里被砍头。他的一个儿子，欧拉齐奥，只在佩鲁贾统治了很短一个时期，并且作为乌尔比诺大公（大公本人也受到了教皇的威胁）的死党，又一次在自己的家族中用最暴力的手段重复了过去的恐怖。他谋杀了他的叔父和三个堂兄弟，以致大公派人告诉他做得过火了。他的兄弟，马拉泰斯达·巴利奥，佛罗伦萨的将军，因1530年的投敌叛国事件而名载史册。马拉泰斯达的儿子利都弗，这个家族的最后一代，通过1534年谋杀教皇使节和官吏而获得了短暂但血腥的统治时期。

我们到处都会遇到里米尼的统治者们的名字。像西吉斯蒙多·马拉泰斯达（死于1467年）一样，一个既肆无忌惮、不敬神灵，又具有军事才能和高度文化的人，是很少见的。但这样一个家族积聚的罪恶最后必将超过才能，不管有多大的才能，都会被这个暴君拖入无底深渊。上面所提到过的西吉斯蒙多的侄子潘多福，成功地保住了自己的地位，原因只有一个，即不管雇佣兵队长被控犯有什么样的罪行，威尼斯人拒绝放弃他；当他的臣民被深深激怒后炮轰他在里米尼的城堡（1497年），后又让他逃掉的时候，尽管他因杀害弟兄和其他暴行而罪行累累，一个威尼斯的长官还是把他带了回来。30年后，马拉泰斯达家族成了不名一文的流亡者。1527年，像在凯撒·波几亚的时代那样，一种瘟疫降临到这些小暴君身上；他们没有几个人活下来，而且没人有好下场。在皮科家族弱小的君主统治下的米朗多拉，1533年，有一个穷学者利略·格雷戈里·吉拉尔第从罗马逃难到了著名的乔万尼的侄子、年迈好客的乔万尼·弗兰切斯科·皮科家里；在关于这个君主正在为自己建立的墓碑的讨论结束后，他写了一篇碑文，这篇碑文题献的日期是这一年的四月。碑文的后记语气沉痛——“今年十月，不幸的君主在夜间遭到侄儿的袭击，并被夺取了生命和王位；而我侥幸脱险，此刻正处在痛苦的深渊中。”

像潘多福·佩特路奇从1490年起在锡耶纳所实行，后来由于派系斗争而分裂的那种没有典型特征的伪暴君专制几乎不值得密切关注。他弱小而恶毒，在一个法学教授和占星术家的帮助下进行统治，不时进行谋杀以恐吓臣民。他夏日的消遣是从阿绵达的山顶向下滚大石块，从不在乎砸到什么东西或什么人。他虽然成功逃脱了凯撒波几亚所设的陷阱；但在死时，仍旧被人唾弃鄙视。他的儿子们在此后许多年内维持着一个合格的统治权。

第四章　大王朝

论及意大利的主要王朝，因阿拉戈纳王朝本身的特点，把它与其他王朝分开讨论较为方便。始于诺曼人时期、以贵族为地方最高权力的形式而延续下来的封建制度，给那不勒斯的政治制度以一种鲜明的色彩；而意大利的其他地方，除了只是教皇领地的南部地区和少数其他地区外，都实行土地的直接使用权，并且法律明令禁止继承权。从1435年以来在那不勒斯统治的大阿尔方索（死于1458年），与他真正或假称的后人不同。他一生辉煌，不怕和人民密切来往，与人交往时态度高贵和蔼，即使在年老时与露克瑞佳·德·阿莱尼亚的恋爱，也是让人称羡而非受人谴责；但是，他奢靡浪费的坏品质，自然会给他带来恶果。肆无忌惮的财政官们在宫中长期握有无限权力，直到破产的国王掠夺了他们的赃款；鼓吹进行宗教改革运动借以向教士们征税；当阿布鲁齐发生大地震时，幸存者被迫赔付死者的税款。通过这些手段，阿尔方索能够以无与伦比的豪华排场来款待显贵的客人；他在无休止的花费中得到快乐，即使让他的敌人受益，并且在文学作品的奖励方面，根本没有任何分寸。波吉奥因翻译色诺芬的《希腊远征波斯记》而得到了500枚金币。

继承他王位的费兰特，是他和一个西班牙女人所生的私生子，但也很可能是瓦伦西亚混血的摩尔人的儿子。不管是他的血统，还是贵族们所设计的谋害他的阴谋使他的性格变得恶毒阴险，他的残酷暴行在同时代的君主中无人能敌。他积极活跃、不知疲倦，被认为是当时最有势力的政治人物之一。没有荒淫挥霍的恶癖，他集中全部力量——其中包括深藏不露和一种势不两立的复仇精神——消灭他的反对者。他受到了全面攻击，因为那些贵族首领们虽然和他有姻亲关系，但也是他的外国敌人的同盟者。采取极端措施成了他日常政策的一部分。他与贵族进行斗争以及聚敛对外战争所需财力的方式，与弗里德里克二世所引入的伊斯兰教国的方式相同：政府专营油和谷类粮食；国家的整个商业由费兰特交由富商弗兰切斯科·科伯拉掌管；科伯拉控制全部海岸的停泊税，并和国王分享利润。财政亏空由强制的贷款、处死刑后没收的财产、公开买卖圣职和向教会团体征收的捐献来弥补。除了不顾所有财产权而进行的狩猎以外，费兰特还有两种乐趣：他喜欢让反对者在他近旁，活着时被关在警卫森严的监狱里；死后尸体涂上香膏防腐，并身穿死者生前所穿的服装。和朋友们谈到这些俘虏时，他常常开心地笑，并且对于他的木乃伊博物馆的任何事毫不隐瞒。他的受害者大多是由于他的背信弃义而落入虎口的人，有些甚至是在御宴上做客时被拘捕的。他对待首相——安多尼洛·佩特路奇——简直是魔鬼的行为。佩特路奇在任时已变得衰老多病，因为日益惧怕死亡而被他不断地勒索“礼物”。最后，因怀疑他参与贵族们最近一次的阴谋，使他找到了逮捕佩特路奇并处以死刑的借口；和他一起死去的有科伯拉。加拉奇奥罗和波吉奥关于所有这一切的叙述方式使人毛骨悚然。

国王的长子，卡拉布里亚大公阿尔方索，在父亲晚年时和他共同执政。他是一个野蛮残暴的浪子，只在坦率这一点上胜过费兰特，他公开宣称对宗教及其习俗的蔑视。意大利专制政权较好和较高贵的特征在这一世系的君主中不会被发现；他们对于他们那个时代的艺术和文化所拥有的一切只是为了奢侈和炫耀。即使真正的西班牙人也几乎总是在意大利堕落；但是这个杂种王室（1494年和1503年）的终结清楚证明它缺乏纯正的血统。费兰特死于精神疾患；阿尔方索以叛国罪指控他的兄弟菲德利哥——这个家族中唯一诚实的人——并以最卑劣的方式侮辱他。尽管阿尔方索到此为止被认为是意大利最有才干的将军之一，但最终他逃到西西里并丢了脑袋；他留下的儿子小费兰特成了法国人和国内叛国者的猎物。像这样的王朝，如果它的子孙想要恢复大业，至少必须和敌人进行殊死的战斗。不过，如科米斯在这件事上所说的——这说法虽然片面但大体正确，“残暴的人从来不会是勇敢的”：没有更残忍的人了。

米兰大公们的专制政治——其统治从吉安加利佐时代以来就是一种最彻底的君主专制制度——显示出15世纪真正的意大利特征。维斯康提家族的最后一个统治者菲利波·马利亚（1412—1447）是一个有着奇特兴趣的人物，幸而给我们留下了一些关于他这种兴趣的描述。一个具有非凡才能和崇高地位的人能因极度恐惧变成什么样子，在这里用可称作数学上的完备性显现出来。国家的全部资源只为一个目的，即确保他的个人安全；而幸运的是，他冷酷的利己主义没有使他堕落到无目的地嗜血杀人的地步。他住在米兰的城堡内，周围环绕着壮丽的花园、凉亭和草坪。数年以来，他从没去过城内，只在乡间短途旅行，那里有他几座富丽堂皇的城堡；由最快的骏马牵引着的舰队可以沿着专门开凿的河道将他带到各城堡中，整个行程安排得极为严格。不管谁进入城堡都会受到无数眼睛的监视；甚至站在窗前也被禁止，以免向城堡外的人发送信号。所有被允许做君王私人侍从的人都受到一系列最严格的检查；随后，一经录用，就被委以最高的外交事务和最谦卑的贴身差役——这两者在宫中都很光荣。这个人进行了长期的艰苦战争，习惯处理头等重要的政治事务，每天都派全权大臣到意大利各地去。他的安全在于，他的臣下不相信其他任何人，他的雇佣兵队长被间谍监视和欺骗，他的大使和高级官员由于人为培养起来的妒忌，特别是由于把诚实之人和恶棍安排在一起的做法而心有隔阂、不团结。他内心的信念也是建立在对立和矛盾的体系上；他相信盲目的必然性，相信星宿的影响，并且同时向各种各样的救星祈祷；他喜欢研读古代作家的作品和法国骑士小说。他不准当他面提及死亡，还让人将垂死的宠臣送出城堡，免得死亡的阴影落到他幸福的居所。但也同样是这个人，他以故意掩盖其伤口，拒绝放血，来加速自己的死亡，最终带着尊严，优雅死去。

他的女婿兼继承者，幸运的雇佣兵队长弗兰切斯科·斯福查（1450—1466），也许是15世纪所有意大利人中最合他那个时代的人的心意了。天才和个人力量的胜利，从没人能像他那样在自己身上表现得如此闪亮耀眼；那些不愿承认他优点的人至少也得为他这个幸运的宠儿而感到惊叹。米兰人公开宣称由如此卓越的君主治理是一种光荣；当他进入城内的时候，蜂拥的群众把骑在马上的他推挤到了大教堂里，而没有给他下马的机会。让我们听一听教皇庇护二世——一个在这类事情上的裁判者——对他生平的评价：

1459年，当这位大公来参加在曼图亚举行的代表大会时，已经60岁了（实际是58岁），但骑在马上的他看起来像一个年轻人；他身材伟岸，仪表堂堂，神色凝重，谈话安详亲切，举止俨然王侯，身心秉赋当世无人能敌，战场上无往不胜——这就是那个使自己从卑微的地位升到控制整个帝国的人。他的妻子美丽贤良，子女犹如天使；他很少生病并且几乎他所有的愿望均已实现。但他也并非没有不幸。他妻子出于忌妒杀死了他的情妇；他的老伙伴和老朋友，特劳伊洛和布鲁诺罗，背弃他而投靠阿尔方索国王；另一个旧友奇阿波伦内因为叛国罪被他处以绞刑；他不得不遭受他的兄弟阿利桑德罗引法国人来攻打他的痛苦；他的一个儿子策划阴谋陷害他而被关进监狱；他作战赢得的安科纳玛驰地区，又以同样的方式失去了。没人享有如此圆满的幸运，以致无需在逆境中拼搏。几乎无忧患之人即幸福之人。

给了幸福的消极定义后，这位知识渊博的教皇离开了读者。要是他能看到未来，或者愿意停下来讨论一个没有任何束缚的暴君专制的后果的话，一个无处不在的事实一定不会逃过他的注意——即对于未来的所有保障的缺失。那些子女们尽管美若天使，接受了精致完整的教育，但长大后都堕落成了无可救药的利己主义的牺牲品。只讲究外表的加利佐·马利亚（1466—1476），以自己漂亮的双手，所付出的高薪，享有的财政信用，贮存的200万金锭，环绕在他身边的卓越人士和所豢养的军队与猎鹰而骄傲。他喜爱自己说话的声音，而当他有机会侮辱一个威尼斯大使时，他会说得很流利，或许也是说得最流利的时候。他常常反复无常，曾让人在一夜之间把一个房间绘满了各种图案；尤其恶劣的是，他常常发疯虐待最亲近的朋友。对于一小撮狂热分子来说，他这个暴君太坏，不该再活下去；他们谋杀了他，然后把国家交由他的兄弟们统治，其中一个兄弟，洛德维科·伊·摩洛，把侄子监禁起来，自己掌握了政权。紧随此次篡位而来的是法国的干涉和降落在整个意大利的灾难。

洛德维科·斯福查被称作“伊·摩洛”，摩尔人，是当时暴君的最完美典型；并且作为自然的产物，几乎消除了我们的道德判断。尽管他采用的手段极端不道德，但他却十分巧妙地使用它们；当了解到一个人不仅在选择的目的上，而且在选择的手段上也要在道德上负责时，也许没有人比他更感到震惊的了；他宁愿认为他尽可能避免过于自由地使用死刑作为惩罚是一种非凡的德行。他认为由于他的政治天赋，意大利人对他的无比尊敬只不过是他应得的。1496年，他吹嘘亚力山大教皇是他的宫廷牧师，马克西米利安皇帝是他的雇佣兵队长，威尼斯是他的宫廷管家，法兰西国王是他的信使，这些人必须听从他的吩咐往来。他有着不可思议的理智，甚至在他面临绝境时（1499年），他也权衡了所有可能的逃跑方式，最后为了荣誉，他决定一切听凭人性的善良；他以从前的一次争吵为借口，驳回了他的弟弟阿斯卡尼奥枢机主教想要继续留在米兰城堡的提议：“主教阁下，不要不高兴，但是我不信任你，尽管你是我弟弟”；他委任一个他一直施予恩惠的人来守卫城堡，作为“他回来的保证”，但是那个人还是背叛了他。在国内，这个摩尔人是一个优秀而有用的统治者，并且直到最后，他还依赖他在米兰和科莫的名望。在后来的岁月中（1496年以后），他过度耗费国家的资源，并且在克雷莫纳，完全出于权宜之计，他命令把一个曾讲话反对新税的可敬公民悄悄闷死。从那时起，他用一个护栏把来访者和他本人隔开，以约束听众，因此那些人和他交谈时，不得不以最高嗓门讲话。在他的自勃艮第王朝灭亡以来欧洲最辉煌的宫廷里，极端不道德的事情到处存在；女儿被父亲所卖，妻子被丈夫所卖，姊妹被兄弟所卖。君主本人积极活跃，永不停歇，并且作为一个独创事业的人，他声称和所有像他自己一样靠个人才能而立身的人——学者、诗人、画家和音乐家——有联系。他创立的学院，与其说是为了学者们教学，倒不如说是为了他自己的目的；对于围绕在他身边的那些卓越人士，他所看重的不是他们的名望，而是他们的交往作伴和效劳。确定无疑的是，起初布拉曼特薪资微薄；而列奥那多直到1496年才得到适当的报酬——并且，如果不是他自愿，有什么能够使他留在宫中呢？也许那个时代没有人能像列奥那多一样，世界对他是开放的；如果关于洛德维科·伊·摩洛的天性中有比较高尚的成分缺乏证据，它可以在这位谜一般的大师在他的宫中长期逗留这件事上被发现。列奥那多后来为凯撒·波几亚和弗朗西斯一世效劳，很可能是由于他对这两人非凡和惊人的性格感兴趣。

这个摩尔人倒台后，他的儿子们在陌生的环境中被不正确地抚养长大。他的长子马西米利亚诺没有像他的地方；他的次子弗兰切斯科还尚有一些他的精神。米兰在那些年代里常常更换统治者，并且在更迭的过程中遭受难以述说的痛苦，尽力确保自己不会再次更换。1512年，在马西米利亚诺和西班牙人的武装力量面前撤退的法国人，被劝诱发表了一项声明，称米兰人不曾参与他们的驱逐，并且，由于没犯叛乱罪，他们可以向一个新征服者投降。一个具有重大政治意义的事实是：在这种过渡时刻，这个不幸的城市像阿拉戈纳家族逃走时的那不勒斯一样，很容易成为一群恶棍（常常是高层的贵族）的猎物。

曼图亚的贡查加家族和乌尔比诺的蒙特费尔特罗家族在15世纪后半期是秩序最好、人才最多的家族之一。贡查加家族是一个还算和谐的家庭，长期以来没有听说他们家出现过谋杀事件，他们家的死者能无所畏惧地展示给世人。弗兰切斯科·贡查加侯爵和他的妻子，伊斯特家的伊莎贝拉，虽有少许不正当行为，却是一对和谐体面的夫妻，并且在他们小而重要的国家不断遭受的危机的时候，他们把儿子们抚养成为成功而卓越的人物。弗兰切斯科，不论是作为政治家或是作为军人，竟会采取一种格外诚实的政策，这是威尼斯皇帝或法兰西国王不可能预料或想要的；但是，自塔罗之战（1495年）以来，就军事上的荣誉而言，他的感觉和表现是一个意大利爱国者，并且把同样的精神传递给了他妻子。每一个忠诚英勇的行为，诸如以保卫法恩扎来抵抗凯撒·波几亚，她都认为是在维护意大利的荣誉。我们对她的评价不需要依靠画家和作家们对她的颂扬，这些人把这位美丽的侯爵夫人描述成她对他们所提供的保护的丰厚回报。她自己的书信向我们显示了她是一个毫不动摇、坚定不移的女士，充满了仁爱幽默的见解。本波、邦德罗、阿里奥斯托和伯尔那多·塔索都把他们的作品送往这个宫廷，即使它弱小且国库空虚。自从过去的乌尔比诺宫廷消亡（1508年）以来，在意大利看不到比贡查加家族的曼图亚宫廷更光耀更有魅力的圈子；并且在某一方面，在活动的自由上，费拉拉宫廷的社交聚会不如曼图亚宫廷。在美术方面，伊莎贝拉有着精准的知识，她的画作少而精，令爱好美术的人看了无不为之动容。

在大菲德利哥（1444—1482）时代，不管他是不是真正的蒙特费尔特罗家族后裔，乌尔比诺所拥有的是一位君主统治的辉煌代表。作为一个雇佣兵队长，他拥有命运无常的军人们的政治品德，一种不独他们所具有的缺点的品德；作为他的狭小领地的统治者，他采取把从国外赚的钱花在国内的计划，并尽可能少地向人民征税。关于他和他的两个继承者圭多巴尔多和弗兰切斯科·马利亚，我们读到如下内容：“他们建造房屋，开垦耕地，在国内居住，并且给许多人提供工作：他们的臣民爱戴他们。”但是不仅仅这个国家，就连这个宫廷也是一件讲究艺术和结构作品。菲德利哥有500个仆从；宫廷的布置像最伟大的君主国的都城一样齐全，但什么都不浪费；一切都有它的目的，一切都得到细心地关注和控制。在宫廷里没有不道德和浪费的恶习：它的作用是一个为其他大家族的子弟们提供军事教育的学校，这些人文化与教育的完善被大公认为是种荣誉。他所建造的宫殿，即使不属于最宏伟的，也是构思设计完美，具有古典风格的。那里存放着他最伟大的珍宝和著名的藏书。在他的统治下人人有工作有钱赚，没有乞丐；治安非常好，因此他常常出去不带武器，并且几乎不带随从。在他那个时代的君主中，唯有他敢在外面公园里散步，或是一边在无人警戒的房间里简单用餐，一边让人为他朗读李维的著作，或者，在斋戒期间朗读一些祈祷方面的著作。同一天下午，他常常听一个关于某个古典主题的讲座，然后去克拉利兹女修道院，隔着格栅和女修道院院长讨论宗教上的事情。晚上他经常在以壮美景色著称的圣弗兰切斯科教堂的草地上督察宫中青年的军事操练，并且确保所有武艺都在以最完美的方式进行训练。在访问作坊里为他干活的工匠时，在和来访的常客交谈时，他都尽最大努力做到温和亲切，平易近人，并尽可能满足每个人当天所提出的请求。难怪他走在街上时，人们跪倒高呼：“殿下啊，上帝保佑您！”他被思想界的人称为“意大利之光”。他才华横溢的儿子圭多巴尔多体弱多病，遭到各种不幸，但最终（1508年）能把国家交到可靠的侄子弗兰切斯科·马利亚（也是教皇优里乌斯二世的侄子）手中；弗兰切斯科·马利亚至少保全了领土免遭外国人的永久占领。令人惊异的是，圭多巴尔多在凯撒·波几亚面前，弗兰切斯科在教皇列奥十世的大军面前，具有何等的信心才能屈服和逃走。每一个人都知道国家从无用的抵抗中受创越少，恢复就越容易，就越受群众欢迎。当洛德维科在米兰做同样的打算时，他忘记了有许多反对他的怨恨因素。圭多巴尔多的宫廷被巴达萨尔·卡斯蒂利昂描述为优雅举止的最高学府而流芳后世，他曾为了对这个宫廷社会表示敬意而当场朗诵他的牧歌《泰西斯》（1506年），后来（1518年）把他的《廷臣论》中对话的场景安排在多才多艺的伊丽莎贝塔·贡查加女公爵的社交圈。

伊斯特家族在费拉拉、德纳和勒佐的统治展现出暴行和受人爱戴这种令人好奇的对照。宫中可怕的事情接二连三；一个王后因为被人指称和继子通奸而被砍头（1425年）；婚生子和私生子逃出宫廷，甚至在国外，他们的生命也受到被派去追杀他们的刺客的威胁（1471年）。来自宫廷外部的阴谋持续不断；一个私生子的私生子企图从合法继承者赫克里一世手中抢夺王冠。据说，后者后来（1493年）发现他妻子受她兄弟那不勒斯的费兰特的教唆要毒死他，所以就把她毒死了。这一系列悲剧的终止是由于两个私生子密谋反对他们的兄弟，掌权的阿尔方索大公一世和枢机主教伊波利托（1506年），这个阴谋被及时发现并判处他们终身监禁。这个国家的财政体系是最完善的一种，而这是必然的，因为意大利的大国和中等国家中没有面临如此的危险并不断需要武装力量和防御工事。统治者们希望人民富裕程度能够跟得上捐税的不断增加；尼科洛侯爵（死于1441年）过去常常表达他的这一愿望，即他的臣民也许能比其他国家的人民更富有。如果人口的快速增长是衡量实际已达到的繁荣的一个尺度，那么一个重要的事实是，1497年，尽管首都有了显著扩大，但仍然没有房子出租。费拉拉是欧洲第一个真正现代的城市；根据统治者的命令，新建了许多大型的、建设优良的城区，由于集中了许多官员阶层，并且积极促进商业贸易的发展，这里首次形成了真正的首府；来自意大利各地富有的逃亡者，尤其是佛罗伦萨人，在费拉拉定居下来，建起了自己的豪华住宅。间接的征税让人勉强能够负担。政府确实采取了其他的意大利暴君，如加利佐·马利亚·斯福查，也用过的减轻民众疾苦的措施：荒年从远处运来谷物，好像是无偿分给了民众；但平常的时候，却用垄断补偿损失，如果不是对谷物的垄断，也是对许多其他生活必需品的垄断——如鱼、盐、肉、水果和蔬菜等，蔬菜是在城墙上和附近精心种植的。然而，最大的收入来源是每年对官位的出售——一种整个意大利都很普遍的风气，而在费拉拉的实行情况，我们有更准确的资料。比如1502年新年，大多数官员以“高价”买到了自己的位置；最多类别的公务员、关税官、法警、公证人、市镇长官、法官，甚至战略家，即省城的副职官员都名列其中。作为高价买官位、“比魔鬼更可恨的”、“榨干人民血汗的人”之一蒂托·斯特罗齐——让我们希望他不是那著名的拉丁诗人——被提及。大约每年的同一个时间，公爵们习惯在费拉拉进行巡回的访问，即所谓的“不时的巡视”，在访问期间他们从更富有的公民那里收取礼物。然而，这些礼物不包括现金，而只是天然的产品。

令费拉拉公爵感到自豪的是，全意大利都知道以下事实：在费拉拉，士兵的薪饷和大学教授的薪资都能一天不差地准时领到；士兵们从不敢随意欺压任何一个市民或农民；这个城市不怕任何攻击，坚不可摧；并且城堡中储藏着数量巨大的金币。似乎没有必要设立两套帐目：财政大臣同时也是公爵家务的管理者。由博尔索（1430—1471年）、赫克里斯一世（至1505年）和阿尔方索一世（至1534年）建造的建筑物非常多，但规模小；这些建筑具有君主家族的特征：尽管喜爱豪华——博尔索每次露面都身穿刺绣衣着，满身珠光宝气——但并没有沉迷于任意的挥霍。阿尔方索也许已预见到他那迷人的小别墅的命运——有着绿荫花园的贝尔维德尔别墅和有着喷泉和漂亮壁画的蒙达那别墅。

不可否认的是，这些君主们不断遭遇到的危险培养了他们身上各种惊人的能力。在这样一个讲究虚饰的世界里，只有具有尽善尽美谈吐的人才有希望获得成功；每一个想要卓尔不群的人都不能不以自己的个人价值来证实他所声称的事情，并显示他自己值得拥有他所寻求的王冠。他们的性格并不是没有阴暗面；但是在他们所有人身上都有当时意大利作为理想所追求的某些品质。当时欧洲哪个君主为了自己的文化，能像阿尔方索一世这样努力呢？他为了学习到法兰西、英格兰和荷兰旅行；通过这种旅行，他获得了这些国家工商业方面精确的知识。责备他闲暇时干镟工工作——尽管这和他铸炮的技术有关，责备他无任何偏见地让身边围绕擅长每种技艺的人是荒唐可笑的。意大利的君主们不像同时代的北欧君主那样，认为只有自己这个阶级值得重视，并把这同样的自高自大传染给贵族阶级。在意大利，君主被许可并且被迫结识和任用社会中每个阶层的人物；贵族，虽然在出身上是一个特权阶级，但在社会交往中却不得不靠个人的才能。这一点我们将在下文中进行更充分的讨论。

费拉拉人对于统治家族的感情是一种奇怪的混合物——既有沉默的恐惧，又有真正意大利人精于算计利益得失的意识，还有现代臣民的忠诚，即个人的钦敬变成一种新的担负责任的思想感情。费拉拉城于1451年建了一座骑马的铜像以纪念他们十年前去世的君主尼科洛；博尔索（1454年）毫不迟疑地把自己也是铜制，不过是坐姿的雕像，建在市场的近旁；除此以外，这个城市在他初登王位时已发布命令为他建“大理石凯旋柱”。某个公民在国外威尼斯时曾当众说过博尔索的坏话，一回国就被告发并被判以流放和没收财产的处罚。一个忠诚的市民努力控制住自己没有在法庭上用刀砍他，这个冒犯者脖子上绕着绳子，走到公爵面前请求彻底饶恕。政府精心配备了间谍；旅店老板被严令要求呈报每天的旅客名单，公爵要亲自过目。在渴望让每个著名客人都感受到礼遇的博尔索统治时期，这种规定的目的是为了殷勤好客；赫克里一世却只是把它用作一种预防措施。在波洛尼亚，在乔万尼二世本蒂伏利奥统治时，规定从一个城门进来的旅客必须领取一张票，才能从另外一个城门出去。一项总是受人欢迎的措施就是突然开除欺压人民的官员。当博尔索亲自逮捕他的首席枢密顾问官时，当赫克里一世开除并贬黜一个多年来一直吸吮人民血汗的收税官时，人们燃起篝火，敲响钟，向他们表示敬意。不过，赫克里一世对他一个部下的态度却让事情走得太远。一个警察局的管理者，或者我们随意把他叫作什么（法庭长），是卢卡的格里高利奥·扎邦特——一个不适合这种职务的本地人。即使是公爵的儿子和弟兄们在此人面前也会发抖；他所开出的的罚金高达成百上千金币，甚至案件还未审理就施以酷刑；他从有钱的罪犯那里接受贿赂，并假传公爵的命令来赦免罪犯。人民无论拿出多少钱给统治者都会愿意，只要能赶走这个“上帝和人类的敌人”。但是赫克里一世却授他以骑士爵位，并让他做自己孩子们的教父；而年复一年扎邦特都能攒下2000金币。他只敢吃自己家里养的鸽子，并且如果没有一队弓箭手和勇士们保护，他不可能走过街道。除掉他的时候到了。1496年，两个学生和一个他致命迫害过的改变宗教信仰的犹太人乘他在家午睡时杀死了他，然后骑着事前准备好的马驰过城内，高喊着：“出来吧！出来吧！我们已经杀死扎邦特了！”追捕者来得太迟，发现他们已经安全越过了边境。针对这件事有很多讽刺作品——其中有一些是以十四行诗的形式，另外一些是以颂歌的形式。

正是完全以这种制度的精神，君主向为朝廷尽忠和为人民造福的下属表达尊敬。当1469年博尔索的私人顾问洛德维科·卡塞拉去世的时候，没有一个法庭或者城内的商业场所或者大学讲堂被允许开放：所有人都不得不送殡到圣多密尼克教堂，因为公爵想要亲自到场。事实上，“参加臣民葬礼的伊斯特家族的第一个人”身穿黑色衣服，走在棺材后边，哭泣着，而后面跟着卡塞拉的亲属，每人由一个廷臣引导：这个普通公民的遗体由贵族们从教堂抬往修道院，在那里被安葬。这种以君主的感情所表示的官方同情首次出现在意大利国家。这种做法的根源也许是一种美好仁慈的感情；其感情的流露，尤其是在诗人中，真挚性常常令人怀疑。阿里奥斯托青年时期的一首诗，哀悼赫克里一世的妻子阿拉贡的莉奥诺拉，除了散见于所有时代的挽歌里的不可避免的墓地花朵以外，还含有某些完全现代的特点：

这一死亡给了费拉拉多年也难以恢复的一击：它的女施主现在是它天堂中的拥护者，因为地上不值得她居住；死亡天使真的没有拿着血污的镰刀像来到我们普通人这里那样来到她那里，而是优雅地带着减轻任何恐惧的和善面容来到她那里。

但是，我们也遇到了一种不同类型的同情。完全依靠自己的保护人之宠爱的小说家们，甚至在君主还没去世就以一种后人看来极不慎重，当时却被认为只是一种无害的赞颂方式向我们讲述了他的爱情故事。抒情诗人甚至走得更远，歌颂他们已合法结婚的君主的非法爱情，例如，安吉洛·波利齐亚诺歌颂“庄严者”洛伦佐的情人们，乔维诺·庞达诺用一种非凡的热情歌颂卡拉布里亚的阿尔方索的情人们。被谈论的这首诗无意中暴露了这个阿拉戈纳统治者的可憎性情；在这些事情方面，他也必须是最幸运的人，否则苦难就降临在那些更成功的人身上吧！这样，最伟大的艺术家们，例如列奥那多·达·芬奇，竟然画他们保护人的情妇们，也不过是一件理所当然的事。

但是伊斯特家族并不满足于别人的赞美；它还要自己为自己庆祝。在斯基法诺亚王宫，博尔索让人把自己画在一系列的历史事件中，赫克里（始于1472年）通过比得上耶稣圣体节的游行来庆祝他的即位周年纪念，商店像礼拜天一样关门，在队伍的中间走着身穿刺绣长袍的君主家族的所有成员（包括私生子）。王冠是荣誉和权威的源泉，个人的显达只能来源于此，这在这个宫廷中长久以来由金马刺勋章被表达出来——一个和中世纪骑士气概没有任何共同点的勋章。赫克里一世在马刺外又加上一把剑、一件金边斗篷和一笔赏金，作为对这些的回报，无疑要求提供经常的服务。

这个宫廷享誉世界的对艺术和文学的保护是通过一所意大利最完善的大学，并以给予为君主个人或宫廷服务的官位来实行的；因此这种保护不需要额外的花费。博亚尔多，作为富裕的乡绅和高官，属于这一类。当阿里奥斯托初露头角的时候，在米兰或佛罗伦萨都不存在真正意义上的宫廷了，很快在乌尔比诺或那不勒斯也没有了。他不得不满足于在枢机主教伊波利托的音乐家和魔术师中占有一席之地，直到阿尔方索招他为自己服务。再后来，托尔夸托·塔索就不一样了，人们嫉妒地寻求让他来宫廷里的机会。

第五章　暴君的反对者

面对这种中央集权，所有发生在国境内的合法反抗都是徒劳的。为了共和国的恢复所需要的环境要素已经被永远摧毁，而这个场地在为暴力和暴君专制做准备。即使拥有封建产业，毫无政治权力的贵族们可以随意地把自己称作圭尔夫派或吉伯林派，可以用加了衬的紧身裤、用有羽毛的帽子，或者用他们喜欢的其他方式来装扮他们的勇士；像马基雅维利这样有思想的人却非常清楚，米兰和那不勒斯已经太“腐败”，不可能建立共和国。有些奇怪的评价落到了这两个现在只是用来给个人争端和家庭争端以官方制裁的所谓政党的身上。有个意大利的君主——内提斯海姆的阿格利巴劝其取缔这两个政党——回答说，他们的不和一年使他收获12000多金币的罚款。1500年，在洛德维科·伊·摩洛短暂回国期间，托尔托纳城的圭尔夫党人为了一劳永逸地消灭他们的反对者，把一部分邻近的法国军队召引到城内来，当然法国人以掠夺和摧毁吉伯林党人开始，但以对圭尔夫党人采取同样的手段，直到托尔托纳城完全被损毁而结束。在像温床一样催生每一种强烈激情的的罗马涅，这两个政党的名字长久以来已经丧失了一切政治意义。人民有一种政治上的错觉，他们常常相信圭尔夫派自然是法国人的同盟，而吉伯林派是西班牙人的同盟。很难看到那些试图通过这种错误取利的人们这样做获得了多大的好处。法兰西，在所有干涉后，最终不得不放弃这个半岛，而西班牙，在摧毁意大利后是什么情况，每一个读者已很了解。

但现在回到文艺复兴时期的暴君。我们可能认为，一个头脑单纯的人可能会辩解说，既然全部权力来自上帝，这些君主们，如果得到全体臣民忠诚可靠的支持，他们自己迟早一定会得到改善并去掉其暴力天性的所有痕迹。但是由激情和野心所激发的性格和想象，不可能期待有这种理智的想法。他们像庸医一样，认为通过消除症状就治愈了疾病，并且幻想着如果杀死暴君，自由自然而然就会到来。或者，甚至连这也没想到，他们只是试图为大家的仇恨提供一个发泄的出口或者为家庭的不幸或为个人的受辱报仇。因为政府拥有绝对的权力，而且不受所有法律的限制，所以反对者以同样的自由选择了自己的武器。薄伽丘公开声明：

要我称呼那个暴君为国王或者君主，并且像对待我的主人一样来忠诚地服从他吗？不，因为他是国家的敌人。我可以使用武器、阴谋、密探、伏击和欺诈来对付他；这样做是一件神圣而必要的事情。没有什么比暴君之血更可接受的献祭了。

我们没有必要讨论个人的事例；马基雅维利，在其《史论集》中著名的一章里，探讨了从希腊暴君时代以来的古今阴谋，并按照其各种各样的计划和结局以冷漠的中立态度进行了分类。我们从中只需注意两种情况：首先是在教堂里实施的谋杀，其次是古代习惯做法的影响。暴君得到如此严密的保卫，以致除了在庄严的宗教礼拜式上，在别处几乎不可能对其下手；而且在别的任何场合都不可能看到整个家族聚在一起。就为此，法布利亚诺人在大弥撒（1435年）当中，当唱到被作为暗号的《使徒信经》中“圣神降孕”时，谋杀了他们的统治家族——贾维斯特利的全家。在米兰，乔万尼·马利亚·维斯康提公爵（1412年）在圣格达多的教堂入口处被暗杀；加利佐·马利亚·斯福查（1476年）在圣斯蒂芬的教堂被暗杀；洛德维科·伊·摩洛（1484年）因从另一个门而不是预料的那个门进入圣安布洛吉奥教堂，而侥幸逃脱了被遗孀波娜女公爵追随者的短剑刺死的命运。暗杀者们在这种行动中没有想要不敬神明；暗杀加利佐的凶手们在谋杀前依旧向教堂的守护圣徒祈祷，并虔诚聆听了第一场弥撒。然而，帕齐家族谋杀洛伦佐·美第奇和朱利亚诺·美第奇（1478年）的阴谋部分地失败了，原因之一是曾说好在一个宴会上实施谋杀的凶手蒙特西科拒绝在佛罗伦萨的大教堂动手。“熟悉那个神圣的地方因此绝无任何恐惧”的教士们中有一个被劝诱着代替他干了此事。

关于对古代习惯做法的效仿，这些古代习惯做法对道德，尤其是我们会经常提到的政治问题的影响，统治者们自己做了榜样，无论在他们的国家观念上还是在他们的个人行为上，他们都公开宣称以古代的罗马帝国为楷模。同样，他们的反对者在用一种审慎的理论开始采取行动时，就用古代的诛戮暴君者作为模式。也许很难证明，在主要问题上——在下这个决心本身方面——他们是有意识地因循了古代的例子；但诉诸于古代的做法却不仅仅是一句空话。关于加利佐·斯福查的谋杀者——兰普尼亚诺、奥尔加提和维斯康提的事例给我们以最惊人的揭露。尽管这三人有个人目的，但他们的冒险行为可以部分地归之于一个更普遍的理由。大约在这个时候，柯拉·德·蒙泰尼，一个人文主义者并且是修辞学教授，已经在米兰的许多青年贵族中间唤起了对于荣耀和爱国事业的一种模糊的热情，而且曾向兰普尼亚诺和奥尔加提提到了他解救米兰的希望。这很快就引起了对他的怀疑：他被从城中驱逐出去，他的学生们放纵于由他所激发起来的狂热中。大约在事发前十天，他们在圣安布洛吉奥的修道院里集会并庄严宣誓。“那时，”奥尔加提说，“在一个远处的角落，在守护圣徒的画像前，我抬眼望着他，为我们自己和他的全体人民恳求他的帮助。”这个城市的天堂中的保护神被祈求保佑这件事，然后他们又向实施谋杀事件的教堂的圣徒圣斯蒂芬祈福。这时，许多同谋者都被告知了这个秘密计划，每夜的集会在兰普尼亚诺的家里举行，暗杀者们用他们的剑鞘为谋杀进行练习。事情成功了，兰普尼亚诺被公爵的一些随从当场杀死；其他人被俘。维斯康提后悔了，但奥尔加提经历了所有酷刑依然坚持这是献给上帝的可以接受的行为，并且当刽子手打断他的肋骨时，他大声说：“勇敢，吉罗拉谟！你会永远被铭记；死亡痛苦，但光荣永存。”

但是无论这种阴谋的目的和意图貌似多么理想，实施阴谋的方式却暴露了所有阴谋者中最坏的那个——卡提利那，一个思想中毫无自由可言的人的影响。锡耶纳的编年史明确地告诉我们，这些阴谋者的所作所为是从撒路斯特那里学来的，这一事实由奥尔加提的自白间接地进一步得到证实。我们在别处也见到了卡提利那这个名字，除了他所遵循的目的外，几乎不可能发现一个更有吸引力的阴谋者的模式了。

在佛罗伦萨人中，无论何时当他们除掉或者试图除掉美第奇家族时，诛戮暴君是一种他们普遍接受和同意的做法。在1494年美第奇家族逃亡后，多那太洛的青铜群像——朱迪思和死去的的霍洛芬斯的铜像——从他们的收藏品中被取出，并被放在总督府前，即现在米开朗琪罗的《大卫》雕像所在的地方；上面刻着“挽救国家的榜样，全体公民建于1495年”。没有比小布鲁图斯更受欢迎的例子了，由于他叛变了罗马帝国，在但丁的《神曲》中他和卡西乌斯以及犹大同处地狱的最底层。密谋反对美第奇家族的朱利亚诺、乔万尼和朱利奥而失败（1513年）的彼埃特罗·保罗·巴斯卡利是布鲁图斯的狂热崇拜者，为了紧随他的步伐，等待找到一个卡西乌斯，他遇到了阿古斯丁诺·卡伯尼，在其身上发现他是这样一个同伙。他在狱中最后所说的话——当时的宗教感情的一个惊人证据——表明他为了要像基督徒那样死去而费了多大的努力从脑中排除那些古代的想象。他的朋友和忏悔神父两人不得不向他保证，圣·托马斯·阿奎那绝对会给那些阴谋者定罪；但后来这个忏悔神父向那个朋友承认，圣·托马斯是有区别的，他允许那些反对违背人民意志强行欺压人民的暴君的阴谋。

在洛伦奇诺·美第奇谋杀了阿利桑德罗公爵（1537年）然后逃走之后，对此事的道歉很有可能是他自己所作，当然是为了他的利益而作，在其中他称赞诛戮暴君是一种最高尚的行为；假设阿利桑德罗是一个合法婚生的美第奇，和他有亲属关系，即使仅仅是远亲，他勇敢地把自己和为国家而杀害自己弟兄的提摩利昂相比。其他人，在同样的情形下，常常和布鲁图斯相比；从米开朗琪罗在巴尔杰洛博物馆里雕塑的布鲁图斯半身像上可以推断，甚至在晚年，米开朗琪罗对于这种想法也并不反对。像几乎他的所有作品一样，这尊雕像他也没有完成，但如同雕像下的声明所写，这当然不是因为谋杀凯撒事件与他的感情有矛盾。

以反对后来时代的君主制形式出现的大众的激进主义在文艺复兴时期的暴君专制国家里是不可能找到的。每一个个人心里抗议暴君专制，但都更愿意和它达成可忍受的或有利的协议，而不愿和别人联合起来消灭它。情况一定像民众联合起来消灭或者驱逐统治家族之前的加米里诺、法布利亚诺和里米尼一样坏。大多数情况下，他们太清楚了，这只是意味着更换主人而已。当然，共和国之星在陨落。

第六章　共和国：威尼斯和佛罗伦萨

意大利的自治城市早期已有些信号证明有把城市转变成国家的力量。剩下的只是这些城市应该联合成一个大联邦；而且这种想法不断被意大利政治家们提起，不管它时不时呈现出来的形式有多么不同。实际上，在12世纪和13世纪的斗争中，强大的联盟其实已由这些城市组成；西斯蒙第持有这种意见：在伦巴第联盟反对巴巴若萨（自1168年始）的最终武装力量形成之时即整个意大利联盟变为可能之时。但是那些更加强大的国家已经发展到具有了一些使任何这样的计划行不通的特点。在商业交易中，他们采取非常极端的方法来减少参与，这会损害竞争者；他们使较弱的邻邦处于一种无助的从属地位——总之，每个国家都想着能够不靠其他国家帮助自己发展下去，这样就为未来侵占其他国家铺平了道路。这位侵占者随着以下情况的发生即将出现：当贵族和人民之间以及贵族各派别之间的长期冲突唤起了人们对一个强有力政府的渴望时，以及当那些准备并且愿意把自己的帮助出卖给最高投标人的雇佣兵队伍已经取代了从市民中征募的军队时，这些军队被党派领袖们认为已不符合他们的要求。暴君们破坏了大多数城市的自由；他们到处受到驱逐，但并不彻底，或者仅仅是短时期的；他们总是被恢复王位，因为国内状况对他们有利，并且反对势力已筋疲力尽。

在那些仍然保持独立的城市中间，有两个对于人类历史具有深刻意义的城市：一是佛罗伦萨，这个不断发生运动的城市，给我们留下了一份三个世纪以来所有参与这种运动的每个人的思想和抱负的记载；二是威尼斯，这个貌似停滞和处于政治秘密状态的城市。所能想象到的对比没有一个比这两个城市所提供给我们的更强烈，这两个城市哪个也不能和迄今为止世上已产生的任何东西作比较。

威尼斯从一开始就认识到自己是一个奇怪而神秘的创造物——一个高于人类灵智的力量的产物。这个城市的庄严奠基是一个传奇故事的主题。413年3月25日中午，来自帕多瓦的移民在利亚尔图放下了第一块石头，以便他们可以在野蛮人的蹂躏下有一个神圣不被侵犯的避难所。后世的作家们把对于这个城市未来的崇高伟大有所预感这件事归之于它的建立者们。安托尼奥·萨伯利科在他六音步诗篇的尊贵叙述中歌颂了这件大事，他让做完献祭仪式的牧师向天高喊：“当从此以后我们尝试伟大事业的时候，愿上帝赐予我们繁荣富足！现在我们跪在粗劣的祭坛前；但如果我们的发誓并非徒劳，上帝啊，成百座用黄金和大理石所建的神殿将为你而立。”这个岛城在15世纪末是世界的珍宝盒。萨伯利科曾描写到，这里有古代的圆屋顶、斜塔，镶嵌大理石的建筑物正面，最富丽的装饰也没有阻碍对每个角落的实际利用时所浓缩的壮观。他带我们到利亚尔图的圣吉亚科米多教堂前拥挤的市场中，全世界的商业正在那里进行交易，不是在喊叫和混乱中，而是在压低声音的嗡嗡声中进行的；广场周围和邻近街道的门廊里坐着成百上千的货币兑换商和金匠，他们头上是一排排没有尽头的商铺和货栈。他描写了桥那边德国人的大商业区，那里有他们的货物和住所，大商业区前，他们的船并排停泊在运河里；再往上是装满了酒和油的整个船队，和它并排，在蜂拥着搬运工的岸上，是商人们住房的圆顶；然后从利亚尔图到圣马可广场一路上是客栈和香料店。所以他带领读者从一个市区到另一个市区，直至最后来到了两所属于公共福利机构的医院——在威尼斯，公共福利机构的数量多到无处可比。不光是在战争战时期，就算是在和平时期，对人民的关怀也是这个政府的特点，它对伤员，甚至是敌人的伤员的照顾，得到了其他国家的敬佩。

每一种公共机构都能在威尼斯找到他们的模式；有序执行退休工作人员的退休金制度，包括给孤儿寡母的抚恤金。富裕、政治安定和对其他国家的了解，使它对于这些问题的思考已经成熟。这些迈着轻轻而小心的步伐、说着经过深思的话语、身材纤细的金发男人，只是在服装和举止上彼此有些细微的差别。装饰品，尤其是珍珠，专供妇人和女孩子们佩戴。那时，尽管在土耳其人那里遭受了一些损失，普遍的繁荣富足仍然令人眼花缭乱；这个城市所积蓄的力量以及整个欧洲对它的偏爱，使它在很久以后能够从通往印度的海路的发现、埃及马穆卢克人的灭亡和坎姆布雷同盟的战争所给予它的沉重打击中生存下来。

出生在蒂沃利附近、有着他那个时代学者们讲话坦率而滔滔不绝习惯的萨伯利科，在别的地方有些惊讶地评论说，早晨来听他讲演的青年贵族们并不能被说服进行政治问题的讨论。“当我问他们，人们对于意大利的某个运动的想法、言论和期待是什么的时候，他们异口同声回答，他们对此事一无所知。”还有，虽然这个国家有严格的强制要求，但许多情况仍然会被那些愿意出高价的人从贵族中比较腐化的人那儿了解到。在15世纪最后的25年，在最高级的官员中间出现了叛国者；教皇们、意大利的君主们，甚至在政府服役的处于社会二等阶层的雇佣兵队长们，都有他们的御用情报员，有时还给这些情报员固定的薪金；事情甚至发展到这样的地步，十人议会发现要非常小心地封锁重要的政治消息，不让大议会知道，甚至认为洛德维科·伊·摩洛在大议会里控制了一定数量的选票。个别犯罪者的绞刑和高额赏金——像给告发犯罪者的人以60金币的终身年金——是否有很大作用，很难判断；引起弊端的主要原因之一是贵族中许多人的贫穷不可能一朝一夕就被消除。1492年，处于贵族中贫穷阶层的两个人强烈提议，国家应该每年救济不担任公职的贫穷贵族70000金币；这个提议几乎要被提到大议会上，在那里也许有多数人支持，这时十人议会及时干涉，并把这两个提议者终身流放到塞浦路斯的尼科西亚去。大约在同一时期，一个姓索伦佐的人因盗窃圣物罪被绞死——尽管不是在威尼斯本城，一个姓康达利尼的人因夜晚入室盗窃罪而被囚禁；康达利尼家族中的另一个人，在1499年，来到总督署里抱怨说他多年没有任职，他每年只有16金币的收入但有九个孩子，他的债务已高达60金币，他不会谋生之道，最近已流落街头。我们能够理解为什么有些比较富有的贵族建造房屋，有时是整排整排的房屋，给他们贫苦的同胞提供免费的住处。这种建造房屋的工程在作为慈善行为的遗嘱中被列出来。

但是，如果威尼斯的敌人把希望认真地建立在这类弊端上，他们就大错特错了。大家也许认为，让最卑微的人也能通过劳动获得丰厚报酬的城市商业活动以及地中海东海岸的殖民地，将使社会中的危险因素远离政治问题；但是热那亚，虽有类似的有利条件，它的政治历史难道不是最动荡的吗？威尼斯社会稳定的根源更多在于，只有在国家团结和谐的环境中才能发现的各种情况的结合。由于无懈可击的位置，它从一开始就能够最充分冷静地思考处理外交事务，而几乎完全忽略瓜分意大利其余各地的党派，避免卷入永久同盟的纠缠，并为那些它认为适合缔结的同盟付出最高的代价。因此，威尼斯性格的基调是一种自豪和傲然独立的精神，这种精神加上可感觉到的意大利其他地区对这个城市的仇恨，就产生了内部团结一致的强烈意识。同时，居民们在与殖民地交易和与大陆领地交易时，被最有力的利益这条纽带联系在一起，迫使大陆领地的人们，也就是一直到贝尔加莫的各城镇的居民只能在威尼斯进行买卖。一个依靠如此人为手段的政权只能通过内部的和谐与团结来维持；这种信念非常广泛地散布在市民中间，以至于阴谋者几乎找不到可以举事的因素。即使有心怀不满的人，也因贵族和自由民之间巨大的区别，而导致彼此之间不容易相互理解。另一方面，在贵族阶层内部，旅行、商业经营还有和土耳其人的不断战争，使他们中的富人和危险分子远离了进行阴谋活动的有效根源——无所事事。在这些战争中，他们被掌权的将领所饶恕，经常到了一种犯罪的程度，如果贵族们这种“彼此给予痛苦”的顾虑不惜以损害正义为代价继续下去的话，威尼斯人加图预言了这个城市的灭亡。即使如此，这种公开的自由活动仍然使威尼斯的贵族们整体来看具有一种健康的倾向。

当嫉妒和野心需要满足时，一个官方牺牲者唾手可得，合法的手段和当局已准备好。所有威尼斯人有目共睹的弗兰切斯科·福斯卡里总督（死于1457年）多年来所遭受的精神上的折磨，是一个只有在贵族统治的国家才可能出现的可怕的报复例子。十人议会插手所有事务，无需上诉就可以处理生死、财务和军事任命的事务，审问官就是其成员，并且十人议会推翻了福斯卡里，像它以前推翻许多有权势的人一样——这个议会每年从整个统治机构大议会中重新选举成员组成，因此十人议会最直接代表着大议会的意志。因为任期短而责任大使其成为乏人问津的一个目标，所以选举中不大可能发生重大的阴谋事件。尽管这个议会和其他权力机关的行径既暴力又难以理解，但真正的威尼斯人却宁可接受也不逃避他们的判决，这不仅仅是因为这个共和国法网恢恢，并且若抓不到本人，就可能采取惩罚他的家人的做法；也是因为在大多数的情形下，它是出于理性动机而不是嗜血的欲望来行事。确实，没有一个国家曾像它一样，对自己的无论国内还是国外的臣民有更强大的道义上的影响。如果元老院中发现叛徒，那么每一个国外的威尼斯人都是自己国家的天生密探这一事实也足以弥补了。在罗马的威尼斯枢机主教把罗马教皇主持、各地枢机主教参加的教议会上院的秘密会议的相关消息发送到国内是一件很自然的事情。枢机主教多密尼克·格里马尼在罗马附近（1500年）让人截取了阿斯卡尼奥·斯福查正送给他弟弟洛德维科·伊·摩洛的文件，并把文件送往威尼斯；他当时正受到严重起诉的父亲在大议会上，换句话说，也就是在全世界面前，要求公众看在他儿子的这一做法上而受到宽大处理。

我们已经提到过威尼斯政府给它的雇佣兵队长薪俸这种行为。唯一能够从雇佣兵队长身上获得他们忠诚的进一步保障在于他们人数众多；由于人数众多，叛变难以实施就像叛变容易被发现一样。看一看威尼斯的军籍表，人们只是惊讶于如此各色人等所组成的军队怎么可能采取任何共同行动。在1495年战役的编制表中，我们看到有15526名骑兵，他们被分成许多小分队。曼图亚的贡查加一人就有1200百名，乔佛里多·波几亚有740名；然后是6个小分队队长，各有600名到700名，10个小分队队长，各有400名，12个小分队队长，各有400名到200名，14个左右的小分队队长，各有200名到100名，9个小分队队长，各有80名，6个小分队队长，各有50名到60名等。这些军队一部分由原有的威尼斯部队组成，一部分由威尼斯城或者乡村贵族所领导的老兵组成；不过，大多数将领是各城市的君主和统治者或者他们的亲属。除这些军队外，还必须加上24000名步兵——我们不知道，他们是怎样被招募和指挥的——还有另外3300名的军队，他们大概属于特殊的职责范围。和平时期，大陆上的城市全部不设防或者由不重要的军队驻守。威尼斯所依靠的，即使不能准确地说是它的臣民的忠诚，也至少是他们的正确意识；在坎姆布雷同盟战争（1509年）中，众所周知，它免去了他们忠诚于政府的发誓，让他们把被外国占领的舒适和他们所习惯的温和的政治作比较。因为他们放弃圣马可并不算作叛国，所以他们不会害怕受到惩罚，并且他们怀着最热切的心情回到了旧主人身边。我们可以附带说一句，这次战争是一个世纪以来反对威尼斯扩张野心的呼吁的结果。事实上，威尼斯人也没有免除那些相信他们的敌人不会采取无理性、轻率行为的聪明过度的人们的错误。受这种乐观主义、也许是贵族统治所具有的奇怪弱点的误导，他们不仅完全忽视了穆罕默德二世为夺取君士坦丁堡所做的准备，而且甚至忽视了查理八世的武装备战，直至意外的打击最终降临。坎姆布雷同盟，在它显然违背两个主要成员——路易七世和教皇优里乌斯二世——的利益方面，是属于同一性质的事件。全意大利反对这个胜利城市的仇恨似乎都汇聚在这个教皇的头脑中，使他看不到外国干涉的恶行；至于阿姆布阿斯枢机主教和他的国王的政策，威尼斯本应该很早就认识到它是怀有恶意的愚笨行为而彻底加以警惕。这个同盟的其他成员由于妒忌参加进来，这种妒忌对于特别富强的国家也许能起到一种有益的矫正作用，但它本身却是一种乞丐般的情绪。威尼斯光荣地经受了这一场斗争，但依然遭受到永久性的伤害。

一个政权基础如此复杂，活动和利益的舞台如此宽广，如果没有系统的全盘监督，没有对于方法和负担、利润和损失的定期估算，是不可想象的。威尼斯可以证实它所声称的，它是，也许和佛罗伦萨一起，是统计科学的诞生地，并被其他较开明的暴君国家所效仿。中世纪的封建国家除了对于领主的权利和财产这些目录外，对于其他一无所知；它把总产量看作是固定的数量，只有仅涉及地产时，它大体上才是如此。另一方面，整个西方城镇从很早就意识到依靠工商业的总产量变化很大；然而，即使在汉萨同盟的最繁荣时代，它们所得到的也不过是一张简单的商业资产负债表。舰队、军队、政治的权力和影响都落在商人总账的借方和贷方之下。在意大利的各城市国家里，一种清醒的政治意识、穆罕默德式的行政管理模式和长期积极的工商业活动结合起来，首次产生了一种真正的统计科学。在南意大利，弗里德里克二世的君主专制国家被组建起来，唯一的目标就是为他所从事的生死斗争确保一个集中的权力。相反在威尼斯，最高的目标则是对于生活和权力的享受、所继承利益的增加、最赚钱的工业形式的创立以及新商业渠道的开辟。

当时的作家以最大的自由来谈论这些事情。我们知道，1422年该城人口达到19万；意大利人可能是第一个没有按照家庭、或者拿得动武器的人、或者有能力行走的人等等来计算人口，而是按照“生命”来计算的人，所以能够为进一步的计算取得最中立的根据。大约在这一时期，当佛罗伦萨人希望和威尼斯结成同盟反对菲利波·马利亚·维斯康提时，当时就被拒绝了，威尼斯依据准确的商业利润相信：一场威尼斯和米兰，也就是卖方和买方之间的战争，是愚蠢的。即使米兰公爵只是扩充军队，米兰人由于必须缴纳较重的赋税，也会变成较差的主顾。“最好让佛罗伦萨人被打败，然后，尽管他们习惯于城邦的生活，但他们也会像卢卡人在困境中所做的那样，到我们这儿定居并带来他们的丝织品和毛织品。”奄奄一息的莫森尼哥总督（1423年）对他派人召集到床前的几个元老的讲话仍然非同寻常。它包含威尼斯全部资源统计账目的主要项目。我说不出是否有或者哪里有对于这份错综复杂的文件的一个详细阐释；作为举例说明，可以引用下列事实。在偿还了400万金币的战争贷款后，国家公债（总额）仍然达到600万金币；往来贸易（似乎是这样）达到1000万金币，文献告诉我们，这可以产出400万金币的利润。3000只“小船”，300只“大船”，和45艘军舰分别配备17000、8000和11000名海员（每艘军舰200多人）。此外，还必须加上16000名造船木工。威尼斯的房屋价值700万，房租收入50万。有1000名贵族收入范围从70到4000金币不等。在另一段里记载着同一年这个国家的一般收入为110万金币；由于战争造成的对于贸易的干扰，这个世纪中期国家收入降到80万金币。

如果威尼斯以这种计算的精神和她所给予它的实际应用，是第一个充分体现了现代政治生活的一个重要方面的国家的话，那么，另一方面，在意大利当时最看重的文化方面，她并没有站在前列。总的来说，对于文学的推动，尤其是在其他各地所盛行的对于古典文化的热情，在这里是缺乏的。萨伯利科说，威尼斯人哲学和雄辩方面的卓越才能本身并不亚于他们商业和政治上的才能；于1459年把柏拉图《法学》的拉丁文译本献给威尼斯总督特列比松的乔治，被任命为哲学教授，年薪150金币，最后把他的《修辞学》献给了元老院。然而，如果我们查看弗兰切斯科·桑索维诺附录在他著名的著作后边的威尼斯文学史，我们就会发现，在14世纪除了历史和神学、法学与医药专著外，几乎没有任何其他作品；在15世纪，直到我们看到伊尔莫劳·巴巴罗和阿尔多·曼纽奇，人文主义的文化对于一个如此重要的城市体现得非常贫乏。贝萨利昂枢机主教遗赠给国家的藏书（1468年）侥幸逃过散失和破坏的命运。帕多瓦大学当然培养对于知识的学习；可是，在那里医学专家和司法专家——后者是写作法律意见的人——收入最高。在意大利的诗歌创作方面，威尼斯所占的比例长久以来就无足轻重，直到16世纪初，她在这方面的不足才有所弥补。就连文艺复兴时期的艺术也是从外部传入这个城市的，就在15世纪末，她才以独立的自由和力量学习进入这一领域。但是我们看到能够说明其知识依然落后的更显著的事例。这个政府，虽然把教士如此完全地置于自己的掌控中，把所有重要教职的任命权都保留在自己手中，并且一次又一次地敢于蔑视罗马教廷，却展现出一种非常独特的官方的虔诚。土耳其征服希腊后，从希腊运入的圣徒遗体和其他遗物被以最大的代价购买，并由总督以庄严的仪式列队恭迎。为了一件无缝的僧袍，决定（1455年）出价10000金币，但最终没有得到。这些做法并不是大家头脑一热的结果，而是政府首脑们冷静决策的结果，并且就是不这样做也不会引起任何评论，在佛罗伦萨，同样情形下，当然就不会这样做了。我们不谈群众的虔诚和他们对于一张亚力山大六世的赦罪券的坚定信仰。但这个国家本身，在它同化教会到一个在其他地方闻所未闻的程度以后，它的结构中确实有着某种宗教成分；并且这个国家的象征，总督本人，出现在12次盛大的有着半宗教性质的游行队伍中。它们几乎全部是为了纪念政治事件的庆典，并且其壮观程度可以和教会的盛大节日相媲美；其中最辉煌的一次，即最著名的“与海结婚”是在基督升天节举行的。

我们发现最进步的政治思想和最多样化的人类发展的形式在佛罗伦萨的历史上结合在一起，从这个意义上说，她称得上是世界上最现代化的国家。在这里，全体人民忙于在暴君专制的城邦里属于单个家庭的事情。那种奇特的佛罗伦萨精神——既有尖锐的批判同时又有艺术的创造——不断地改变着这个国家的社会政治状况，并不断地描述和评价这种变化。因此佛罗伦萨成了政治学说和理论、实验和突然变革的家园，但也像威尼斯一样，成了统计科学的家园，而且超越其他国家，独自成了在现代意义上的历史再现的家园。古罗马的辉煌和熟悉古罗马最主要的作家对佛罗伦萨并非没有影响。乔万尼·维兰尼承认在1300年的罗马纪念节庆典上，他第一次产生了写作他那部伟大作品的念头，一回到家就马上开始写起来。然而那一年的20万朝圣者中间有多少人在天赋和文学旨趣上也许像他一样，但还是没有写出他们自己城邦的历史！因为不是所有人都能用这种想法鼓励自己：“罗马在陨落；我的城市在兴起，已准备好完成伟大的事业，因此我想要叙述它过去的历史，并希望把故事一直写到现代，只要我一息尚存。”佛罗伦萨通过其历史学者们获得了比历史见证更进一步的东西——盛名，超越了意大利任何其他城市。

我们现在的任务并不是要写这座卓越城市国家的历史，而只是要说明佛罗伦萨人因之感谢这一历史的知识分子的自由和独立。

意大利其他任何一个城市的政党斗争都没有这样激烈，开始得那么早，持续得那么长久。关于这些斗争的描述确实开始于较晚的时期，但这些描述清楚地证明了佛罗伦萨批判主义精神的优越性。

这些斗争危机的牺牲者之一，是在家乡和流放生活中成长起来的但丁·阿利基里，这是一个多么伟大的政治家啊！他在强硬的诗行中，表达了对于故乡城市宪法不断修改和实验的轻蔑，只要同样的政治事件再次发生，这些诗行就会一直流传下去。他用既蔑视又向往、足以拨动同胞心弦的话语向家乡人发表讲话。但是他的思想遍布意大利和整个世界；如果他对于帝国的热情像他所构想的，只不过是一种幻想，那也必须承认，对于一种新生的政治事业的青春梦想就他而言，具有诗歌的崇高壮丽。他很自豪是第一个走上这条路的人，当然是沿着亚里士多德的足迹，却又是独立地以他自己的方式行走的人。他理想的皇帝是一个富有正义感和人道主义精神的法官，他只依靠上帝，是得到大自然、正义和上帝意志所认可的罗马帝国之世界统治的继承人。根据这一观点，征服世界是正义的行为，是建立在罗马帝国和世界其他国家之间的神授裁决上，并且上帝许可这个帝国这样做，因为在其荣光下，他成为人，出生时上报给奥古斯都皇帝的人口普查，死去时呈送给庞提乌斯·彼拉多的审判。也许我们发现很难欣赏这些和其他类似的辩解；但是但丁的热情总会使我们同意他的意见。在他的信件中，他作为最早的时事评论员之一出现，并且也许是第一个以这种形式出版政治小册子的俗人。他开始得很早，在比阿特丽丝死后不久，他就写了一本关于佛罗伦萨这个国家的小册子——《给世界上的伟大人物》；而从他被放逐时起，在后来的岁月里所发表的公开言论全都针对皇帝、君主和枢机主教。在这些信件和他的著作《俗语论》中，反复萦绕着一种用极端痛苦的辛劳所换来的感觉，即这个被放逐者也许只可以在别处，而不是在他的家乡找到一个语言和文化的知识分子的家园，这个家园不可能从他身边带走。关于这一点，我们在下文中要详述。

相较于维兰尼两兄弟——乔万尼和马提奥——的深刻的政治思索，我们更感激其新颖而实际的观察、佛罗伦萨统计的要素和对其他国家的重要短评。在这里贸易和商业也曾推动了经济学和政治学的发展。世界上没有任何一个地方关于财政事务有这样准确的资料。阿维尼翁的教廷的财产，在教皇约翰二十二世去世时达到2500万金弗罗林，如果不是根据可靠的权威记载，会令人难以置信。只有在佛罗伦萨这里，我们才能见到像英格兰国王从佛罗伦萨的巴尔第和佩鲁齐家族那里所签订的巨额贷款，他们在国王陛下身上损失了136.5万金弗罗林（1338年）——这是他们自己及其合伙人的钱——但不管怎么说他们还是从这次打击中恢复了过来。这里记载着有关佛罗伦萨这个时期现状的更重要的事实：国家收入（超过30万金弗罗林）和花销；这个城市的人口数——这是按照面包的消耗量，比如每人的口粮，只是大约估计——定为9万人，还有整个领土上的人口数；在每年受洗的5800到6000个婴儿中间，男婴比女婴多出300到500人；在小学生中，有8000到10000人学习阅读，六所学校里的1000到1200人学习算术；除此之外，还有600个学生在四所学校里学习拉丁文法和逻辑。接着记载着以下各项的统计：教会和修道院、医院——有1000多个床位、羊毛贸易——附有最宝贵的详细资料、造币厂、城市的粮食供应、公职人员等等。我们在翻阅中也偶然了解了许多稀奇古怪的事实：例如在1353年，当首次确定发行公债时，方济各会修道士怎样在布道坛上赞成这项措施，而多米尼克会修道士和奥古斯丁会修道士怎样反对它。有关黑死病的经济上的后果，整个欧洲没有任何其他地方像这个城市一样做过或者能够作出观察和描述。只有一个佛罗伦萨人才可能把下面这种情况记录下来：人们是怎样期待着减少的人口会使各种物品价格便宜，相反，劳务和商品的价格，在这种期待没有实现的情况下，又是如何涨了一倍；普通人是怎样最初根本不愿意工作而只沉湎于享乐；在这个城市是怎样必须付给极高的薪资才能找到男女仆人；农民是怎样只耕作最好的土地而任由其余土地荒芜；庞大的遗产是怎样在瘟疫中遗赠给穷人而后来似乎毫无用处，因为穷人或者已经死去或者已不再贫穷。最后，利用一个无子女的慈善家给这个城市的每一个乞丐六个“达那利”银币的大额遗赠的机会，文献试图对佛罗伦萨的乞丐情况做一个全面的统计。

这种对于事物的统计观点后来在佛罗伦萨得以更高度的发展，与此有关值得注意的一点是，一般说来，我们能够看到它与历史的更高方面、与艺术以及通常所说的文化的联系。在同一文献中，1422年的一份财产报表提到了“新市场”周围的72个交换所；流通中的硬币的数量（200万金弗罗林）；然后是当时新兴的金织工业；丝制品；菲利波·布鲁内莱斯科——当时正忙于从坟墓中挖掘古代建筑；共和国大臣列奥那多·阿雷提诺正努力复兴古代文学和修辞学；最后，它谈到了这个城市当时不受政治斗争影响的普遍繁荣和意大利摆脱了外国雇佣兵的幸运。上面所引述的大约从同一年开始的威尼斯统计，当然证明了威尼斯所拥有的更大财富和利润，以及更广阔的商业范围；在佛罗伦萨派出首批军舰（1422年）到亚力山大港之前，威尼斯长久以来就已是海上霸主。但是每一个读者都能够清楚地认识到佛罗伦萨文献更高的精神气魄。这些以及各种类似的一览表每隔十年再次出现，系统地加以安排和列表显示，而在其他地方我们最多发现一些偶然的简单介绍。我们能够对名列第一位的美第奇家族的财产和产业形成一个约略的估计；他们从1434年到1471年用于慈善、公共建筑和各种税的付出不少于663755金弗罗林，其中40多万是柯西莫一个人承担的，而洛伦佐·麦格尼菲柯很高兴这笔钱花得如此恰当。在1478年，我们对于这个城市的商业和贸易再次有了非常重要、在此方面算是完整的发现，其中一些可以全部或部分地被看作属于精致的艺术品——比如那些必须与锦缎、金银刺绣、木雕镶嵌、在大理石和沙石上的阿拉伯式雕花、蜡像、珠宝以及金制品等等打交道的商业和贸易。佛罗伦萨人对于外部生活系统化的与生俱来的才能在他们关于农业、商业和家庭经济方面的著作中得到表现，他们这些书籍明显优于15世纪其他欧洲人的著作。出版这些著作的选集是正确的决定，尽管需要做大量的研究以便从中提炼出清楚而明确的结论。不论怎样，我们认识这个城市毫不费力，在这里，弥留之际的父母在他们的遗嘱中请求政府，如果他们的儿子拒绝从事一份常规的工作就罚他们1000弗罗林。

16世纪的上半叶，也许世界上没有一个国家拥有像瓦尔奇对于佛罗伦萨的辉煌描写那样的文献资料。它在这个城市的自由和伟大沉入坟墓之前，在叙述性的统计上，像很多其他事情一样，给我们留下了另一个范例。

可是，这种对于外部生活的统计上的估计始终如一地伴随着对于我们已提到过的政治事件的叙述。

佛罗伦萨不仅存在于比意大利和整个欧洲的自由国家更变化多端的政治形式下，而且它在这些政治形式上的反映更深刻。它是一面忠实的镜子，反映了个人以及阶级和反复无常的整体的关系。如弗鲁瓦沙尔所描绘的那样，反映法兰西和法兰德斯伟大的市民民主的图画，以及14世纪德意志编年史作者的叙述，确实非常重要；但在思想的全面和故事的合乎情理的发展上，没有一部作品能和佛罗伦萨人的相比拟。贵族的统治、暴君、中产阶级和无产阶级的斗争，有限制的和没有限制的民主、伪民主、一家一户的秘密、萨沃那罗拉的神权政治，以及为美第奇的暴君专制铺平道路的混合政治形式——全被非常详尽地描述出来，以至于演员最隐秘的动机都暴露在灯光之下。马基雅维利在他的佛罗伦萨历史（到1492年止）中把故乡城市描述为一个活着的有机体，把它的发展描述为一个自然而单独的过程；他是现代人中第一个将此上升到这样一种观念的人。我们的研究范围不包括判断马基雅维利是否并在哪些点上歪曲了历史，像他的卡斯特鲁乔·卡斯特拉卡内传这个臭名昭著的例子——关于那位典型暴君的一幅空想出来的图画。我们也许可以发现一些反驳他所著《佛罗伦萨史》的每一行的材料，但整部著作伟大而独特的价值不会受到影响。他的同时代的人和后继者们，亚科波·彼蒂、圭奇阿尔狄尼、塞尼、瓦尔奇、维托利，这是一组多么卓越优秀的名字啊！这些大师们向我们讲述的是多么精彩的故事啊！这里展现着佛罗伦萨共和国最后几十年里所发生的伟大而值得纪念的戏剧性事件。这本记载了当时世界所能呈现的最高最独特生活的衰落的多卷本著作，在一个人看来，也许不过像是一部奇闻异事集，在另一个人心里也许会唤起他看到如此高贵而富丽堂皇的生活像船只失事般毁灭所产生的魔鬼般的喜悦，对于第三个人来说，也许看起来像是一个伟大的历史审判；对于所有人它将永远是一个思索和研究的对象。永远扰乱这个城市和平的恶行，就是它对于像比萨这样曾经强大而现在被征服的对手的统治——一种其后果必然是长期暴力状态的统治。唯一的补救措施——当然是一个极端的办法，而且除了萨沃那罗拉没人能说服佛罗伦萨接受——就是选择恰当时机消灭托斯卡纳，使它变成一个自由城市的联邦国家。后来，这个不过是一个过去时代的梦想的计划把卢卡的一个爱国公民送上了绞刑架（1548年）。由于这一恶行，并由于佛罗伦萨的注定要倒霉的圭尔夫派对一个外国君主抱有同情，佛罗伦萨不断遭到外国的干涉，带来了随后的所有灾难。但是谁不敬佩这个民族呢？这个民族由可敬的传教士培养起一种持久不变的高尚心境，以至于首次在意大利树立了不杀降敌的榜样，虽然它过去的整个历史所教导的无非是复仇与消灭。那种把爱国主义融入具有道德新生的人身上的光辉，当从远处看时，也许好像很快就消逝了；但它最好的结果却在值得纪念的1529至1530年之围中重新闪耀。他们是“傻瓜”，像圭奇阿尔狄尼当时所写的，给佛罗伦萨带来了这一风暴，但他自己也承认他们做成了好像是让人难以置信的事情；当他宣称明智的人民会逃脱这一危险时，他的意思不过是说佛罗伦萨本应该默默地、不光彩地投降，落入敌手。毫无疑问这会保存它壮丽的城郊和花园，还有无数市民的生命和富足的生活，但是相较于它最伟大最崇高的一次记忆来，这就很不体面。

在许多主要优点方面，佛罗伦萨人是意大利人，一般来说也是现代欧洲人的模式和最早的类型；同样，在许多缺点方面他们也是如此。当但丁把这个总是在修改其政体的城市和一个不断变换姿势以摆脱痛苦的病人相比较时，他用比较的方式触及了佛罗伦萨政治生活的永恒特征。那些认为通过把现存势力和各种趋势结合起来就可以创造一种政体的重大现代谬论，不断地在动乱的时候出现；就连马基雅维利也没有完全免于此。从不缺乏这样的政治艺术家，他们通过对政治权力的一种巧妙分配和划分，通过最复杂的间接选举，通过设立名义上的职务的方法，寻求建立事情的一种永久秩序，并且寻求满足或者欺骗富人，同样还有穷人。他们天真地效法古代的做法，借用政党名称“清流党”、“贵族党”，是一件自然的事。从那时起人们就习惯了这些名称并赋予它们一种传统的欧洲意义，而所有先前的党派名称则纯粹具有民族性，这些名字或者代表不和的原因，或者是由于事件偶然得名。但是，一个名字对于一个政治事业色彩的渲染或褪去，其作用是多么大啊！

在所有那些认为有可能建设一个国家的人们当中，最无与伦比、最伟大的是马基雅维利。他把存在的各种力量看作是有生命和主动的，对于可能的选择，有一个大的而准确的看法，试图既不误导自己也不误导别人。没人比他更能不受虚荣和浮夸的影响，确实，他写作不是为民众，而是为君主和管理者，或是为个人的朋友。对于他的危险并不在于天才的装模作样或对于思想观点顺序安排的错误，而是在于他显然难以控制的强大的想象力。他的政治评价的客观性，在真实性方面有时令人震惊；但它是生死危亡之际而非平常之需的标志，那时，很难相信正义，或者信任别人有公正的行为。我们抛弃了对于他的道德上的声讨，我们已经看到我们自己这个世纪的政治家们是从什么意义上理解政治道德的。不管怎么说，马基雅维利能够在自己的事业中忘记自己。事实上，尽管他的作品（除了个别词句）完全没有热情，并且最后佛罗伦萨人自己把他看作是一个罪人，但他是一个完完全全的爱国者。尽管他像他的大多数同时代人一样，在言语和道德方面很自由，但他始终思考的是国家的福利。

他在佛罗伦萨建立一个新政治制度的最完整的方案是在他纪念教皇列奥十世的文章中提出来的，此文作于小洛伦佐·美第奇——乌尔比诺公爵（死于1519年）——死后，他曾把他的著作《君主论》献给这位公爵。国家那时正处于穷途末路、腐败不堪的状态，所提出的补救措施在道德上并不总是正当的；但非常有趣的是看到他如何希望建立具有温和民主形式的共和国，它好像是美第奇家族的女继承人。我们想象不出一个比这更巧妙的对教皇、对教皇的各种信徒，以及对佛罗伦萨的不同利益作出让步的计划；我们可以想象自己在观察一个钟表的装置。原则、观察报告、比较、政治预测诸如此类，大量出现在其著作《史论集》中，其中闪耀着远见卓识的光辉。例如，他清楚地认识到共和制度及其组织机构的尽管不是一以贯之却是持续不断的发展规律，并要求宪法要灵活、能变化，作为避免杀戮和放逐的唯一手段。同样的原因，为了防范私人的暴力和外国的干涉——“所有自由的死亡杀手”——他希望看到引进一种司法程序（“起诉”）来处置被憎恨的市民，而在此之前佛罗伦萨只有审理丑闻案件的法庭。他以大师的手笔使不情愿判决和非自愿判决各具特点，这两种判决在共和国家的紧要关头起着非常重要的作用。有一次，他被他的想象力和各种事件的压力所误导，作出了与他能力不相符的事——称赞了人民，他说人民比任何君主能更好地选出他们自己的官员，并且能够用“善意的劝告”来使他们改正错误。关于托斯卡纳政府，他毫不怀疑它属于他的故乡城市，在一篇特别的“论文”中，他强调重新征服比萨是一个生死攸关的问题；他痛惜阿雷佐在1502年的叛乱之后没有被夷为平地；他整体上承认，必须允许意大利的共和国自由扩张，增加领土，以便在国内享有和平，并且不会受到外来的攻击；但他宣称，佛罗伦萨总是从错误的一端开始，从一开始就树立了比萨、卢卡和锡耶纳这些死敌，而“被待如兄弟”的皮斯托亚自愿地服从它。

把15世纪仍然存在的其他几个共和国和这个独特的城市——这个意大利的，确实也是现代欧洲精神的最重要的创造工厂——作比较是不合乎情理的。锡耶纳苦于其最严重的组织弊病，就此来说，它艺术上和工业上的相对繁荣一定不会误导我们。伊尼亚斯·希尔维优斯从他的家乡心怀向往，远望“快乐的”德意志帝国城市，那里没有土地和货物的没收充公，没有恣意妄为的官吏，没有政治党派所有这些使生活更加痛苦的因素。热那亚几乎不在我们讨论的范围内，因为在安德烈·多利亚的时代之前，它几乎没有参与文艺复兴。确实，里维埃拉的居民在意大利人中间以蔑视所有更高的文化而臭名昭著。党派之争在这里表现出非常激烈的特性，并且极为严重地扰乱了整个生活进程，以至于我们很难理解，热那亚人在经过这么多革命和侵略之后，怎么设法恢复到一个能持久的状况。也许是由于这一事实：几乎所有参加公共事务的人同时几乎无一例外地都是积极经商的人。热那亚的例子以惊人的方式表明拥有远方的殖民地与什么样的不安全财富和庞大的商业，什么样的内部骚乱，是可以和谐共存的。

卢卡在15世纪并不重要。

第七章　外交政策

意大利的大多数城市国家，就像在其内部政体结构上是艺术品，即深思熟虑和精心改造适应的结果一样，它们彼此之间以及和外国的关系也是一种艺术品。这些国家几乎全都是新近篡权的产物，这一事实对于他们的对外政策和对内政策一样有着致命的影响。它们没有一个无保留地承认另一个国家；对于建立和巩固一个朝代起过作用的同样的机会也可以颠覆另一个朝代。是否能保持安定和平，并不总是一件由暴君来做选择的事。所有非法政权无一例外必然进行运动和扩张。所以意大利就变成了一个“外交政策”的舞台，这种政策，也像在其他国家一样，逐渐地获得了一个公认的国际法律体系的地位。这种对于国际事务既无偏见也无道德顾虑的纯客观处理，达到了完美的程度；有时其本身并非没有某种美好和伟大之处，但整体来说，它却给我们以无底深渊的印象。

阴谋、军队、同盟、腐化和谋反构成了这一时期意大利的外部历史。尤其是威尼斯很久以来都受到各方谴责，指责它试图征服整个半岛，或者逐渐削弱半岛的力量，以致最终一个个国家必定会落入她手中。但根据深入观察，这种怨言很明显并非来自人民，而是来自被人民所憎恶的宫廷和官员阶层，而威尼斯的温和政府已经为自己获得普遍的信任作了保证。就连有着难以控制的从属城市的佛罗伦萨，除了对威尼斯商业上的妒忌和威尼斯在罗马涅的发展，也发现自己相对于威尼斯处在一种虚假的地位。最后，坎姆布雷同盟确实给了这个全意大利本应该以联合的力量给予支持的国家以沉重一击。

其他国家也被同样不友好的感情所驱使，时刻准备使用其邪恶本性所想到的斗争手段来互相攻击。洛德维科·伊·摩洛，那不勒斯的阿拉戈纳国王们和教皇西克塔斯四世——不必说那些较小的政权——使意大利处于一种持续不断的危险动荡之中。要是这种残暴的角逐仅限于意大利就好了；但这种角逐具有这一性质，即最终会向外国人——尤其是向法兰西人和土耳其人——寻求干涉和帮助。

人民大众的同情完全在法兰西一边。佛罗伦萨从未停止过以令人震惊的天真承认其对于法兰西人有着老圭尔夫派的偏爱。当查理八世出现在阿尔卑斯山南部地区时，全意大利以一种他本人及其追随者似乎都不能解释的热情迎接他。在意大利人的想象中，以萨沃那罗拉为例，一个明智、公正和强有力的救世主和统治者的理想形象仍然活着，不同之处在于：他不再是但丁所祈求的皇帝，而是法兰西的卡贝族国王。这种幻想随着他的离去破灭了；但很久以后，所有人才明白查理八世、路易十二世和弗朗西斯一世是怎样完全误解了他们和意大利的真正关系，以及受到多么低劣动机的引导。就君主们来说，他们试图用完全不同的方式来利用法兰西。当法英战争结束时，当路易十一世四面八方到处布置他外交的罗网时，当勃艮第的查理开始他愚蠢的冒险行动时，意大利各内阁政府准备在各个方面应付他们。很明显，即使法兰西从没要求过那不勒斯和米兰的领土，它的干涉也只是个时间问题，并且它过去对热那亚和皮埃蒙特的干涉仅仅是一个要仿效的先例。其实，威尼斯人早在1462年就已经预料到这一点了。米兰的加利佐·马利亚公爵在勃艮第战争中显然既是路易的同盟又是查理的同盟，因此他有理由害怕来自双方的攻击，他这种战争期间的道义上的恐惧在他的书信里明显地表现出来。就像“豪华者”洛伦佐所理解的使四个主要的意大利政权保持均势的计划，只是一种令人愉快的乐观主义精神的假设，这种乐观主义精神比一个试验政策的轻率和佛罗伦萨的圭尔夫主义的迷信有过之而无不及，并一直坚持往最好处着想。当“豪华者”洛伦佐对那不勒斯的费兰特和教皇西克塔斯四世作战，路易十一世向他提供援助时，他回答说：“我不能把自己的利益置于全意大利的安全之上，但愿在这个国家尝试他们力量的想法从未进入过法兰西国王们的头脑中！要是他们这样做，意大利就完了。”对于其他君主，法兰西国王是轮流吓唬他们自己和他们的敌人的鬼怪，每当他们看到再也没有可行的办法来走出困境时，他们就威胁着要把他召来。在教皇们这方面，则幻想他们可以利用法兰西而对自己没有任何危险，甚至英诺森八世也想象他可以撤退到北方生气，然后从那里率领一支法兰西军队作为征服者返回意大利。

的确，有思想的人在查理八世远征之前很久就预见了外国的征服。当查理再次回到阿尔卑斯山的那一边时，每个人都清楚地看到一个干涉的时代已经开始。这时不幸一个个纷至沓来；法兰西和西班牙这两个主要侵略者，已经成为欧洲的强大政权，他们已不再满足于口头上的效忠，而是拼死争夺在意大利的势力和领土，人们对此明白得太晚了。他们已经开始变得和意大利的中央集权国家相似，实际上是开始模仿它们，只不过是放大比例地模仿。吞并领土或交换领土的计划一时间无限增多。其结果，如大家所熟知，是西班牙的完全胜利，它就像反宗教改革的剑和盾一样，长期使教廷位列它的其他附属国之中。哲学家们的悲叹只能向他们表明，那些引狼入室的人都没有好下场。

在同一时期，和土耳其人结成的联盟也毫无顾忌或掩饰；这一做法被认为不比任何其他政治上的权宜之计更糟糕。西方基督教界团结的信仰在十字军东征过程的不同时期被严重动摇过，弗里德里克二世也许已经摆脱了这种信仰。但是，东方各民族新近的发展和希腊帝国的危急与灭亡在整个西欧又重燃旧日的感情，虽然它不如以前强烈。然而，意大利对此却是个惊人的例外。尽管对土耳其人和来自他们的实际危险怀有极大的恐惧，但是几乎没有一个举足轻重的政府不和穆罕默德二世及其继承者们共同密谋反对意大利其他国家的。即使他们没有这样做，人们仍然相信他们这样做了；这种恶行也敌不过派间谍在威尼斯的贮水池里下毒，这是对那不勒斯国王阿尔方索的继承者们的指控。对于西吉斯蒙多·马拉泰斯达那样的恶棍，人们不能期待他会作出比竟然召土耳其人进入意大利更好的事情来。但是我们读到，穆罕默德在其他意大利政府，尤其是威尼斯的怂恿下，曾经从其手中强夺了奥特朗托（1480年）的那不勒斯的阿拉戈纳君主们，后来也煽动苏丹巴雅泽特二世反对威尼斯人。对于洛德维科·伊·摩洛也有同样的指控。“在土耳其人手中被害者的鲜血和囚犯们的凄惨境遇，都在呼吁上帝报复他。”国史编撰者说。在政府能够得知一切消息的威尼斯，大家都知道，佩札罗的统治者，摩尔的表兄弟乔万尼·斯福查曾经招待去米兰途中的土耳其大使们。15世纪的教皇中最受人尊敬的两位，尼古拉五世和庇护二世，因土耳其人的势力发展感到深深的悲痛而死去，的确，后者是在希望亲自率领十字军东征的准备中死去的；他们的继承者们贪污了基督教界为此目的而捐献的财物，并把作为回报而颁发的赎罪券降为私人的商业投机买卖。英诺森八世为了获得逃亡者杰姆王子的兄弟巴雅泽特二世所付的报酬，同意把杰姆王子关进监狱做其看守；而亚历山大六世支持在君士坦丁堡的洛德维科·伊·摩洛所采取的推进土耳其对威尼斯攻击的措施（1498年），因此威尼斯用召开宗教会议来威胁他。很明显，弗朗西斯一世和苏里曼二世之间臭名昭著的联盟并不是什么新鲜事或者前所未闻的事。

确实，我们发现这样的例子：在全体居民看来，整体归顺土耳其人似乎并不是特别的罪恶。即使它只是作为对于压迫人民的政府的一种威胁而被提出，那也至少证明这种想法已被大家所熟知。早在1480年，巴蒂斯塔·曼托万诺就使我们清楚地明白亚德里亚海岸的大部分居民预见到这种事情，尤其安科那渴望发生这种事。当罗马涅遭受列奥十世的压迫统治时，拉文纳的一个代表公开对罗马教皇的使者，枢机主教朱利奥·美第奇说：“主教大人，尊敬的威尼斯共和国因怕和教皇的争端不会接受我们；但是，如果土耳其人来到腊古扎，我们将把自己置于他们掌控下。”

对于当时西班牙人开始的对于意大利的奴役来说，这是一种可怜却并非毫无根据的安慰，至少这个国家免去了等待其在土耳其统治下要堕入的原始野蛮状态。尽管它已四分五裂，但靠它自身的力量几乎不可能逃脱这一命运。

有着所有这些弊端，如果说这一时期意大利政治家的才能还有值得我们称赞之处，那只是由于它对那些不受恐惧、激情或恶意影响的问题的切合实际而无成见的处理。这里没有效仿北方风气对各种权利进行人为规划的封建制度；有的只是每一个人所拥有的像在理论上一样在实践中所持有的权力。这里没有侍从贵族在君主头脑中培养中世纪的会产生各种奇怪后果的荣誉感；而是君主们和顾问官员们根据特殊事件的紧急状态和他们心中的目的采取一致的行动。对于那些不管来自何处的效劳同盟者的人，不会对有可能疏远支持者的特权阶级有自豪感；出身无足轻重的雇佣兵队长这一阶层的存在，足以清楚表明真正的权力掌握在哪种人手中；最后，开明的暴君手中的政府，有着同时代北方诸国无可比拟的对本国和邻邦的准确了解，并且能够最精确地估计友邦和敌国经济上和道义上的能力。那些统治者，虽有严重错误，但都是天生的统计学大师。与这样的一些人一起，谈判是可能的；可以设想，当把实际的理由摆在他们面前时，他们是会被说服的，并且他们的观点也会被修改。当那不勒斯伟大的阿尔方索成为菲利波·马利亚·维斯康提的阶下囚时（1434年），他能够使监禁他的人相信：安茹家族在那不勒斯的统治而不是他自己的统治将使法兰西人成为意大利的主人；菲利波·马利亚没要赎金就释放了他，并和他结成联盟。一个北方的君主几乎不会作出同样的事情，道德观念在其他方面像维斯康提的君主当然也不会。对于注重自身利益的巨大信心表现在“豪华者”洛伦佐对背信弃义的那不勒斯的费兰特访问中——费兰特当然想要囚禁他，并且这样做绝不是过于审慎——这次访问令佛罗伦萨人普遍感到震惊。因为拘捕一个强大的君主，勒令他签字要不然就侮辱他，然后再释放，就像“大胆者”查理在佩龙纳对路易十一所为（1468年），对于意大利人来说，似乎是一种疯狂的举动；因此人们预计洛伦佐载誉归来，要不然就是一去不返。政治说服的艺术，在此时，被提到一定的高度——尤其是被威尼斯的大使们——北方各民族首次从意大利人那里获得一种概念，并且正式的演说提供了一个极不完全的观点。这些演说只不过是人文主义者的辞令。外交中虽另有客气的礼节，但在必要时，也不乏粗暴而率直的讲话。像马基雅维利那样的一个人在他的《使节》中是以一种悲哀的色彩出现的。尽管得到有限的指示，装备又很寒酸，并且被看作是一个地位卑下的代表，但他绝没有失去他自由而广泛的观察力或是喜爱生动逼真的描写的才能。

这本书将专门有一部分讨论对于作为个人和作为民族的人的研究，这一研究在意大利人中间是和对于人类生活的外部状况的研究相互联系的。

第八章　战争艺术

这里必须简要地说明，战争艺术是采取什么步骤而表现出一种深思熟虑的产物的特点。所有的西方国家，中世纪时对个别兵士的训练在当时普遍的攻守体系的范围内是很完备的。在围攻和筑城设防的艺术方面，也并不缺乏心灵手巧的发明家。但是，战略和战术两方面的发展却受到了军队中服役的性质和期限以及贵族们的野心的阻碍，这些贵族们大敌当前却争论地位的优先问题，并且只是缺少纪律而招致了像克雷西和莫佩提乌斯那样伟大战役的失败。相反，意大利是第一个采取需要一种完全不同的组织的雇佣兵制度的国家；并且较早引进火器促使战争成为平民的事务，这不仅是因为最坚固的城堡也抵挡不住炮轰，而且也是因为工程师、枪炮铸造师和炮手们——这些属于贵族以外的另一个阶层的人们——的技术当时在战役中最重要。让人感到遗憾的是，过去曾经是这个小而组织良好的雇佣兵队伍灵魂的个人价值，将会遭到这些在远处发挥作用的新手段的破坏；有些雇佣兵队长至少是极端反对引进最近德意志发明的步枪的。我们读到保罗·维特利，当他识别出大炮并自己使用时，他挖掉了敌军战俘“火枪手”的眼睛，砍掉了他们的手，因为他认为，一个勇敢的、也许是高贵的骑士，被一个平凡卑贱的步卒所杀伤是可耻的。然而总的来说，这些新发现直到意大利人在建筑防御工事和攻打它们的方法两方面成为全欧洲的导师时才被接受和采用。像乌尔比诺的菲德利哥和费拉拉的阿尔方索那样的君主都精通这一科目，与此相比，就连马克西米利安一世的知识也显得很肤浅。在意大利，早于其他地方，有一种全面的军事科学和技术；在这里，第一次，只有很强的指挥才能本身才受到大家无偏见的喜爱，确实，这一指挥才能也许是由于党派的频繁更换和雇佣兵队长完全感情用事的情绪所产生的。在1451年和1452年发生在弗兰切斯科·斯福查和亚科波·皮奇尼诺之间的米兰与威尼斯战争期间，学者吉安·安托尼奥·波尔切洛·德·潘多尼参加了后者的指挥总部，他受那不勒斯的阿尔方索的委派，撰写这一战役的报告。这个报告是用虽不是最纯粹却很流畅的拉丁文写的，有点过于追求当时人文主义的夸张风格，它模仿凯撒的《高卢战记》，一些演讲词、奇闻怪事之类散布其间。在此之前的100年以来，人们一直认真地争论西庇阿·阿非利加奴斯和汉尼拔谁更伟大，皮奇尼诺在全书中偏偏被称为西庇阿，而斯福查偏被称为汉尼拔。但是关于米兰的军队也得写一些正面的事情；这位博学者参见了斯福查，由他陪同检视了军队，高度称赞他所看到的一切，并答应把它写下来传诸后代。除了他，当时意大利的作品对于战争和战略手段的描述也很丰富，这些作品不仅供专业人士而且也为受一般教育的人士阅读使用。而同时代北方人的记叙，如迪博尔德·席林所著《勃艮第战争》则仍然保留纯编年史的平铺直叙、就事论事、枯燥乏味的特点。最伟大的军事艺术爱好者马基雅维利当时正忙于创作他的《战争艺术》，他曾以军事爱好者的身份进行创作。但是，士兵个人的发展在一对或者多对决斗者的公开而严肃的决斗中得到了最充分的体现，这种决斗早在著名的“巴尔莱达挑战”（1503年）之前很久就有了。胜利者得到保证会获得诗人和学者的赞扬，而北方的战士则得不到。这些决斗的结果不再被看作是上帝的判决，而被看作是个人才能的胜利，并且在旁观者的心中，它似乎既是一场激烈竞争的裁决，也是一种军队或国家荣誉的满足感。

很显然，这种对于战争事务的纯粹理性的处理方式，即使没有强烈的政治仇恨，但在某些情况下，如已答应部队可以劫掠城市时，就会产生最残暴的恶行。斯福查曾被迫准许他的士兵抢劫皮亚琴察（1447年），这个市镇经过40天的蹂躏后，长期无人居住，最后不得不用武力强迫人们迁来居住。然而像这样的暴行比之后来由外国军队，特别是西班牙军队所带给意大利的悲惨命运算不了什么。在这些西班牙人身上，或许是些许的东方人的血液，或者是熟悉异端裁判所场面，竟释放出人类天性中魔鬼的一面。在看到他们在普拉托、罗马和其他地方的所作所为之后，很难对“天主教徒”斐迪南和查理五世产生任何更大的兴趣，他们知道这是什么样的游牧人群，然而却不加约束。从这些统治者的密室里逐渐曝光的大批文献材料，将永远是历史资料的重要来源；但从这样的人身上不可能期盼找到任何政治概念的硕果。

第九章　罗马教皇政府

罗马教会的教皇政府和领地是这样奇怪的产物，以至于我们到目前为止，在确定意大利城市国家的一般特点时，只是偶尔提到过它们。其他国家极感兴趣的对于政治计谋的审慎选择和改变适应，我们在罗马却很少看到；因为在这里，宗教权力经常能够掩盖或弥补世俗权力的缺陷。在14世纪和15世纪初，当教皇被带到阿维尼翁监禁起来时，这个国家经历了像火炙烤般的多么严峻的考验啊！起初，一切都陷于混乱之中，但教皇有金钱、军队和一位伟大的政治家兼将军——西班牙人阿尔沃诺斯，他重新使这个教会国家完全顺服。在教会分立时，这个国家所面临的最终解体的危险更大，那时罗马教皇和法国教皇双方都没有充足的财力重新征服新近丢失的国家；但这在罗马教会恢复统一之后，在马丁五世时做到了，而在又一次面临同样的危险时，又在尤金尼斯四世时做到了。但是这个教会国家在意大利的各个政权当中一直是个完全异常的国家；在罗马本城及其附近，教皇正遭到科伦纳、奥尔西尼、萨维利和安吉拉拉等大家族的公然反抗；在翁布里亚、边境地区、罗马涅和那些市民共和国——教皇政府对于它们的忠诚一直以来没有什么感激——已经几乎不存在了；它们已经被一群大大小小的君主王朝所取代，这些王朝的忠诚和服从并不重要。作为靠自身的能力而自我独立的政权，它们只关注自己；从这一点来看，它们之中最重要的王朝我们已讨论过。

尽管如此，也几乎不能省却对教皇政府作几句一般的评述。在15世纪的进程中，新的奇怪的危险和考验降临到这个国家，因为这个民族的政治精神开始在各方面控制它，并且把它拉进自己的活动范围内。这些危险中最次要的来自人民或来自外国；最严重的根植于教皇们自身的性格。

此刻，让我们先撇开阿尔卑斯山那一边的国家不论。当教皇政府在意大利面临致命危险时，它没有也不可能从当时路易十一统治下的法兰西，或者从被玫瑰战争牵涉很大精力的英格兰，或者从当时秩序混乱的西班牙王国，或者从新近在巴塞尔宗教会议上被出卖的德意志获得一点帮助。在意大利本国，有一些受过教育，甚至没受过教育的人们，他们的民族虚荣心因教皇政府的意大利性质而感到荣幸；许多人的个人利益取决于教皇政府具有和保持这种性质；广大的人民群众仍然信仰教皇赐福和授任圣职的功德；其中像维特洛佐·维特利那样臭名昭著的罪人，在教皇的儿子令人把他绞死的时候，还在祈求亚历山大六世赦免他的罪恶。但是，就是把所有这些同情的理由加在一起，也不足以从敌人手中拯救教皇政府，要是后者真正认真起来，并且知道怎样利用人们对这个制度的妒忌和仇恨的话。

就在指望外援如此渺茫的时候，在教皇政府内部出现了最危险的症状，像它此时这样，以世俗的意大利君主政府的精神生活做事，它就不能不像它们那样遭受同样阴暗的经历；但是，它自身特殊的本性给予这些阴影一抹特有的色彩。

就罗马这个城市本身而论，它内部的煽动力量微乎其微，如此众多的是被人民的骚动驱逐之后又回来的教皇，并且教廷驻在罗马对于罗马人的利益，意义如此重大。但是，罗马不仅有时候表现出一种明确的反教皇的激进主义，而且在当时所策划的最严重的阴谋中，表明有来自外部的无形操纵。斯蒂法诺·波尔卡罗反对尼古拉五世（1453年）——那位对这个城市的繁荣付出最多的教皇——的阴谋就是如此。波尔卡罗的目的是彻底推翻教皇的统治，他有杰出的同谋者，尽管他们的名字没有留传下来，但肯定能在当时意大利的国家政府里找到。就在这位教皇的任期内，洛伦佐·瓦拉以希望罗马教会国家快速世俗化，作为他那著名的反对君士坦丁礼物的慷慨激昂演说的结论。

教皇庇护二世不得不与之斗争的卡提里那集团（1460年），同样坦率地公开宣称，他们决心推翻教士的政府，这个集团的领袖提伯吉奥把责任推在确定他那一年能实现愿望的占卜者身上。罗马的几个主要人物塔伦特君主、亚科波·皮奇尼诺雇佣兵队长都是提伯吉奥的同谋和支持者。确实，当我们想一想富有的高级教士的邸宅中所积聚的赃物——阴谋者尤其关注阿奎莱雅枢机主教——我们很惊讶，在一个几乎不设防的城市，这样的企图竟然没有更频繁、更成功。教皇庇护二世宁愿住在任何地方也不愿住在罗马，保罗二世则被置于极大的不安之中，因为一些被撤职的人在普拉提那的指挥下将梵蒂冈围困了20天。要是教皇政权不根除那些贵族集团——这些抢劫帮派正是在其保护下才出头肇事的——它早晚一定会是这些阴谋活动的牺牲品。

这一任务由可怕的教皇西克塔斯四世承担起来。他是第一个把罗马和邻近地区完全置于他控制之下的教皇，特别是在击败了科伦纳家族以后，无论是在他的意大利政策上还是在教会的内部事务上，他都敢于以蛮横无理的挑衅态度行事，并蔑视来自欧洲各地的怨言和召集宗教裁判会议的威胁。他用买卖圣职的办法来获得他自己必需的钱款，这种买卖的范围之广一下子增加到闻所未闻的程度，从枢机主教的任命到最小恩惠的赐予无不如此。西克塔斯自己若不求助这种手段就不会得到教皇的高位。

如此普遍的腐败也许早晚会给罗马教廷带来灾难性后果，但是这还是不可知的未来之事。裙带关系就不是如此了，它一度产生了导致教皇政权彻底毁灭的威胁。在所有的“族亲”中，枢机主教彼埃得罗·利阿里奥起初享有西克塔斯主要，几乎是全部的宠爱。很快他就吸引了全意大利的目光，部分是由于他那极度奢华的生活，部分是由于有关他反对宗教和他政治计划的传言。他和米兰的加利佐·马利亚公爵商定（1473年），后者成为伦巴第国王，然后后者供以金钱和军队帮助他回到罗马，登上教皇的宝座；好像西克塔斯会自愿地向他屈服。这个计划，通过使教皇职位世袭制，最终会使这个教皇国家世俗化，但因彼埃得罗的突然去世而失败。第二个“族亲”吉罗拉谟·利阿里奥，一直是个俗世的人，没有寻求过教皇职位。从这个时候起，这些“族亲”因为要为自己建立世俗的君主国，变成了意大利混乱的新根源。教皇们甚至试图实现他们对那不勒斯所提出的封建权益的要求，以讨他们的欢心。但是，自从卡利克塔斯三世失败后，这样的计划不再可行了，吉罗拉谟·利阿里奥在征服佛罗伦萨（谁知道还有多少其他地方）的企图失败后，也不得不满足于在教皇领土范围内建立国家。罗马涅的君主们和城市暴君们威胁着要彻底摆脱教皇至高无上的权力，并且面临着很快变成斯福查或威尼斯人的猎物的危险，这时罗马出面阻止它，这样做被认为是正当的。但是，在这样的时刻和状况下，谁能保证已变成君主的“族亲”及其后人对于他们已不再在乎的教皇会继续服从呢？即使在教皇的一生中，他对于自己的儿子或侄子也并不总是有把握，因此驱逐前任教皇的“族亲”而代之以自己“族亲”的诱惑非常强烈。整个制度对于教皇政权本身的反作用具有最严重的性质；所有无论世俗的或者宗教的强制手段，为了道德上最不可靠的目的而被毫无顾忌地使用，教皇的所有其他目标相对于这些目的都被变成从属的了。当这些目的不惜以革命和流放的一切代价达到的时候，一个只对毁灭教皇政权最感兴趣的王朝就建立起来了。

在西克塔斯去世的时候，吉罗拉谟只能靠他自己的最大努力和他妻子的娘家斯福查家族的帮助，来维持他篡夺的弗尔利和伊摩拉的世俗君主政权。在西克塔斯去世之后的选举教皇会议上（1484年）——英诺森八世在此会议上当选——发生了一件似乎给教皇政权提供一个新的外部保障的事件。两个枢机主教，同时是统治家族的君主——费兰特国王的儿子阿拉戈纳的乔万尼和摩尔的兄弟阿斯卡尼奥·斯福查，最厚颜无耻地卖掉了他们的选票；因此，那不勒斯和米兰的统治家族，由于能够获得赃物，不管怎么说，对教皇制度的继续存在变得有兴趣。在下届选举教皇会议上，除五人外，当所有的枢机主教都出卖自己时，阿斯卡尼奥又一次获得巨额贿赂，但并未抱有在下一次选举中自己会成为被支持的候选人的希望。

至于“豪华者”洛伦佐，极力希望美第奇家族不要两手空空被发配远方。他把自己的女儿玛达丽娜嫁给新教皇——第一位公开承认自己有孩子的教皇——的儿子弗兰切斯克托·奇博，他不仅期望他自己的儿子枢机主教乔万尼，即后来的列奥十世能得到种种恩惠，而且也期望他的女婿能快速升迁。但关于后者，他的要求是不可能的事。在英诺森八世统治下，国家曾由其建立起来的蛮横鲁莽的裙带关系失去了任何机会，因为弗兰切斯克托自己是个卑劣的家伙，像他的父亲教皇一样，他寻求权力只是为了最卑下的目的聚敛钱财。然而，父亲和儿子施政的这种方式早晚一定会导致最后的大灾祸——国家的解体。要是西克塔斯是通过出售宗教的高位和恩典的办法来充实他的国库的话，那么至于英诺森和他的儿子，则是设立了一个出售世俗恩典的部门，这里高价出售对谋杀罪和屠杀罪的赦免。每一笔罚款中有150金币付给教皇的国库，多出来的钱归给弗兰切斯克托。罗马，在这个教皇任期的后期，蜂拥着有执照的和没执照的暗杀者；西克塔斯曾开始压制的宗派集团又和以前一样活跃起来；在梵蒂冈受到很好保卫的教皇，对于时不时地设置一个陷阱，偶尔能捕获一个富有的犯罪者感到满意。对于弗兰切斯克托，主要问题是知道在教皇去世时能够用什么办法带着装得满满的宝箱逃跑。他最终在听到他父亲死亡的一个假报告时（1490年）暴露了自己，他企图带走教皇国库中所有的钱，当这证明是不可能的事时，他坚持无论如何土耳其的王子杰姆必须和他一起走，作为一个活资本，以备卖个好价钱，也许卖给那不勒斯的费兰特。很难估计遥远时期的政治可能性，但我们禁不住要问自己这个问题，罗马是否在这样的两三任教皇之后还能幸存下来。甚至对于欧洲信仰宗教的国家，让事情发展到了这种地步——不仅旅行者和朝圣者，而且罗马国王马克西米利安的整个使团人员，都在罗马的邻近地区被剥得只剩衬衫，并且使节们经常还没踏足城内就不得不转回来——也是非常鲁莽的。

对于才华横溢的亚历山大六世（1492—1503年在位），这样的状况与其深受鼓舞的权力概念和权力乐趣是不相容的。他做的第一件事就是恢复公共秩序——至少是暂时恢复——和按时支付一切薪金。

严格地说，像我们现在正在讨论意大利文明的空话一样，既然波几亚家族和那不勒斯的家族同样都不是意大利人，这个教皇可以忽略不谈。亚历山大在公众场合和凯撒说西班牙语；露克瑞佳一进入费拉拉，就在那儿穿着西班牙服装，受到西班牙滑稽戏演员的歌唱欢迎；他们的心腹侍从，也像在1500年战争中凯撒最声名狼藉的军队一样，由西班牙人组成；甚至他的绞刑刽子手唐·米切莱托和他的下毒杀手塞瓦斯蒂安·平松·克里蒙尼斯似乎同样是西班牙籍。除其他成就外，凯撒以真正的西班牙方式在围起来的场地中按照斗牛术的规则杀死了六条野公牛。但是，在这个家族里似乎已达顶点的罗马的腐败，在他们来到这个城市时已经得到高度发展。

他们的为人以及所做的事情经常被详细地描述着。他们的直接目的——实际上他们达到了——是彻底征服这个教皇国家。所有那些小暴君——其中大部分是教廷多少有点难以驾驭的封臣——都被驱逐或消灭了，就是在罗马城内，所谓的圭尔夫派的奥尔西尼以及所谓的吉伯林派的科伦纳这两个大宗派集团也被消灭了。但是，所采用的手段具有极为恐怖的性质，要不是父亲和儿子同时被毒死这件事的突然介入而改变了整个局势的面貌的话，这些手段当然会最终导致教皇政权的毁灭。基督教界道德上的愤慨对于亚历山大来说，当然不是招致危险的什么大不了的根源；在国内，他的力量足够强大，可以迫使人们恐惧和服从；外国统治者被争取到他那一边，路易十二甚至尽全力帮助他。整个欧洲的人民几乎想不出在中部意大利正在发生什么事。唯一真正充满危险的时刻——当查理八世在意大利的时候——意外幸运地过去了，就是在那时，也不是教皇政权处于如此的危险中，而是亚历山大有被一个更可尊敬的教皇所取代的危险。教皇政权巨大、永久和日益增长的危险存在于亚历山大本人，尤其是在他儿子凯撒·波几亚的身上。

在父亲的天性中，野心、贪婪、肉欲与坚强和才华横溢的品质结合在一起。所有来自权力和奢侈的享乐，从他教皇任期的第一天起，就最大部分地授予了自己。为达此目的，在手段的选择上，他毫无顾忌；人们马上知道了他会为他选举时所受的损失赔偿自己更多的钱财，并且卖者的买卖圣职罪将会远远超过买者的买卖圣职罪。必须记住，亚历山大先前所担任过的副财政大臣和其他职务已经教会他比教廷的任何其他成员对于各种收入来源都更熟悉，更能实际利用。早在1494年，一个白袍僧，热那亚的亚当——他曾经在罗马讲道攻击过买卖圣职一事——被发现遭人谋杀在床上，身上有20处伤。如果不付出巨额的金钱，几乎没有一个枢机主教能得到任命。

但是，当教皇逐渐受到儿子凯撒·波几亚影响的时候，他的暴力措施就呈现出那种必然对所追求目的起作用的凶暴残忍的性质。在和罗马的贵族以及罗马涅的暴君斗争中的所作所为，在背信弃义和野蛮程度方面甚至超过了世人所熟悉的那不勒斯的阿拉戈纳统治者们的措施；而那种欺诈天赋也更高一筹。凯撒孤立父亲，谋杀弟兄、姻弟兄和其他亲属或廷臣——或者是这些人得到教皇恩宠的时候，或者是他们在任何其他方面的地位于他不利的时候——所采用的方式，实在是骇人听闻。亚历山大被迫默许谋杀他最爱的儿子，甘底亚公爵，因为他自己每时每刻也都生活在对凯撒的恐惧中。

凯撒的最终目的是什么呢？就连在他暴政的最后几个月，当他已经在西尼加利亚谋杀了雇佣兵队长，并且实质上已是这个教皇国家的主人时（1503年），那些站在他左右的人们所给予的谦虚回答是，公爵只是希望镇压宗派集团和暴君们，所有这一切都只为了教廷的利益；至于公爵自己，除罗马涅的君主身份外，他别无所求，而且由于他为所有后来的教皇们除去了奥尔西尼和科伦纳两大家族，他已赢得了教皇们的感激。但是没人愿意承认这是他的最终目的。亚历山大教皇本人，当把他的儿子托付威尼斯保护时，在和威尼斯大使的讨论中，说得比这更透彻。“我要确保，”他说，“将来有一天教皇政府或者属于他，或者属于你们。”凯撒当然也加上一句，没有威尼斯的同意，没人能够成为教皇，为此目的，威尼斯的枢机主教们只好团结在一起。他指的是不是他自己，我们不能说；不管怎么样，他父亲的声明足以证明他的目的在于教皇的宝座。我们进一步从露克瑞佳·波几亚那里得到了一定数量的间接的证据，这是就埃科尔·斯特罗齐的诗中某些段落很可能反映了她作为费拉拉的女大公允许自己使用的表达。在这里，也主要谈到了凯撒对于教皇政权的希望；但是时不时地也暗示了他对全意大利最高统治权的期望；最后使我们了解到的是，作为世俗的统治者，凯撒的这些计划是最伟大的，为了这些计划，他先前放弃了他的枢机主教的职位。事实上，凯撒，在亚历山大死后是否被选为教皇，都打算不惜任何代价保有这个教皇国家；但是在他犯了所有这些重大罪行后，就是作为教皇他也不可能永久地保有这个国家，这一点不可能有任何疑问。如果有人，那也是他能够使教廷的国家世俗化，为了保住这些国家，他将不得不这样做。除非我们受到很大的欺骗，否则这就是马基雅维利对这个重大罪犯心怀隐秘同情的真正原因；只能希望凯撒，别无他人，“将从伤口中拔出剑来”，换句话说，就是消灭这个教皇政权——所有外国干涉和所有分裂意大利的根源。那些认为能揣测凯撒目的的阴谋者，当向凯撒提出托斯卡纳王国的希望时，好像是被轻蔑地打发走了。

但是，从他的这些前提中得出的所有符合逻辑的结论都是无效的，这不是因为他的不可理解的天才——事实上他具有的天才的特点和弗里德兰大公一样少；而是因为他采用的手段与任何大而始终如一的行动方针不一致。确实，如果没有终止他统治的意外事件的发生，也许在他的穷凶极恶中存在着拯救教皇政权的前景。

即使我们假定他在这个教皇国家中消灭那些小暴君，除收获同情外别无所得，即使我们把那支由意大利的最优秀的官兵所组成、由列奥那多·达·芬奇作总工程师、在1502年继承财富的军队作为他伟大计划的证明，其他事实仍具有如此一种无理性的特点，以至于我们的判断，像当时的观察家们的判断一样，完全不知道如何解释它们。这类事实之一就是凯撒对于新征服国家的蹂躏和虐待，而他仍想保有和统治它。另外一个事实就是这个教皇任期最后几十年的罗马和教廷的状况。无论是父子曾起草一份公布处死人员的正式名单，还是一个接一个地解决谋杀事件，无论哪种情况，这对波几亚父子都是志在秘密消灭所有那些挡道的或者觊觎其遗产的人。在这些遗产中，现金和动产构成最小的一部分，教皇更庞大的收益来源是：那些教会高级僧侣由于被杀死而停发的薪俸，在这些职位空缺期间的该项薪俸，还有这些被害者的继任者所填补的空缺职位的价钱。威尼斯大使保罗·卡佩洛在1500年宣称：“每夜都发现四五个被谋杀的人，这些人中有主教、高级教士和其他人，因此整个罗马都在颤抖，害怕被公爵（凯撒）消灭。”他自己常常带着卫士们夜间在罗马城内漫步，我们有一切理由相信他这样做不仅仅是因为像提贝留一样害怕在白天会暴露他此时令人厌恶的相貌；而且也是因为要满足他杀人嗜血的疯狂欲望，也许甚至是对那些他不认识的人下手。

早在1499年，绝望的情绪如此巨大、如此普遍，以至于许多教皇卫士们都遭伏击被杀死。而这对波几亚父子不能用公开的暴力来袭击的那些人，就成了他们毒药的牺牲品。对于有些需要慎重的情况，他们使用一种味道可口的白色粉末，这种粉末并不当场而是慢慢地、逐渐地起作用，并且能够放在任何菜肴或酒里而不被发现。杰姆王子在被亚历山大交付给查理八世（1495年）之前已经在一杯甜酒里喝下去一些。在这对波几亚父子事业的最后，他们由于偶然品尝了本来为一个富有的枢机主教准备的蜜饯反而被这种粉末毒死了。教皇史的摘录史官乌诺弗利奥·潘维尼奥提到了三个奉亚历山大之命被毒死的枢机主教奥尔西尼、费雷里奥和米奇尔，并暗示还有第四个，即乔万尼·波几亚；而凯撒把他置于自己的控制之下——尽管也许富有的高级教士在当时很少有死在罗马而不引起这种怀疑的。就连那些已经离开罗马城退居到某个地方市镇潜心书斋的学者也逃不脱这种无情的毒杀。一种隐秘的恐怖似乎笼罩着教皇；穿透墙壁和卧室的风暴雷电，在早些时候经常光顾惊吓他；在1500年，当这些现象再次发生的时候，它们被认为是“魔鬼的故事”。关于这些事件的故事，最后好像是通过有众多人参加的1500年的大赦年纪念盛典，被广泛地传播到欧洲的所有国家；不需别的，只是那声名狼藉的赦罪券交易就足以让人把所有目光投向罗马。除了回国的朝圣者们，奇怪的白袍忏悔者也从意大利来到了北方，其中有来自这个教皇国家的伪装的逃亡者，他们不可能保持沉默。然而没人能估算出在这种流言蜚语和基督教界的愤慨变成亚历山大的紧急危险的根源之前，它们可能发展到了什么地步。潘维尼奥在别处说：“要不是他为儿子进行的伟大计划由于去世而终止，为了得到所有其他富有的枢机主教和高级教士的财产，他将会除掉这些人。”如果凯撒在他父亲去世时，自己没有卧病在床，他有什么不可能得到啊！那将是一个什么样的教皇秘密选举啊——他此时，全副武装，可以勒令由于他考虑周到地毒杀而人数减少的教皇选举团选举他——并且当时并没有法国军队在近旁！在做这样一种假设时，后果不堪设想。

这种假设没有发生，取而代之的是庇护三世当选的那次教皇秘密选举会议，并且，在他很快去世后，是优里乌斯二世当选的会议——这两次选举都是全体反应的结果。

不管优里乌斯二世的私人道德可能是什么样，从根本上说他是教皇政权的救世主。他对于自他叔父西克塔斯任教皇以来的各种事件的熟悉，使他对于教皇权威的根据和条件有着深刻的认识。基于这些根据和条件，他制定了自己的政策，并在这一政策上倾注他坚定意志的全部力量和热情。他不是通过买卖圣职的方法而是在全体赞成中登上教皇宝座的台阶，而且不管怎样，随后他停止了教廷最高职位的不加掩饰的买卖。优里乌斯有亲信，其中有一些是卑劣的，但是一种特殊的运气使他凌驾于“族亲”的诱惑之上。他的弟弟乔万尼·德拉·罗维里是乌尔比诺的女继承人——蒙特费尔特罗家族最后一代，圭多巴尔多的妹妹——的丈夫，他们结婚后在1491年生下一个儿子弗兰切斯科·马利亚·罗维里，他既是教皇的侄子同时又是乌尔比诺公爵爵位的继承人。优里乌斯在别处——或者是在战场上或者是以外交方式——得到的东西，他都自豪地赠给了教会而不是他的家族；他把他发现处于解体状态的教会领土遗赠给完全屈服于他的继承者，因而增加了新领土帕尔马和皮亚琴察。费拉拉没有被划入教廷版图并不是他的错。在圣安吉洛城堡中储存的70万金币将会由地方长官只移交给未来的教皇。他使他自己成为枢机主教，事实上是所有在罗马去世的教士的财产继承人，并且这是通过最专制的手段做到的；但他没有谋杀或者毒死他们任何一个人。他在一个人在意大利被迫或者做锤子或者做铁砧的时代，在个性比最无可争议的权力更有力量的时代，亲自率领军队打仗，这对他来说是无可避免的需要，也为他带来诸多好处。如果说尽管他大声疾呼“把野蛮人赶出去！”，然而他又比任何人都对西班牙人在意大利扎下稳固的根基贡献更大，他可能认为这是一件对于教皇政权来说无关紧要的事，或者甚至，像当时的情况，是比较有利的事情。在意大利的君主们只热爱反对教廷渎圣计划的时代里，教廷对谁能够比对西班牙更快地寻求真诚而持久的尊敬呢？但尽管这样，他那种既不吞咽愤怒也不隐藏真正好意的强有力的独特本性，整体给人一种对于他的处境非常有利的印象——“好厉害的教皇”。他甚至能够比较敢于问心无愧地召集一个针对罗马的宗教会议，以公然蔑视全欧洲的反对派所提出的召开宗教会议的叫嚷。一个这种类型的统治者需要某个体现他的概念的伟大外部象征；优里乌斯在圣彼得大教堂的重建中找到了它。大教堂重建的计划，正像布拉曼特希望表现的，也许是能够想象的统一权力的最壮观表达。除建筑外，在其他艺术中，这个教皇的面貌和记忆也以其最理想的形式流传下来。并非毫无意义的是：就连当时的拉丁文诗篇也对优里乌斯表现出一种与对其前任们迥然不同的热情。在枢机主教阿德里安·达·科尔内多所作的《优里乌斯二世的旅程》一诗结尾，进入波洛尼亚城独具一种辉煌壮丽之感，乔万尼·安多尼奥·弗拉密尼奥在一篇最美好的挽歌里，呼吁这位教皇的爱国精神给意大利以保护。

在他的拉特兰宗教会议的章程中，优里乌斯庄严地痛斥教皇选举中的买卖圣职一事。在他1513年去世后，爱财的枢机主教们试图通过以下提议逃避这个禁令：当选的候选人目前为止所拥有的用于捐赠的资金和担任的职位应该在枢机主教们中间平分，这样，他们就会选举那位资产最多的枢机主教——无能的拉斐尔·利阿里奥。但是，出现了一个主要来自神圣教皇选举团的较年轻成员们的反对力量，他们渴望一位自由开明的教皇，从而使这个可耻的计划没有成功。乔万尼·美第奇当选，即著名的列奥十世。

我们在讨论文艺复兴的全盛时期的时候将经常谈到他；在这里我们仅仅希望指出在他的统治下，教皇政权再一次遭受重大的国内外的危险。这些危险当中，我们不算佩特路奇、德·绍利斯、利阿里奥和科尔内多（1517年）这些枢机主教们的阴谋，这些阴谋最多偶尔带来人员的变化，并且对此列奥找到了真正的解药——创造性地任命了前所未闻的31个新枢机主教，这是一个带有额外好处的措施，至少在某些情况下，奖赏了真正的功绩。

但是，列奥在任职期间的前两年所允许自己踩踏的某些小径，危险到了极点。他认真地尽力通过谈判确保他的兄弟朱利亚诺得到那不勒斯王国，并确保他的侄子洛伦佐得到一个强大的北部意大利国家，由米兰、托斯卡纳、乌尔比诺和费拉拉组成。很显然，这个教皇国家，这样四面八方被围在里面，将会成为美第奇家族的一个附属国，并且事实上也没有进一步使其世俗化的必要。

这个计划在当时的政治状况下遇到了无法逾越的障碍。朱利亚诺很早去世了。为了给洛伦佐做准备，列奥着手从乌尔比诺驱逐弗兰切斯科·马利亚·德拉·罗维里公爵，但是从这个战争中除了仇恨和贫困，别无所得；并且，当1519年洛伦佐追随他的叔父进入坟墓时，列奥被迫把艰难赢得的占领地交给了教廷。他是被强制这样做的，因此并无荣誉，要是他自愿这样做，那将会是他不朽的光荣。他企图攻击费拉拉的阿尔方索，但实际上只攻击了少数小暴君和雇佣兵队长们，这件事肯定不能提高他的名声。并且这发生在一个西方君主越来越习惯于以意大利的这个省或那个省作赌注进行大规模政治赌博的时候。既然在最后几十年里他们在国内权力的增长如此巨大，谁能保证他们的野心还没扩展到教廷属邦就会停止呢？列奥亲眼目睹了在1527年所实现的事情的序幕；在1520年底，几个西班牙的步兵队伍出现在教皇领土的边界——好像是他们做主——目的是强迫教皇付给占领军特别税，但是被教皇的军队赶回去了。公众反对僧侣统治腐败的情绪也在后来几年快速地达到顶点，像小皮科·德拉·米朗多拉那些放眼未来的人们迫切要求改革。与此同时，路德也已出现在历史舞台上。

在阿德里安六世（1522—1523年）的统治下，为伟大的德国宗教改革运动所实行的少数几个怯懦的改进来得太迟了。他对目前为止事态的发展，如买卖圣职、裙带关系、挥霍无度、抢劫掠夺和荒淫放荡，除声明表示极端厌恶外，几乎无所作为。从路德教徒那方面来的危险绝不是最大的；一个来自威尼斯的敏锐的观察家吉罗拉谟·尼格罗说出了他的恐惧——一个迅速而可怕的灾难就要降临罗马这个城市。

在克莱门七世的统治下，罗马的整个地平线上雾气氤氲，好像非洲风暴笼罩在坎帕尼亚地区的浅灰色沉重面纱，以致最后几个夏季几欲令人窒息而死。教皇在国内外均遭人痛恨。有识之士满心忧虑，隐士现身在罗马的街头和广场，预言意大利和世界的命运，并把教皇叫作“反基督者”；科伦纳宗派集团公然抬头；那个仅仅其存在对于教皇政权就是一个永久威胁的坚贞不屈的枢机主教蓬佩奥·科伦纳，在1526年冒险突然袭击了这个城市，希望克莱门被杀或被俘后，在查理五世的帮助下，立刻就能成为教皇。后者设法逃到了圣安吉洛城堡，这对罗马来说并非什么福气，并且他自己逃过这一劫的命运倒不如说比死亡更差。

由于一系列的只有强者敢于一试、却给弱者招致毁灭的谎话欺骗，克莱门招来了波旁和弗隆兹堡统帅下的德意志与西班牙军队的进犯（1527年）。可以肯定地说，查理五世内阁是打算给予他严重惩罚的，并且事前不能估算出没有薪饷、出身游牧部落的抢劫者的狂热会把他们带到多远。要不是众所周知罗马是这次远征的目标，想不给任何饷金在德意志征兵，就会是白费力气。给波旁的书面命令有一天可能被发现，这些书面命令还有可能被证明是措词温和的。但是，历史的批判不会允许自己被领入歧途。这个天主教国王和皇帝多亏他的运气，教皇和枢机主教们没有被他的军队杀害。要是此事发生的话，世界上任何诡辩都不能为他在这次犯罪中的责任开脱。对无数无足轻重的人们的大屠杀，对其余人们的劫掠，以及所有严刑拷打和买卖人口的恐怖，足以清楚表明在“罗马的劫掠”中可能发生的事情。

查理似乎本来希望从这个第二次逃到圣安吉洛城堡的教皇处勒索一大笔钱，然后把他带到那不勒斯的。克莱门逃到奥尔维多肯定没有得到西班牙方面的默许，这个皇帝是否曾认真考虑过人人都已为此做好准备的把教廷属邦世俗化，他是否真的是被英格兰的亨利八世的抗议所劝阻而没有这样做，也许绝不会弄明白了。

但是如果真有这样的计划，它们也不可能持续太久：从这个被蹂躏的城市中兴起了一种既改革教廷又改革这个国家的新精神。这种新精神马上被人感觉到了。枢机主教萨多莱托是许多见证人中的一个，他这样写道：

如果通过我们受苦能够偿还上帝的愤怒和正义，如果这些可怕的惩罚重新为更好的法律和道德开辟道路，那么我们的不幸也许不是最大的……属于上帝的，他将给予照顾；在我们面前是一种改革的生活，任何暴力都不能从我们手中夺走。让我们管控我们的行为和思想吧，以便只有在上帝那里寻求教会全体教士的真正荣光和我们自己真正的伟大和力量。

事实上，1527年这个生死存亡的一年，目前来说有个成果：持重的人们能够重新使他们的声音得以倾听。罗马所遭受的苦难如此深重，甚至在保罗三世的统治下，也不能回归到列奥十世的那种放荡腐败的状况。

教皇政府在它的苦难如此深重的时候开始激发出一种半宗教半政治的同情。国王们不能容忍他们中有人僭取教皇监禁犯人的权利，因而订立了《亚眠条约》（1527年8月18日），目的之一就是释放克莱门。因此，无论如何，他们要利用帝国军队的行为所引起的公众的反感。同时，皇帝甚至在西班牙也遇到大麻烦，在那里高级教士和贵族们一见他就提出最迫切的劝谏。当计划着由僧侣和世俗人组成、全体穿丧服的总代表团时，查理害怕像几年前镇压的暴动一样会引起乱子，就禁止了这一计划。他不仅不敢延长对教皇的虐待，而且，甚至除了对国外政治的所有考虑，他绝对是被迫与他曾如此严重伤害过的教皇政府和解。因为肯定与他背道而驰的德意志人的性格，在他看来像一般德意志的事情一样，不能作为制订一项政策的基础。也有可能，像一个威尼斯人所坚持的，罗马劫掠这个负担的记忆沉重地压在他的良心上，他倾向于快速抵罪，这种想法掩藏在佛罗伦萨人永久臣服于美第奇家族这件事中。教皇的“族亲”，新位的公爵阿利桑德罗·美第奇娶了皇帝的私生女。

在之后的岁月中，一次宗教会议的方案使查理能够在所有基本问题上把教皇政府置于自己的控制下，同时既保护它又压迫它。所有危险中最大的危险——世俗化——这一来自教皇政府内部，来自教皇们自己本身和他们的“族亲”的危险，由于德国宗教改革运动而中止了数个世纪。正像这个危险本身曾使反对罗马（1527年）的远征成为可能并获得成功一样，这一危险也迫使教皇政权重新变成全世界宗教力量的表现，把它自己从所处的卑鄙的堕落状态中提升到处于这一改革运动的所有反动势力的领导者的地位。克莱门七世任期中的后来数年，以及在保罗三世、保罗四世及其继任者们的统治时期，面临半个欧洲的背叛而有所发展的教会是一个新的、得到提高的僧侣统治，它避免了先前时代所有重大而危险的丑行，尤其是企图扩张领土以及与天主教君主们结盟的“裙带关系”，现在它被一种新生的宗教力量所推动，把主要工作放在恢复已失去的事情上。它当时只是在反对宗教分离者中才存在下来，也才为现在的人们所理解。在这个意义上能够完全正确地说，教皇政权的精神拯救应归功于它的俗世的敌人。这时它的政治地位，尽管肯定是在西班牙的永久监护之下，也变得十分稳固；几乎没费力气，在它的附庸国灭亡时，它就继承了伊斯特和德拉·罗维里家族，即费拉拉和乌尔比诺的公国的合法世系。但是，没有这一宗教改革运动，整个教皇国家早就会传到世俗手中。

Introduction

This work bears the title of an essay in the strictest sense of the word. No one is more conscious than the writer with what limited means and strength he has addressed himself to a task so arduous. And even if he could look with greater confidence upon his own researches, he would hardly thereby feel more assured of the approval of competent judges. To each eye, perhaps, the outlines of a given civilization present a different picture; and in treating of a civilization which is the mother of our own, and whose influence is still at work among us, it is unavoidable that individual judgement and feeling should tell every moment both on the writer and on the reader. In the wide ocean upon which we venture, the possible ways and directions are many; and the same studies which have served for this work might easily, in other hands, not only receive a wholly different treatment and application, but lead also to essentially different conclusions. Such indeed is the importance of the subject, that it still calls for fresh investigation, and may be studied with advantage from the most varied points of view. Meanwhile we are content if a patient hearing is granted us, and if this book be taken and judged as a whole. It is the most serious difficulty of the history of civilization that a great intellectual process must be broken up into single, and often into what seem arbitrary categories, in order to be in any way intelligible. It was formerly our intention to fill up the gaps in this book by a special work on the art of the Renaissance — an intention, however, which we have been able to fulfil only in part. The struggle between the popes and the Hohenstaufen left Italy in a political condition which differed essentially from that of other countries of the West. While in France, Spain and England the feudal system was so organized that, at the close of its existence, it was naturally transformed into a unified monarchy, and while in Germany it helped to maintain, at least outwardly, the unity of the empire, Italy had shaken it off almost entirely. The emperors of the fourteenth century, even in the most favourable case, were no longer received and respected as feudal lords, but as possible leaders and supporters of powers already in existence; while the papacy, with its creatures and allies, was strong enough to hinder national unity in the future, not strong enough itself to bring about that unity. Between the two lay a multitude of political units — republics and despots — in part of long standing, in part of recent origin, whose existence was founded simply on their power to maintain it. In them for the first time we detect the modern political spirit of Europe, surrendered freely to its own instincts, often displaying the worst features of an unbridled egotism, outraging every right, and killing every germ of a healthier culture. But, wherever this vicious tendency is overcome or in any way compensated, a new fact appears in history — the state as the outcome of reflection and calculation, the state as a work of art. This new life displays itself in a hundred forms, both in the republican and in the despotic states, and determines their inward constitution, no less than their foreign policy. We shall limit ourselves to the consideration of the completer and more clearly defined type, which is offered by the despotic states.

The internal condition of the despotically governed states had a memorable counterpart in the Norman empire of Lower Italy and Sicily, after its transformation by the emperor Frederick II. Bred amid treason and peril in the neighbourhood of the Saracens, Frederick, the first ruler of the modern type who sat upon a throne, had early accustomed himself to a thoroughly objective treatment of affairs. His acquaintance with the internal condition and administration of the Saracenic states was close and intimate; and the mortal struggle in which he was engaged with the papacy compelled him, no less than his adversaries, to bring into the field all the resources at his command. Frederick's measures (especially after the year 1231) are aimed at the complete destruction of the feudal state, at the transformation of the people into a multitude destitute of will and of the means of resistance, but profitable in the utmost degree to the exchequer. He centralized, in a manner hitherto unknown in the West, the whole judicial and political administration. No office was henceforth to be filled by popular election, under penalty of the devastation of the offending district and of the enslavement of its inhabitants. The taxes, based on a comprehensive assessment, and distributed in accordance with Muhammadan usages, were collected by those cruel and vexatious methods without which, it is true, it is impossible to obtain any money from Orientals. Here, in short, we find, not a people, but simply a disciplined multitude of subjects, who were forbidden, for example, to marry out of the country without special permission, and under no circumstances were allowed to study abroad. The university of Naples was the first we know of to restrict the freedom of study, while the East, in these respects at all events, left its youth unfettered. It was after the example of Muhammadan rules that Frederick traded on his own account in all parts of the Mediterranean, reserving to himself the monopoly of many commodities, and restricting in various ways the commerce of his subjects. The Fatimite Caliphs, with all their esoteric unbelief, were, at least in their earlier history, tolerant of all the differences in the religious faith of their people; Frederick, on the other hand, crowned his system of government by a religious inquisition, which will seem the more reprehensible when we remember that in the persons of the heretics he was persecuting the representatives of a free municipal life. Lastly, the internal police, and the kernel of the army for foreign service, was composed of Saracens who had been brought over from Sicily to Nocera and Lucera — men who were deaf to the cry of misery and careless of the ban of the Church. At a later period the subjects, by whom the use of weapons had long been forgotten, were passive witnesses of the fall of Manfred and of the seizure of the government by Charles of Anjou; the latter continued to use the system which he found already at work.

At the side of the centralizing emperor appeared a usurper of the most peculiar kind: his vicar and son-in-law, Ezzelino da Romano. He stands as the representative of no system of government or administration, for all his activity was wasted in struggles for supremacy in the eastern part of Upper Italy; but as a political type he was a figure of no less importance for the future than his imperial protector Frederick. The conquests and usurpations which had hitherto taken place in the Middle Ages rested on real or pretended inheritance and other such claims, or else were effected against unbelievers and excommunicated persons. Here for the first time the attempt was openly made to found a throne by wholesale murder and endless barbarities, by the adoption, in short, of any means with a view to nothing but the end pursued. None of his successors, not even Cesare Borgia, rivalled the colossal guilt of Ezzelino; but the example once set was not forgotten, and his fall led to no return of justice among the nations, and served as no warning to future transgressors.

It was in vain at such a time that St Thomas Aquinas, a born subject of Frederick, set up the theory of a constitutional monarchy, in which the prince was to be supported by an upper house named by himself, and a representative body elected by the people. Such theories found no echo outside the lecture-room, and Frederick and Ezzelino were and remain for Italy the great political phenomena of the thirteenth century. Their personality, already half legendary, forms the most important subject of The Hundred Old Tales, whose original composition falls certainly within this century. In them Ezzelino is spoken of with the awe which all mighty impressions leave behind them. His person became the centre of a whole literature from the chronicle of eye-witnesses to the half-mystical tragedy of later poets.

Despots of the Fourteenth Century

The tyrannies, great and small, of the fourteenth century afford constant proof that examples such as these were not thrown away. Their misdeeds cried forth loudly and have been circumstantially told by historians. As states depending for existence on themselves alone, and scientifically organized with a view to this object, they present to us a higher interest than that of mere narrative.

The deliberate adaptation of means to ends, of which no prince out of Italy had at that time a conception, joined to almost absolute power within the limits of the state, produced among the despots both men and modes of life of a peculiar character. The chief secret of government in the hands of the prudent ruler lay in leaving the incidence of taxation so far as possible where he found it, or as he had first arranged it. The chief sources of income were: a land tax, based on a valuation; definite taxes on articles of consumption and duties on exported and imported goods; together with the private fortune of the ruling house. The only possible increase was derived from the growth of business and of general prosperity. Loans, such as we find in the free cities, were here unknown; a well-planned confiscation was held a preferable means of raising money, provided only that it left public credit unshaken — an end attained, for example, by the truly oriental practice of deposing and plundering the director of the finances.

Out of this income the expenses of the little court, of the bodyguard, of the mercenary troops, and of the public buildings were met, as well as of the buffoons and men of talent who belonged to the personal attendants of the prince. The illegitimacy of his rule isolated the tyrant and surrounded him with constant danger; the most honourable alliance which he could form was with intellectual merit, without regard to its origin. The liberality of the northern princes of the thirteenth century was confined to the knights, to the nobility which served and sang. It was otherwise with the Italian despot. With his thirst for fame and his passion for monumental works, it was talent, not birth, which he needed. In the company of the poet and the scholar he felt himself in a new position, almost, indeed in possession of a new legitimacy.

No prince was more famous in this respect than the ruler of Verona, Can Grande della Scala, who numbered among the illustrious exiles whom he entertained at his court representatives of the whole of Italy. The men of letters were not ungrateful. Petrarch, whose visits at the courts of such men have been so severely censured, sketched an ideal picture of a prince of the fourteenth century. He demands great things from his patron, the lord of Padua, but in a manner which shows that he holds him capable of them.

Thou must not be the master but the father of thy subjects, and must love them as thy children; yea, as members of thy body. Weapons, guards and soldiers thou mayest employ against the enemy — with thy subjects goodwill is sufficient. By citizens, of course, I mean those who love the existing order; for those who daily desire change are rebels and traitors, and against such a stern justice may take its course.

Here follows, worked out in detail, the purely modern fiction of the omnipotence of the state. The prince is to take everything into his charge, to maintain and restore churches and public buildings, to keep up the municipal police, to drain the marshes, to look after the supply of wine and corn; so to distribute the taxes that the people can recognize their necessity; he is to support the sick and the helpless, and to give his protection and society to distinguished scholars, on whom his fame in after ages will depend.

But whatever might be the brighter sides of the system, and the merits of individual rulers, yet the men of the fourteenth century were not without a more or less distinct consciousness of the brief and uncertain tenure of most of these despotisms. Inasmuch as political institutions like these are naturally secure in proportion to the size of the territory in which they exist, the larger principalities were constantly tempted to swallow up the smaller. Whole hecatombs of petty rulers were sacrificed at this time to the Visconti alone. As a result of this outward danger an inward ferment was in ceaseless activity; and the effect of the situation on the character of the ruler was generally of the most sinister kind. Absolute power, with its temptations to luxury and unbridled selfishness, and the perils to which he was exposed from enemies and conspirators, turned him almost inevitably into a tyrant in the worst sense of the word. Well for him if he could trust his nearest relations! But where all was illegitimate, there could be no regular law of inheritance, either with regard to the succession or to the division of the ruler's property; and consequently the heir, if incompetent or a minor, was liable in the interest of the family itself to be supplanted by an uncle or cousin of more resolute character. The acknowledgement or exclusion of the bastards was a fruitful source of contest; and most of these families in consequence were plagued with a crowd of discontented and vindictive kinsmen. This circumstance gave rise to continual outbreaks of treason and to frightful scenes of domestic bloodshed. Sometimes the pretenders lived abroad in exile, and like the Visconti, who practised the fisherman's craft on the Lake of Garda, viewed the situation with patient indifference. When asked by a messenger of his rival when and how he thought of returning to Milan, one gave the reply, 'By the same means as those by which I was expelled, but not till his crimes have outweighed my own.' Sometimes, too, the despot was sacrificed by his relations, with the view of saving the family, to the public conscience which he had too grossly outraged. In a few cases the government was in the hands of the whole family, or at least the ruler was bound to take their advice; and here, too, the distribution of property and influence often led to bitter disputes.

The whole of this system excited the deep and persistent hatred of the Florentine writers of that epoch. Even the pomp and display, with which the despot was perhaps less anxious to gratify his own vanity than to impress the popular imagination, awakened their keenest sarcasm. Woe to an adventurer if he fell into their hands, like the upstart Doge Agnello of Pisa (1364), who used to ride out with a golden sceptre, and show himself at the window of his house, 'as relics are shown', reclining on embroidered drapery and cushions, served like a pope or emperor, by kneeling attendants. More often, however, the old Florentines speak on this subject in a tone of lofty seriousness. Dante saw and characterized well the vulgarity and commonplace which marked the ambition of the new princes. 'What mean their trumpets and their bells, their horns and their flutes; but come, hangman — come, vultures?' The castle of the tyrant, as pictured by the popular mind, is a lofty and solitary building, full of dungeons and listening-tubes, the home of cruelty and misery. Misfortune is foretold to all who enter the service of the despot, who even becomes at last himself an object of pity: he must needs be the enemy of all good and honest men; he can trust no one, and can read in the faces of his subjects the expectation of his fall. 'As despotisms rise, grow, and are consolidated, so grows in their midst the hidden element which must produce their dissolution and ruin.' But the deepest ground of dislike has not been stated; Florence was then the scene of the richest development of human individuality, while for the despots no other individuality could be suffered to live and thrive but their own and that of their nearest dependants. The control of the individual was rigorously carried out, even down to the establishment of a system of passports.

The astrological superstitions and the religious unbelief of many of the tyrants gave, in the minds of their contemporaries, a peculiar colour to this awful and Godforsaken existence. When the last Carrara could no longer defend the walls and gates of the plague-stricken Padua, hemmed in on all sides by the Venetians (1405), the soldiers of the guard heard him cry to the devil 'to come and kill me'.

The most complete and instructive type of the tyranny of the fourteenth century is to be found unquestionably among the Visconti of Milan, from the death of the Archbishop Giovanni onwards (1354). The family likeness which shows itself between Bernabò and the worst of the Roman emperors is unmistakable; the most important public object was the prince's boar-hunting; whoever interfered with it was put to death with torture; the terrified people were forced to maintain 5,000 boar-hounds, with strict responsibility for their health and safety. The taxes were extorted by every conceivable sort of compulsion; seven daughters of the prince received a dowry of 100,000 gold florins apiece; and an enormous treasure was collected. On the death of his wife (1384) an order was issued 'to the subjects' to share his grief, as once they had shared his joy, and to wear mourning for a year. The coup de main (1385) by which his nephew Giangaleazzo got him into his power — one of those brilliant plots which make the heart of even late historians beat more quickly — was strikingly characteristic of the man.

In Giangaleazzo that passion for the colossal which was common to most of the despots shows itself on the largest scale. He undertook, at the cost of 300,000 golden florins, the construction of gigantic dykes, to divert in case of need the Mincio from Mantua and the Brenta from Padua, and thus to render these cities defenceless. It is not impossible, indeed, that he thought of draining away the lagoons of Venice. He founded that most wonderful of all convents, the Certosa of Pavia, and the cathedral of Milan, 'which exceeds in size and splendour all the churches of Christendom'. The Palace in Pavia, which his father Galeazzo began and which he himself finished, was probably by far the most magnificent of the princely dwellings of Europe. There he transferred his famous library, and the great collection of relics of the saints, in which he placed a peculiar faith. It would have been strange indeed if a prince of this character had not also cherished the highest ambitions in political matters. King Wenceslaus made him Duke (1395); he was hoping for nothing less than the kingdom of Italy or the imperial crown, when (1402) he fell ill and died. His whole territories are said to have paid him in a single year, besides the regular contribution of 1,200,000 gold florins, no less than 800,000 more in extraordinary subsidies. After his death the dominions which he had brought together by every sort of violence fell to pieces; and for a time even the original nucleus could with difficulty be maintained by his successors. What might have become of his sons Giovanni Maria (died 1412) and Filippo Maria (died 1417), had they lived in a different country and among other traditions, cannot be said. But, as heirs of their house, they inherited that monstrous capital of cruelty and cowardice which had been accumulated from generation to generation.

Giovanni Maria, too, is famed for his dogs, which were no longer, however, used for hunting but for tearing human bodies. Tradition has preserved their names, like those of the bears of the Emperor Valentinian I. In May 1409, when war was going on, and the starving populace cried to him in the streets, Pace! Pace!, he let loose his mercenaries upon them, and 200 lives were sacrificed; under penalty of the gallows it was forbidden to utter the words pace and guerra, and the priests were ordered, instead of dona nobis pacem, to say tranquillitatem. At last a band of conspirators took advantage of the moment when Facino Cane, the chief condottiere of the insane ruler, lay ill at Pavia, and cut down Giovanni Maria in the church of San Gottardo at Milan; the dying Facino on the same day made his officers swear to stand by the heir Filippo Maria, whom he himself urged his wife to take for a second husband. His wife, Beatrice di Tenda, followed his advice. We shall have occasion to speak of Filippo Maria later on.

And in times like these Cola di Rienzi was dreaming of founding on the rickety enthusiasm of the corrupt population of Rome a new state which was to comprise all Italy. By the side of rulers such as those whom we have described, he seems no better than a poor deluded fool.

Despots of the Fifteenth Century

The despotisms of the fifteenth century show an altered character. Many of the less important tyrants, and some of the greater, like the Scala and the Carrara, had disappeared, while the more powerful ones, aggrandized by conquest, had given to their systems each its characteristic development. Naples, for example, received a fresh and stronger impulse from the new Aragonese dynasty. A striking feature of this epoch is the attempt of the condottieri to found independent dynasties of their own. Facts and the actual relations of things, apart from traditional estimates, are alone regarded; talent and audacity win the great prizes. The petty despots, to secure a trustworthy support, begin to enter the service of the larger states, and become themselves condottieri, receiving in return for their services money and impunity for their misdeeds, if not an increase of territory. All, whether small or great, must exert themselves more, must act with greater caution and calculation, and must learn to refrain from too wholesale barbarities; only so much wrong is permitted by public opinion as is necessary for the end in view, and this the impartial bystander certainly finds no fault with. No trace is here visible of that half-religious loyalty by which the legitimate princes of the West were supported; personal popularity is the nearest approach we can find to it. Talent and calculation are the only means of advancement. A character like that of Charles the Bold, which wore itself out in the passionate pursuit of impracticable ends, was a riddle to the Italians. 'The Swiss were only peasants, and if they were all killed, that would be no satisfaction for the Burgundian nobles who might fall in the war. If the duke got possession of all Switzerland without a struggle, his income would not be 5,000 ducats the greater.' The medieval features in the character of Charles, his chivalrous aspirations and ideals, had long become unintelligible to the Italians. The diplomatists of the South, when they saw him strike his officers and yet keep them in his service, when he maltreated his troops to punish them for a defeat, and then threw the blame on his counsellors in the presence of the same troops, gave him up for lost. Louis XI, on the other hand, whose policy surpasses that of the Italian princes in their own style, and who was an avowed admirer of Francesco Sforza, must be placed in all that regards culture and refinement far below these rulers.

Good and evil lie strangely mixed together in the Italian states of the fifteenth century. The personality of the ruler is so highly developed, often of such deep significance, and so characteristic of the conditions and needs of the time, that to form an adequate moral judgement on it is no easy task.

The foundation of the system was and remained illegitimate, and nothing could remove the curse which rested upon it. The imperial approval or investiture made no change in the matter, since the people attached little weight to the fact that the despot had bought a piece of parchment somewhere in foreign countries, or from some stranger passing through his territory. If the emperor had been good for anything — so ran the logic of uncritical common sense — he would never have let the tyrant rise at all. Since the Roman expedition of Charles IV, the emperors had done nothing more in Italy than sanction a tyranny which had arisen without their help; they could give it no other practical authority than what might flow from an imperial charter. The whole conduct of Charles in Italy was a scandalous political comedy. Matteo Villani relates how the Visconti escorted him round their territory, and at last out of it; how he went about like a hawker selling his wares (privileges, etc.) for money; what a mean appearance he made in Rome, and how at the end, without even drawing the sword, he returned with replenished coffers across the Alps. Sigismund came, on the first occasion at least (1414), with the good intention of persuading John XXIII to take part in his council; it was on that journey, when pope and emperor were gazing from the lofty tower of Cremona on the panorama of Lombardy, that their host, the tyrant Gabrino Fondolo, was seized with the desire to throw them both over. On his second visit Sigismund came as a mere adventurer; for more than half a year he remained shut up in Siena, like a debtor in gaol, and only with difficulty, and at a later period, succeeded in being crowned in Rome. And what can be thought of Frederick III? His journeys to Italy have the air of holidaytrips or pleasure-tours made at the expense of those who wanted him to confirm their prerogatives, or whose vanity it flattered to entertain an emperor. The latter was the case with Alfonso of Naples, who paid 150,000 florins for the honour of an imperial visit. At Ferrara, on his second return from Rome (1469), Frederick spent a whole day without leaving his chamber, distributing no less than eighty titles; he created knights, counts, doctors, notaries — counts, indeed, of different degrees, as, for instance, counts palatine, counts with the right to create doctors up to the number of five, counts with the right to legitimatize bastards, to appoint notaries, and so forth. The chancellor, however, expected in return for the patents in question a gratuity which was thought excessive at Ferrara. The opinion of Borso, himself created Duke of Modena and Reggio in return for an annual payment of 4,000 gold florins, when his imperial patron was distributing titles and diplomas to all the little court, is not mentioned. The humanists, then the chief spokesmen of the age, were divided in opinion according to their personal interests, while the emperor was greeted by some of them with the conventional acclamations of the poets of imperial Rome. Poggio confessed that he no longer knew what the coronation meant; in the old times only the victorious Imperator was crowned; and then he was crowned with laurel.

With Maximilian I begins not only the general intervention of foreign nations, but a new imperial policy with regard to Italy. The first step — the investiture of Lodovico il Moro with the duchy of Milan and the exclusion of his unhappy nephew — was not of a kind to bear good fruits. According to the modern theory of intervention, when two parties are tearing a country to pieces, a third may step in and take its share, and on this principle the empire acted. But right and justice were appealed to no longer. When Louis XII was expected in Genoa (1502), and the imperial eagle was removed from the hall of the ducal palace and replaced by painted lilies, the historian Senarega asked what, after all, was the meaning of the eagle which so many revolutions had spared, and what claims the empire had upon Genoa. No one knew more about the matter than the old phrase that Genoa was a camera imperii. In fact, nobody in Italy could give a clear answer to any such questions. At length, when Charles V held Spain and the empire together, he was able by means of Spanish forces to make good imperial claims; but it is notorious that what he thereby gained turned to the profit, not of the empire, but of the Spanish monarchy.

Closely connected with the political illegitimacy of the dynasties of the fifteenth century was the public indifference to legitimate birth, which to foreigners — for example, to Comines — appeared so remarkable. The two things went naturally together. In northern countries, as in Burgundy, the illegitimate offspring were provided for by a distinct class of appanages, such as bishoprics and the like; in Portugal an illegitimate line maintained itself on the throne only by constant effort; in Italy, on the contrary, there no longer existed a princely house where, even in the direct line of descent, bastards were not patiently tolerated. The Aragonese monarchs of Naples belonged to the illegitimate line, Aragon itself falling to the lot of the brother of Alfonso I. The great Frederick of Urbino was, perhaps, no Montefeltro at all. When Pius II was on his way to the Congress of Mantua (1459), eight bastards of the house of Este rode to meet him at Ferrara, among them the reigning duke Borso himself and two illegitimate sons of his illegitimate brother and predecessor Lionello. The latter had also had a lawful wife, herself an illegitimate daughter of Alfonso I of Naples by an African woman. The bastards were often admitted to the succession where the lawful children were minors and the dangers of the situation were pressing; and a rule of seniority became recognized, which took no account of pure of impure birth. The fitness of the individual, his worth and capacity, were of more weight than all the laws and usages which prevailed elsewhere in the West. It was the age, indeed, in which the sons of the popes were founding dynasties. In the sixteenth century, through the influence of foreign ideas and of the Counter-Reformation which then began, the whole question was judged more strictly: Varchi discovers that the succession of the legitimate children 'is ordered by reason, and is the will of heaven from eternity'. Cardinal Ippolito de' Medici founded his claim to the lordship of Florence on the fact that he was perhaps the fruit of a lawful marriage, and at all events son of a gentlewoman, and not, like Duke Alessandro, of a servant girl. At this time began those morganatic marriages of affection which in the fifteenth century, on grounds either of policy or morality, would have had no meaning at all.

But the highest and the most admired form of illegitimacy in the fifteenth century was presented by the condottiere, who, whatever may have been his origin, raised himself to the position of an independent ruler. At bottom, the occupation of Lower Italy by the Normans in the eleventh century was of this character. Such attempts now began to keep the peninsula in a constant ferment.

It was possible for a condottiere to obtain the lordship of a district even without usurpation, in the case when his employer, through want of money or troops, provided for him in this way; under any circumstances the condottiere, even when he dismissed for the time the greater part of his forces, needed a safe place where he could establish his winter quarters, and lay up his stores and provisions. The first example of a captain thus portioned is John Hawkwood, who was invested by Gregory XI with the lordship of Bagnacavallo and Cotignola. When with Alberigo de Barbiano Italian armies and leaders appeared upon the scene, the chances of founding a principality, or of increasing one already acquired, became more frequent. The first great bacchanalian outbreak of military ambition took place in the duchy of Milan after the death of Giangaleazzo (1402). The policy of his two sons was chiefly aimed at the destruction of the new despotisms founded by the condottieri; and from the greatest of them, Facino Cane, the house of Visconti inherited, together with his widow, a long list of cities, and 400,000 golden florins, not to speak of the soldiers of her first husband whom Beatrice di Tenda brought with her. From henceforth that thoroughly immoral relation between the governments and their condottieri, which is characteristic of the fifteenth century, became more and more common. An old story — one of those which are true and not true, everywhere and nowhere — describes it as follows: The citizens of a certain town (Siena seems to be meant) had once an officer in their service who had freed them from foreign aggression; daily they took counsel how to recompense him, and concluded that no reward in their power was great enough, not even if they made him lord of the city. At last one of them rose and said, 'Let us kill him and then worship him as our patron saint.' And so they did, following the example set by the Roman senate with Romulus. In fact, the condottieri had reason to fear none so much as their employers; if they were successful, they became dangerous, and were put out of the way like Roberto Malatesta just after the victory he had won for Sixtus IV (1482); if they failed, the vengeance of the Venetians on Carmagnola showed to what risks they were exposed (1432). It is characteristic of the moral aspect of the situation that the condottieri had often to give their wives and children as hostages, and notwithstanding this, neither felt nor inspired confidence. They must have been heroes of abnegation, natures like Belisarius himself, not to be cankered by hatred and bitterness; only the most perfect goodness could save them from the most monstrous iniquity. No wonder then if we find them full of contempt for all sacred things, cruel and treacherous to their fellows — men who cared nothing whether or no they died under the ban of the Church. At the same time, and through the force of the same conditions, the genius and capacity of many among them attained the highest conceivable development, and won for them the admiring devotion of their followers; their armies are the first in modern history in which the personal credit of the leader is the one moving power. A brilliant example is shown in the life of Francesco Sforza; no prejudice of birth could prevent him from winning and turning to account when he needed it a boundless devotion from each individual with whom he had to deal; it happened more than once that his enemies laid down their arms at the sight of him, greeting him reverently with uncovered heads, each honouring in him 'the common father of the men-at-arms'. The race of the Sforza has this special interest, that from the very beginning of its history we seem able to trace its endeavours after the crown. The foundation of its fortune lay in the remarkable fruitfulness of the family; Francesco's father, Jacopo, himself a celebrated man, had twenty brothers and sisters, all brought up roughly at Cotignola, near Faenza, amid the perils of one of the endless Romagnole vendettas between their own house and that of the Pasolini. The family dwelling was a mere arsenal and fortress; the mother and daughters were as warlike as their kinsmen. In his thirteenth year Jacopo ran away and fled to Panicale to the papal condottiere Boldrino — the man who even in death continued to lead his troops, the word of order being given from the bannered tent in which the embalmed body lay, till at last a fit leader was found to succeed him. Jacopo, when he had at length made himself a name in the service of different condottieri, sent for his relations, and obtained through them the same advantages that a prince derives from a numerous dynasty. It was these relations who kept the army together when he lay a captive in the Castel dell'Uovo at Naples; his sister took the royal envoys prisoner with her own hands, and saved him by this reprisal from death. It was an indication of the breadth and the range of his plans that in monetary affairs Jacopo was thoroughly trustworthy; even in his defeats he consequently found credit with the bankers. He habitually protected the peasants against the licence of his troops, and reluctantly destroyed or injured a conquered city. He gave his well-known mistress, Lucia, the mother of Francesco, in marriage to another, in order to be free for a princely alliance. Even the marriages of his relations were arranged on a definite plan. He kept clear of the impious and profligate life of his contemporaries, and brought up his son Francesco to the three rules: 'Let other men's wives alone; strike none of your followers, or, if you do, send the injured man far away; don't ride a hard-mouthed horse, or one that drops his shoe.' But his chief source of influence lay in the qualities, if not of a great general, at least of a great soldier. His frame was powerful, and developed by every kind of exercise; his peasant's face and frank manners won general popularity; his memory was marvellous, and after the lapse of years could recall the names of his followers, the number of their horses, and the amount of their pay. His education was purely Italian: he devoted his leisure to the study of history, and had Greek and Latin authors translated for his use. Francesco, his still more famous son, set his mind from the first on founding a powerful state, and through brilliant generalship and a faithlessness which hesitated at nothing, got possession of the great city of Milan (1447—50).

His example was contagious. Aeneas Sylvius wrote about this time: 'In our change-loving Italy, where nothing stands firm, and where no ancient dynasty exists, a servant can easily become a king.' One man in particular, who styles himself 'the man of fortune', filled the imagination of the whole country: Giacomo Piccinino, the son of Niccolò. It was a burning question of the day if he, too, would succeed in founding a princely house. The greater states had an obvious interest in hindering it, and even Francesco Sforza thought it would be all the better if the list of self-made sovereigns were not enlarged. But the troops and captains sent against him, at the time, for instance, when he was aiming at the lordship of Siena, recognized their interest in supporting him: 'If it were all over with him, we should have to go back and plough our fields.' Even while besieging him at Orbetello, they supplied him with provisions; and he got out of his straits with honour. But at last fate overtook him. All Italy was betting on the result, when (1465), after a visit to Sforza at Milan, he went to King Ferrante at Naples. In spite of the pledges given, and of his high connections, he was murdered in the Castel Nuovo. Even the condottieri, who had obtained their dominions by inheritance, never felt themselves safe. When Roberto Malatesta and Frederick of Urbino died on the same day (1482), the one at Rome, the other at Bologna, it was found that each had recommended his state to the care of the other. Against a class of men who themselves stuck at nothing, everything was held to be permissible. Francesco Sforza, when quite young, had married a rich Calabrian heiress, Polissena Russa, Countess of Montalto, who bore him a daughter; an aunt poisoned both mother and child, and seized the inheritance.

From the death of Piccinino onwards, the foundations of new states by the condottieri became a scandal not to be tolerated. The four great powers, Naples, Milan, the papacy and Venice, formed among themselves a political equilibrium which refused to allow of any disturbance. In the States of the Church, which swarmed with petty tyrants, who in part were, or had been, condottieri, the nephews of the popes, since the time of Sixtus IV, monopolized the right to all such undertakings. But at the first sign of a political crisis, the soldiers of fortune appeared again upon the scene. Under the wretched administration of Innocent VIII it was near happening that a certain Boccalino, who had formerly served in the Burgundian army, gave himself and the town of Osimo, of which he was master, up to the Turkish forces; fortunately, through the intervention of Lorenzo the Magnificent, he proved willing to be paid off, and took himself away. In the year 1495, when the wars of Charles VIII had turned Italy upside down, the condottiere Vidovero, of Brescia, made trial of his strength: he had already seized the town of Cesena and murdered many of the nobles and the burghers; but the citadel held out, and he was forced to withdraw. He then, at the head of a band lent him by another scoundrel, Pandolfo Malatesta of Rimini, son of the Roberto already spoken of, and Venetian condottiere, wrested the town of Castelnuovo from the Archbishop of Ravenna. The Venetians, fearing that worse would follow, and urged also by the pope, ordered Pandolfo, 'with the kindest intentions', to take an opportunity of arresting his good friend: the arrest was made, though 'with great regret', whereupon the order came to bring the prisoner to the gallows. Pandolfo was considerate enough to strangle him in prison, and then show his corpse to the people. The last notable example of such usurpers is the famous castellan of Musso, who, during the confusion in the Milanese territory which followed the battle of Pavia (1525), improvised a sovereignty on the Lake of Como.

The Smaller Despotisms

It may be said in general of the despotisms of the fifteenth century that the greatest crimes are most frequent in the smallest states. In these, where the family was numerous and all the members wished to live in a manner befitting their rank, disputes respecting the inheritance were unavoidable. Bernardo Varano of Camerino put two of his brothers to death (1434), wishing to divide their property among his sons. Where the ruler of a single town was distinguished by a wise, moderate and humane government, and by zeal for intellectual culture, he was generally a member of some great family, or politically dependent on it. This was the case, for example, with Alessandro Sforza, Prince of Pesaro (d. 1473), brother of the great Francesco, and step-father of Frederick of Urbino. Prudent in administration, just and affable in his rule, he enjoyed, after years of warfare, a tranquil reign, collected a noble library, and passed his leisure in learned or religious conversation. A man of the same class was Giovanni II Bentivoglio of Bologna (1462—1506), whose policy was determined by that of the Este and the Sforza. What ferocity and bloodthirstiness is found, on the other hand, among the Varani of Camerino, the Malatesta of Rimini, the Manfreddi of Faenza, and above all among the Baglioni of Perugia. We find a striking picture of the events in the last-named family, towards the close of the fifteenth century, in the admirable historical narratives of Graziani and Matarazzo.

The Baglioni were one of those families whose rule never took the shape of an avowed despotism. It was rather a leadership exercised by means of their vast wealth and of their practical influence in the choice of public officers. Within the family one man was recognized as head; but deep and secret jealousy prevailed among the members of the different branches. Opposed to the Baglioni stood another aristocratic party, led by the family of the Oddi. In 1487 the city was turned into a camp, and the houses of the leading citizens swarmed with bravos; scenes of violence were of daily occurrence. At the burial of a German student, who had been assassinated, two colleges took arms against one another; sometimes the bravos of the different houses even joined battle in the public square. The complaints of the merchants and artisans were vain; the papal governors and nipoti held their tongues, or took themselves off on the first opportunity. At last the Oddi were forced to abandon Perugia, and the city became a beleaguered fortress under the absolute despotism of the Baglioni, who used even the cathedral as barracks. Plots and surprises were met with cruel vengeance; in the year 1491, after 130 conspirators who had forced their way into the city were killed and hung up at the Palazzo Comunale, thirty-five altars were erected in the square, and for three days mass was performed and processions held, to take away the curse which rested on the spot. A nephew of Innocent VIII was in open day run through in the street. A nephew of Alexander VI, who was sent to smooth matters over, was dismissed with public contempt. All the while the two leaders of the ruling house, Guido and Ridolfo, were holding frequent interviews with Suor Colomba of Rieti, a Dominican nun of saintly reputation and miraculous powers, who under penalty of some great disaster ordered them to make peace — naturally in vain. Nevertheless the chronicle takes the opportunity to point out the devotion and piety of the better men in Perugia during this reign of terror. When in 1494 Charles VIII approached, the Baglioni from Perugia and the exiles encamped in and near Assisi conducted the war with such ferocity that every house in the valley was levelled to the ground. The fields lay untilled, the peasants were turned into plundering and murdering savages, the fresh-grown bushes were filled with stags and wolves, and the beasts grew fat on the bodies of the slain, on so-called 'Christian flesh'. When Alexander VI withdrew (1495) into Umbria before Charles VIII, then returning from Naples, it occurred to him, when at Perugia, that he might now rid himself of the Baglioni once for all; he proposed to Guido a festival or tournament, or something else of the same kind, which would bring the whole family together. Guido, however, was of the opinion 'that the most impressive spectacle of all would be to see the whole military force of Perugia collected in a body', whereupon the pope abandoned his project. Soon after, the exiles made another attack in which nothing but the personal heroism of the Baglioni won them the victory. It was then that Simonetto Baglione, a lad of scarcely eighteen, fought in the square with a handful of followers against hundreds of the enemy: he fell at last with more than twenty wounds, but recovered himself when Astorre Baglione came to his help, and mounting on horseback in gilded armour with a falcon on his helmet, 'like Mars in bearing and in deeds, plunged into the struggle'.

At that time Raphael, a boy of twelve years of age, was at school under Pietro Perugino. The impressions of these days are perhaps immortalized in the small, early pictures of St Michael and St George: something of them, it may be, lives eternally in the great painting of St Michael: and if Astorre Baglione has anywhere found his apotheosis, it is in the figure of the heavenly horseman in the Heliodorus.

The opponents of the Baglioni were partly destroyed, partly scattered in terror, and were henceforth incapable of another enterprise of the kind. After a time a partial reconciliation took place, and some of the exiles were allowed to return. But Perugia became none the safer or more tranquil: the inward discord of the ruling family broke out in frightful excesses. An opposition was formed against Guido and Ridolfo and their sons Gianpaolo, Simonetto, Astorre, Gismondo, Gentile, Marcantinio and others, by two great-nephews, Grifone and Carlo Barciglia; the latter of the two was also nephew of Varano, Prince of Camerino, and brother-in-law of one of the former exiles, Ieronimo della Penna. In vain did Simonetto, warned by sinister presentiment, entreat his uncle on his knees to allow him to put Penna to death: Guido refused. The plot ripened suddenly on the occasion of the marriage of Astorre with Lavinia Colonna, at midsummer 1500. The festival began and lasted several days amid gloomy forebodings, whose deepening effect is admirably described by Matarazzo. Varano fed and encouraged them with devilish ingenuity: he worked upon Grifone by the prospect of undivided authority, and by stories of an imaginary intrigue of his wife Zenobia with Gianpaolo. Finally each conspirator was provided with a victim. (The Baglioni lived all of them in separate houses, mostly on the site of the present castle.) Each received fifteen of the bravos at hand; the remainder were set on the watch. In the night of 15 July the doors were forced, and Guido, Astorre, Simonetto and Gismondo were murdered; the others succeeded in escaping.

As the corpse of Astorre lay by that of Simonetto in the street, the spectators, 'and especially the foreign students', compared him to an ancient Roman, so great and imposing did he seem. In the features of Simonetto could still be traced the audacity and defiance which death itself had not tamed. The victors went round among the friends of the family, and did their best to recommend themselves; they found all in tears and preparing to leave for the country. Meantime the escaped Baglioni collected forces without the city, and on the following day forced their way in, Gianpaolo at their head, and speedily found adherents among others whom Barciglia had been threatening with death. When Grifone fell into their hands near Sant' Ercolano, Gianpaolo handed him over for execution to his followers. Barciglia and Penna fled to Varano, the chief author of the tragedy, at Camerino; and in a moment, almost without loss, Gianpaolo became master of the city.

Atalanta, the still young and beautiful mother of Grifone, who the day before had withdrawn to a country house with the latter's wife Zenobia and two children of Gianpaolo, and more than once had repulsed her son with a mother's curse, now returned with her daughter-in-law in search of the dying man. All stood aside as the two women approached, each man shrinking from being recognized as the slayer of Grifone, and dreading the malediction of the mother. But they were deceived: she herself besought her son to pardon him who had dealt the fatal blow, and he died with her blessing. The eyes of the crowd followed the two women reverently as they crossed the square with blood-stained garments. It was Atalanta for whom Raphael afterwards painted the world-famed Deposition, with which she laid her own maternal sorrows at the feet of a yet higher and holier suffering.

The cathedral, in the immediate neighbourhood of which the greater part of this tragedy had been enacted, was washed with wine and consecrated afresh. The triumphal arch, erected for the wedding, still remained standing, painted with the deeds of Astorre and with the laudatory verses of the narrator of these events, the worthy Matarazzo.

A legendary history, which is simply the reflection of these atrocities, arose out of the early days of the Baglioni. All the members of this family from the beginning were reported to have died an evil death — twenty-seven on one occasion together; their houses were said to have been once before levelled to the ground, and the streets of Perugia paved with the bricks — and more of the same kind. Under Paul III the destruction of their palaces really took place.

For a time they seemed to have formed good resolutions, to have brought their own party into order, and to have protected the public officials against the arbitrary acts of the nobility. But the old curse broke out again like a smouldering fire. In 1520 Gianpaolo was enticed to Rome under Leo X, and there beheaded; one of his sons, Orazio, who ruled in Perugia for a short time only, and by the most violent means, as the partisan of the Duke of Urbino (himself threatened by the pope), once more repeated in his own family the horrors of the past. His uncle and three cousins were murdered, whereupon the duke sent him word that enough had been done. His brother, Malatesta Baglione, the Florentine general, has made himself immortal by the treason of 1530; and Malatesta's son Ridolfo, the last of the house, attained, by the murder of the legate and the public officers in the year 1534, a brief but sanguinary authority.

Here and there we meet with the names of the rulers of Rimini. Unscrupulousness, impiety, military skill and high culture have been seldom combined in one individual as in Sigismondo Malatesta (d. 1467). But the accumulated crimes of such a family must at last outweigh all talent, however great, and drag the tyrant into the abyss. Pandolfo, Sigismondo's nephew, who has been mentioned already, succeeded in holding his ground, for the sole reason that the Venetians refused to abandon their condottiere, whatever guilt he might be chargeable with; when his subjects, after ample provocation, bombarded him in his castle at Rimini (1497), and afterwards allowed him to escape, a Venetian commissioner brought him back, stained as he was with fratricide and every other abomination. Thirty years later the Malatesta were penniless exiles. In the year 1527, as in the time of Cesare Borgia, a sort of epidemic fell on the petty tyrants; few of them outlived this date, and none to their own good. At Mirandola, which was governed by insignificant princes of the house of Pico, lived in the year 1533 a poor scholar, Lilio Gregorio Giraldi, who had fled from the sack of Rome to the hospitable hearth of the aged Giovanni Francesco Pico, nephew of the famous Giovanni; the discussions as to the sepulchral monument which the prince was constructing for himself gave rise to a treatise, the dedication of which bears the date of April in this year. The postscript is a sad one — 'In October of the same year the unhappy prince was attacked in the night and robbed of life and throne by his brother's son; and I myself escaped narrowly, and am now in the deepest misery.'

A pseudo-despotism without characteristic features, such as Pandolfo Petrucci exercised from the year 1490 in Siena, then torn by faction, is hardly worth a closer consideration. Insignificant and malicious, he governed with the help of a professor of jurisprudence and of an astrologer, and frightened his people by an occasional murder. His pastime in the summer months was to roll blocks of stone from the top of Monte Amiata, without caring what or whom they hit. After succeeding, where the most prudent failed, in escaping from the devices of Cesare Borgia, he died at last forsaken and despised. His sons maintained a qualified supremacy for many years afterwards.

The Greater Dynasties

In treating of the chief dynasties of Italy, it is convenient to discuss the Aragonese, on account of its special character, apart from the rest. The feudal system, which from the days of the Normans had survived in the form of a territorial supremacy of the barons, gave a distinctive colour to the political constitution of Naples; while elsewhere in Italy, excepting only in the southern part of the ecclesiastical dominion, and in a few other districts, a direct tenure of land prevailed, and no hereditary powers were permitted by the law. The great Alfonso, who reigned in Naples from 1435 onwards (d. 1458), was a man of another kind than his real or alleged descendants. Brilliant in his whole existence, fearless in mixing with his people, dignified and affable in intercourse, admired rather than blamed even for his old man's passion for Lucrezia d'Alagnam, he had the one bad quality of extravagance, from which, however, the natural consequence followed. Unscrupulous financiers were long omnipotent at court, till the bankrupt king robbed them of their spoils; a crusade was preached as a pretext for taxing the clergy; when a great earthquake happened in the Abruzzi, the survivors were compelled to make good the contributions of the dead. By such means Alfonso was able to entertain distinguished guests with unrivalled splendour; he found pleasure in ceaseless expense, even for the benefit of his enemies, and in rewarding literary work knew absolutely no measure. Poggio received 500 pieces of gold for translating Xenophon's Cyropaedeia.

Ferrante, who succeeded him, passed as his illegitimate son by a Spanish lady, but was not improbably the son of a half-caste Moor of Valencia. Whether it was his blood or the plots formed against his life by the barons which embittered and darkened his nature, it is certain that he was equalled in ferocity by none among the princes of his time. Restlessly active, recognized as one of the most powerful political minds of the day, and free from the vices of the profligate, he concentrated all his powers, among which must be reckoned profound dissimulation and an irreconcilable spirit of vengeance, on the destruction of his opponents. He had been wounded in every point in which a ruler is open to offence; for the leaders of the barons, though related to him by marriage, were yet the allies of his foreign enemies. Extreme measures became part of his daily policy. The means for this struggle with his barons, and for his external wars, were exacted in the same Muhammadan fashion which Frederick II had introduced: the government alone dealt in oil and corn; the whole commerce of the country was put by Ferrante into the hands of a wealthy merchant, Francesco Coppola, who had entire control of the anchorage on the coast, and shared the profits with the king. Deficits were made up by forced loans, by executions and confiscations, by open simony, and by contributions levied on the ecclesiastical corporations. Besides hunting, which he practised regardless of all rights of property, his pleasures were of two kinds: he liked to have his opponents near him, either alive in well-guarded prisons, or dead and embalmed, dressed in the costume which they wore in their lifetime. He would chuckle in talking of the captives with his friends, and made no secret whatever of the museum of mummies. His victims were mostly men whom he had got into his power by treachery; some were even seized while guests at the royal table. His conduct to his first minister, Antolello Petrucci, who had grown sick and grey in his service, and from whose increasing fear of death he extorted 'present after present', was literally devilish. At length the suspicion of complicity with the last conspiracy of the barons gave the pretext for his arrest and execution. With him died Coppola. The way in which all this is narrated in Caracciolo and Porzio makes one's hair stand on end.

The elder of the king's sons, Alfonso, Duke of Calabria, enjoyed in later years a kind of co-regency with his father. He was a savage, brutal profligate, who in point of frankness alone had the advantage of Ferrante, and who openly avowed his contempt for religion and its usages. The better and nobler features of the Italian despotisms are not to be found among the princes of this line; all that they possessed of the art and culture of their time served the purposes of luxury or display. Even the genuine Spaniards seem to have almost always degenerated in Italy; but the end of this cross-bred house (1494 and 1503) gives clear proof of a want of blood. Ferrante died of mental care and trouble; Alfonso accused his brother Federigo, the only honest member of the family, of treason, and insulted him in the vilest manner. At length, though he had hitherto passed for one of the ablest generals in Italy, he lost his head and fled to Sicily, leaving his son, the younger Ferrante, a prey to the French and to domestic treason. A dynasty which had ruled as this had done must at least have sold its life dear, if its children were ever to hope for a restoration. But, as Comines one-sidedly and yet on the whole rightly observes on this occasion, 'Jamais homme cruel ne fut plus hardi': there was never a more cruel man.

The despotism of the dukes of Milan, whose government from the time of Giangaleazzo onwards was an absolute monarchy of the most thoroughgoing sort, shows the genuine Italian character of the fifteenth century. The last of the Visconti, Filippo Maria (1412—47), is a character of peculiar interest, and of which fortunately an admirable description has been left us. What a man of uncommon gifts and high position can be made by the passion of fear is here shown with what may be called a mathematical completeness. All the resources of the state were devoted to the one end of securing his personal safety, though happily his cruel egotism did not degenerate into a purposeless thirst for blood. He lived in the Citadel of Milan, surrounded by magnificent gardens, arbours and lawns. For years he never set foot in the city, making his excursions only in the country, where lay several of his splendid castles; the flotilla which, drawn by the swiftest horses, conducted him to them along canals constructed for the purpose, was so arranged as to allow of the application of the most rigorous etiquette. Whoever entered the Citadel was watched by a hundred eyes; it was forbidden even to stand at the window, lest signs should be given to those without. All who were admitted among the personal followers of the prince were subjected to a series of the strictest examinations; then, once accepted, were charged with the highest diplomatic commissions, as well as with the humblest personal services — both in this court being alike honourable. And this was the man who conducted long and difficult wars, who dealt habitually with political affairs of the first importance, and every day sent his plenipotentiaries to all parts of Italy. His safety lay in the fact that none of his servants trusted the others, that his condottieri were watched and misled by spies, and that the ambassadors and higher officials were baffled and kept apart by artificially nourished jealousies, and in particular by the device of coupling an honest man with a knave. His inward faith, too, rested upon opposed and contradictory systems; he believed in blind necessity, and in the influence of the stars, and offering prayers at one and the same time to helpers of every sort; he was a student of the ancient authors, as well as of French tales of chivalry. And yet the same man, who would never suffer death to be mentioned in his presence, and caused his dying favourites to be removed from the castle, that no shadow might fall on the abode of happiness, deliberately hastened his own death by closing up a wound, and, refusing to be bled, died at last with dignity and grace.

His son-in-law and successor, the fortunate condottiere Francesco Sforza (145o—66), was perhaps of all the Italians of the fifteenth century the man most after the heart of his age. Never was the triumph of genius and individual power more brilliantly displayed than in him; and those who would not recognize his merit were at least forced to wonder at him as the spoilt child of fortune. The Milanese claimed it openly as an honour to be governed by so distinguished a master; when he entered the city the thronging populace bore him on horseback into the cathedral, without giving him the chance to dismount. Let us listen to the balance-sheet of his life, in the estimate of Pope Pius II, a judge in such matters:

In the year 1459, when the duke came to the congress at Mantua, he was sixty (really fifty-eight) years old; on horseback he looked like a young man; of a lofty and imposing figure, with serious features, calm and affable in conversation, princely in his whole bearing, with a combination of bodily and intellectual gifts unrivalled in our time, unconquered on the field of battle — such was the man who raised himself from a humble position to the control of an empire. His wife was beautiful and virtuous, his children were like the angels of heaven; he was seldom ill, and all his chief wishes were fulfilled. And yet he was not without misfortune. His wife, out of jealousy, killed his mistress; his old comrades and friends, Troilo and Brunoro, abandoned him and went over to King Alfonso; another, Ciarpollone, he was forced to hang for treason; he had to suffer it that his brother Alessandro set the French upon him; one of his sons formed intrigues against him, and was imprisoned; the March of Ancona, which he had won in war, he lost again the same way. No man enjoys so unclouded a fortune, that he has not somewhere to struggle with adversity. He is happy who has but few troubles.

With this negative definition of happiness the learned pope dismisses the reader. Had he been able to see into the future, or been willing to stop and discuss the consequences of an uncontrolled despotism, one pervading fact would not have escaped his notice — the absence of all guarantee for the future. Those children, beautiful as angels, carefully and thoroughly educated as they were, fell victims, when they grew up, to the corruption of a measureless egotism. Galeazzo Maria (1466—76), solicitous only of outward effect, took pride in the beauty of his hands, in the high salaries he paid, in the financial credit he enjoyed, in his treasure of two million pieces of gold, in the distinguished people who surrounded him, and in the army and birds of chase which he maintained. He was fond of the sound of his own voice, and spoke well, most fluently, perhaps, when he had the chance of insulting a Venetian ambassador. He was subject to caprices, such as having a room painted with figures in a single night; and, what was worse, to fits of senseless debauchery and of revolting cruelty to his nearest friends. To a handful of enthusiasts, he seemed a tyrant too bad to live; they murdered him, and thereby delivered the state into the power of his brothers, one of whom, Lodovico il Moro, threw his nephew into prison, and took the government into his own hands. From this usurpation followed the French intervention, and the disasters which befell the whole of Italy.

Lodovico Sforza, called 'il Moro', the Moor, is the most perfect type of the despot of that age, and, as a kind of natural product, almost disarms our moral judgement. Notwithstanding the profound immorality of the means he employed, he used them with perfect ingeniousness; no one would probably have been more astonished than himself to learn that for the choice of means as well as of ends a human being is morally responsible; he would rather have reckoned it as a singular virtue that, so far as possible, he had abstained from too free a use of the punishment of death. He accepted as no more than his due the almost fabulous respect of the Italians for his political genius. In 1496 he boasted that the Pope Alexander was his chaplain, the Emperor Maximilian his condottiere, Venice his chamberlain, and the King of France his courier, who must come and go at his bidding. With marvellous presence of mind he weighed, even in his last extremity (1499), all possible means of escape, and at length decided, to his honour, to trust to the goodness of human nature; he rejected the proposal of his brother, the Cardinal Ascanio, who wished to remain in the Citadel of Milan, on the ground of a former quarrel: 'Monsignore, take it not ill, but I trust you not, brother though you be'; and appointed to the command of the castle, 'that pledge of his return', a man to whom he had always done good, but who nevertheless betrayed him. At home the Moor was a good and useful ruler, and to the last he reckoned on his popularity both in Milan and in Como. In later years (after 1496) he had overstrained the resources of his state, and at Cremona had ordered, out of pure expediency, a respectable citizen, who had spoken against the new taxes, to be quietly strangled. Since that time, in holding audiences, he kept his visitors away from his person by means of a bar, so that in conversing with him they were compelled to speak at the top of their voices. At his court, the most brilliant in Europe, since that of Burgundy had ceased to exist, immorality of the worst kind was prevalent; the daughter was sold by the father, the wife by the husband, the sister by the brother. The prince himself was incessantly active, and, as son of his own deeds, claimed relationship with all who, like himself, stood on their personal merits — with scholars, poets, artists and musicians. The academy which he founded served rather for his own purposes than for the instruction of scholars; nor was it the fame of the distinguished men who surrounded him which he heeded, so much as their society and their services. It is certain that Bramante was scantily paid at first; Leonardo, on the other hand, was up to 1496 suitably remunerated — and besides, what kept him at the court, if not his own free will? The world lay open to him, as perhaps to no other mortal man of that day; and if proof were wanting of the loftier element in the nature of Lodovico il Moro, it is found in the long stay of the enigmatic master at his court. That afterwards Leonardo entered the service of Cesare Borgia and Francis I was probably due to the interest he felt in the unusual and striking character of the two men.

After the fall of the Moor, his sons were badly brought up among strangers. The elder, Massimiliano, had no resemblance to him; the younger, Francesco, was at all events not without spirit. Milan, which in those years changed its rulers so often, and suffered so unspeakably in the change, endeavored to secure itself against a reaction. In the year 1512 the French, retreating before the arms of Maximilian and the Spaniards, were induced to make a declaration that the Milanese had taken no part in their expulsion, and, without being guilty of rebellion, might yield themselves to a new conqueror. It is a fact of some political importance that in such moments of transition the unhappy city, like Naples at the flight of the Aragonese, was apt to fall a prey to gangs of (often highly aristocratic) scoundrels.

The house of Gonzaga at Mantua and that of Montefeltro of Urbino were among the best ordered and richest in men of ability during the second half of the fifteenth century. The Gonzaga were a tolerably harmonious family; for a long period no murder had been known among them, and their dead could be shown to the world without fear. The Marquis Francesco Gonzaga and his wife, Isabella of Este, in spite of some few irregularities, were a united and respectable couple, and brought up their sons to be successful and remarkable men at a time when their small but most important state was exposed to incessant danger. That Francesco, either as statesman or as soldier, should adopt a policy of exceptional honesty, was what neither the emperor, nor Venice, nor the King of France could have expected or desired; but certainly since the battle of the Taro (1495), so far as military honour was concerned, he felt and acted as an Italian patriot, and imparted the same spirit to his wife. Every deed of loyalty and heroism, such as the defence of Faenza against Cesare Borgia, she felt as a vindication of the honour of Italy. Our judgement of her does not need to rest on the praises of the artists and writers who made the fair princess a rich return for her patronage; her own letters show her to us as a woman of unshaken firmness, full of kindliness and humorous observation. Bembo, Bandello, Ariosto and Bernardo Tasso sent their works to this court, small and powerless as it was, and empty as they found its treasury. A more polished and charming circle was not to be seen in Italy, since the dissolution (1508) of the old court of Urbino; and in one respect, in freedom of movement, the society of Ferrara was inferior to that of Mantua. In artistic matters Isabella had an accurate knowledge, and the catalogue of her small but choice collection can be read by no lover of art without emotion.

In the great Federigo (1444—82), whether he were a genuine Montefeltro or not, Urbino possessed a brilliant representative of the princely order. As a condottiere he shared the political morality of soldiers of fortune, a morality of which the fault does not rest with them alone; as ruler of his little territory he adopted the plan of spending at home the money he had earned abroad, and taxing his people as lightly as possible. Of him and his two successors, Guidobaldo and Francesco Maria, we read: 'They erected buildings, furthered the cultivation of the land, lived at home, and gave employment to a large number of people: their subjects loved them.' But not only the state, but the court too, was a work of art and organization, and this in every sense of the word. Federigo had 500 persons in his service; the arrangements of the court were as complete as in the capitals of the greatest monarchs, but nothing was wasted; all had its object, and all was carefully watched and controlled. The court was no scene of vice and dissipation: it served as a school of military education for the sons of other great houses, the thoroughness of whose culture and instruction was made a point of honour by the duke. The palace which he built, if not one of the most splendid, was classical in the perfection of its plan; there was placed the greatest of his treasures, the celebrated library. Feeling secure in a land where all gained profit or employment from his rule, and where none were beggars, he habitually went about unarmed and almost unaccompanied; alone among the princes of his time he ventured to walk in an open park, and to take his frugal meals in an open chamber, while Livy, or in time of fasting some devotional work, was read to him. In the course of the same afternoon he would listen to a lecture on some classical subject, and thence would go to the monastery of the Clarisses and talk of sacred things through the grating with the abbess. In the evening he would overlook the martial exercises of the young people of his court on the meadow of San Francesco, known for its magnificent view, and saw to it well that all the feats were done in the most perfect manner. He strove always to be affable and accessible to the utmost degree, visiting the artisans who worked for him in their shops, holding frequent audiences, and, if possible, attending to the requests of each individual on the same day that they were presented. No wonder that the people, as he walked along the street, knelt down and cried: 'Dio ti mantenga, signore!' He was called by thinking people 'the light of Italy'. His gifted son Guidobaldo, visited by sickness and misfortune of every kind, was able at the last (1508) to give his state into the safe hands of his nephew Francesco Maria (nephew also of Pope Julius II), who at least succeeded in preserving the territory from any permanent foreign occupation. It is remarkable with what confidence Guidobaldo yielded and fled before Cesare Borgia and Francesco before the troops of Leo X; each knew that his restoration would be all the easier and the more popular the less the country suffered through a fruitless defence. When Lodo-vico made the same calculation at Milan, he forgot the many grounds of hatred which existed against him. The court of Guidobaldo has been made immortal as the high school of polished manners by Baldassare Castiglione, who represented his eclogue 'Thyrsis' before, and in honour of, that society (1506), and who afterwards (1518) laid the scene of the dialogue of his Cortigiano in the circle of the accomplished Duchess Elisabetta Gonzaga.

The government of the family of Este at Ferrara, Modena and Reggio displays curious contrasts of violence and popularity. Within the palace frightful deeds were perpetrated; a princess was beheaded (1425) for alleged adultery with a step-son; legitimate and illegitimate children fled from the court, and even abroad their lives were threatened by assassins sent in pursuit of them (1471). Plots from without were incessant; the bastard of a bastard tried to wrest the crown from the lawful heir, Ercole I; this latter is said afterwards (1493) to have poisoned his wife on discovering that she, at the instigation of her brother Ferrante of Naples, was going to poison him. This list of tragedies is closed by the plot of two bastards against their brothers, the ruling Duke Alfonso I and Cardinal Ippolito (1506), which was discovered in time, and punished with imprisonment for life. The financial system in this state was of the most perfect kind, and necessarily so, since none of the large or second-rate powers of Italy were exposed to such danger and stood in such constant need of armaments and fortifications. It was the hope of the rulers that the increasing prosperity of the people would keep pace with the increasing weight of taxation, and the Marquis Niccolò (d. 1441) used to express the wish that his subjects might be richer than the people of other countries. If the rapid increase of the population be a measure of prosperity actually attained, it is certainly a fact of importance that in the year 1497, notwithstanding the wonderful extension of the capital, no houses were to be let. Ferrara is the first really modern city in Europe; large and well-built quarters sprang up at the bidding of the ruler: here, by the concentration of the official classes and the active promotion of trade, was formed for the first time a true capital; wealthy fugitives from all parts of Italy, Florentines especially, settled and built their palaces at Ferrara. But the indirect taxation, at all events, must have reached a point at which it could only just be borne. The government, it is true, took measures of alleviation which were also adopted by other Italian despots, such as Galeazzo Maria Sforza: in time of famine corn was brought from a distance and seems to have been distributed gratuitously; but in ordinary times it compensated itself by the monopoly, if not of corn, of many other of the necessaries of life — fish, salt, meat, fruit and vegetables, which last were carefully planted on and near the walls of the city. The most considerable source of income, however, was the annual sale of public offices, a usage which was common throughout Italy, and about the working of which at Ferrara we have more precise information. We read, for example, that at the new year 1502 the majority of the officials bought their places at 'prezzi salati'; public servants of the most various kinds, custom-house officers, bailiffs (massari), notaries, 'podestà', judges and even captains, i. e. lieutenant-governors of provincial towns, are quoted by name. As one of the 'devourers of the people' who paid dearly for their places, and who were 'hated worse than the devil', Tito Strozza — let us hope not the famous Latin poet — is mentioned. About the same time every year the dukes were accustomed to make a round of visits in Ferrara, the so-called 'andar per ventura', in which they took presents from, at any rate, the more wealthy citizens. The gifts, however, did not consist of money, but of natural products.

It was the pride of the duke for all Italy to know that at Ferrara the soldiers received their pay and the professors at the university their salary not a day later than it was due; that the soldiers never dared lay arbitrary hands on a citizen or peasant; that the town was impregnable to assault; and that vast sums of coined money were stored up in the citadel. To keep two sets of accounts seemed unnecessary: the Minister of Finance was at the same time manager of the ducal household. The buildings erected by Borso (1430—71), by Ercole I (till 1505), and by Alfonso I (till 1534), were very numerous, but of small size; they are characteristic of a princely house which, with all its love of splendour — Borso never appeared but in embroidery and jewels — indulged in no ill-considered expense. Alfonso may perhaps have foreseen the fate which was in store for his charming little villas, the Belvedere with its shady gardens, and Montana with its fountains and beautiful frescoes.

It is undeniable that the dangers to which these princes were constantly exposed developed in them capacities of a remarkable kind. In so artificial a world only a man of consummate address could hope to succeed; each candidate for distinction was forced to make good his claims by personal merit and show himself worthy of the crown he sought. Their characters are not without dark sides; but in all of them lives something of those qualities which Italy then pursued as its ideal. What European monarch of the time laboured for his own culture as, for instance, Alfonso I? His travels in France, England and the Netherlands were undertaken for the purpose of study: by means of them he gained an accurate knowledge of the industry and commerce of these countries. It is ridiculous to reproach him with the turner's work which he practised in his leisure hours, connected as it was with his skill in the casting of cannon, and with the unprejudiced freedom with which he surrounded himself by masters of every art. The Italian princes were not, like their contemporaries in the North, dependent on the society of an aristocracy which held itself to be the only class worth consideration, and which infected the monarch with the same conceit. In Italy the prince was permitted and compelled to know and to use men of every grade in society; and the nobility, though by birth a caste, were forced in social intercourse to stand upon their personal qualifications alone. But this is a point which we shall discuss more fully in the sequel.

The feeling of the Ferrarese towards the ruling house was a strange compound of silent dread, of the truly Italian sense of well-calculated interest, and of the loyalty of the modern subject: personal admiration was transferred into a new sentiment of duty. The city of Ferrara raised in 1451 a bronze equestrian statue to their Prince Niccolò, who had died ten years earlier; Borso (1454) did not scruple to place his own statue, also of bronze, but in a sitting posture, hard by in the market; in addition to which the city, at the beginning of his reign, decreed to him a 'marble triumphal pillar'. A citizen who, when abroad in Venice, had spoken ill of Borso in public was informed against on his return home, and condemned to banishment and the confiscation of his goods; a loyal subject was with difficulty restrained from cutting him down before the tribunal itself, and with a rope round his neck the offender went to the duke and begged for a full pardon. The government was well provided with spies, and the duke inspected personally the daily list of travellers which the inn-keepers were strictly ordered to present. Under Borso, who was anxious to leave no distinguished stranger unhonoured, this regulation served a hospitable purpose; Ercole I used it simply as a measure of precaution. In Bologna, too, it was then the rule, under Giovanni II Bentivoglio, that every passing traveller who entered at one gate must obtain a ticket in order to go out at another. An unfailing means of popularity was the sudden dismissal of oppressive officials. When Borso arrested in person his chief and confidential counsellors, when Ercole I removed and disgraced a tax-gatherer who for years had been sucking the blood of the people, bonfires were lighted and the bells were pealed in their honour. With one of his servants, however, Ercole let things go too far. The director of the police, or by whatever name we should choose to call him (capitano di giustizia), was Gregorio Zampante of Lucca — a native being unsuited for an office of this kind. Even the sons and brothers of the duke trembled before this man; the fines he inflicted amounted to hundreds and thousands of ducats, and torture was applied even before the hearing of a case: bribes were accepted from wealthy criminals, and their pardon obtained from the duke by false representations. Gladly would the people have paid any sum to this ruler for sending away the 'enemy of God and man'. But Ercole had knighted him and made him godfather to his children; and year by year Zampante laid by 2,000 ducats. He dared only eat pigeons bred in his own house, and could not cross the street without a band of archers and bravos. It was time to get rid of him; in 1496 two students and a converted Jew whom he had mortally offended killed him in his house while he was taking his siesta, and then rode through the town on horses held in waiting, raising the cry, 'Come out! Come out! We have slain Zampante!' The pursuers came too late, and found them already safe across the frontier. Of course it now rained satires — some of them in the form of sonnets, others of odes.

It was wholly in the spirit of this system that the sovereign imposed his own respect for useful servants on the court and on the people. When in 1469 Borso's privy councillor Lodovico Casella died, no court of law or place of business in the city, and no lecture-room at the university, was allowed to be open: all had to follow the body to San Domenico, since the duke intended to be present. And, in fact, 'the first of the house of Este who attended the corpse of a subject' walked, clad in black, after the coffin, weeping, while behind him came the relatives of Casella, each conducted by one of the gentlemen of the court: the body of the plain citizen was carried by nobles from the church into the cloister, where it was buried. Indeed this official sympathy with princely emotion first came up in the Italian states. At the root of the practice may be a beautiful, humane sentiment; the utterance of it, especially in the poets, is, as a rule, of equivocal sincerity. One of the youthful poems of Ariosto, on the death of Leonora of Aragon, wife of Ercole I, contains besides the inevitable graveyard flowers, which are scattered in the elegies of all ages, some thoroughly modern features:

This death had given Ferrara a blow which it would not get over for years: its benefactress was now its advocate in heaven, since earth was not worthy of her; truly the angel of Death did not come to her, as to us common mortals, with blood-stained scythe, but fair to behold [onesta] and with so kind a face that every fear was allayed.

But we meet, also, with a sympathy of a different kind. Novelists, depending wholly on the favour of their patrons, tell us the love-stories of the prince, even before his death, in a way which, to later times, would seem the height of indiscretion, but which then passed simply as an innocent compliment. Lyrical poets even went so far as to sing the illicit flames of their lawfully married lords, e. g. Angelo Poliziano, those of Lorenzo the Magnificent, and Gioviano Pontano, with a singular gusto, those of Alfonso of Calabria. The poem in question betrays unconsciously the odious disposition of the Aragonese ruler; in these things too, he must needs be the most fortunate, else woe be to those who are more successful! That the greatest artists, for example Leonardo, should paint the mistresses of their patrons was no more than a matter of course.

But the house of Este was not satisfied with the praises of others; it undertook to celebrate them itself. In the Palazzo Schifanoia Borso caused himself to be painted in a series of historical representations, and Ercole (from 1472 on) kept the anniversary of his accession to the throne by a procession which was compared to the feast of Corpus Christi; shops were closed as on Sunday; in the centre of the line walked all the members of the princely house (bastards included) clad in embroidered robes. That the crown was the fountain of honour and authority, that all personal distinction flowed from it alone, had been long expressed at this court by the Order of the Golden Spur — an order which had nothing in common with medieval chivalry. Ercole I added to the spur a sword, a gold-laced mantle and a grant of money, in return for which there is no doubt that regular service was required.

The patronage of art and letters for which this court has obtained a world-wide reputation was exercised through the university, which was one of the most perfect in Italy, and by the gift of places in the personal or official service of the prince; it involved consequently no additional expense. Boiardo, as a wealthy country gentleman and high official, belonged to this class. At the time when Ariosto began to distinguish himself, there existed no court, in the true sense of the word, either at Milan or Florence, and soon there was none either at Urbino or at Naples. He had to content himself with a place among the musicians and jugglers of Cardinal Ippolito till Alfonso took him into his service. It was otherwise at a later time with Torquato Tasso, whose presence at court was jealously sought after.

The Opponents of the Despots

In face of this centralized authority, all legal opposition within the borders of the state was futile. The elements needed for the restoration of a republic had been for ever destroyed, and the field prepared for violence and despotism. The nobles, destitute of political rights, even where they held feudal possessions, might call themselves Guelphs or Ghibellines at will, might dress up their bravos in padded hose and feathered caps or how else they pleased; thoughtful men like Machiavelli knew well enough that Milan and Naples were too 'corrupt' for a republic. Strange judgements fall on these two so-called parties, which now served only to give an official sanction to personal and family disputes. An Italian prince, whom Agrippa of Nettesheim advised to put them down, replied that their quarrels brought him more than 12,000 ducats a year in fines. And when in the year 1500, during the brief return of Lodovico il Moro to his states, the Guelphs of Tortona summoned a part of the neighbouring French army into the city, in order to make an end once for all of their opponents, the French certainly began by plundering and ruining the Ghibellines, but finished by doing the same to the Guelphs, till Tortona was utterly laid waste. In Romagna, the hotbed of every ferocious passion, these two names had long lost all political meaning. It was a sign of the political delusion of the people that they not seldom believed the Guelphs to be the natural allies of the French and the Ghibellines of the Spaniards. It is hard to see that those who tried to profit by this error got much by doing so. France, after all her interventions, had to abandon the peninsula at last, and what became of Spain, after she had destroyed Italy, is known to every reader.

But to return to the despots of the Renaissance. A pure and simple mind, we might think, would perhaps have argued that, since all power is derived from God, these princes, if they were loyally and honestly supported by all their subjects, must in time themselves improve and lose all traces of their violent origin. But from characters and imaginations inflamed by passion and ambition, reasoning of this kind could not be expected. Like bad physicians, they thought to cure the disease by removing the symptoms, and fancied that if the tyrant were put to death, freedom would follow of itself. Or else, without reflecting even to this extent, they sought only to give a vent to the universal hatred, or to take vengeance for some family misfortune or personal affront. Since the governments were absolute, and free from all legal restraints, the opposition chose its weapons with equal freedom. Boccaccio declares openly:

Shall I call the tyrant king or prince, and obey him loyally as my lord? No, for he is the enemy of the commonwealth. Against him I may use arms, conspiracies, spies, ambushes and fraud; to do so is a sacred and necessary work. There is no more acceptable sacrifice than the blood of a tyrant.

We need not occupy ourselves with individual cases; Machiavelli, in a famous chapter of his Discorsi, treats of the conspiracies of ancient and modern times from the days of the Greek tyrants downwards, and classifies them with cold-blooded indifference according to their various plans and results. We need make but two observations, first on the murders committed in church, and next on the influence of classical antiquity. So well was the tyrant guarded that it was almost impossible to lay hands upon him elsewhere than at solemn religious services; and on no other occasion was the whole family to be found assembled together. It was thus that the Fabrianese murdered the members of their ruling house, the Chiavelli, during high mass (1435), the signal being given by the words of the Creed, 'Et incarnatus est.' At Milan the Duke Giovan Maria Visconti (1412) was assassinated at the entrance of the church of San Gottardo, Galeazzo Maria Sforza (1476) in the church of Santo Stefano, and Lodovico il Moro only escaped (1484) the daggers of the adherents of the widowed Duchess Bona through entering the church of Sant' Ambrogio by another door than that by which he was expected. There was no intentional impiety in the act; the assassins of Galeazzo did not fail to pray before the murder to the patron saint of the church, and to listen devoutly to the first mass. It was, however, one cause of the partial failure of the conspiracy of the Pazzi against Lorenzo and Giuliano Medici (1478), that the brigand Montesecco, who had bargained to commit the murder at a banquet, declined to undertake it in the cathedral of Florence. Certain of the clergy 'who were familiar with the sacred place, and consequently had no fear' were induced to act in his stead.

As to the imitation of antiquity, the influence of which on moral and more especially on political questions we shall often refer to, the example was set by the rulers themselves, who, both in their conception of the state and intheir personal conduct, took the old Roman empire avowedly as their model. In like manner their opponents, when they set to work with a deliberate theory, took pattern by the ancient tyrannicides. It may be hard to prove that in the main point — in forming the resolve itself — they consciously followed a classical example; but the appeal to antiquity was no mere phrase. The most striking disclosures have been left us with respect to the murderers of Galeazzo Sforza — Lampugnani, Olgiati and Visconti. Though all three had personal ends to serve, yet their enterprise may be partly ascribed to a more general reason. About this time Cola de' Montani, a humanist and professor of eloquence, had awakened among many of the young Milanese nobility a vague passion for glory and patriotic achievements, and had mentioned to Lampugnani and Olgiati his hope of delivering Milan. Suspicion was soon aroused against him: he was banished from the city, and his pupils were abandoned to the fanaticism he had excited. Some ten days before the deed they met together and took a solemn oath in the monastery of Sant' Ambrogio. 'Then,' says Olgiati, 'in a remote corner I raised my eyes before the picture of the patron saint, and implored his help for ourselves and for all his people.' The heavenly protector of the city was called on to bless the undertaking, as was afterwards St Stephen, in whose church it was fulfilled. Many of their comrades were now informed of the plot, nightly meetings were held in the house of Lampugnani, and the conspirators practised for the murder with the sheaths of their daggers. The attempt was successful, but Lampugnani was killed on the spot by the attendants of the duke; the others were captured. Visconti was penitent, but Olgiati through all his tortures maintained that the deed was an acceptable offering to God, and exclaimed while the executioner was breaking his ribs, 'Courage, Girolamo! Thou wilt long be remembered; death is bitter, but glory is eternal.'

But however idealistic the object and purpose of such conspiracies may appear, the manner in which they were conducted betrays the influence of that worst of all conspirators, Catiline — a man in whose thoughts freedom had no place whatever. The annals of Siena tell us expressly that the conspirators were students of Sallust, and the fact is indirectly confirmed by the confession of Olgiati. Elsewhere, too, we meet with the name of Catiline, and a more attractive pattern of the conspirator, apart from the end he followed, could hardly be discovered.

Among the Florentines, whenever they got rid of, or tried to get rid of, the Medici, tyrannicide was a practice universally accepted and approved. After the flight of the Medici in 1494, the bronze group of Donatello — Judith with the dead Holofernes — was taken from their collection, and placed before the Palazzo della Signoria, on the spot where the David of Michelangelo now stands, with the inscription, 'Exemplum salutis publicae cives posuere 1495'. No example was more popular than that of the younger Brutus, who, in Dante, lies with Cassius and Judas Iscariot in the lowest pit of hell, because of his treason to the empire. Pietro Paolo Boscoli, whose plot against Giuliano, Giovanni and Giulio Medici failed (1513), was an enthusiastic admirer of Brutus, and in order to follow his steps, only waited to find a Cassius. Such a partner he met with in Agostino Capponi. His last utterances in prison — a striking evidence of the religious feeling of the time — show with what an effort he rid his mind of these classical imaginations, in order to die like a Christian. A friend and the confessor both had to assure him that St Thomas Aquinas condemned conspirators absolutely; but the confessor afterwards admitted to the same friend that St Thomas drew a distinction and permitted conspiracies against a tyrant who had forced himself on a people against their will.

After Lorenzino Medici had murdered the Duke Alessandro (1537), and then escaped, an apology for the deed appeared, which is probably his own work, and certainly composed in his interest, in which he praises tyrannicide as an act of the highest merit; on the supposition that Alessandro was a legitimate Medici, and, therefore, related to him, if only distantly, he boldly compares himself with Timoleon, who slew his brother for his country's sake. Others, on the same occasion, made use of the comparison with Brutus, and that Michelangelo himself, even late in life, was not unfriendly to ideas of this kind, may be inferred from his bust of Brutus in the Bargello. He left it unfinished, like nearly all his works, but certainly not because the murder of Cesare was repugnant to his feeling, as the couplet beneath declares.

A popular radicalism in the form in which it is opposed to the monarchies of later times is not to be found in the despotic states of the Renaissance. Each individual protested inwardly against despotism but was rather disposed to make tolerable or profitable terms with it, than to combine with others for its destruction. Things must have been as bad as at Camerino, Fabriano or Rimini before the citizens united to destroy or expel the ruling house. They knew in most cases only too well that this would but mean a change of masters. The star of the republics was certainly on the decline.

The Republics: Venice and Florence

The Italian municipalities had, in earlier days, given signal proof of that force which transforms the city into the state. It remained only that these cities should combine in a great confederation; and this idea was constantly recurring to Italian statesmen, whatever differences of form it might from time to time display. In fact, during the struggles of the twelfth and thirteenth centuries, great and formidable leagues actually were formed by the cities; and Sismondi is of the opinion that the time of the final armaments of the Lombard confederation against Barbarossa (from 1168 on) was the moment when a universal Italian league was possible. But the more powerful states had already developed characteristic features which made any such scheme impracticable. In their commercial dealings they shrank from no measures, however extreme, which might damage their competitors; they held their weaker neighbours in a condition of helpless dependence — in short, they each fancied they could get on by themselves without the assistance of the rest, and thus paved the way for future usurpation. The usurper was forthcoming when long conflicts between the nobility and the people, and between the different factions of the nobility, had awakened the desire for a strong government, and when bands of mercenaries ready and willing to sell their aid to the highest bidder had superseded the general levy of the citizens, which party leaders now found unsuited to their purposes. The tyrants destroyed the freedom of most of the cities; here and there they were expelled, but not thoroughly, or only for a short time; and they were always restored, since the inward conditions were favourable to them, and the opposing forces were exhausted.

Among the cities which maintained their independence are two of deep significance for the history of the human race: Florence, the city of incessant movement, which has left us a record of the thoughts and aspirations of each and all who, for three centuries, took part in this movement, and Venice, the city of apparent stagnation and of political secrecy. No contrast can be imagined stronger than that which is offered us by these two, and neither can be compared to anything else which the world had hitherto produced.

Venice recognized itself from the first as a strange and mysterious creation — the fruits of a higher power than human ingenuity. The solemn foundation of the city was the subject of a legend. On 25 March 413, at midday, the emigrants from Padua laid the first stone at the Rialto, that they might have a sacred, inviolable asylum amid the devastations of the barbarians. Later writers attributed to the founders the presentiment of the future greatness of the city; M. Antonio Sabellico, who has celebrated the event in the dignified flow of his hexameters, makes the priest who completes the act of consecration cry to heaven, 'When we hereafter attempt great things, grant us prosperity! Now we kneel before a poor altar; but if our vows are not made in vain, a hundred temples, O God, of gold and marble shall arise to Thee.' The island city at the end of the fifteenth century was the jewel-casket of the world. It is so described by the same Sabellico, with its ancient cupolas, its leaning towers, its inlaid marble facades, its compressed splendour, when the richest decoration did not hinder the practical employment of every corner of space. He takes us to the crowded piazza before San Giacometto at the Rialto, where the business of the world is transacted, not amid shouting and confusion, but with the subdued hum of many voices; where in the porticoes round the square and in those of the adjoining streets sit hundreds of money-changers and goldsmiths, with endless rows of shops and warehouses above their heads. He describes the great Fondaco of the Germans beyond the bridge, where their goods and their dwellings lay, and before which their ships are drawn up side by side in the canal; higher up is a whole fleet laden with wine and oil, and parallel with it, on the shore swarming with porters, are the vaults of the merchants; then from the Rialto to the square of St Mark come the inns and the perfumers' cabinets. So he conducts the reader from one quarter of the city to another till he comes at last to the two hospitals which were among those institutions of public utility nowhere so numerous as at Venice. Care for the people, in peace as well as in war, was characteristic of this government, and its attention to the wounded, even to those of the enemy, excited the admiration of other states.

Public institutions of every kind found in Venice their pattern; the pensioning of retired servants was carried out systematically, and included a provision for widows and orphans. Wealth, political security and acquaintance with other countries had matured the understanding of such questions. These slender fair-haired men with quiet cautious steps and deliberate speech differed but slightly in costume and bearing from one another; ornaments, especially pearls, were reserved for the women and girls. At that time the general prosperity, notwithstanding the losses sustained from the Turks, was still dazzling; the stores of energy which the city possessed and the prejudice in its favour diffused throughout Europe enabled it at a much later time to survive the heavy blows which were inflicted by the discovery of the sea route to the Indies, by the fall of the Mamelukes in Egypt, and by the war of the League of Cambrai.

Sabellico, born in the neighbourhood of Tivoli, and accustomed to the frank loquacity of the scholars of his day, remarks elsewhere with some astonishment that the young nobles who came of a morning to hear his lectures could not be prevailed on to enter into political discussions. 'When I ask them what people think, say and expect about this or that movement in Italy, they all answer with one voice that they know nothing about the matter.' Still, in spite of the strict imposition of the state, much was to be learned from the more corrupt members of the aristocracy by those who were willing to pay enough for it. In the last quarter of the fifteenth century there were traitors among the highest officials; the popes, the Italian princes, and even second-rate condottieri in the service of the government had informers in their pay, sometimes with regular salaries; things went so far that the Council of Ten found it prudent to conceal important political news from the Council of the Pregadi, and it was even supposed that Lodovico il Moro had control of a definite number of votes among the latter. Whether the hanging of single offenders and the high rewards — such as a life-pension of sixty ducats paid to those who informed against them — were of much avail, it is hard to decide; one of the chief causes of this evil, the poverty of many of the nobility, could not be removed in a day. In the year 1492 a proposal was urged by two of that order, that the state should spend 70,000 ducats for the relief of those poorer nobles who held no public office; the matter was near coming before the Great Council, in which it might have had a majority, when the Council of Ten interfered in time and banished the two proposers for life to Nicosia in Cyprus. About this time a Soranzo was hanged, though not in Venice itself, for sacrilege, and a Contarini put in chains for burglary; another of the same family came in 1499 before the Signoria, and complained that for many years he had been without an office, that he had only sixteen ducats a year and nine children, that his debts amounted to sixty ducats, that he knew no trade and had lately been turned on to the streets. We can understand why some of the wealthier nobles built houses, sometimes whole rows of them, to provide free lodging for their needy comrades. Such works figure in wills among deeds of charity.

But if the enemies of Venice ever founded serious hopes upon abuses of this kind, they were greatly in error. It might be thought that the commercial activity of the city, which put within reach of the humblest a rich reward for their labour, and the colonies on the eastern shores of the Mediterranean would have diverted from political affairs the dangerous elements of society. But had not the political history of Genoa, notwithstanding similar advantages, been of the stormiest? The cause of the stability of Venice lies rather in a combination of circumstances which were found in union nowhere else. Unassailable from its position, it had been able from the beginning to treat of foreign affairs with the fullest and calmest reflection and ignore nearly altogether the parties which divided the rest of Italy, to escape the entanglement of permanent alliances, and to set the highest price on those which it thought fit to make. The keynote of the Venetian character was, consequently, a spirit of proud and contemptuous isolation, which, joined to the hatred felt for the city by the other states of Italy, gave rise to a strong sense of solidarity within. The inhabitants meanwhile were united by the most powerful ties of interest in dealing both with the colonies and with the possessions on the mainland, forcing the population of the latter, that is, of all the towns up to Bergamo, to buy and sell in Venice alone. A power which rested on means so artificial could only be maintained by internal harmony and unity; and this conviction was so widely diffused among the citizens that the conspirator found few elements to work upon. And the discontented, if there were such, were held so far apart by the division between the noble and the burgher that a mutual understanding was not easy. On the other hand, within the ranks of the nobility itself, travel, commercial enterprise and the incessant wars with the Turks saved the wealthy and dangerous from that fruitful source of conspiracies — idleness. In these wars they were spared, often to a criminal extent, by the general in command, and the fall of the city was predicted by a Venetian Cato, if this fear of the nobles 'to give one another pain' should continue at the expense of justice. Nevertheless this free movement in the open air gave the Venetian aristocracy, as a whole, a healthy bias.

And when envy and ambition called for satisfaction an official victim was forthcoming, and legal means and authorities were ready. The moral torture, which for years the Doge Francesco Foscari (d. 1457) suffered before the eyes of all Venice, is a frightful example of a vengeance possible only in an aristocracy. The Council of Ten, which had a hand in everything, which disposed without appeal of life and death, of financial affairs and military appointments, which included the Inquisitors among its number, and which overthrew Foscari, as it had overthrown so many powerful men before — this council was yearly chosen afresh from the whole governing body, the Gran Consiglio, and was consequently the most direct expression of its will. It is not probable that serious intrigues occurred at these elections, as the short duration of the office and the accountability which followed rendered it an object of no great desire. But violent and mysterious as the proceedings of this and other authorities might be, the genuine Venetian courted rather than fled their sentence, not only because the republic had long arms, and if it could not catch him might punish his family, but because in most cases it acted from rational motives and not from a thirst for blood. No state, indeed, has ever exercised a greater moral influence over its subjects, whether abroad or at home. If traitors were to be found among the Pregadi, there was ample compensation for this in the fact that every Venetian away from home was a born spy for his government. It was a matter of course that the Venetian cardinals at Rome sent home news of the transactions of the secret papal consistories. The Cardinal Domenico Grimani had the dispatches intercepted in the neighbourhood of Rome (1500) which Ascanio Sforza was sending to his brother Lodovico it Moro, and forwarded them to Venice; his father, then exposed to a serious accusation, claimed public credit for this service of his son before the Gran Consiglio; in other words, before all the world.

The conduct of the Venetian government to the condottieri in its pay has been spoken of already. The only further guarantee of their fidelity which could be obtained lay in their great number, by which treachery was made as difficult as its discovery was easy. In looking at the Venetian army list, one is only surprised that among forces of such miscellaneous composition any common action was possible. In the catalogue for the campaign of 1495 we find 15,526 horsemen, broken up into a number of small divisions. Gonzaga of Mantua alone had as many as 1,200, and Gioffredo Borgia 740; then follow six officers with a contingent of 600 to 700, ten with 400, twelve with 400 to 200, fourteen or thereabouts with 200 to 100, nine with 80, six with 50 to 60, and so forth. These forces were partly composed of old Venetian troops, partly of veterans led by Venetian city or country nobles; the majority of the leaders were, however, princes and rulers of cities or their relatives. To these forces must be added 24,000 infantry — we are not told how they were raised or commanded — with 3,300 additional troops, who probably belonged to the special services. In time of peace the cities of the mainland were wholly unprotected or occupied by insignificant garrisons. Venice relied, if not exactly on the loyalty, at least on the good sense of its subjects; in the war of the League of Cambrai (1509) it absolved them, as is well known, from their oath of allegiance, and let them compare the amenities of a foreign occupation with the mild government to which they had been accustomed. As there had been no treason in their desertion of St Mark, and consequently no punishment was to be feared, they returned to their old masters with the utmost eagerness. This war, we may remark parenthetically, was the result of a century's outcry against the Venetian desire for aggrandizement. The Venetians, in fact, were not free from the mistake of those over-lever people who will credit their opponents with no irrational and inconsiderate conduct. Misled by this optimism, which is, perhaps, a peculiar weakness of aristocracies, they had utterly ignored not only the preparations of Muhammad II for the capture of Constantinople, but even the armaments of Charles VIII, till the unexpected blow fell at last. The League of Cambrai was an event of the same character, in so far as it was clearly opposed to the interests of the two chief members, Louis XII and Julius II. The hatred of all Italy against the victorious city seemed to be concentrated in the mind of the pope, and to have blinded him to the evils of foreign intervention; and as to the policy of Cardinal d'Amboise and his king, Venice ought long before to have recognized it as a piece of malicious imbecility, and to have been thoroughly on its guard. The other members of the League took part in it from that envy which may be a salutary corrective to great wealth and power, but which in itself is a beggarly sentiment. Venice came out of the conflict with honour, but not without lasting damage.

A power, whose foundations were so complicated, whose activity and interests filled so wide a stage, cannot be imagined without a systematic oversight of the whole, without a regular estimate of means and burdens, of profits and losses. Venice can fairly make good its claim to be the birthplace of statistical science, together, perhaps, with Florence, and followed by the more enlightened despotisms. The feudal state of the Middle Ages knew of nothing more than catalogues of signorial rights and possessions (urbaria); it looked on production as a fixed quantity, which it approximately is, so long as we have to do with landed property only. The towns, on the other hand, throughout the West must from very early times have treated production, which with them depended on industry and commerce, as exceedingly variable; but, even in the most flourishing times of the Hanseatic League, they never got beyond a simple commercial balance-sheet. Fleets, armies, political power and influence fall under the debit and credit of a trader's ledger. In the Italian states a clear political consciousness, the pattern of Muhammadan administration, and the long and active exercise of trade and commerce combined to produce for the first time a true science of statistics. The absolute monarchy of Frederick II in Lower Italy was organized with the sole object of securing a concentrated power for the death-struggle in which he was engaged. In Venice, on the contrary, the supreme objects were the enjoyment of life and power, the increase of inherited advantages, the creation of the most lucrative forms of industry, and the opening of new channels for commerce.

The writers of the time speak of these things with the greatest freedom. We learn that the population of the city amounted in the year 1422 to 190,000 souls; the Italians were, perhaps, the first to reckon, not according to hearths, or men able to bear arms, or people able to walk, and so forth, but according to animae, and thus to get the most neutral basis for further calculation. About this time, when the Florentines wished to form an alliance with Venice against Filippo Maria Visconti, they were for the moment refused, in the belief, resting on accurate commercial returns, that a war between Venice and Milan, that is, between seller and buyer, was foolish. Even if the duke simply increased his army, the Milanese, through the heavier taxation they must pay, would become worse customers. 'Better let the Florentines be defeated, and then, used as they are to the life of a free city, they will settle with us and bring their silk and woollen industry with them, as the Lucchese did in their distress.' The speech of the dying Doge Mocenigo (1423) to a few of the senators whom he had sent for to his bedside is still more remarkable. It contains the chief elements of a statistical account of the whole resources of Venice. I cannot say whether or where a thorough elucidation of this perplexing document exists; by way of illustration, the following facts may be quoted. After repaying a war-loan of four million ducats, the public debt (il monte) still amounted to six million ducats; the current trade (so it seems) ten million, which yielded, the text informs us, a profit of four million. The 3,000 navigli, the 300 navi, and the 45 galleys were manned respectively by 17,000, 8,000 and 11,ooo seamen (more than 200 for each galley). To these must be added 16,000 shipwrights. The houses in Venice were valued at seven million, and brought in a rent of half a million. There were 1,000 nobles whose income ranged from 70 to 4,000 ducats. In another passage the ordinary income of the state in that same year is put at 1,100,000 ducats; through the disturbance of trade caused by the wars it sank about the middle of the century to 800,000 ducats.

If Venice, by this spirit of calculation, and by the practical turn which she gave it, was the first fully to represent one important side of modern political life, in that culture, on the other hand, which Italy then prized most highly she did not stand in the front rank. The literary impulse, in general, was here wanting, and especially that enthusiasm for classical antiquity which prevailed elsewhere. The aptitude of the Venetians, says Sabellico, for philosophy and eloquence was in itself not less remarkable than for commerce and politics. George of Trebizond, who, in 1459, laid the Latin translation of Plato's Laws at the feet of the doge, was appointed professor of philology with a yearly salary of 150 ducats, and finally dedicated his Rhetoric to the Signoria. If, however, we look through the history of Venetian literature which Francesco Sansovino has appended to his well-known book, we shall find in the fourteenth century almost nothing but history, and special works on theology, jurisprudence and medicine; and in the fifteenth century, till we come to Ermolao Barbaro and Aldo Manucci, humanistic culture is, for a city of such importance, most scantily represented. The library which Cardinal Bessarion bequeathed to the state (1468) narrowly escaped dispersion and destruction. Learning was certainly cultivated at the university of Padua, where, however, the physicians and the jurists — the latter as the authors of legal opinions — received by far the highest pay. The share of Venice in the poetical creations of the country was long insignificant, till, at the beginning of the sixteenth century, her deficiencies were made good. Even the art of the Renaissance was imported into the city from without, and it was not before the end of the fifteenth century that she learned to move in this field with independent freedom and strength. But we find more striking instances still of intellectual backwardness. This government, which had the clergy so thoroughly in its control, which reserved to itself the appointment to all important ecclesiastical offices, and which, one time after another, dared to defy the court of Rome, displayed an official piety of a most singular kind. The bodies of saints and other relics imported from Greece after the Turkish conquest were bought at the greatest sacrifices and received by the doge in solemn procession. For the coat without a seam it was decided (1455) to offer 10,000 ducats, but it was not to be had. These measures were not the fruit of any popular excitement, but of the tranquil resolutions of the heads of the government, and might have been omitted without attracting any comment, and at Florence, under similar circumstances, would certainly have been omitted. We shall say nothing of the piety of the masses, and of their firm belief in the indulgences of an Alexander VI. But the state itself, after absorbing the Church to a degree unknown elsewhere, had in truth a certain ecclesiastical element in its composition, and the doge, the symbol of the state, appeared in twelve great processions (andate) in a half-clerical character. They were almost all festivals in memory of political events, and competed in splendour with the great feasts of the Church; the most brilliant of all, the famous marriage with the sea, fell on Ascension Day.

The most elevated political thought and the most varied forms of human development are found united in the history of Florence, which in this sense deserves the name of the most modern state in the world. Here the whole people are busied with what in the despotic cities is the affair of a single family. That wondrous Florentine spirit, at once keenly critical and artistically creative, was incessantly transforming the social and political condition of the state, and as incessantly describing and judging the change. Florence thus became the home of political doctrines and theories, of experiments and sudden changes, but also, like Venice, the home of statistical science, and alone and above all other states in the world, the home of historical representation in the modern sense of the phrase. The spectacle of ancient Rome and a familiarity with its leading writers were not without influence; Giovanni Villani confesses that he received the first impulse to his great work at the jubilee of the year 1300, and began it immediately on his return home. Yet how many among the 200,000 pilgrims of that year may have been like him in gifts and tendencies and still did not write the history of their native cities! For not all of them could encourage themselves with the thought, 'Rome is sinking; my native city is rising, and ready to achieve great things, and therefore I wish to relate its past history, and hope to continue the story to the present time, and as long as my life shall last.' And besides the witness to its past, Florence obtained through its historians something further — a greater fame than fell to the lot of any other city of Italy.

Our present task is not to write the history of this remarkable state, but merely to give a few indications of the intellectual freedom and independence for which the Florentines were indebted to this history.

In no other city of Italy were the struggles of political parties so bitter, of such early origin, and so permanent. The descriptions of them, which belong, it is true, to a somewhat later period, give clear evidence of the superiority of Florentine criticism.

And what a politician is the great victim of these crises, Dante Alighieri, matured alike by home and by exile! He uttered his scorn of the incessant changes and experiments in the constitution of his native city in verses of adamant, which will remain proverbial so long as political events of the same kind recur; he addressed his home in words of defiance and yearning which must have stirred the hearts of his countrymen. But his thoughts ranged over Italy and the whole world; and if his passion for the Empire, as he conceived it, was no more than an illusion, it must yet be admitted that the youthful dreams of a newborn political speculation are in his case not without a poetical grandeur. He is proud to be the first who trod this path, certainly in the footsteps of Aristotle, but in his own way independently. His ideal emperor is a just and humane judge, dependent on God only, the heir of the universal sway of Rome to which belonged the sanction of nature, of right and of the will of God. The conquest of the world was, according to this view, rightful, resting on a divine judgement between Rome and the other nations of the earth, and God gave his approval to this Empire, since under it he became Man, submitting at his birth to the census of the Emperor Augustus, and at his death to the judgement of Pontius Pilate. We may find it hard to appreciate these and other arguments of the same kind, but Dante's passion never fails to carry us with him. In his letters he appears as one of the earliest publicists, and is perhaps the first layman to publish political tracts in this form. He began early. Soon after the death of Beatrice he addressed a pamphlet on the state of Florence 'to the Great ones of the Earth', and the public utterances of his later years, dating from the time of his banishment, are all directed to emperors, princes and cardinals. In these letters and in his book De Vulgari Eloquio the feeling, bought with such bitter pains, is constantly recurring that the exile may find elsewhere than in his native place an intellectual home in language and culture, which cannot be taken from him. On this point we shall have more to say in the sequel.

To the two Villani, Giovanni as well as Matteo, we owe not so much deep political reflection as fresh and practical observations, together with the elements of Florentine statistics and important notices of other states. Here too trade and commerce had given the impulse to economical as well as political science. Nowhere else in the world was such accurate information to be had on financial affairs. The wealth of the papal court at Avignon, which at the death of John XXII amounted to 25 million gold florins, would be incredible on any less trustworthy authority. Here only, at Florence, do we meet with colossal loans like that which the King of England contracted from the Florentine houses of Bardi and Peruzzi, who lost to His Majesty the sum of 1,365,000 gold florins (1338) — their own money and that of their partners — and nevertheless recovered from the shock. Most important facts are here recorded as to the condition of Florence at this time: the public income (over 300,000 gold florins) and expenditure; the population of the city, here only roughly estimated, according to the consumption of bread, in bocche, i. e. mouths, put at 90,000, and the population of the whole territory; the excess of 300 to 500 male children among the 5,800 to 6,000 annually baptized; the schoolchildren, of whom 8,000 to 10,000 learned reading, 1,000 to 1,200 in six schools arithmetic; and besides these, 600 scholars who were taught Latin grammar and logic in four schools. Then follow the statistics of the churches and monasteries; of the hospitals, which held more than a thousand beds; of the wool-trade, with its most valuable details; of the mint, the provisioning of the city, the public officials, and so on. Incidentally we learn many curious facts; how, for instance, when the public funds (monte) were first established, in the year 1353, the Franciscans spoke from the pulpit in favour of the measure, the Dominicans and Augustinians against it. The economical results of the black death were and could be observed and described nowhere else in all Europe as in this city. Only a Florentine could have left it on record how it was expected that the scanty population would have made everything cheap, and how instead of that labour and commodities doubled in price; how the common people at first would do no work at all, but simply gave themselves up to enjoyment; how in the city itself servants and maids were not to be had except at extravagant wages; how the peasants would only till the best lands, and left the rest uncultivated; and how the enormous legacies bequeathed to the poor at the time of the plague seemed afterwards useless, since the poor had either died or had ceased to be poor. Lastly, on the occasion of a great bequest, by which a childless philanthropist left six danari to every beggar in the city, the attempt is made to give a comprehensive statistical account of Florentine mendicancy.

This statistical view of things was at a later time still more highly cultivated at Florence. The noteworthy point about it is that, as a rule, we can perceive its connection with the higher aspects of history, with art, and with culture in general. An inventory of the year 1422 mentions, within the compass of the same document, the seventy-two exchange offices which surrounded the Mercato Nuovo; the amount of coined money in circulation (2 million golden florins); the then new industry of gold spinning; the silk wares; Filippo Brunellesco, then busy in digging classical architecture from its grave; and Leonardo Aretino, secretary of the republic, at work at the revival of ancient literature and eloquence; lastly, it speaks of the general prosperity of the city, then free from political conflicts, and of the good fortune of Italy, which had rid itself of foreign mercenaries. The Venetian statistics quoted above, which date from about the same year, certainly give evidence of larger property and profits and of a more extensive scene of action; Venice had long been mistress of the seas before Florence sent out its first galleys (1422) to Alexandria. But no reader can fail to recognize the higher spirit of the Florentine documents. These and similar lists recur at intervals of ten years, systematically arranged and tabulated, while elsewhere we find at best occasional notices. We can form an approximate estimate of the property and the business of the first Medici; they paid for charities, public buildings and taxes from 1434 to 1471 no less than 663,755 gold florins, of which more than 400,000 fell on Cosimo alone, and Lorenzo il Magnifico was delighted that the money had been so well spent. In 1478 we have again a most important and in its way complete view of the commerce and trades of this city, some of which may be wholly or partly reckoned among the fine arts — such as those which had to do with damasks and gold or silver embroidery, with woodcarving and intarsia, with the sculpture of arabesques in marble and sandstone, with portraits in wax, and with jewellery and work in gold. The inborn talent of the Florentines for the systematization of outward life is shown by their books on agriculture, business and domestic economy, which are markedly superior to those of other European people in the fifteenth century. It has been rightly decided to publish selections of these works, although no little study will be needed to extract clear and definite results from them. At all events, we have no difficulty in recognizing the city, where dying parents begged the government in their wills to fine their sons 1,000 florins if they declined to practise a regular profession.

For the first half of the sixteenth century probably no state in the world possesses a document like the magnificent description of Florence by Varchi. In descriptive statistics, as in so many things besides, yet another model is left to us, before the freedom and greatness of the city sank into the grave.

This statistical estimate of outward life is, however, uniformly accompanied by the narrative of political events to which we have already referred.

Florence not only existed under political forms more varied than those of the free states of Italy and of Europe generally, but it reflected upon them far more deeply. It is a faithful mirror of the relations of individuals and classes to a variable whole. The pictures of the great civic democracies in France and in Flanders, as they are delineated in Froissart, and the narratives of the German chroniclers of the fourteenth century, are in truth of high importance; but in comprehensiveness of thought and in the rational development of the story none will bear comparison with the Florentines. The rule of the nobility, the tyrannies, the struggles of the middle class with the proletariat, limited and unlimited democracy, pseudo-democracy, the primacy of a single house, the theocracy of Savonarola, and the mixed forms of government which prepared the way for the Medicean despotism — all are so described that the inmost motives of the actors are laid bare to the light. At length Machiavelli in his Florentine history (down to 1492) represents his native city as a living organism and its development as a natural and individual process; he is the first of the moderns who has risen to such a conception. It lies without our province to determine whether and in what points Machiavelli may have done violence to history, as is notoriously the case in his life of Castruccio Castracani — a fancy picture of the typical despot. We might find something to say against every line of the Storie Fiorentine, and yet the great and unique value of the whole would remain unaffected. And his contemporaries and successors, Jacopo Pitti, Guicciardini, Segni, Varchi, Vettori, what a circle of illustrious names! And what a story it is which these masters tell us! The great and memorable drama of the last decades of the Florentine republic is here unfolded. The voluminous record of the collapse of the highest and most original life which the world could then show may appear to one but as a collection of curiosities, may awaken in another a devilish delight at the shipwreck of so much nobility and grandeur, to a third may seem like a great historical assize; for all it will be an object of thought and study to the end of time. The evil, which was for ever troubling the peace of the city, was its rule over once powerful and now conquered rivals like Pisa — a rule of which the necessary consequence was a chronic state of violence. The only remedy, certainly an extreme one and which none but Savonarola could have persuaded Florence to accept, and that only with the help of favourable chances, would have been the well-timed dissolution of Tuscany into a federal union of free cities. At a later period this scheme, then no more than the dream of a past age, brought (1548) a patriotic citizen of Lucca to the scaffold. From this evil and from the ill-starred Guelph sympathies of Florence for a foreign prince, which familiarized it with foreign intervention, came all the disasters which followed. But who does not admire the people, which was wrought up by its venerated preacher to a mood of such sustained loftiness, that for the first time in Italy it set the example of sparing a conquered foe, while the whole history of its past taught nothing but vengeance and extermination? The glow which melted patriotism into one with moral regeneration may seem, when looked at from a distance, to have soon passed away; but its best results shine forth again in the memorable siege of 1529—30. They were 'fools', as Guicciardini then wrote, who drew down this storm upon Florence, but he confesses himself that they achieved things which seemed incredible; and when he declares that sensible people would have got out of the way of the danger, he means no more than that Florence ought to have yielded itself silently and ingloriously into the hands of its enemies. It would no doubt have preserved its splendid suburbs and gardens, and the lives and prosperity of countless citizens; but it would have been the poorer by one of its greatest and most ennobling memories.

In many of their chief merits the Florentines are the pattern and the earliest type of Italians and modern Europeans generally; they are so also in many of their defects. When Dante compares the city which was always mending its constitution with the sick man who is continually changing his posture to escape from pain, he touches with the comparison a permanent feature of the political life of Florence. The great modern fallacy that a constitution can be made, can be manufactured by a combination of existing forces and tendencies, was constantly cropping up in stormy times; even Machiavelli is not wholly free from it. Constitutional artists were never wanting who by an ingenious distribution and division of political power, by indirect elections of the most complicated kind, by the establishment of nominal offices, sought to found a lasting order of things, and to satisfy or to deceive the rich and the poor alike. They naïvely fetch their examples from classical antiquity, and borrow the party names ottimati, aristocrazia, as a matter of course. The world since then has become used to these expressions and given them a conventional European sense, whereas all former party names were purely national, and either characterized the cause at issue or sprang from the caprice of accident. But how a name colours or discolours a political cause!

But of all who thought it possible to construct a state, the greatest beyond all comparison was Machiavelli. He treats existing forces as living and active, takes a large and an accurate view of alternative possibilities, and seeks to mislead neither himself nor others. No man could be freer from vanity or ostentation; indeed, he does not write for the public, but either for princes and administrators or for personal friends. The danger for him does not lie in an affectation of genius or in a false order of ideas, but rather in a powerful imagination which he evidently controls with difficulty. The objectivity of his political judgement is sometimes appalling in its sincerity; but it is the sign of a time of no ordinary need and peril, when it was a hard matter to believe in right, or to credit others with just dealing. Virtuous indignation at his expense is thrown away upon us who have seen in what sense political morality is understood by the statesmen of our own century. Machiavelli was at all events able to forget himself in his cause. In truth, although his writings, with the exception of very few words, are altogether destitute of enthusiasm, and although the Florentines themselves treated him at last as a criminal, he was a patriot in the fullest meaning of the word. But free as he was, like most of his contemporaries, in speech and morals, the welfare of the state was yet his first and last thought.

His most complete programme for the construction of a new political system at Florence is set forth in the memorial to Leo X, composed after the death of the younger Lorenzo Medici, Duke of Urbino (d. 1519), to whom he had dedicated his Prince. The state was by that time in extremities and utterly corrupt, and the remedies proposed are not always morally justifiable; but it is most interesting to see how he hopes to set up the republic in the form of a moderate democracy, as heiress to the Medici. A more ingenious scheme of concessions to the pope, to the pope's various adherents, and to the different Florentine interests cannot be imagined; we might fancy ourselves looking into the works of a clock. Principles, observations, comparisons, political forecasts and the like are to be found in numbers in the Discorsi, among them flashes of wonderful insight. He recognizes, for example, the law of a continuous though not uniform development in republican institutions, and requires the constitution to be flexible and capable of change, as the only means of dispensing with bloodshed and banishments. For a like reason, in order to guard against private violence and foreign interference — 'the death of all freedom' — he wishes to see introduced a judicial procedure (accusa) against hated citizens, in place of which Florence had hitherto had nothing but the court of scandal. With a masterly hand the tardy and involuntary decisions are characterized, which at critical moments play so important a part in republican states. Once, it is true, he is misled by his imagination and the pressure of events into unqualified praise of the people, which chooses its officers, he says, better than any prince, and which can be cured of its errors by 'good advice'. With regard to the government of Tuscany, he has no doubt that it belongs to his native city, and maintains, in a special Discorso, that the reconquest of Pisa is a question of life or death; he deplores that Arezzo, after the rebellion of 1502, was not razed to the ground; he admits in general that Italian republics must be allowed to expand freely and add to their territory in order to enjoy peace at home, and not to be themselves attacked by others, but declares that Florence had always begun at the wrong end, and from the first made deadly enemies of Pisa, Lucca and Siena, while Pistoia, 'treated like a brother', had voluntarily submitted to her.

It would be unreasonable to draw a parallel between the few other republics which still existed in the fifteenth century and this unique city — the most important workshop of the Italian, and indeed of the modern European spirit. Siena suffered from the gravest organic maladies, and its relative prosperity in art and industry must not mislead us on this point. Aeneas Sylvius looks with longing from his native town over to the 'merry' German imperial cities, where life is embittered by no confiscations of land and goods, by no arbitrary officials, and by no political factions. Genoa scarcely comes within range of our task, as before the time of Andrea Doria it took almost no part in the Renaissance. Indeed, the inhabitant of the Riviera was proverbial among Italians for his contempt of all higher culture. Party conflicts here assumed so fierce a character, and disturbed so violently the whole course of life, that we can hardly understand how, after so many revolutions and invasions, the Genoese ever contrived to return to an endurable condition. Perhaps it was owing to the fact that nearly all who took part in public affairs were at the same time almost without exception active men of business. The example of Genoa shows in a striking manner with what insecurity wealth and vast commerce, and with what internal disorder the possession of distant colonies, are compatible.

Lucca is of small significance in the fifteenth century.